<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Aging (Albany NY)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ImpactJ</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Aging (Albany NY)</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1945-4589</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Impact Journals LLC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">20519775</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2898019</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Circadian clock proteins control adaptation to novel environment and
                        memory formation</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Circadian clock and habituation</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>A.Kondratova</surname><given-names>Anna</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>V.Dubrovsky</surname><given-names>Yuliya</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Antoch</surname><given-names>Marina P.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kondratov</surname><given-names>Roman V.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><sup>1</sup> Lerner Research Institute, Cleveland Clinic, Cleveland, OH 44195, USA
            </aff><aff id="A2"><sup>2</sup> Department of Biological, Geological and Environmental Sciences
                    and Center for Gene Regulation in Health and Disease, Cleveland State
                    University, Cleveland, OH 44115, USA  
            </aff><aff id="A3"><sup>3</sup> Department of Molecular and Cellular Biology, Roswell Park Cancer
                    Institute, Buffalo, NY 14203, USA
            </aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold>Correspondence: </bold>:
                        Roman V. Kondratov, PhD, Department of Biological, Geological and
                        Environmental Sciences and Center for Gene Regulation in Health and
                        Disease, Cleveland State University, 2121 Euclid avenue, Cleveland, OH 44115, USA <email>r.kondratov@csuohio.edu </email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>5</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>2</day><month>5</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><volume>2</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>285</fpage><lpage>297</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>4</month><year>2010</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>4</month><year>2010</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9;2010 A.Kondratova et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2010</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>
                     Deficiency of
                        the transcription factor BMAL1, a core component of the circadian clock,
                        results in an accelerated aging phenotype in mice. The circadian clock
                        regulates many physiological processes and was recently implicated in
                        control of brain-based activities, such as memory formation and the
                        regulation of emotions. Aging is accompanied by the decline in brain
                        physiology, particularly decline in the response and adaptation to novelty.
                        We investigated the role of the circadian clock in exploratory behavior and
                        habituation to novelty using the open field paradigm. We found that mice
                        with a deficiency of the circadian transcription factor BMAL1 display
                        hyperactivity in novel environments and impaired intra- and intersession
                        habituation, indicative of defects in short- and long-term memory
                        formation. In contrast, mice double-deficient for the circadian proteins
                        CRY1 and CRY2 (repressors of the BMAL1-mediated transcription) demonstrate
                        reduced activity and accelerated habituation when compared to wild type
                        mice. Mice with mutation in theClock gene (encoding the BMAL1
                        transcription partner) show normal locomotion, but increased rearing
                        activity and impaired intersession habituation. BMAL1 is highly expressed
                        in the neurons of the hippocampus - a brain region associated with spatial
                        memory formation; BMAL1 deficiency disrupts circadian oscillation in gene
                        expression and reactive oxygen species homeostasis in the brain, which may
                        be among the possible mechanisms involved. Thus, we suggest that the
                        BMAL1:CLOCK activity is critical for the proper exploratory and habituation
                        behavior, and that the circadian clock prepares
                        organism for a new round of everyday activities through optimization of
                        behavioral learning.
                </p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>transcription</kwd><kwd>aging</kwd><kwd>oxidative stress</kwd><kwd>hippocampus</kwd><kwd>gene expression</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>The ability to explore the outside world
                        and compare old and new information is critical for animal's survival. The
                        proper exploratory behavior in novel unpredictable situations (brought about by
                        weather changes, activity of other animals, etc.) allows distinguishing
                        meaningful and ignoring not important novel stimuli and their combinations.
                        Habituation, one of the simplest forms of non-associative learning, is the
                        mechanism providing an animal with the means to dampen the perception of repetitive neutral stimuli and
                        be ready to effectively detect a novel stimulus with a yet unknown significance,
                        and therefore is vitally important for the interaction of an organism with its
                        environment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>]. Both response to novelty and habituation change with age,
                        but molecular mechanisms underlying these changes remain mostly unknown.
                    
            </p><p>Recently we have demonstrated that a deficiency of the
                        transcription factor BMAL1 in mice results in accelerated aging [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>]. BMAL1
                        activity is critical for the operation of the circadian clock - a genetically
                        determined time-keeping system generating 24-hour oscillations in physiology
                        and behavior known as the circadian rhythms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>]. The involvement of the
                        circadian clock in the control of brain-based activities such as sleep [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>],
                        reward behavior [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>] and regulation of mood [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>] has been reported.
                        Recently, a connection between the circadian clock and memory has been
                        suggested: mice with deficiencies of different components of the circadian
                        clock demonstrate impairments of some types of memory and learning [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>]. Here
                        we hypothesize that the circadian clock is involved in the regulation of the
                        adaptation to the new environment, and investigate this hypothesis using a set
                        of circadian mutants - mice with targeted disruptions of circadian genes <italic>Bmal1</italic>
                        or <italic>Cry1 </italic>and <italic>Cry2</italic>, or with the mutation of the <italic>Clock</italic>
                        [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>] gene. These genes encode proteins representing the core components of
                        the circadian clock. Transcription factors BMAL1 and CLOCK form a transcription
                        complex activating expression of target genes including circadian transcription
                        repressors CRY1 and CRY2. In turn, CRY1 and CRY2 suppress activity of the
                        BMAL1:CLOCK complex, including their own expression, thus generating a negative
                        feedback loop; expression of several other genes important for the functional
                        clock (i.e. <italic>Per1, 2 and 3</italic>) is also under the transcription control of
                        the BMAL1:CLOCK complex [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>].
                    
            </p></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s2"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2_1"><title>Hyperactivity
                            and impaired habituation of <italic>Bmal1-/-</italic> mice
                        </title><p>The exploratory behavior of the wild type
                            and <italic>Bmal1-/-</italic> mice in novel environment was tested in the open field
                            paradigm (OF). For this, 3-months old male mice were placed in a bright-lit
                            50x50 inches square box and monitored for the pattern of their exploratory
                            behavior for 1 hour with 5-min resolution. In order to assess intersessional
                            habituation, animals were exposed to the same environment 24 hours later. 
                            Activity of <italic>Bmal1-/-</italic>  mice in novel environment was strikingly different
                            from that of wild type mice. <italic>Bmal1-/-</italic> mice demonstrated significantly
                            increased locomotion (horizontal activity) on day1 [F[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>] = 19.21, P = 0.007]
                            and day2 [F[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>] = 27.36, P = 0.0004] (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>, left panel).  Total distance
                            traveled by <italic>Bmal1-/-</italic> animals during 1h on days 1 and 2 of the OF
                            experiment was respectively 2.7-fold and 4.7-fold higher than that of the wild
                            type mice. The pattern of activity in wild type and <italic>Bmal1-/- </italic>mice was
                            also very different. As expected based on previous studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>], on day1 the
                            distance traveled by wild type mice during the first 15 min of the OF session
                            was 3.1-fold higher than during the last 15 min [t-test P &#x0003c;0.0001]; on day2,
                            it was 2.8-fold higher [t-test P &#x0003c;0.001]. Such a decrease with time on both
                            first and second days of the experiment results from animals' habituation to a
                            new environment within each OF session. When compared to day1, total activity
                            of wild type mice on day2 was also significantly reduced [F[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>] = 13.37, P =
                            0.015] (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref> and 5, left), indicating that a long-term memory reflecting
                            experience obtained on day1 has been formed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>]. In contrast, on day1 the
                            difference in distance traveled by <italic>Bmal1-/-</italic> mice during the first 15 min
                            of the OF session was only 1.6-fold higher than during the last 15 min [t-test
                            P &#x0003c;0.01], whereas there was no difference on day2. Remarkably, the total
                            distances traveled by <italic>Bmal1-/-</italic> mice during the first and the second days
                            were virtually identical (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>, lower left), and no statistically
                            significant difference was detected between days 1 and 2 of the test [F[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>] =
                            3.83, P = 0.107] (Figure1, left).
                        
                </p><p>In
                            the same experiments, vertical (rearing) activity was measured by registering
                            the sequential crossing of beams up and down in vertical direction. Similar to
                            the difference in horizontal activity, total rearing activity of <italic>Bmal1-/-</italic>
                            mice was significantly increased compared to wild type animals (2.3-fold and
                            4.7-fold on days 1 [F[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>] = 13.92, P = 0.014] and 2 [F[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>] = 22.57, P =
                            0.00031], respectively (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>, right panel).  On day2 wild type mice
                            demonstrated 1.9-fold reduction in total rearing activity [F[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>] = 24.34, P =
                            0.004], whereas no difference between the two days was detected in <italic>Bmal1-/-</italic>
                            animals [F[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>] = 0.37, P = 0.568] (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>, lower right). In contrast to
                            differences displayed in   horizontal activity, animals of both genotypes
                            displayed similar rearing activity during the first 5 min of exposure to the
                            new environment. After this, rearing activity of wild type animals gradually
                            decreased, whereas in <italic>Bmal1-/-</italic> mice it increased and stayed elevated for
                            the duration of testing (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>, right). On day 2, the temporal pattern of
                            rearing activity in animals of both genotypes did not differ much from the one
                            displayed on day1. Taken together, these data indicate that deficiency in core
                            circadian component, BMAL1, affects not only rhythmicity in locomotor activity,
                            but other patterns of behavior as well. Specifically, when placed in a new
                            environment, BMAL1-deficient mice display novelty-induced hyperactivity in
                            locomotion and rearing behavior, and deficits in inter- and intrasessional
                            habituation.
                        
                </p></sec><sec id="s2_2"><title>BMAL1
                            is expressed in hippocampal and cortical neurons
                        </title><p>BMAL1
                            is expressed in many different tissues and organs. Brain-specific <italic>Bmal1</italic>
                            expression at the mRNA level has been demonstrated for the suprachiasmatic
                            nucleus of the anterior hypothalamus (SCN),  the residence of the master
                            circadian clock, as well as for other brain regions including the cortex and
                            hippocampus formation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>]. To investigate the distribution of BMAL1
                            protein in the brain, we performed <italic>in situ</italic> immunofluorescent staining
                            using BMAL1-specific antibody (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2a</xref>). High expression of
                            BMAL1 was detected in the pyramidal neurons of the hippocampus and in the
                            neurons of the subiculum and enthorhinal cortex of wt mice. Neurons of the
                            neocortex were also positive for BMAL1. Specificity of the signal was confirmed
                            by the parallel staining of the brains of <italic>Bmal1-/-</italic> mice. Thus, BMAL1
                            protein is expressed in brain structures associated with memory formation.
                        
                </p><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><title>Open field analysis of exploratory activity and habituation of wild type and <italic>Bmal1-/-</italic>
                                                mice.</title><p>
                                            Locomotor and rearing activity were measured in 5 min increments during 1
                                            hr. (Upper panel) locomotor and rearing activity of wt and <italic>Bmal1-/-</italic>
                                            mice on day1; (middle panel) relative locomotor activity (normalized to
                                            average distance covered on day1) and relative rearing activity (normalized
                                            to average rearing level on day1) of wt mice on days 1 and 2; (lower panel)
                                            relative locomotor and rearing activity  of <italic>Bmal1-/-</italic> mice on days 1
                                            and 2 (* P&#x0003c;0.05).
                                    
                        </p></caption><graphic xlink:href="aging-02-285-g001"/></fig><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><title>Expression of circadian proteins in brain structures.</title><p>(<bold>a</bold>)
                                                Immunostaining of sagittal brain sections of wt and <italic>Bmal-/-</italic> mice
                                                with BMAL1 specific antibodies. Counterstaining with DAPI was used to
                                                detect nuclei. Pyramidal neurons of hippocampal areas CA1 and CA3, granular
                                                cells of the dentate gyrus and neurons of subiculum expressing BMAL1 are
                                                shown. (<bold>b</bold>) Circadian profile of <italic>Cry1</italic> and <italic>Per2</italic> mRNAs in
                                                the brain of wt (filled circles) and <italic>Bmal1-/- </italic>mice (open circles) as
                                                measured by real-time PCR. (* p&#x0003c;0.05).
                                        
                        </p></caption><graphic xlink:href="aging-02-285-g002"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2_3"><title>BMAL1
                            deficiency disrupts circadian expression of <italic>mPer2</italic> and <italic>mCry1</italic> genes
                            in the brain
                        </title><p>In
                            complex with CLOCK (or its close tissue-specific homolog, NPAS2) BMAL1 controls
                            rhythmic expression of target genes, and BMAL1 deficiency results in disruption
                            of rhythmic pattern of gene expression in the SCN and liver [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>]. We decided to
                            investigate how the absence of BMAL1 will affect the expression of BMAL1 target
                            genes in the brain. As demonstrated in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2b</xref>, rhythmic pattern of
                            expression of two core circadian genes, <italic>mPer2</italic> and <italic>mCry1</italic> in the
                            brain of BMAL1-deficient animals was significantly impaired with the <italic>mPer2</italic>
                            gene being mostly down-regulated and <italic>mCry1</italic> up-regulated. This pattern of
                            expression was previously observed in the SCN and liver of <italic>Bmal1</italic>-/- mice
                            and was attributed to the dual role of the BMAL1:CLOCK complex in transcription
                            regulation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>]. Importantly, both PER2 and
                            CRY1 were recently implicated in memory and learning [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref>].
                        
                </p></sec><sec id="s2_4"><title>BMAL1
                            deficiency results in disruption of ROS homeostasis in the brain
                        </title><p>Aging is associated with increased oxidative stress in
                            many tissues, including the brain. Recently, oxidative stress and misbalance in
                            reactive oxygen/nitrogen species (ROS/RNS) homeostasis was proposed as a
                            mechanism for age-dependent changes in brain physiology, including decline in
                            memory and learning [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref>]. Previously we have demonstrated that BMAL1 is
                            directly involved in the regulation of ROS/RNS homeostasis, and that
                            accelerated aging characteristic for  <italic>Bmal1-/-</italic> mice, at least in part,
                            can be attributed to excessive production of ROS in some tissues of <italic>Bmal1-/-</italic>
                            animals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>]. This prompted us to compare the levels of ROS in the brain of wild
                            type and <italic>Bmal1-/-</italic> mice.
                        
                </p><fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><title>BMAL1 deficiency disrupts ROS homeostasis in the brain.</title><p> (<bold>a</bold>) ROS
                                                level in the brain of wt and <italic>Bmal1-/-</italic> mice was detected in the indicated
                                                time points of the circadian cycle. (<bold>b</bold>) Average ROS level in the
                                                brain of wt and <italic>Bmal1-/-</italic> mice for 24h (* P&#x0003c;0.05).
                                        
                        </p></caption><graphic xlink:href="aging-02-285-g003"/></fig><p>To
                            account for possible daily fluctuations, the level of ROS was measured in
                            brains of wild type and <italic>Bmal1-/-</italic> mice collected throughout the day every
                            4 hrs. The level of ROS in the total brain extracts did not show any obvious
                            circadian pattern; however, at each time point it was significantly higher in <italic>Bmal1-/-</italic>
                            mice (except for the time of maximum level of ROS for the wild type (CT34)). As
                            a result, in mutant mice the average daily levels of ROS in the brain were 20%
                            higher [t-test P &#x0003c; 0.01] (Figure3b). Thus, BMAL1 deficiency results in
                            excessive production of ROS and chronic oxidative stress in the brain, which
                            may affect various brain-specific metabolic processes including memory
                            formation.
                        
                </p></sec><sec id="s2_5"><title>Deficiency
                            of circadian proteins CLOCK and CRY1,2 differentially alters habituation and
                            exploratory activity
                        </title><p>The
                            observed behavioral phenotype of <italic>Bmal1-/-</italic> mice may result from
                            desynchronization of physiological activity of neurons due to disruption of the
                            circadian oscillator. On the other hand, it may be unique to <italic>Bmal1-/-</italic>
                            mice and result from disruption of the BMAL1-dependent control of tissue
                            homeostasis. To discriminate between these two possible mechanisms in the
                            regulation of hyperactivity and habituation, we studied the exploratory
                            behavior of arrhythmic mice with disrupted activity of other circadian
                            proteins.
                        
                </p><p>We have chosen mice with the deficiency
                            of the two <italic>Cry</italic> genes (<italic>Cry1,2-/- </italic>double knockout mice) and mice with the homozygous mutation of the BMAL1 transcription
                            partner, CLOCK (<italic>Clock/Clock </italic>mutant mice). Previous work has shown that
                            these two models, along with the <italic>Bmal1-/-</italic> model, may be approximated by
                            two opposite functional states of the BMAL1:CLOCK transcription complex. Thus,
                            functional deficiency in BMAL1 or CLOCK proteins results in the absence of
                            transactivation of the target genes, while the absence of the CRY1,2 proteins
                            cause constantly elevated expression of circadian target genes. All these
                            mutants demonstrate disruption of rhythmic pattern of locomotor activity and at
                            the gene expression level [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>].
                        
                </p><p><italic>Cry1,2-/-</italic> and <italic>Clock/Clock</italic> mice were placed in novel
                            environment, similarly to experiments described for wild type and <italic>Bmal1-/-</italic>
                            animals. In contrast to <italic>Bmal1-/-</italic> mice, they did not demonstrate
                            hyperactivity in locomotion: the activity of <italic>Clock/Clock</italic> on day1 was
                            indistinguishable from that of the wild type [F[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>] = 1.77, P = 0.241], while <italic>Cry1,2-/-</italic>
                            animals were even less active [F[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>] = 3.23, P = 0.132] (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref> and 5, left
                            panels). Both <italic>Clock/Clock</italic> [F(11,55) = 13.12, P&#x0003c;0.001] and <italic>Cry1,2-/-</italic>
                            [F(11,55) = 8.02, P&#x0003c;0.001] mice showed intrasessional habituation on day1
                            similar to that of the wild type mice: distance traveled during the last 15
                            minutes decreased more than 2 fold compared to the first 15 minutes. On day2, <italic>Clock/Clock</italic>
                            mice demons-trated the level of locomotor activity indistinguishable [F[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>] =
                            3.95, P = 0.103] from that on day1.  Thus, although <italic>Clock/Clock</italic> mice
                            showed intrasessional habituation similar to wild type (both on days 1 and 2),
                            there was no intersessional habituation (no significant difference between days
                            1 and 2). These data suggest that that <italic>Clock/Clock</italic> mutant mice have
                            normal formation of the immediate memory of novel context and impaired
                            long-term memory. Locomotor activity of <italic>Cry1,2-/-</italic> mice on day2 was
                            significantly lower than on day1 (Figures 4 and 5, left) (2.0 folds, [F[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>] =
                            27.19, P = 0.003]), suggesting that <italic>Cry1,2-/-</italic> demonstrate both intra-
                            and intersessional habituation.
                        
                </p><p>While the level of horizontal activity of <italic>Clock/Clock</italic>
                            mutants was similar to the horizontal activity of wild type mice, <italic>Clock/Clock</italic>
                            mutants demonstrated elevated rearing activity [F[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>] = 7.65,  P = 0.04],
                            which was intermediate between that of wild type and <italic>Bmal1-/-</italic> animals (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref> and 5, right). In contrast with the case of locomotion (normal intarsessional
                            habituation and no intersessional habituation), there was no difference in rearing activity of <italic>Clock/Clock</italic> mutants between
                            day1 and day2 [F[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>] = 0.44, P = 0.538], and only insignifi-cant decrease in
                            rearing between the first and the last 15 min of the experiment on both days
                            (T-test P = 0.1 and P = 0.6, respectively). Rearing behavior of <italic>Cry1,2-/-</italic>
                            mice on day1 was similar to wt (with a tendency to be lower) (T-test=0.6) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>, right); however, rearing activity of <italic>Cry1,2-/-</italic> on day2 constantly
                            remained at the habituated level and was significantly lower than wt [F[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>] =
                            48.63, P&#x0003c;0.001] (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>, right).
                        
                </p><fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><title>Open field analysis of exploratory activity and habituation of <italic>Clock/Clock</italic>
                                                and <italic>Cry1,2-/-</italic> mice.</title><p> Relative locomotor and rearing
                                            activity of <italic>Clock/Clock</italic> and <italic>Cry1,2-/-</italic>  mice on days 1 and 2
                                            (normalized to the average distance/activity level on day1) (* P&#x0003c;0.05).
                                    
                        </p></caption><graphic xlink:href="aging-02-285-g004"/></fig><p>Taken together, these results demonstrate a correlation
                            between the level of activity and memory formation on one hand and transcription
                            status of the BMAL1:CLOCK complex on the other.
                        
                </p><fig id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p><bold> Exploratory
                                                    activity of wild type and circadian mutant mice.</bold> (<bold>Upper panel</bold>)
                                            Locomotor and rearing activity measured in 5 min increments during 1 hr on
                                            day1 for wt (diamonds), <italic>Bmal1-/-</italic> (squares), <italic>Clock/Clock</italic>
                                            (triangles) and <italic>Cry1,2-/-</italic> (crosses) mice. Statistically significant
                                            difference with wt activity is shown as p values. Difference between wt, <italic>Clock/Clock</italic>
                                            and <italic>Cry1,2-/-</italic> locomotor activities, and between rearing activities
                                            of <italic>Bmal1-/-</italic> vs. <italic>Clock/Clock</italic> and wt vs. <italic>Cry1,2-/-</italic> is
                                            not statistically significant. (<bold>Lower panel</bold>) Cumulative traveled
                                            distance and rearing activity on days 1 and 2; For upper panels p values of
                                            statistically significant differences between wild type and circadian
                                            mutants are indicated. For lower panels * P&#x0003c;0.05.
                                    
                        </p></caption><graphic xlink:href="aging-02-285-g005"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2_6"><title>Deficiency
                            in activity of the core circadian proteins BMAL1, CLOCK or CRY1,2 results in
                            different behavioral patterns in the open field
                        </title><p>Cumulative
                            data on locomotor and rearing activities showing significant differences
                            between the animals of all tested genotypes are summarized in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>. Thus,
                            total distance traveled by <italic>Bmal1-/-</italic> mice on both days greatly exceeded
                            the distance traveled by the wild type [day1 fold 2.8, t-test P &#x0003c;0.01; day2
                            fold 4.7, P &#x0003c;0.001], <italic>Clock/Clock</italic> [day1 fold 2.3, t-test P &#x0003c;0.01;
                            day2 fold 2.4, P &#x0003c;0.01], or <italic>Cry1,2-/-</italic> [day1 fold 3.9, t-test P
                            &#x0003c;0.001; day2 fold 6.9, P &#x0003c;0.001] animals (Figure5, left panels). <italic>Cry1,2-/-</italic>
                            mice demonstrated the lowest level of horizontal activity, while the locomotion
                            of the <italic>Clock/ </italic><italic>Clock</italic> animals was comparable to that of the wild type. Remarkably, the horizontal activity of <italic>Bmal1-/-</italic>
                            and <italic>Clock/Clock</italic> mutants remained the same on both days of the experiment, whereas wild type and <italic>Cry1,2-/-</italic>
                            animals demonstrated significant reduction in activity on day2 [wt fold 2.0
                            t-test P &#x0003c;0.02; <italic>Cry1,2-/-</italic> fold 2.1, P &#x0003c;0.01] (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>, lower
                            left). Rearing activity of <italic>Bmal1-/-</italic> and <italic>Clock/Clock</italic> animals was
                            elevated compared to wt [<italic>Bmal1-/-</italic> day1 fold 2.3, t-test P &#x0003c;0.01, day2
                            fold 4.7, P &#x0003c;0.001; <italic>Clock/Clock</italic> day1 fold 1.8, P &#x0003c;0.01, day2 fold
                            3.2, P &#x0003c;0.001] and showed no differences between the two sessions. In
                            contrast, wild type and <italic>Cry1,2-/-</italic> mice showed low rearing activity and
                            robust intra- and intersessional habituation  (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>, right panels).
                        
                </p><fig id="F6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p><bold> Circadian
                                                    mutant mice do not demonstrate anxiety phenotype.</bold> (<bold>Upper panel,
                                                    left</bold>) Average horizontal velocity for all genotypes measured during 1h
                                            on days 1 and 2.  Average velocity does not significantly differ between wt
                                            and <italic>Bmal1-/-</italic> animals; slight (~15%) but statistically significant
                                            decrease in average velocity is detected for <italic>Clock/Clock</italic> and <italic>Cry1,2-/-</italic>
                                            mice compared with wt and <italic>Bmal1-/-</italic>.  (<bold>Upper panel, right</bold>)
                                            Cumulative time spent in the center for all genotypes measured during 1 hr
                                            on days 1 and 2. (<bold>Lower panel</bold>) Time spent in the center square of
                                            the open field arena on days 1 and 2 by wt, <italic>Clock/Clock, Bmal1-/-,</italic>
                                            and <italic>Cry1,2-/-</italic> mice. *P&#x0003c;0.05.
                                    
                        </p></caption><graphic xlink:href="aging-02-285-g006"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2_7"><title>Circadian
                            mutants demonstrate normal or decreased anxiety levels in the open field
                        </title><p>The increase/decrease in the distance
                            traveled by different circadian mutants may result from either differences in
                            time spent in motion vs. rest time, or from the differences in the velocity
                            among the genotypes. However, an average velocity of animals, calculated based
                            on horizontal distance and time in horizontal motion, was mostly uniform in
                            animals of all genotypes, except for <italic>Clock</italic> and <italic>Cry1,2-/-</italic>  mice
                            that showed slight (~15%) but statistically significant reduction of speed
                            [t-test P &#x0003c;0.05] (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>, upper left). This suggests that <italic>Bmal1-/-</italic>
                            and <italic>Clock/Clock</italic> mice were in  fact longer in motion,
                            whereas <italic>Cry1,2-/-</italic> were less in motion on both days when compared to wild
                            type, rendering a hyperactivity phenotype for <italic>Bmal1-/-</italic> and <italic>Clock/Clock</italic>animals.
                        
                </p><p>High
                            locomotor and rearing activity and deficit of contextual habituation often
                            correlate with elevated level of anxiety, which can be accessed by the amount
                            of time spent in the center of the OF (a risk-taking behavior) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>]. To
                            evaluate the level of anxiety in animals of all four circadian genotypes, we
                            compared the time they spent in the central zone of the OF (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>). On day1
                            of the experiment, <italic>Bmal1-/-</italic> and wild type mice spent about 14% of the
                            time in the central zone, while the corresponding time in <italic>Cry1,2-/-</italic> and <italic>Clock/Clock</italic>
                            mice was more than two-fold higher (37% and 30% respectively [t-test P
                            &#x0003c;0.01]) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>, upper right).  The differences between the wild type and <italic>Bmal1-/-,</italic>
                            and between <italic>Clock/Clock</italic> and <italic>Cry1,2-/-</italic> animals were not
                            significant. Compared to day1, the amount of time spent in the center on day2
                            was not changed in <italic>Bmal1-/-</italic> , whereas in wild type and <italic>Cry1,2-/-</italic>
                            mice it was decreased two-fold [t-test P &#x0003c;0.01]. Interestingly, cumulative center
                            time of <italic>Clock/Clock</italic> mice on day2 showed even a tendency for increase but
                            did not reach statistical significance. Thus, none of the tested circadian
                            mutants displayed a pro-anxiety phenotype in the open field paradigm. On the
                            contrary, <italic>Clock/Clock</italic> and <italic>Cry1,2-/-</italic> demonstrated opposite, more
                            risk-taking behavior. A decrease in center time on day2 observed in wild type
                            and <italic>Cry1,2-/-</italic> mice correlates with a decrease in total locomotor and
                            vertical exploratory activity (indicative of habituation).  <italic>Bmal1-/-</italic> again
                            did not demonstrate any difference in performance between days 1 and  2, while <italic>Clock/Clock</italic>
                            mutant mice demonstrated an increase in time spent in the center.
                            Interestingly, mice of different genotypes had different patterns of the
                            risk-taking behavior. Wild type mice "took the risk" of short raids in the
                            middle of the brightly-lit arena during the first 30 min and then moved mainly
                            along the walls or sit in one of the corners (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>, middle left). <italic>Bmal1-/-</italic>
                            mice continued to move across the center during the entire session (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>,
                            lower left). Both <italic>Cry1,2-/-</italic> and <italic>Clock/Clock</italic> mice had an increase
                            in time spent in the center after first 10 min, during which they had prolonged
                            periods of sitting in the middle of the arena - a very unlikely behavior for wt
                            mice (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>, middle and lower right). These data clearly demonstrate the
                            lack of correlation between the locomotor/rearing activity and time spent in
                            the center of the open field in different circadian mutants. Thus, hyperactive <italic>Bmal1-/-</italic>
                            demonstrated "normal" level of anxiety, while both hyperactive <italic>Clock/Cl</italic>ock
                            and hypoactive <italic>Cry1,2-/-</italic> had decreased level of anxiety. Therefore,
                            hyperactivity and deficit of contextual habituation of <italic>Bmal1-/-</italic> and <italic>Clock/Clock</italic>
                            cannot be explained by the increase in the level of anxiety in these mice.
                        
                </p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s3"><title>Discussion</title><p>Decline in mental performance, including
                        deficits in memory formation, learning and adaptation to novelty are hallmarks
                        of aging. At the same time, it is well documented that the activity of the
                        circadian clock decreases with age [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>]. Reciprocal relationships between the
                        decline in the circadian clock activity and deterioration in mental performance
                        are currently a subject for active discussions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref>]. In this study we propose
                        that the activity of the circadian proteins is important for adaptation to
                        novelty, which is one of the aspects of daily interactions between an organism
                        and its changing environment. Our results demonstrate that habituation to
                        novelty is differentially altered in mice with a deficiency/mutation of the
                        core circadian genes <italic>Bmal1</italic>, <italic>Clock</italic>, or <italic>Cry1</italic> and <italic>Cry2 </italic> and
                        correlates with the transcription activity status of the BMAL1:CLOCK: [CRY1,2]  complex.
                    
            </p><p>Exploration behavior is thought to be induced by a novelty
                        detected by the hippocampus which works as a comparator of the stored spatial
                        "maps" - memory of visited places - and perception of an unknown space. As the
                        animal acquires information of the new space, a novel spatial map is generated
                        and exploratory behavior ceases (which is referred to as intrasession
                        habituation in the open field paradigm, and depends on working memory). When
                        placed in the same environment on consequent days, mice demonstrate
                        significantly reduced exploratory activity, which is interpreted as a sign of
                        acquiring of long-term memory about the place (intersessional habituation)
                        [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>]. Thus, habituation is thought to depend on short- and long-term
                        memory [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref>]. Deficiency in the intrasession habituation of <italic>Bmal1-/-</italic>
                        mice is indicative for working memory impairments. Recently, circadian
                        modulation of short-term memory was shown in Drosophila [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref>] and humans [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref>].  Severe
                        deficiency in the intersession habituation demonstrated by <italic>Bmal1-/-</italic> and <italic>Clock/Clock</italic>
                        mice both in locomotion and rearing suggests that <italic>Bmal1-/-</italic> and <italic>Clock/Clock</italic>
                        mice lack memory of the previous day experience and allows speculating that
                        transcription activity of the BMAL1:CLOCK complex is necessary for the LTM
                        formation, which requires <italic>de novo</italic> synthesis of both RNA and protein 
                        [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref>].  Importantly, LTM was shown to depend on time of the day for LTM
                        acquisition/retrieval [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref>], which may reflect daily fluctuations in BMAL1:CLOCK
                        transcription activity.  Facilitation of both intra- and intersession
                        habituation demonstrated by <italic>Cry1,2-/-</italic> mice further strengthens the role
                        of BMAL1, CLOCK and CRY1,2-associated transactivation and transrepression of
                        gene expression in memory function. Interestingly, although <italic>Cry1,2-/-</italic>
                        mice exhibit a deficit in time-place learning, which was attributed to
                        disrupted time-keeping system, no deficits were observed in learning abilities
                        of <italic>Cry1,2-/-</italic> mice in several not-time associated learning tasks [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref>].
                        Our results suggest that LTM and/or STM formation in these animals is
                        facilitated; however, more specific learning/memory tests are necessary to
                        dissect various types of memory influenced by CRY1,2 as well as other circadian
                        proteins. These observations and several recent reports indicate a close
                        connection between the activity of the circadian system and memory formation.
                        Circadian cycling was recently proposed as a mechanism for the proper memory
                        consolidation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">33</xref>], probably through the circadian oscillation of MAP kinase
                        activity reported in the mouse hippocampus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">34</xref>]. Circadian modulation of memory
                        formation has been shown for different model organisms such as Aplysia,
                        Drosophila, zebrafish and rodents; a growing body of evidence implicates the
                        circadian regulation of learning and cognitive performance in humans [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>]. More
                        data on specific roles of individual circadian proteins in different forms of
                        memory are accumulated from studies of mice with deficiencies in these
                        proteins. Thus, mice deficient in NPAS2 have
                        impaired cued and contextual fear memory [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">35</xref>]. <italic>Per2-/-</italic> mice demonstrate
                        impairment in trace fear memory, but not in cued fear memory [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>]. <italic>Per1-/-</italic>
                        mice exhibit spatial learning deficits in the radial arm maze [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>]. 
                    
            </p><p>Exposure to a novel environment is mildly stressful and
                        inherently arousing experience for mice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>]. Failure of the <italic>Bmal1-/- </italic>mice
                        to habituate within a single session could also be attributed to their
                        inability to cope with the novelty-induced stress resulting from functional
                        disruption of one or several brain modulatory systems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref>], which might be the
                        cause of hyperactivity in both locomotion and rearing in these mice. Indeed,
                        the circadian clock is involved in control of the rate-limiting enzyme in the
                        biosynthesis of dopamine - tyrosine hydrolase (TH, also known as monooxygenase)
                        expression; TH expression is reduced in <italic>Per1</italic>-deficient mice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>], whereas
                        it is greatly elevated in <italic>Clock/Clock</italic> mutants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>]. Significant
                        hyperactivity in the open field was reported for several transgenic mice with
                        disturbed dopamine regulation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">36</xref>]. Interestingly, recently was shown that
                        modulation of the hippocampus-dependent memory by attention is
                        dopamine-mediated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref>]. Further study on dopamine level and bioavailability in
                        circadian mutants will help to determine whether the observed changes in the
                        activity of circadian mutants occur through dopamine-dependent or independent
                        mechanisms. On the other hand, hyperactivity is often associated with elevated
                        anxiety [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">38</xref>]; however, the anxiety level of <italic>Bmal1-/-</italic> mice did not
                        significantly differ from the wild animals judging by the time spent in the
                        center of the arena. Importantly, hyperactivity of <italic>Bmal1-/- </italic>mice was
                        associated with novelty, because average home cage activity does not differ
                        between wt and <italic>Bmal1-/-</italic> animals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>]. In contrast, <italic>Clock/Clock</italic>
                        mutant mice exhibited the pattern of horizontal activity similar to wild type;
                        however, their rearing activity was almost two-fold higher compared with wt.
                        Horizontal locomotion correlates with cognitive component of exploratory
                        behavior, while rearing behavior is considered to reflect motivational
                        component [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref>]; together with the fact that <italic>Clock/Clock</italic> mutants spent in
                        the center of the open field arena twice more time than wt animals, these data
                        suggest that <italic>Clock/Clock</italic> mice demonstrate enhanced activity-based
                        arousal and reduced anxiety, which is in good agreement with observations made
                        by [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">39</xref>]. In sharp contrast to <italic>Bmal1-/-</italic> and <italic>Clock/Clock</italic> mutant
                        mice, <italic>Cry1,2-/-</italic> mice were less active in the open field experiments; at
                        the same time, time spent in the center of the open field arena was almost
                        three-fold higher in <italic>Cry1,2-/-</italic> mice when compared to wild type and <italic>Bmal1-/-</italic>,
                        and was comparable with that of the <italic>Clock/Clock</italic> mutants - the pattern
                        which can be interpreted as a sign of greatly reduced anxiety in these animals.
                        These observations reinforce the previously reported data on the involvement of
                        the circadian proteins in the regulation of mood [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>]. 
                    
            </p><p>ROS/RNS are important regulators of cellular signaling; any
                        misbalance can be critical for brain physiology and affect various mental
                        functions, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">40</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">42</xref>], therefore, their production and detoxification are tightly
                        controlled by the system of ROS/RNS-generating and antioxidant enzymes. Chronic
                        oxidative stress in an aging brain is one of the main reasons for
                        age-associated mental decline [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref>]. Here we show that BMAL1 deficiency
                        significantly disturbs the normal ROS level in the brain. Thus, BMAL1-dependent
                        control of ROS can be one of the potential mechanisms of the observed
                        behavioral changes of the circadian mutants. Indeed, as already has been
                        mentioned above, the circadian oscillation of MAP kinase activity in the
                        hippocampus is critical for memory formation, although the mechanisms of cyclic
                        activity of MAPK are unclear [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">34</xref>]. ROS are critical regulator of MAP kinase
                        activation and MAP kinase signaling pathway [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref>], thus, the observed circadian
                        oscillation of ROS level in the brain can be at least partially responsible for
                        the oscillation of MAPK activity.
                    
            </p><p>Using
                        experimental settings within the open field paradigm, which embraces the
                        established behavioral tests for exploration and adaptation to novelty in rodents,
                        we have found that activity of the core circadian clock proteins BMAL1, CLOCK
                        and CRY1,2 is necessary for the regulation of exploratory behavior in mice.
                        Opposite phenotypes of <italic>Bmal1-/-</italic> and <italic>Clock/Clock</italic> mutant mice on
                        one hand and <italic>Cry1,2-/-</italic> on the other suggest that the changes in the
                        novelty-induced behavior in these animals are not the result of the general
                        disruption of the circadian clock, but rather indicate that individual protein components of  the molecular clock
                        play non-identical roles in habituation. Therefore, the exploratory performance
                        depends on the mutual balance of activities of these proteins, while the
                        general regulation of these activities by the circadian clock warrants the
                        optimization of the performance. It is well documented that aging affects the
                        circadian system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>]; here we suggest that aging also affects the mutual
                        balance between circadian proteins, which in turn affects mental performance.
                        Our results suggest the involvement of the circadian proteins in
                        fundamental processes of memory formation, and
                        encourage further investigations into the role of the circadian proteins in
                        memory, learning behavior and age-associated mental decline.
                    
            </p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s4"><title>Experimental
                        procedures</title><p>
                <underline>Animals.
                </underline> <italic>Bmal1-/-</italic>mice were obtained from Dr. C.
                        Bradfield (University of Wisconsin)  [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>], <italic>Clock</italic> mutant mice were
                        obtained from Dr. J. Takahashi (Northwestern University) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>], and <italic>Cry1,2-/-</italic>knockout mice were obtained from Dr. A. Sancar (University of North
                        Carolina at Chapel Hill) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>]; details of target gene knockout strategies and
                        animal generations can be found in the above cited publications. All mutants
                        were backcrossed to C57BL/6J inbred strain (The Jackson Laboratory, Bar Harbor,   ME, USA) for 12 generations. Wild type and <italic>Bmal1-/-</italic> mice were
                        generated by breeding of <italic>Bmal1+/-</italic> males with <italic>Bmal1+/-</italic> females. <italic>Clock</italic>
                        mutants were generated by breeding of <italic>Clock/Clock</italic> males with <italic>Clock/wt</italic>
                        females, <italic>Cry1,2-/-</italic> were generated by breeding of <italic>Cry1,2-/-</italic> males
                        with <italic>Cry1+/-, Cry2-/-</italic> females. Wild type mice generated as a result of <italic>Bmal1+/-</italic>
                        breeding were used as a control for all experiments (since after 10 backcross
                        generations the line is 99% genetically identical to the recipient strain,
                        mutants (backcrossed to C57BL/6J for 12 generations) and wild type were
                        considered as congenic with C57BL/6J background).  For all experiments wild
                        type and mutant mice were randomly picked from several independent litters. 
                        Animals were maintained on a 12:12 light:dark cycle with lights on at 7:00 am,
                        on regular diet. For tissue collection animals were transferred to constant
                        darkness and tissue samples were collected with 4 hour intervals beginning
                        after 34 hours of exposure to DD, immediately frozen on dry ice and stored at -
                        80&#x000b0;C. All animal studies were conducted in accordance with the regulations of
                        the Committee on Animal Care and Use at Cleveland State University and Roswell
                        Park Cancer Institute.
                    
            </p><p>
                <underline>Open field exploration.
                </underline> A mouse was
                        placed in the bright-lit 50x50 inches Plexiglas square box, and the activity of
                        the animal was monitored with 16x16 photobeam activity system (San Diego
                        Instruments). Animal activity was recorded every 5 minutes during 1 hour on the
                        day1 and day2 (24h later), and analyzed using Open Field Software. All
                        experiments were performed with 3-4 month old male mice between 11 am and 4 pm,
                        at least 6 animals of each genotype were analyzed.
                    
            </p><p>
                <underline>RNA isolation and real-time PCR analysis.  
                </underline>Total RNA was isolated from the brain with TriZol
                        reagent (Invitrogen) according to the manufacturer's protocol. RNA quantitation
                        was performed using TaqMan real-time RT-PCR, relative mRNA abundance was
                        calculated using the comparative delta-Ct method with GAPDH mRNA as standard. Procedure
                        and primer sequence was previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>].
                    
            </p><p>
                <underline>Immunohistochemical analysis.
                </underline> Frozen brain coronal sections (10 &#x003bc;m)
                        were fixed with 4% PFA dissolved in PBS (pH 7.5) for 10 min, permeabilized with
                        0.5% Triton X-100 for 5 min. The sections were incubated with primary
                        anti-BMAL1 antibodies raised in guinea pig  followed by incubation with donkey
                        anti-guinea pig secondary antibody labeled with DyLight488 (Jackson
                        ImmunoResearch laboratories), incubated for 1 min with 
                        4'-6-Diamidino-2-phenylindole (DAPI, 300nM, Invitrogen), mounted under cover
                        slips using Fluoromount G  media (SouthernBiotech). The slides were kept in the
                        dark at +4<sup>o</sup>C until use. Microphotographs were taken with the aid of
                        Leica DMR upright microscope equipped with Princeton Instruments MicroMax 5
                        MHz-cooled CCD camera and ImagePro software.
                    
            </p><p>
                <underline>ROS
                                analysis.
                </underline> ROS levels were determined in tissue extracts using
                        ROS sensitive fluorescent dye as described elsewhere [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>]. Briefly, brain was
                        immediately frozen on dry ice and stored at -70<sup>o</sup> C until analysis.
                        After mixing with 10 volumes of homogenization buffer and normalizing by
                        protein content, brain extracts were mixed with dichlorodihydrofluorescein
                        (DCF) in homogenization buffer and incubated in the dark at 37<sup> o</sup> C
                        for 30 min. Fluorescence at 495/535nm was measured using Victor2 Wallac
                        microplate reader (Perkin Elmer). At least 3 animals were used for analysis for
                        every time point and genotype.
                    
            </p><p>
                <underline>Statistical
                                analysis.
                </underline> Six male mice of each
                        genotype were used for all experiments. Data are shown as mean + standard
                        deviation. SigmaStat software package was used for analysis. Effects of
                        genotype (circadian mutants versus wild type) and novel/familiar environment
                        (day1 versus day2) on behavioral variables collected in open field experiments
                        were tested for significance with Two Way Repeated Measures ANOVA. Bonferoni
                        t-test was used for all pairwise multiple comparison procedures. Unpaired
                        Student's t-test was used for comparison of total activities between day1 and
                        day2 for the same genotype or the same day for different genotypes. Unpaired
                        Student's t-test was used for comparison of between genotype variations in
                        relative gene expression and ROS level at different time points. P&#x0003c;0.05 was
                        considered as statistically significant.
                    
            </p></sec></body><back><ack><p>We
                        thank Yelena Kondratova for the editorial help. This work was supported by
                        start-up fund and AHA grant 0835155N to R.V.K. and NIH grants CA102522 and
                        GM075226 to M.P.A.
                    
            </p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors of this manuscript have no conflict of
                            interests to declare.
                        
                </p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cerbone</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sadile</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><article-title>Behavioral habituation to spatial novelty: interference and noninterference studies</article-title><source>Neurosci Biobehav Rev</source><year>1994</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>497</fpage><lpage>518</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7708363</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Leussis</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Bolivar</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name><article-title>Habituation in rodents: a review of behavior, neurobiology, and genetics</article-title><source>Neurosci Biobehav Rev,</source><year>2006</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>1045</fpage><lpage>1064</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16774787</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rankin</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Abrams</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Barry</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhatnagar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Clayton</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Colombo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Coppola</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Geyer</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Glanzman</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Marsland</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>McSweeney</surname><given-names>FK</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><article-title>Habituation revisited: an updated and revised description of the behavioral characteristics of habituation</article-title><source>Neurobiol Learn Mem</source><year>2009</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>135</fpage><lpage>138</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18854219</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kondratov</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name><name><surname>Kondratova</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorbacheva</surname><given-names>VY</given-names></name><name><surname>Vykhovanets</surname><given-names>OV</given-names></name><name><surname>Antoch</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><article-title>Early aging and age-related pathologies in mice deficient in BMAL1, the core componentof the circadian clock</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>2006</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>1868</fpage><lpage>1873</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16847346</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kondratov</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorbacheva</surname><given-names>VY</given-names></name><name><surname>Antoch</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><article-title>The role of mammalian circadian proteins in normal physiology and genotoxic stress responses</article-title><source>Curr Top Dev Biol</source><year>2007</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>173</fpage><lpage>216</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17338917</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Franken</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Dijk</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><article-title>Circadian clock genes and sleep homeostasis</article-title><source>Eur J Neurosci</source><year>2009</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>1820</fpage><lpage>1829</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19473235</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Abarca</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Albrecht</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Spanagel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><article-title>Cocaine sensitization and reward are under the influence of circadian genes and rhythm</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2002</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>9026</fpage><lpage>9030</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12084940</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>McClung</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sidiropoulou</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Vitaterna</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Nestler</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><article-title>Regulation of dopaminergic transmission and cocaine reward by the Clock gene</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2005</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>9377</fpage><lpage>9381</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15967985</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hampp</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ripperger</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Houben</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmutz</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Blex</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Perreau-Lenz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunk</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Spanagel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahnert-Hilger</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Meijer</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Albrecht</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><article-title>Regulation of monoamine oxidase A by circadian-clock components implies clock influence on mood</article-title><source>Curr Biol</source><year>2008</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>678</fpage><lpage>683</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18439826</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Roybal</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Theobold</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>DiNieri</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Russo</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Krishnan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Chakravarty</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Peevey</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Oehrlein</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Birnbaum</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Vitaterna</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Orsulak</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Nestler</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlezon</surname><given-names>WA Jr</given-names></name><name><surname>McClung</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><article-title>Mania-like behavior induced by disruption of CLOCK</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2007</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>6406</fpage><lpage>6411</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17379666</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gerstner</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyons</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>KP Jr</given-names></name><name><surname>Loh</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Rawashdeh</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Eckel-Mahan</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Roman</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><article-title>Cycling behavior and memory formation</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2009</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>12824</fpage><lpage>12830</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19828795</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bunger</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilsbacher</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Moran</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Clendenin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Radcliffe</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hogenesch</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradfield</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><article-title>Mop3 is an essential component of the master circadian pacemaker in mammals</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2000</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>1009</fpage><lpage>1017</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11163178</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Antoch</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Vitaterna</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilsbacher</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Sangoram</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinto</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><article-title>Functional identification of the mouse circadian Clock gene by transgenic BAC rescue</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1997</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>655</fpage><lpage>667</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9160756</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vitaterna</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Selby</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Todo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Niwa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fruechte</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hitomi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Thresher</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishikawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyazaki</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Sancar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Differential regulation of mammalian period genes and circadian rhythmicity by cryptochromes 1 and 2</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>1999</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>12114</fpage><lpage>12119</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10518585</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Harms</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kivimae</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Saez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><article-title>Posttranscriptional and posttranslational regulation of clock genes</article-title><source>J Biol Rhythms</source><year>2004</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>361</fpage><lpage>373</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15534317</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kalueff</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><article-title>Locomotory patterns, spatiotemporal organization of exploration and spatial memory in serotonin transporter knockout mice</article-title><source>Brain Res</source><year>2007</year><volume>1169</volume><fpage>87</fpage><lpage>97</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17692295</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Linster</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><article-title>Neurobiology of a simple memory</article-title><source>J Neurophysiol</source><year>2008</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>2</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18463176</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jilg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lesny</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Peruzki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwegler</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Selbach</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Dehghani</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Stehle</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><article-title>Temporal dynamics of mouse hippocampal clock gene expression support memory processing</article-title><source>Hippocampus</source><year>2010</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>377</fpage><lpage>388</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19437502</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kondratov</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name><name><surname>Shamanna</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kondratova</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorbacheva</surname><given-names>VY</given-names></name><name><surname>Antoch</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><article-title>Dual role of the CLOCK/BMAL1 circadian complex in transcriptional regulation</article-title><source>FASEB J</source><year>2006</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>530</fpage><lpage>532</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16507766</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Dragich</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kudo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Odom</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name><name><surname>Welsh</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Dell</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Colwell</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><article-title>Expression of the circadian clock gene Period2 in the hippocampus: possible implications for synaptic plasticity and learned behaviour</article-title><source>ASN Neuro</source><year>2009</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>152</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Van</surname><given-names>der Zee EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Havekes</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Barf</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Hut</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Nijholt</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerkema</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><article-title>Circadian time-place learning in mice depends on Cry genes</article-title><source>Curr Biol</source><year>2008</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>844</fpage><lpage>848</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18514517</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yankner</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><article-title>Neural mechanisms of ageing and cognitive decline</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2010</year><volume>464</volume><fpage>529</fpage><lpage>535</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20336135</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stansfield</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirstein</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><article-title>Chronic cocaine or ethanol exposure during adolescence alters novelty-related behaviors in adulthood</article-title><source>Pharmacol Biochem Behav</source><year>2007</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>637</fpage><lpage>642</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17395255</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hofman</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Swaab</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><article-title>Living by the clock: the circadian pacemaker in older people</article-title><source>Ageing Res Rev</source><year>2006</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16126012</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Neill</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><article-title>Healthy clocks, healthy body, healthy mind</article-title><source>Trends Cell Biol</source><year>2009</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>36</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19926479</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Crusio</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><article-title>Genetic dissection of mouse exploratory behaviour</article-title><source>Behav Brain Res</source><year>2001</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>132</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11682103</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>O'Keefe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>Hippocampus, theta, and spatial memory</article-title><source>Curr Opin Neurobiol</source><year>1993</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>917</fpage><lpage>924</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8124075</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lever</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Burton</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Keefe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>Rearing on hind legs, environmental novelty, and the hippocampal formation</article-title><source>Rev Neurosci</source><year>2006</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>133</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16703946</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lyons</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Roman</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><article-title>Circadian modulation of short-term memory in Drosophila</article-title><source>Learn Mem</source><year>2009</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19117913</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vandewalle</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Archer</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Wuillaume</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Balteau</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Degueldre</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Luxen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Maquet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Dijk</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><article-title>Functional magnetic resonance imaging-assessed brain responses during an executive task depend on interaction of sleep homeostasis, circadian phase, and PER3 genotype</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2009</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>7948</fpage><lpage>7956</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19553435</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Costa-Mattioli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sossin</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name><name><surname>Klann</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonenberg</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><article-title>Translational control of long-lasting synaptic plasticity and memory</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>2009</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>10</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19146809</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chaudhury</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Colwell</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><article-title>Circadian modulation of learning and memory in fear-conditioned mice</article-title><source>Behav Brain Res</source><year>2002</year><volume>133</volume><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12048177</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Sweatt</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><article-title>Rhythms of memory</article-title><source>Nat Neurosci</source><year>2008</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>993</fpage><lpage>994</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18725902</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Eckel-Mahan</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Phan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheiner</surname><given-names>ZS</given-names></name><name><surname>Storm</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><article-title>Circadian oscillation of hippocampal MAPK activity and cAmp: implications for memory persistence</article-title><source>Nat Neurosci</source><year>2008</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1074</fpage><lpage>1082</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19160506</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Estill</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Michnoff</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Rutter</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Reick</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Diaz-Arrastia</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>McKnight</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><article-title>Impaired cued and contextual memory in NPAS2-deficient mice</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2000</year><volume>288</volume><fpage>2226</fpage><lpage>2230</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10864874</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gainetdinov</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wetsel</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaber</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Caron</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><article-title>Role of serotonin in the paradoxical calming effect of psychostimulants on hyperactivity</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1999</year><volume>283</volume><fpage>397</fpage><lpage>401</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9888856</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Muzzio</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kentros</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kandel</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><article-title>What is remembered? Role of attention on the encoding and retrieval of hippocampal representations</article-title><source>J Physiol</source><year>2009</year><volume>587</volume><fpage>2837</fpage><lpage>2854</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19525568</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Belzung</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Griebel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><article-title>Measuring normal and pathological anxiety-like behaviour in mice: a review</article-title><source>Behav Brain Res</source><year>2001</year><volume>125</volume><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>149</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11682105</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Easton</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Arbuzova</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Turek</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name><article-title>The circadian Clock mutation increases exploratory activity and escape-seeking behavior</article-title><source>Genes Brain Behav</source><year>2003</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12882315</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gahtan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Auerbach</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Groner</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Segal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Reversible impairment of long-term potentiation in transgenic Cu/Zn-SOD mice</article-title><source>Eur J Neurosci</source><year>1998</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>538</fpage><lpage>544</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9749716</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hidalgo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Carrasco</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Munoz</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Nunez</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><article-title>A role for reactive oxygen/nitrogen species and iron on neuronal synaptic plasticity</article-title><source>Antioxid Redox Signal</source><year>2007</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>245</fpage><lpage>255</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17115937</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Serrano</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Klann</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><article-title>Reactive oxygen species and synaptic plasticity in the aging hippocampus</article-title><source>Ageing Res Rev</source><year>2004</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>431</fpage><lpage>443</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15541710</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Torres</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Mitogen-activated protein kinase pathways in redox signaling</article-title><source>Front Biosci</source><year>2003</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>369</fpage><lpage>391</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>