<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Anc Sci Life</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Anc Sci Life</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ASL</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Ancient Science of Life</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0257-7941</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2249-9547</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Medknow Publications &#x00026; Media Pvt Ltd</publisher-name><publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27621522</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4995859</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ASL-35-232</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0257-7941.188188</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Efficacy of <italic>Nasya</italic> (nasal medication) in coma: A case study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ramteke</surname><given-names>Rajkala S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Patil</surname><given-names>Panchakshari D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Thakar</surname><given-names>Anup B.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">Department of Panchakarma, Institute for Post Graduate Teaching and Research in Ayurveda, Gujarat Ayurved University, Jamnagar, Gujarat, India</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>1</label>Department of Pharmacology Laboratory, Institute for Post Graduate Teaching and Research in Ayurveda, Gujarat Ayurved University, Jamnagar, Gujarat, India</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold>Address for correspondence:</bold> Dr. Rajkala Shankar Ramteke, Department of Panchakarma, Institute for Post Graduate Teaching and Research in Ayurveda, Gujarat Ayurved University, Jamnagar - 361 008, Gujarat, India. E-mail: <email xlink:href="vaidyarajkala@gmail.com">vaidyarajkala@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>Apr-Jun</season><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>35</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>232</fpage><lpage>235</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; 2016 Ancient Science of Life</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 License, which allows others to remix, tweak, and build upon the work non-commercially, as long as the author is credited and the new creations are licensed under the identical terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>For emergency conditions, Ayurveda has never been given importance in recent times. However, there are certain emergency conditions where biomedicine has limitations but, Ayurveda can provide solution. Classics have many references regarding management of acute conditions like syncope, coma, episodic conditions of bronchial asthma, epilepsy, etc., In the present study, a 61 year female patient had a two year history of hypertension and was suffering with coma. She was treated with an Ayurvedic treatment modality. <italic>Nasya</italic> (nasal medication) of <italic>Trika&#x01e6d;u c&#x0016b;r&#x01e47;a</italic> (powder) for seven days, followed by <italic>dh&#x0016b;map&#x00101;na</italic> (~fumigation) with <italic>sa&#x01e45;khy&#x00101;sth&#x00101;pana</italic> (consciousness restorative) drugs for seven days was administered. The outcome of this management was appreciable, as it resulted in positive changes in Glasgow Coma Scale (GSCS) from 3 to 11.</p></abstract><kwd-group><title>KEYWORDS</title><kwd>Coma</kwd><kwd>glasgow coma scale</kwd><kwd>nasal medication</kwd><kwd><italic>Nasya</italic></kwd><kwd><italic>Sanyasa</italic></kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-1"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Ayurvedic medicines are often considered effective for treating chronic and lifestyle-related diseases only and have not been thoroughly evaluated for treating acute or terminal illnesses. In one of the published case reports it has been claimed that Ayurveda is not only effective in chronic diseases, but also effective in conditions like metastatic liver diseases where other systems of medicine are not feasible.[<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]</p><p><italic>Pa&#x000f1;cakarma</italic> is one of the specialized therapeutic applications of Ayurveda. It not only cleanses the entire bodily system but is also considered as the drug delivery method to target sites. <italic>Pa&#x000f1;cakarma</italic> has wide field of applications such as <italic>&#x0015b;odhana</italic> (purification), <italic>b&#x01e5b;hma&#x01e47;a</italic> (nourishing therapy) or <italic>&#x0015b;amana</italic> (palliative measures).[<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] And there are some procedures of <italic>pa&#x000f1;cakarma</italic> which have been specified for remedial purposes such as <italic>&#x0015b;irodh&#x00101;r&#x00101;</italic> in insomnia.[<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] <italic>Nasya</italic> (nasal medication) which is one among <italic>pa&#x000f1;cakarmas</italic>, delivers drug to the brain, thereby acting on whole body.[<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] It plays role in majority of the conditions arising due to pathologies of <italic>&#x0016b;rdhv&#x00101;&#x01e45;ga</italic> (supra clavicular region).</p><p>Coma (from the Greek <italic>Koma</italic>, meaning &#x0201c;deep sleep&#x0201d;) is a state of unconsciousness lasting for more than six hours, in which a person cannot be awakened; fails to respond normally to painful stimuli, light, or sound; lacks a normal sleep-wake cycle; and does not initiate voluntary actions.[<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]</p><p>The second most common cause of coma, which makes up about 25% of comatose patients, occurs from lack of oxygen, generally resulting from cardiac arrest.[<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] Twenty percent of comatose states result from the side effects of a stroke.[<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]</p><p>In Ayurveda <italic>sanny&#x00101;sa</italic> (coma) occurs when <italic>do&#x01e63;as</italic> get acutely aggravated due to the action of speech, mind and body. After entering the site of <italic>pr&#x00101;&#x01e47;&#x00101;yatana</italic> (<italic>elan vital</italic>) i.e. heart, they weaken the individual and bring about absolute unconsciousness in the patient.[<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] The coma does not subside without the administration of proper medicines.[<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] In the management of coma, application of nasal drops, fumigation and powders have been indicated.[<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] Caraka has brought up ten drugs for restoration of consciousness.[<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]</p><p>For an ethically bound Ayurvedic physician, it is a truly demanding condition when physician is asked for an intervention despite the known terminal condition of the patient. Caraka gives a code of action for these conditions by saying that, &#x0201c;if you don&#x02019;t intervene, one is certain to die, if you intervene however, it may be otherwise.&#x0201d;[<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]</p><p>In the present case study, one such case of hypoxic coma with three score on Glasgow Coma Scale (GGCS) was managed with Ayurvedic treatment modality. It was a challenge to give medicines to the comatose patient. Considering the condition of patient, it was decided to administer smoke of medicines as <italic>dh&#x0016b;ma nasya</italic> (nasal medication). Nasal medication with <italic>Trika&#x01e6d;u</italic> powder (<italic>pradhamana nasya</italic>) is advocated in <italic>Sanny&#x00101;sa cikits&#x00101;</italic> by Caraka and V&#x00101;gbha&#x01e6d;a.[<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref><xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] Hence a treatment methodology was planned accordingly in this patient. The patient reported a remarkable recovery in the form of coma reversal, regained sensorium along with increased muscle power.</p></sec><sec id="sec1-2"><title>CASE REPORT</title><p>A sixty one year old female patient in coma since 28.8.2010, was visited by the attending physician at the patient's residence on 22.10.1010. As per patient's attendant, patient was in Intensive Care Unit (ICU), for 28 days. Patient was thereafter discharged, maintaining Ryle's tube <italic>in situ</italic>, tracheotomy, gastric tube and oxygen inhalation along with the advice to continue physiotherapy and symptomatic treatment.</p><p>On the first day of visit (22.10.2010) at the patient's residence, the patient was spotted in coma condition, not responding to verbal or painful stimuli, not opening eyes and lacking in voluntary movement of muscles. Radiological investigations revealed acute infarct in right Middle Cerebral Artery (MCA) territory causing mass effect over frontal horn of right lateral ventricle and right cerebral sulci. Changes of diffuse cerebral cortical atrophy were seen in the form of prominent left sided cerebral sulci, cisterns and ventricular cisterns. The patient was also a known case of Hypertension and on medications (Tablet Aten 50 mg) for the last 2 years. Chest X-ray disclosed prominent broncho-vascular marking with costo-phrenic angles clear. Ultrasonography (USG Abdomen) revealed normal study, ECG was also reported normal, and other laboratory parameters were within normal limits. Bearing in mind the bad prognosis and relatively insignificant impact of the contemporary interventions made upon, an Ayurvedic intervention was opted for this case running in parallel to the biomedical interventionsalready in place.</p><p>An Ayurvedic intervention in the form of nasal medication with powder and smoke was administered simultaneously with biomedical therapies. <italic>Pradhamana nasya</italic> was performed with <italic>Trika&#x01e6d;u c&#x0016b;r&#x01e47;a</italic> (powder) [<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>], being blowed into the nostril of the patient through a tube of 15 cm length (approx. 6 <italic>a&#x01e45;gula</italic>), having openings at both ends.[<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] This was performed for seven days.</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Ingredients of <italic>Trika&#x01e6d;u C&#x0016b;r&#x01e47;a</italic> used in <italic>Pradhamana Nasya</italic></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ASL-35-232-g001"/></table-wrap><p>Afterwards, the patient was treated with inhalation of fumes[<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] from a <italic>dh&#x0016b;ma</italic> stick (<italic>A&#x01e45;gula</italic>) made up of with five drugs referred to as <italic>sa&#x01e45;khy&#x00101;sth&#x00101;pna</italic> drugs (consciousness restoring drugs) [<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>]. This procedure was followed three times in each nostril in the morning hours and continued for seven days. Vital data was recorded daily, this included readings of temperature, blood pressure, heart rate (pulse), respiratory rate, and oxygen saturation to evaluate the patient's metabolism, fluid status, heart function, vascular integrity, and tissue oxygenation. Daily assessments were done for GGCS [<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>]. First response was noticed in the form of opening of eyes on 3<sup>rd</sup> day after initiation of the Ayurvedic therapy. The patient was kept under close monitoring for the preceding days. Followup of the patient was maintained for a fortnight and on the last day of followup, the patient was reported to have GGCS-11 [<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>]. Patient started opening eyes and responding to some commands given to open mouth, close eyes, move legs.</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Ingredients of <italic>Dh&#x0016b;ma Nasya</italic></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ASL-35-232-g002"/></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Glasgow coma scale assessment of the patient before and after <italic>Nasya</italic></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ASL-35-232-g003"/></table-wrap></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec1-3"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>While describing Coma, Caraka states that when <italic>v&#x00101;ta</italic> affects the site of mind, which has already become frail it disturbs the mind and brings about unconsciousness. Similarly <italic>pitta</italic> and <italic>kapha</italic> as well disturb the mind, resulting in the unconsciousness of the individual.[<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] <italic>Trika&#x01e6d;u</italic> is mentioned in the management of coma and in powder form because of its <italic>t&#x0012b;k&#x01e63;&#x01e47;a</italic> (~sharp) tendency which may directly stimulate the brain. It may do so by entering through cribriform plate and act on neurotransmitters in the brain to stimulate the excitatory neural activity. Among all sensations, only smell and taste projects both to higher cortical areas and to the limbic system. This is the probable reason that certain odors and tastes can evoke strong emotional response. Olfactory receptors react to odorant stimuli in the same way as most sensory receptors react to their specific stimuli; a generator potential (depolarization) develops and triggers one or more nerve impulses.[<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]</p><p>Connection of nose to brain[<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] can be explained anatomically and physiologically as follows &#x02013; on each side of the nose bundles, slender unmyelinated axons of the olfactory receptors extend through olfactory foramina in the cribriform plate. These bundles of axons are termed olfactory nerves, they terminate in paired masses of grey matter in the brain called olfactory bulb which lie inferior to frontal lobes. Axons of olfactory bulb neurons extend posteriorly and form olfactory tract which projects into a region called lateral of olfactory area which is located at inferior and medial surface of the temporal lobe. Drugs administered through powder inhalation may stimulate the limbic system region and hypothalamus.</p><p>Anatomically from the lateral olfactory area, a pathway also extends to the frontal lobe directly and indirectly via thalamus. Reticular Activating System (RAS) consists of fibres that project on to the reticular formation through the thalamus to the cerebral cortex[<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] as the smoke of the drugs used in our intervention has properties like subtle and pungent, it may directly stimulate the thalamus and activate RAS which provokes higher degree of consciousness in comatose patient.</p><p>The same action is also elaborated by V&#x00101;gbha&#x01e6d;a who claims that the drugs administered through the nose will enter the brain and pacifiy the <italic>do&#x01e63;as</italic>.[<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] Consciousness restoring drugs were selected due to their action through <italic>v&#x0012b;rya</italic> (potency). All the medicines of this group have <italic>t&#x0012b;k&#x01e63;&#x01e47;a</italic>, <italic>u&#x01e63;&#x01e47;a</italic> (hot), <italic>vyav&#x00101;y&#x0012b;</italic>, <italic>vik&#x00101;s&#x0012b;</italic> properties, which may stimulate the brain. Considering all the properties of these medicines, smoke form of these medicines was used. Drugs such as <italic>Ja&#x01e6d;&#x00101;m&#x00101;&#x01e43;s&#x0012b;</italic> (<italic>Nordostachys ja&#x01e6d;&#x00101;m&#x00101;&#x01e43;s&#x0012b;</italic> DC.), <italic>Vac&#x00101;</italic> (<italic>Acorus calamus</italic> Linn.), <italic>Guggulu</italic> (<italic>Commiphora wightii</italic> (Arn.) Bhandari), <italic>Hi&#x01e45;gu</italic> (<italic>Ferula narthrex</italic> Boiss.), <italic>Br&#x00101;hm&#x0012b;</italic> (<italic>Bacopa monerri</italic> (L.) Pennell.) are proven brain stimulants.</p><p>It may be proposed that, as the route of administration, pharmacokinetics, and pharmacodynamics were entirely different, there was no drug-drug interaction between Ayurvedic and Allopathic medicines.</p><p>It is the specialty of Ayurveda that without piercing the body of patient, drug delivery can be done using different means. Generally, a person who is unable to voluntarily open the eyes, does not have a sleep-wake cycle, unresponsive to strong tactile (painful), or verbal stimuli and who generally scores between 3 and 8 on the GSCS is considered in coma.[<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] In the present case, the outcome was appreciable as patient responded and there was improvement in score. Patient opened eyes and started responding to commands. Improvement in the condition of the patient can be appraised by the statement of patient's husband that she started crying on being scolded. This marked improvement was a result of only fourteen days <italic>pa&#x000f1;cakarma</italic> therapy. This case report has been shared to provide evidence that consciousness can be regained in a comatose patient with Ayurvedic drugs, and Ayurveda can be the last ray of hope in circumstances where other systems of medicine have failed.</p><sec id="sec2-1"><title>Financial support and sponsorship</title><p>Nil.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-2"><title>Conflicts of interest</title><p>There are no conflicts of interest.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rastogi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rastogi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ayurvedic intervention in metastatic liver disease</article-title><source>J Altern Complement Med</source><year>2012</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>719</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22830973</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Paradkar</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name></person-group><source>Ashtang Hridaya of Vagbhata, Sutra Sthana; Nasyavidhi Adhyaya. Reprint Edition</source><year>2006</year><issue>Ch. 20, Ver. 1</issue><publisher-loc>Varanasi</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Chowkhamba Krishnadas Academy</publisher-name><fpage>287</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Paradkar</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name></person-group><source>Ashtang Hridaya of Vagbhata, Sutra Sthana; Gandushadividhi Adhyaya. Reprint Edition</source><year>2006</year><issue>Ch. 22, Ver. 24</issue><publisher-loc>Varanasi</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Chowkhamba Krishnadas Academy</publisher-name><fpage>301</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Paradkar</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ashtang Hridaya of Vagbhata, Sutra Sthana; Nasyavidhi Adhyaya. Reprint Edition</article-title><year>2006</year><issue>Ch. 20, Ver. 5</issue><publisher-loc>Varanasi</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Chowkhamba Krishnadas Academy</publisher-name><fpage>287</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weyhenmyeye</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallman</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group><source>Rapid Review Neuroscience</source><year>2007</year><edition>1st ed</edition><publisher-loc>Philadelphia</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Mosby, Elsevier</publisher-name><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>9</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liversedge</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirsch</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coma</article-title><source>Anaesth Intensive Care Med</source><year>2010</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>337</fpage><lpage>9</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Busl</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Greer</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hypoxic-ischemic brain injury: Pathophysiology, neuropathology and mechanisms</article-title><source>NeuroRehabilitation</source><year>2010</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20130351</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Acharya</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Charaka Samhita of Agnivesha, Sutra Sthana, Vidhishonita Adhyaya. Reprint Edition</article-title><year>2011</year><issue>Ch. 24, Ver. 44</issue><publisher-loc>Varanasi</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Chaukhambha Orientalia</publisher-name><fpage>126</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Acharya</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Charaka Samhita of Agnivesha, Sutra Sthana, Vidhishonita Adhyaya. Reprint Edition</article-title><year>2011</year><issue>Ch. 24, Ver. 42</issue><publisher-loc>Varanasi</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Chaukhambha Orientalia</publisher-name><fpage>126</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Acharya</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Charaka Samhita of Agnivesha, Sutra Sthana, Vidhishonita Adhyaya. Reprint Edition</article-title><year>2011</year><issue>Ch. 24, Ver. 46, 52</issue><publisher-loc>Varanasi</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Chaukhambha Orientalia</publisher-name><fpage>126</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Acharya</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Charaka Samhita of Agnivesha, Sutra Sthana, Shadvirechanshatashritiya Adhyaya. Reprint Edition</article-title><year>2011</year><issue>Ch. 4, Ver. 18</issue><publisher-loc>Varanasi</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Chaukhambha Orientalia</publisher-name><fpage>34</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Acharya</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Charaka Samhita of Agnivesha, Chikitsa Sthana, Udarachikitsa Adhyaya. Reprint Edition</article-title><year>2011</year><issue>Ch. 13, Ver. 176</issue><publisher-loc>Varanasi</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Chaukhambha Orientalia</publisher-name><fpage>499</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Acharya</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Charaka Samhita of Agnivesha, Sutra Sthana, Yajjapurushiya Adhyaya. Reprint Edition</article-title><year>2011</year><issue>Ch. 25, Ver. 46</issue><publisher-loc>Varanasi</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Chaukhambha Orientalia</publisher-name><fpage>133</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Paradkar</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ashtanga Hridaya of Vagbhata, Chikitsa Sthana; Madatyayadi Chikitsa Adhyaya. Reprint Edition</article-title><year>2006</year><issue>Ch. 7, Ver. 110-115</issue><publisher-loc>Varanasi</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Chowkhamba Krishnadas Academy</publisher-name><fpage>642</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Paradkar</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ashtanga Hridaya of Vagbhata, Sutra Sthana; Nasyavidhi Adhyaya. Reprint Edition</article-title><year>2006</year><issue>Ch. 20, Ver. 8</issue><publisher-loc>Varanasi</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Chowkhamba Krishnadas Academy</publisher-name><fpage>288</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Acharya</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Commentary Ayurveda Dipika of Chakrapanidatta on Charaka Samhita, Siddhi Sthana, Trimarmiya Siddhi Adhyaya. Reprint Edition</article-title><year>2011</year><issue>Ch. 9, Ver. 91</issue><publisher-loc>Varanasi</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Chaukhambha Orientalia</publisher-name><fpage>722</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Acharya</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Charaka Samhita of Agnivesha, Sutra Sthana, Vidhishonita Adhyaya. Reprint Edition</article-title><year>2011</year><issue>Ch. 24, Ver. 25-29</issue><publisher-loc>Varanasi</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Chaukhambha Orientalia</publisher-name><fpage>125</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tortora</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Grabowski</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><source>Principles of Anatomy and Physiology</source><year>1996</year><edition>8th ed</edition><issue>Ch. 16</issue><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Harper Collins College Publishers</publisher-name><fpage>454</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Acharya</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name></person-group><source>Charaka Samhita of Agnivesha, Siddhi Sthana, Trimarmiyasiddhi Adhyaya. Reprint Edition</source><year>2011</year><issue>Ch. 9, Ver. 88</issue><publisher-loc>Varanasi</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Chaukhambha Orientalia</publisher-name><fpage>722</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tortora</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Grabowski</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><source>Principles of Anatomy and Physiology</source><year>1996</year><edition>8th ed</edition><issue>Ch. 16</issue><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Harper Collins College Publishers</publisher-name><fpage>455</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group><source>Ashtanga Sangraha of Vriddha Vagbhata, Sutra Sthana; Nasyavidhi Adhyaya</source><year>2006</year><edition>1st ed</edition><issue>Ch. 29, Ver. 3</issue><publisher-loc>Varanasi</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Chowkhamba Krishnadas Academy</publisher-name><fpage>223</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><source>University of North Carolina. Chapel Hill: University and Russ Rowlett. Glasgow Coma Scale</source><year>c2000</year><date-in-citation>Last updated on 2001 Jul 30; Last accessed on 2014 Jul 08</date-in-citation><comment>Available from:
<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.unc.edu/~rowlett/units/scales/glasgow.htm">http://www.unc.edu/~rowlett/units/scales/glasgow.htm</uri></comment></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>