<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="rapid-communication" xml:lang="EN"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Biochemistry</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Biochemistry</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bi</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="coden">bichaw</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Biochemistry</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0006-2960</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1520-4995</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American
Chemical Society</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24742290</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4018079</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/bi500108s</article-id><article-categories><subj-group><subject>Accelerated Publication</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Dynamic Inhomogeneity in the Photodynamics of Cyanobacterial
Phytochrome Cph1</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath1"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Peter
W.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">&#x02020;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath2"><name><surname>Rockwell</surname><given-names>Nathan C.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">&#x02021;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath3"><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>Shelley S.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">&#x02021;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath4"><name><surname>Lagarias</surname><given-names>J. Clark</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">&#x02021;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="ath5"><name><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>Delmar S.</given-names></name><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="other">*</xref><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">&#x02020;</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><sup>&#x02020;</sup>Department of Chemistry and <sup>&#x02021;</sup>Department of Molecular Cellular Biology, <institution>University of California at Davis</institution>, One Shields Avenue, Davis, California 95616, <country>United States</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Department of Chemistry, University
of California at Davis, Davis, CA 95616. E-mail: <email>dlarsen@ucdavis.edu</email>. Telephone: <phone>(530) 754-9075</phone>.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>17</day><month>04</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>17</day><month>04</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>06</day><month>05</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>53</volume><issue>17</issue><fpage>2818</fpage><lpage>2826</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>01</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>17</day><month>04</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2014 American Chemical Society</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><copyright-holder>American Chemical Society</copyright-holder></permissions><abstract><p content-type="toc-graphic"><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="bi-2014-00108s_0007" id="ab-tgr1"/></p><p>Phytochromes
are widespread red/far-red photosensory proteins well
known as critical regulators of photomorphogenesis in plants. It is
often assumed that natural selection would have optimized the light
sensing efficiency of phytochromes to minimize nonproductive photochemical
deexcitation pathways. Surprisingly, the quantum efficiency for the
forward P<sub>r</sub>-to-P<sub>fr</sub> photoconversion of phytochromes
seldom exceeds 15%, a value very much lower than that of animal rhodopsins.
Exploiting ultrafast excitation wavelength- and temperature-dependent
transient absorption spectroscopy, we resolve multiple pathways within
the ultrafast photodynamics of the N-terminal PAS-GAF-PHY photosensory
core module of cyanobacterial phytochrome Cph1 (termed Cph1&#x00394;)
that are primarily responsible for the overall low quantum efficiency.
This inhomogeneity primarily reflects a long-lived fluorescent subpopulation
that exists in equilibrium with a spectrally distinct, photoactive
subpopulation. The fluorescent subpopulation is favored at elevated
temperatures, resulting in anomalous excited-state dynamics (slower
kinetics at higher temperatures). The spectral and kinetic behavior
of the fluorescent subpopulation strongly resembles that of the photochemically
compromised and highly fluorescent Y<sub>176</sub>H variant of Cph1&#x00394;.
We present an integrated, heterogeneous model for Cph1&#x00394; that
is based on the observed transient and static spectroscopic signals.
Understanding the molecular basis for this dynamic inhomogeneity holds
potential for rational design of efficient phytochrome-based fluorescent
and photoswitchable probes.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement><funding-source>National Institutes of Health, United States</funding-source></funding-statement></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>document-id-old-9</meta-name><meta-value>bi500108s</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>document-id-new-14</meta-name><meta-value>bi-2014-00108s</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>ccc-price</meta-name><meta-value/></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes id="notes-1"><fn-group><fn id="d31e164" fn-type="funding-statement"><p>This work was
supported by a grant from the Chemical Sciences, Geosciences, and
Biosciences Division, Office of Basic Energy Sciences, Office of Science,
U.S. Department of Energy (DOE Contract DE-FG02-09ER16117), to both
J.C.L. and D.S.L. Partial support for protein purification was also
provided by National Institutes of Health Grant GM068552 to J.C.L.</p></fn></fn-group></notes></front><body><p id="sec1">Phytochromes are photoreceptors
first discovered in plants, where they function as critical developmental
regulators, and later found in fungi, bacteria, and algae.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref></sup> Phytochromes utilize photoisomerization of a covalently attached,
heme-derived linear tetrapyrrole (bilin) chromophore (Figure <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) to photoconvert between two states. Phytochromobilin
and phycocyanobilin chromophores are incorporated in plant and cyanobacterial
phytochromes, respectively. Both proteins possess red/far-red photocycles
in which their dark-stable, red-absorbing P<sub>r</sub> state (peak
absorption at 640&#x02013;680 nm) reversibly photointerconverts with
a metastable far-red-absorbing P<sub>fr</sub> photoproduct (700&#x02013;740
nm). Photoconversion effects structural changes that are subsequently
transduced by cellular signaling pathways. In plants, phytochromes
regulate many processes, including germination, shade avoidance, and
flowering.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref></sup> Phytochrome engineering in
crop plants thus holds great agronomic potential.</p><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Stereodiagram showing
protein&#x02013;chromophore interactions in
the Cph1&#x00394; P<sub>r</sub> state.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">20</xref></sup> The
PCB chromophore is shown with Tyr176 and Cys259, which is covalently
attached to PCB.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="bi-2014-00108s_0001" id="gr1" position="float"/></fig><p>Red/far-red photocycles
of phytochromes are well separated from
those of blue-sensing photoproteins, leading to increasing focus on
phytochromes as reporters for biological imaging and as a basis for
red-responsive modules in synthetic biology.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref>&#x02212;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref></sup> In such applications,
high quantum yields are desirable. The excited-state population generated
upon photoexcitation undergoes productive photoisomerization and fluorescence,
with quantum yields denoted by &#x003a6;<sub>photo</sub> and &#x003a6;<sub>fluor</sub>, in addition to other nonradiative deexcitation pathways.
Despite the availability of crystal structures and multiple spectroscopic
studies, our understanding of the photodynamic processes immediately
following photoexcitation does not adequately explain the observed
fluorescence and photochemical quantum efficiencies of plant and cyanobacterial
phytochromes. Photoisomerization of the bilin 15,16-double bond occurs
with a low P<sub>r</sub>-to-P<sub>fr</sub> &#x003a6;<sub>photo</sub> of &#x0003c;20% for nearly all known phytochromes, while the room-temperature
P<sub>r</sub> fluorescence yield can vary in a range of 0.1&#x02013;3%.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref>&#x02212;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref></sup> Moreover, &#x003a6;<sub>photo</sub> for phytochrome is lower than
those reported for distantly related cyanobacteriochromes that use
the same chromophore.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref>&#x02212;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref></sup> These data indicate that both &#x003a6;<sub>photo</sub> and &#x003a6;<sub>fluor</sub> reflect specific protein&#x02013;chromophore
interactions rather than an intrinsic property of bilins per se. Indeed,
in different protein contexts (e.g., the phycobiliproteins and mutant
apophytochromes), &#x003a6;<sub>fluor</sub> for PCB chromophores can
reach 100% at the expense of photochemistry.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref></sup></p><p>Excited-state decay of phytochromes is multiphasic, which
has been
interpreted in varying ways, including excited-state equilibrium,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref></sup> partial <italic>Z</italic>-to-<italic>E</italic> isomerization in the excited state,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref></sup> and excited-state proton transfer.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref></sup> Despite
support for a homogeneous P<sub>r</sub> ground state,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref></sup> ongoing studies of the cyanobacterial phytochrome Cph1
from <italic>Synechocystis</italic> sp. PCC6803 implicate its heterogeneity,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19">19</xref></sup> providing the rationale for the investigation presented here. Cph1
from <italic>Synechocystis</italic> has proven to be an excellent
model system for plant phytochromes because of its robust recombinant
expression and the availability of a crystal structure for the conserved
photosensory core module (Figure <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">21</xref></sup> The full length Cph1 protein consists of a PAS-GAF-PHY photosensory
core module (termed Cph1&#x00394;) coupled to a C-terminal histidine
kinase domain.</p><p>In Cph1, red light initiates the forward P<sub>r</sub>-to-P<sub>fr</sub> conversion, affording the primary isomerized
intermediate
(Lumi-R) on a picosecond time scale.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref22">22</xref>&#x02212;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref26">26</xref></sup> Lumi-R subsequently evolves on the ground-state electronic surface
via several spectroscopically distinct intermediates ultimately generating
the P<sub>fr</sub> signaling state on an approximately millisecond
time scale.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref28">28</xref></sup> Primary Lumi-R formation for
Cph1&#x00394; has been studied with both electronic<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref23">23</xref></sup> and vibrational<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref24">24</xref>&#x02212;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref26">26</xref></sup> transient spectroscopies,
often with contradictory conclusions. All studies resolve multiexponential
excited-state decay kinetics, typically ascribed to either complex
nonexponential dynamics arising from a single ground-state population
(the &#x0201c;homogeneous perspective&#x0201d;) or an ensemble of ground-state
subpopulations, each exhibiting single-exponential dynamics (the &#x0201c;inhomogeneous
perspective&#x0201d;). Resonant Raman intensity analysis and hybrid
quantum mechanics/molecular mechanics simulations support a homogeneous
P<sub>r</sub> state,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref29">29</xref></sup> also corroborated
by earlier pump&#x02013;dump&#x02013;probe (PDP) studies.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref24">24</xref></sup> In contrast, solid-state nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) resolved
two P<sub>r</sub> subpopulations: one structure consistent with the
known crystal structure and a second interpreted as having a modified
charge distribution and hydrogen bond network.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref30">30</xref></sup> More recent PDP experiments also implicate a heterogeneous
P<sub>r</sub> ground state for a red-absorbing cyanobacteriochrome
(CBCR).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref31">31</xref></sup> The fluorescence excitation spectrum
of the Cph1&#x00394; P<sub>r</sub> state exhibits a small but significant
blue shift relative to the absorption spectrum.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref></sup> Given that both are static measurements, this discrepancy
is consistent with a blue-shifted fluorescent subpopulation (although
it does not exclude distinct excited-state populations reflecting
isomers across a low-barrier hydrogen bond). Moreover, equilibrium
between such subpopulations could explain reversible temperature effects
on the P<sub>r</sub> absorption band that have been attributed to
thermal spectral broadening of a homogeneous population.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref></sup></p><p>Resolution of the question of P<sub>r</sub> ground-state heterogeneity
has broad implications. If understood, ground-state heterogeneity
of Cph1 not only will help reconcile conflicting interpretations of
available spectroscopic and X-ray crystallographic data (discussed
later) but also will inform our understanding of the merits and limitations
of Cph1 as a model system for plant phytochromes. Additionally, a
fluorescent subpopulation in wild-type Cph1 (WT) potentially provides
a rationale for the behavior of the fluorescent, photochemically inactive
Y<sub>176</sub>H variant of Cph1 (YH), because this mutation in both
Cph1 and plant phytochromes blue shifts the P<sub>r</sub> absorption
maximum while also greatly increasing &#x003a6;<sub>fluor</sub>. Here,
we revisit the P<sub>r</sub> photodynamics for Cph1&#x00394; using a
combination of static fluorescence, temperature-dependent static/transient
absorption, and excitation wavelength-dependent transient absorption
spectroscopies for both WT and YH. Surprisingly, WT exhibits an inverted
Arrhenius effect on excited-state decay, with faster decay occurring
at lower temperatures. Using global analysis and singular-value decomposition
(SVD), five coexisting ground-state subpopulations were resolved in
thermal equilibrium, allowing quantitative interpretation of &#x003a6;<sub>fluor</sub> and &#x003a6;<sub>photo</sub> and reconciling various independent
spectroscopic observations. Our study thus represents definitive evidence
of Cph1 P<sub>r</sub> ground-state heterogeneity at ambient temperatures
and also correlates the observed photodynamics of different coexisting
excited-state subpopulations with observed rates and yields of double-bond
photoisomerization.</p><sec sec-type="methods" id="sec2"><title>Experimental Procedures</title><sec id="sec2.1"><title>Protein Purification</title><p><italic>Escherichia coli</italic> strain LMG194 (Invitrogen) was
cotransformed with two plasmids,
pBAD-Cph1(N514)-CBD and pPL-PCB, to permit production of holo-Cph1&#x00394; <italic>in vivo</italic>. Transformed cells were selected on rich medium
(RM) plates containing 100 mg/mL ampicillin and 50 mg/mL kanamycin.
An individual colony was cultured overnight in RM (AMP50 KAN25) and
inoculated with a 1:500 ratio in 100 mL of RM. Upon reaching an optical
density (OD) of 0.5 at 600 nm, the culture was transferred to 900
mL of LB (Luria-Bertani medium or lysogeny broth) containing 50 mg/mL
ampicillin, 25 mg/mL kanamycin, and 1 mM isopropyl &#x003b2;-<sc>d</sc>-1-thiogalactopyranoside for a total expression of 6 L. After 1 h
at 37 &#x000b0;C and after the sample had been shaken at 250 rpm in a
shaker-incubator (Innova 4340 from New Brunswick Scientific), arabinose
was added to a final concentration of 0.002% (w/v) followed by incubation
for 1 h prior to a decrease in the temperature to 20 &#x000b0;C for 16
h. Subsequently, cells were harvested by centrifugation at 5000<italic>g</italic> for 10 min and stored at &#x02212;80 &#x000b0;C. The pellet
was resuspended at 1 g of wet weight/4 mL of lysis buffer A [25 mM
Hepes-Na (pH 8.0), 500 mM NaCl, and 1 mM EDTA] and 0.1% (v/v) Triton
X-100. Cells were lysed by two passes through a microfluidizer (M-110Y)
at 15000 psi, and all subsequent steps were conducted at 4 &#x000b0;C.
The crude lysate was clarified by centrifugation (35000 rpm, Ti-60
Beckman, 30 min) and applied to a 30 mL chitin column (New England
Biolabs), which was washed thoroughly with buffer A at a rate of 1
mL/min. Intein-mediated cleavage was induced by flushing the column
with 1 bed volume of elution buffer (buffer A and 1 mM dithiothreitol
and overnight incubation at 4 &#x000b0;C). Eluted fractions containing
Cph1&#x00394;(N514) were pooled and concentrated in Amicon spin prep
columns (10000 kDa cutoff) and dialyzed overnight at 4 &#x000b0;C in
1 L of buffer B [25 mM Tes-KOH (pH 8.0), 25 mM KCl, and 10% glycerol].</p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><title>Transient Absorption Measurements</title><p>The primary light
source was an amplified Ti:sapphire laser system (Spectra Physics
Spitfire Pro) that delivered 1 kHz pulses at a &#x003bb;<sub>center</sub> of 790 nm with an energy of 2.4 mJ and a 40 fs full width at half-maximum
(fwhm) duration. The laser beam was split into separate pathways for
the independent generation of the pump and probe pulses. The pump
pulses were produced by a home-built noncollinear optical parametric
amplifier (NOPA).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref32">32</xref></sup> For temperature-dependent
studies, a single NOPA generated 630 nm light with a 20 nm fwhm bandwidth
at 300 nJ/pulse. For the dual-excitation wavelength interleaved pump&#x02013;probe
(DEWI-PP), two NOPAs were used to generate 600 and 650 nm pump pulses
at a 20 nm bandwidth and powers of 300 and 200 nJ, respectively. Broadband
white-light probe pulses (300&#x02013;770 nm) were generated by focusing
a portion of the fundamental 790 nm pulses into a slowly translating
2 mm CaF<sub>2</sub> crystal. These probe pulses were mechanically
delayed with respect to the pump pulses by a computer-controlled linear
motor stage (Newport IMS 600LM), which provided a maximal delay of
7 ns.</p><p>The pump pulses were mechanically chopped at 500 Hz to
generate a Pump-ON and Pump-OFF sequence. For DEWI-PP, two choppers
mechanically chopped two excitation pulses at frequencies of 500 and
250 Hz to generate four pulse sequences (each 1 ms): Pump-1-ON/Pump-2-OFF/Probe,
Pump-1-OFF/Pump-2-ON/Probe, Pump-1-ON/Pump-2-On/Probe, and Pump-1-OFF/Pump-2-OFF/Probe.
These pulse sequences allowed nearly simultaneous (separated by milliseconds)
pump&#x02013;probe measurements of two different excitation pulses
on the same sample. Thus, the DEWI-PP approach ensures that the primary
experimental variable is the excitation energy, which was successfully
utilized previously to study excitation-dependent dynamics in carotenoids
and phytochrome-related CBCRs.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref></sup></p><p>After being temporally and spatially overlapped with the pump pulses
in the Cph1&#x00394; sample, the broadband probe light was detected
by an imaging spectrograph (Oriel MS 127) equipped with a 256 pixel
photodiode array (Hamamatsu S3901 and C7884). The resulting transient
absorption signals had an &#x0223c;100 fs temporal resolution [instrumental
response function (IRF)], estimated by the rise of the excited-state
absorption (ESA) band at 490 nm. The polarizations of pump and probe
pulses were set at 54.7&#x000b0; (magic angle) with respect to each other
to eliminate any anisotropic effects to the signals. The pump beam
size was significantly greater (3-fold) than the probe beam size at
the sample to eliminate any aberrations due to spatial chirp of pump
and probe beams, which was confirmed by dithering the pump pulse a
little to show the uniform decay of the signals.</p><p>The samples
were passed continuously through a quartz 2 mm flow
cell that was back illuminated with a 720 nm LED light source (Epitex
Inc., model L720-66-60). For temperature-dependent studies, a refrigerating
circulator (Fisher Scientific Isotemp 1016D) circulated water at 8,
25, and 40 &#x000b0;C to a custom-made bath in contact with a sample
bath in the flow system. Before an experiment, the sample was circulated
at a set temperature for 10 min to ensure temperature equilibration.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><title>SVD Analysis</title><p>The temperature-dependent absorbance spectra
of WT were analyzed with MATLAB version 7.11.0. Two SVD vectors were
extracted, and the two basis sets, photoactive and fluorescent basis,
were constructed by the linear combination of the two vectors with
a good fit. Modified Gibbs&#x02013;Helmholtz equation fitting to a
van&#x02019;t Hoff plot based on a SVD analysis concentration was simulated
by MATLAB Curve Fitting Toolbox version 3.0.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec3"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec3.1"><title>WT Cph1&#x00394;
and YH Variant Spectra Exhibit Distinct Temperature
Dependence</title><p>Fluorescence spectra for WT and YH at 25 &#x000b0;C
are both shown in Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>. WT and YH have
identical maxima at 645 and 672 nm (excitation and emission, respectively).
Consistent with previous work,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref></sup> the absorption maximum
of WT Cph1&#x00394; at 25 &#x000b0;C is significantly red-shifted relative
to the excitation maximum (Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>C, red curve).
The absorption maximum of YH at 25 &#x000b0;C is the same as the fluorescence
excitation maximum at 645 nm (Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>D, red
curve). The absorption spectra for WT and YH were both temperature-dependent;
the observed changes were fully reversible in the range from 4 to
43 &#x000b0;C (Figure S1 of the <xref rid="notes-2" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref>). As previously reported,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref></sup> WT exhibits an isosbestic
point at 600 nm with the absorption maximum blue shifting with a decrease
in temperature (Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>C, inset), approaching
that of the excitation spectrum. The absorbance also decreases in
the peak region (&#x0223c;660 nm) while increasing on the blue shoulder
at &#x0003c;600 nm. In contrast, YH exhibits a different temperature dependence
(Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>D): the peak absorbance decreases
with an increase in temperature, and the absorption maximum undergoes
a slight red shift with an isosbestic point at a much longer wavelength
(655 nm). These observations are consistent with the presence of a
blue-shifted population in the WT that is increasingly populated at
high temperatures, a population that may predominate in the fluorescent,
blue-shifted YH variant.</p><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Static measurements on the P<sub>r</sub> state
of Cph1&#x00394;.
Static fluorescence excitation (black) and emission (red) with peak
wavelengths indicated in respective color (A and B) and absorption
(C and D) spectra are shown for WT (A and C) and YH (B and D) Cph1&#x00394;.
Absorption spectra at indicated temperatures are shown; the arrow
in the inset emphasizes the spectral shifting of the peak as a function
of increasing temperature. The vertical dash indicates 645 nm.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="bi-2014-00108s_0002" id="gr2" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec3.2"><title>WT Cph1&#x00394; Exhibits
Inverted Arrhenius Excited-State Kinetics</title><p>Because the temperature
dependence of static spectra can be interpreted
many ways, we collected pump&#x02013;probe (PP) transient absorption
spectra for both WT and YH at 8, 25, and 40 &#x000b0;C using the same
excitation pulse at 630 nm (Figure <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> and Figure
S2 of the <xref rid="notes-2" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref>). PP signals
at each temperature were scaled to the initial amplitude of the 490
nm band of excited-state absorption (ESA), where other overlapping
signals such as ground-state bleach, stimulated emission, and Lumi-R
absorption are minimized or absent (Figure S2 of the <xref rid="notes-2" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref>). Data in Figure <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> are thus normalized to the initial excited-state P<sub>r</sub>*
population to allow meaningful comparison of the excited-state signals
and Lumi-R quantum yields (&#x003a6;<sub>photo</sub>). YH exhibited
an excited-state decay significantly slower than that of WT (Figure <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>), consistent with single-molecule studies of this
variant.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref33">33</xref></sup> YH exhibited standard Arrhenius kinetics,
i.e., faster excited-state decay at elevated temperatures. WT instead
exhibited inverted Arrhenius kinetics, with slower excited-state decay
at elevated temperatures. Inverse temperature effects have previously
been described for photoactive proteins. For example, proton dissociation
in GFP<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref34">34</xref></sup> and the adduct formation reaction
in the flavin-based blue light sensors of the LOV (light, oxygen,
voltage) family<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref35">35</xref></sup> show slower kinetics
at elevated temperatures. For these proteins, an apparent transition
temperature that separates regimes with positive and negative activation
energies was observed.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref36">36</xref></sup> These observations
support conformational transitions that activate or deactivate certain
reaction pathways, which imply the existence of a heterogeneous mixture
of conformations near the transition temperature.</p><fig id="fig3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Temperature-dependent
PP spectroscopy. PP experiments were performed
at 8, 25, and 40 &#x000b0;C (blue, green, and red, respectively). (A
and C) Kinetic traces are shown at 490 nm for WT and YH Cph1&#x00394;.
Arrows indicate the trend with an increase in temperature. These kinetic
traces are fit with respective global analysis models (Figure <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> and Figure S4I&#x02013;L of the <xref rid="notes-2" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref>). (B) Comparison of early (at 1 ps)
and later (scaled by 5.5-fold, at 110, 150, and 200 ps for 8, 25,
and 40 &#x000b0;C, respectively) transient spectra of WT. (D) Comparison
between the 25 &#x000b0;C WT and Y<sub>176</sub>H transient spectra at
150 ps, with a difference between them (gray) compared to Lumi-R (magenta).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="bi-2014-00108s_0003" id="gr3" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec3.3"><title>Excited-State Decay of
the YH Variant Matches That of a WT Subpopulation</title><p>We employed
a two-step procedure to analyze the transient data.
First, we decomposed the temperature-dependent PP signals for both
proteins using global analysis with a sequential model (Figures S3
and S4 of the <xref rid="notes-2" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref>).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref37">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref38">38</xref></sup> In the second step, global analysis using a target model to describe
the underlying populations was conducted following further data collection
(see below). The sequential model analyzed PP signals by extracting
a finite number of exponentially decaying and sequentially interconverting
spectral components with fixed difference spectra (evolution-associated
difference spectrum or EADS, termed wtEADS and yhEADS for WT and YH,
respectively). Good fitting of the WT and YH signals at each temperature
required seven and four populations, respectively (wtEADS1&#x02013;wtEADS7
and yhEASD1&#x02013;yhEADS4, respectively). At 25 &#x000b0;C, WT exhibited
multiexponential dynamics with relaxation times (&#x003c4;) of 120 fs,
2.3 ps, 13 ps, 99 ps, and 800 ps and a nondecaying population (Figure
S3A&#x02013;C of the <xref rid="notes-2" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref>). YH Cph1&#x00394; also exhibited multiexponential dynamics, with
&#x003c4; values of 120 fs, 9 ps, 120 ps, and 1.6 ns (Figure S4I&#x02013;L
of the <xref rid="notes-2" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref>). Comparable,
but not identical, lifetimes were observed for the respective proteins
at other temperatures (Figures S3 and S4 of the <xref rid="notes-2" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref>).</p><p>At 1 ps, WT Cph1&#x00394; exhibited
a greater absolute amplitude from 525 to 700 nm at 8 &#x000b0;C than
at 25 and 40 &#x000b0;C signals (Figure <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>B), well
represented by wtEADS2 (Figure S4B of the <xref rid="notes-2" ref-type="notes">Supporting
Information</xref>). At later times, this difference was lost, well
represented by wtEADS4 (Figure <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>B and Figure
S4C of the <xref rid="notes-2" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref>). Thus,
temperature-dependent effects are more notable at short times and
are lost after approximately 100 ps. After 150 ps, the WT and YH signals
at 25 &#x000b0;C differed only in the 650&#x02013;750 nm region (Figure <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>D). Notably, the difference between them was identical
to that exhibited by the Lumi-R spectrum (Figure <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>D), indicating that the only difference between WT and YH
signals at 150 ps is Lumi-R formation in WT. A 1&#x02013;2% photoactivity
that is expected for YH<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref></sup> could not be
resolved in the current data. These results thus demonstrate that
the slower phases of excited-state decay in WT are spectrally equivalent
to those of the fluorescent, photochemically compromised YH variant,
which is further supported by the 8 and 40 &#x000b0;C transient signals
(Figure S3 of the <xref rid="notes-2" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref>).</p><p>On the basis of this spectral equivalence, the &#x0201c;crossover
region&#x0201d; between 580 and 630 nm can indicate the relative amplitude
of a YH-like population in WT. YH shows a consistent negative amplitude
in this region, while WT shows a positive amplitude at short times
[&#x0003c;50 ps (Figure S2 of the <xref rid="notes-2" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref>)]; therefore, a negative amplitude correlates with the depletion
of a YH-like population. Moreover, a negative amplitude also correlates
with temperature. For example, a negative amplitude at 605 nm under
the same excitation energy condition is greater at 40 &#x000b0;C than
at 25 and 8 &#x000b0;C (Figure S2F of the <xref rid="notes-2" ref-type="notes">Supporting
Information</xref>). These results provide a potential explanation
for the inverted Arrhenius effect of WT: a subpopulation with slower
excited-state dynamics similar to those of YH becomes increasingly
significant at higher temperatures.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.4"><title>WT Cph1&#x00394; Mimics the
YH Variant at Short Excitation Wavelengths</title><p>A YH-like subpopulation
in WT would be preferentially excited at
shorter wavelengths, because the YH variant is blue-shifted relative
to the WT absorption band and instead matches the WT fluorescence
excitation band (see above). We therefore undertook a dual-excitation
wavelength interleaved pump&#x02013;probe (DEWI-PP) study on both proteins
(Figure S5 of the <xref rid="notes-2" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref>). In DEWI-PP,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref></sup> two independent PP experiments
are performed simultaneously with a train of alternating excitation
pulses differing in center wavelength and/or line shape. This approach
minimizes experimental variation such as sample degradation, flow
rate, temperature, and laser stability. We used pulses centered at
600 and 670 nm (Figure <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>A) to target the putative
YH-like and WT populations, respectively.</p><fig id="fig4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>DEWI-PP of WT Cph1&#x00394;.
(A) Absorbance of WT P<sub>r</sub> overlaid
with excitation spectra at 600 and 670 nm (blue and red, respectively).
(B and C) Excitation wavelength-dependent kinetic traces at 490 and
630 nm, respectively. (D) Excitation wavelength-dependent quantum
yields of Lumi-R represented by a 695 nm probe wavelength. These kinetic
traces were fit with a global target model (Figure <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="bi-2014-00108s_0004" id="gr4" position="float"/></fig><p>WT Cph1&#x00394; exhibited pronounced
excitation wavelength dependence
in DEWI-PP (Figure S5B,C of the <xref rid="notes-2" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref>). Decay kinetics of P<sub>r</sub>* at 490 nm are distinctly slower
after initiation with 600 nm light than with 670 nm light (Figure <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>B). At 630 nm, in the crossover region, excitation
at 600 nm results in a negative amplitude that persists beyond the
experimental time scale (Figure <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>C). By contrast,
excitation at 670 nm results in an initial positive amplitude that
decays to a negative amplitude by 10 ps. At 695 nm, the peak of the
Lumi-R absorption band (Figure <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>D), excitation
wavelength-dependent quantum yield is clearly resolved, with the higher-energy
excitation at 600 nm having a &#x003a6;<sub>photo</sub> that is lower
than the lower-energy excitation at 670 nm (Figure <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>D).</p><p>The YH variant also exhibited wavelength-dependent
effects in DEWI-PP
(Figure S5H,I of the <xref rid="notes-2" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref>). For example, 670 nm excitation produced a more pronounced negative
amplitude in the region assigned to ground-state bleach and stimulated
emission. However, the excited-state decay kinetics of YH Cph1&#x00394;
exhibited negligible wavelength dependence (Figure S5J of the <xref rid="notes-2" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref>), demonstrating that the
kinetic effects observed with WT Cph1&#x00394; are an authentic property
of the protein scaffolding and are not an artifact of the DEWI-PP
experiment on the PCB chromophore.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.5"><title>Integrated Analysis of
Cph1&#x00394; Dynamics</title><p>Our studies
demonstrate that WT Cph1&#x00394; exhibits discrepant absorption and
fluorescence excitation maxima, temperature effects on absorption
spectra, inverted Arrhenius excited-state dynamics, multiphasic excited-state
decay, including a component mimicking that of the YH variant, and
excitation wavelength-dependent photodynamics. These results are consistent
with a heterogeneous P<sub>r</sub> ground state in WT Cph1&#x00394;.
We therefore used a heterogeneous target model in the second step
of data analysis. An integrated model with five subpopulations (Figure <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>) was constructed to
describe the effects of temperature and excitation wavelength within
the framework of global target analysis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref37">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref38">38</xref></sup> Target analysis extracts time-independent spectra (species-associated
difference spectra) or SADS (Figures S4E&#x02013;H and S6E&#x02013;H
of the <xref rid="notes-2" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref>) and corresponding
time-dependent concentration profiles for the constituent (sub)populations
in the model (Figure S7 of the <xref rid="notes-2" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref>). Each SADS represents the spectrum of a particular microscopic
subpopulation within the postulates of the model and its underlying
connectivity scheme. Key features of the target model are presented
below, with further details in the <xref rid="notes-2" ref-type="notes">Supporting
Information</xref>.</p><p>(1) Five subpopulations coexist in thermal
equilibrium, grouped into two spectrally distant categories: the fast-decaying
&#x0201c;photoactive&#x0201d; (P<sub>r</sub> 1 and 2) and slow-decaying
&#x0201c;fluorescent&#x0201d; populations (P<sub>r</sub> 3&#x02013;5).
For each subpopulation, the initial 120 fs decay from the sequential
model (Figure S3 of the <xref rid="notes-2" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref>) is assigned as Franck&#x02013;Condon relaxation. The latter are
spectrally and kinetically identical to those of YH Cph1&#x00394; (Figures
S4I&#x02013;L and S6I&#x02013;L of the <xref rid="notes-2" ref-type="notes">Supporting
Information</xref> for temperature-dependent and DEWI-PP signals,
respectively). While P<sub>r</sub> 1 and 2 share identical SADS (Figure
S4E&#x02013;H and S6E&#x02013;H of the <xref rid="notes-2" ref-type="notes">Supporting
Information</xref>) and are thought to have the same static absorption
spectrum, only P<sub>r</sub> 2 generates Lumi-R. Similar heterogeneity
was also observed in phytochrome-related cyanobacteriochrome NpR6012g4
photodynamics.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref></sup></p><p>(2) Each subpopulation
exhibits normal Arrhenius kinetics, with
a higher temperature inducing faster P<sub>r</sub>* decay kinetics.
The inverted Arrhenius kinetics observed in WT Cph1&#x00394; (Figure <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>A) are explained by temperature-dependent changes
in the occupation of P<sub>r</sub> subpopulations: for example, at
8 &#x000b0;C, the 630 nm pump-induced occupancies of photoactive and
fluorescent P<sub>r</sub>* populations are 73 and 27%, respectively
[P<sub>r</sub> 1 + P<sub>r</sub> 2 and P<sub>r</sub> 3 + P<sub>r</sub> 4 + P<sub>r</sub> 5, respectively (Table <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="other">1</xref>)], while they are 64 and 36% at 25 &#x000b0;C and 53 and 47% at 40
&#x000b0;C, respectively (Figure <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> and Table <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="other">1</xref>).</p><p>(3) Excitation wavelength dependence is
modeled on the basis of
the kinetic parameters obtained at 25 &#x000b0;C with the 630 nm pump
pulse by varying only the initial occupancy of P<sub>r</sub>*. For
600 nm excitation, the photoactive/fluorescent P<sub>r</sub>* population
ratio is modeled as 52/48, while for 670 nm excitation, the ratio
is 75/25 (Table <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="other">1</xref>).</p><p>(4) The model predicts
&#x003a6;<sub>photo</sub> values of 9.5 and
12% for the 600 and 670 nm excitation signals, respectively (Figure
S7D of the <xref rid="notes-2" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref> and Table <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="other">2</xref>). For 630 nm excitation, &#x003a6;<sub>photo</sub> was temperature-independent at approximately 14% (Figure S7A&#x02013;C
of the <xref rid="notes-2" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref> and Table <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="other">2</xref>). With 630 nm excitation, apparent temperature
independence arises due to offsetting factors: the photoactive P<sub>r</sub> 2 population is excited less efficiently at 40 &#x000b0;C, but
the efficiency of Lumi-R generation is higher. Lower-energy excitation
(670 nm) selectively excites more of P<sub>r</sub> 2 (Figure <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>).</p><p>(5) SADS are temperature-independent (Figure
S4E&#x02013;H of the <xref rid="notes-2" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref>). DEWI-PP SADS of WT Cph1&#x00394;
are excitation wavelength-dependent (Figure S6E&#x02013;H of the <xref rid="notes-2" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref>), likely because of an
intrinsic red-edge effect.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref39">39</xref></sup> SADS of &#x0201c;fluorescent
populations&#x0201d; from DEWI-PP signals (Figure S6G of the <xref rid="notes-2" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref>) qualitatively reproduce
DEWI-PP signals from YH Cph1&#x00394; (Figure S6I&#x02013;L of the <xref rid="notes-2" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref>).</p><fig id="fig5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Integrated target model
for both PP experiments. P<sub>r</sub> 1&#x02013;5
reflect subpopulations in thermal equilibrium, where P<sub>r</sub> 1 and 2 are red-shifted subpopulations and P<sub>r</sub> 3&#x02013;5
are blue-shifted subpopulations. The relative amplitude of initially
excited subpopulations under different experimental conditions is
indicated. Parameters for 8, 25, and 40 &#x000b0;C are colored blue,
green, and red, respectively. DEWI-PP was performed at 25 &#x000b0;C,
and occupancy parameters are color-coded as gray and black for 600
and 670 nm excitation, respectively.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="bi-2014-00108s_0005" id="gr5" position="float"/></fig><table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Initial Occupancies of Each Subpopulation
under Each Experimental Condition of Temperature and Excitation Pulse
Energy<xref rid="tbl1-fn1" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="0"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="char" char="."/></colgroup><thead><tr><th style="border:none;" align="center">&#x000a0;</th><th colspan="3" align="center" char=".">photoactive
population occupancy (%)<hr/></th><th colspan="4" align="center" char=".">fluorescent
population occupancy (%)<hr/></th></tr><tr><th style="border:none;" align="center">&#x000a0;</th><th style="border:none;" align="center" char=".">P<sub>r</sub>&#x000a0;1</th><th style="border:none;" align="center" char=".">P<sub>r</sub>&#x000a0;2</th><th style="border:none;" align="center" char=".">total</th><th style="border:none;" align="center" char=".">P<sub>r</sub>&#x000a0;3</th><th style="border:none;" align="center" char=".">P<sub>r</sub>&#x000a0;4</th><th style="border:none;" align="center" char=".">P<sub>r</sub>&#x000a0;5</th><th style="border:none;" align="center" char=".">total</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">temperature dependence (630 nm excitation)</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left: 2em;" align="left">8&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">25</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">48</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">73</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">4</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">17</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">6</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">27</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left: 2em;" align="left">25&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">16</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">48</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">64</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">8</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">21</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">7</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">36</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left: 2em;" align="left">40&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">13</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">40</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">53</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">11</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">29</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">7</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">47</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">excitation energy dependence (at 25&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C)</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left: 2em;" align="left">600 nm excitation</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">20</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">32</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">52</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">5</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">38</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">5</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">48</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left: 2em;" align="left">670 nm excitation</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">35</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">40</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">75</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">3</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">18</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">5</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">26</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl1-fn1"><label>a</label><p>The five subpopulations, P<sub>r</sub> 1&#x02013;5, are categorized as photoactive (P<sub>r</sub> 1 and
2) and fluorescent (P<sub>r</sub> 3&#x02013;5) populations.
These parameters are based on the target model from Figure <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="tbl2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Lumi-R Quantum Yields (&#x003a6;<sub>Lumi-R</sub>) under Each
Experimental Condition of Temperature
and Excitation Pulse Energy<xref rid="tbl2-fn1" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="0"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="char" char="."/></colgroup><thead><tr><th style="border:none;" align="center">&#x000a0;</th><th style="border:none;" align="center" char=".">P<sub>r</sub>&#x000a0;2 occupancy (%)</th><th style="border:none;" align="center" char=".">branching % to Lumi-R</th><th style="border:none;" align="center" char=".">&#x003a6;<sub>Lumi-R</sub> (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">temperature dependence (630 nm excitation)</td><td style="border:none;" align="center" char=".">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;" align="center" char=".">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;" align="center" char=".">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left: 2em;" align="left">8&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">48</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">29</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">14</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left: 2em;" align="left">25&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">48</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">30</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">14.4</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left: 2em;" align="left">40&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">40</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">34</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">13.6</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">excitation energy dependence (at 25&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C)</td><td style="border:none;" align="center" char=".">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;" align="center" char=".">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;" align="center" char=".">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left: 2em;" align="left">600 nm excitation</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">32</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">30</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">9.6</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left: 2em;" align="left">670 nm excitation</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">40</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">30</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">12</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl2-fn1"><label>a</label><p>The branching ratio is calculated
based on &#x003c4; (P<sub>r</sub> 2* &#x02192; P<sub>r</sub> 2) and &#x003c4;
(P<sub>r</sub> 2* &#x02192; Lumi-R) in Figure <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>. The &#x003a6;<sub>Lumi-R</sub> is calculated by P<sub>r</sub> 2 occupancy &#x000d7; branching % to Lumi-R.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The resulting model provides a good fit to both temperature-dependent
PP signals and DEWI-PP signals (Figures S2 and S5 of the <xref rid="notes-2" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref>). For example, the wtEADS6
derived from sequential analysis (corresponding to Lumi-R formation)
showed a slight discrepancy in the Lumi-R peak wavelength for the
two DEWI-PP data sets (Figure S6D of the <xref rid="notes-2" ref-type="notes">Supporting
Information</xref>). Such a discrepancy is not seen for the Lumi-R
SADS from the target model (Figure S6H of the <xref rid="notes-2" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref>). Moreover, the target model correctly
predicts the inverse Arrhenius effect (Figure <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>), excitation wavelength-dependent kinetics (Figure <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>), and excitation wavelength-dependent quantum yield (Figure <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec3.6"><title>Modeling the Inverted Arrhenius Effect</title><p>The excellent
agreement of the model in fitting both the temperature-dependent and
DEWI-PP signals (Figure <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>) strongly supports
the underlying dynamic heterogeneity hypothesis. As a model describing
the behavior of the excited-state populations, it formally describes
the distribution of excited-state subpopulations generated by a given
excitation. We therefore sought similar information about the P<sub>r</sub> ground state. We applied singular-vector decomposition (SVD)
(Figure <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>) of the temperature-dependent absorption
spectra (Figure S1D&#x02013;F of the <xref rid="notes-2" ref-type="notes">Supporting
Information</xref>) to estimate the absolute ratio of ground-state
subpopulations. In analyzing the transient signals, we had postulated
that the subpopulations within the fluorescent and photoactive categories
were spectrally indistinguishable. We therefore used only two bases,
fluorescent and photoactive, in analyzing the static spectra. The
calculated fluorescent basis is blue-shifted relative to that of WT
(Figure <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>A) and is similar to that of YH (Figure <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>C), overlapping well with the WT fluorescence excitation
spectrum (Figure <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>C). The photoactive basis
is red-shifted relative to the fluorescent basis, as expected. The
temperature-dependent ground-state subpopulation partitioning obtained
from SVD is also consistent with the partitioning estimated from the
integrated model for the temperature-dependent signals (Figure <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>B). This analysis thus quantitatively reproduces
the static spectral behavior of WT Cph1&#x00394; and is consistent with
the heterogeneous target model. Moreover, the equivalent distributions
obtained for static and transient signals indicate that the heterogeneity
arises in the P<sub>r</sub> ground state and that the distribution
of ground-state subpopulations gives rise to an equivalent distribution
of excited-state subpopulations.</p><fig id="fig6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>SVD analysis of temperature-dependent
absorbance spectra of WT.
(A) Photoactive (red) and fluorescent (blue) bases representing P<sub>r</sub> 1 and 2 and P<sub>r</sub> 3&#x02013;5, respectively, are compared
to the WT absorbance spectra (black) at 25 &#x000b0;C. WT was simulated
(green) as 67% photoactive and 31% fluorescent. (B) Temperature-dependent
concentrations of photoactive and fluorescent bases were determined
for static measurements using SVD (red diamonds and blue circles,
respectively) and are compared to those estimated by temperature-dependent
PP (empty diamonds and circles). (C) The fluorescent basis (blue)
is compared to the YH absorption spectrum at 25 &#x000b0;C (black) and
the WT fluorescence excitation spectrum (magenta). (D) van&#x02019;t
Hoff plot for WT Cph1&#x00394; subpopulations extracted from SVD concentrations
from panel B. Data were fit to a standard model (orange, &#x00394;<italic>C</italic><sub><italic>p</italic></sub> = 0) and eq <xref rid="eq1" ref-type="disp-formula">1</xref> (green). The thermodynamic parameters with a standard model
fit are as follows (at 25 &#x000b0;C): &#x00394;<italic>S</italic> = 21.4
&#x000b1; 2.3 cal mol<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> K<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>, &#x00394;<italic>H</italic> = 6.76 &#x000b1; 0.68 kcal/mol, and &#x00394;<italic>G</italic> = 364 cal/mol. Parameters with a fitting according to eq <xref rid="eq1" ref-type="disp-formula">1</xref>: &#x00394;<italic>C</italic><sub><italic>p</italic></sub> = 446 &#x000b1; 53 cal mol<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> K<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>, &#x00394;<italic>S</italic> = 22.1 &#x000b1; 0.9 cal mol<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> K<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>, &#x00394;<italic>H</italic> = 7.05 &#x000b1; 0.27
kcal/mol, and &#x00394;<italic>G</italic> = 458 cal/mol.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="bi-2014-00108s_0006" id="gr6" position="float"/></fig><p>SVD analysis also allowed us to examine the subpopulation
partitioning
in the static spectra in more detail, which gave the ratio of photoactive
and fluorescent populations at each temperature, allowing derivation
of the equilibrium constant for their interconversion at that temperature.
This allows construction of a van&#x02019;t Hoff plot (Figure <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>D), which demonstrates a nonlinear relationship
of ln <italic>K</italic> versus 1/<italic>T</italic>. Such nonlinear
van&#x02019;t Hoff plots are often observed in protein folding studies
and are indicative of a change in heat capacity (&#x00394;<italic>C</italic><sub><italic>p</italic></sub>) between folded and unfolded states.
A similar interpretation can readily be applied to photoactive and
fluorescent subpopulations if one assumes that they are structurally
different. Assuming that &#x00394;<italic>C</italic><sub><italic>p</italic></sub> is constant in the temperature range being studied here and
is defined as <italic>C</italic><sub><italic>p</italic></sub>(fluorescent)
&#x02013; <italic>C</italic><sub><italic>p</italic></sub>(photoactive),
the change in the free energy for photoactive&#x02013;fluorescent interconversion
would follow eq <xref rid="eq1" ref-type="disp-formula">1</xref>:<disp-formula id="eq1"><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="bi-2014-00108s_m001" position="anchor"/><label>1</label></disp-formula>where <italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> is a
reference temperature (25 &#x000b0;C) and &#x00394;<italic>H</italic><sub>m</sub> is the change in enthalpy at that temperature.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref40">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref41">41</xref></sup> Employing the standard relationship between free energy change &#x00394;<italic>G</italic> and equilibrium constant <italic>K</italic> allows the
van&#x02019;t Hoff plot to be fit with eq <xref rid="eq1" ref-type="disp-formula">1</xref> (Figure <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>D, green curve), resulting in good agreement with
the observed data with a &#x00394;<italic>C</italic><sub><italic>p</italic></sub> of 446 cal mol<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> K<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>.
Agreement is much poorer if the data are instead fit to a standard
linear relationship with a &#x00394;<italic>C</italic><sub><italic>p</italic></sub> of 0 (Figure <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>D, orange curve). This
analysis demonstrates that the static spectra are described well by
the target model and that there is a change in heat capacity upon
fluorescent&#x02013;photoactive interconversion.</p><p>We also analyzed
the Arrhenius kinetics of the microscopic rate
constants derived from target analysis of temperature-dependent PP
studies (Figure <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). The fast relaxation process
with 120 fs is temperature-independent, consistent with Franck&#x02013;Condon
relaxation after photoexcitation. Evolution of the relaxed excited-state
subpopulations follows normal Arrhenius kinetics. Surprisingly, the
activation energies (<italic>E</italic><sub>a</sub>) show an unexpected
pattern: the fast-decaying P<sub>r</sub> 1 and 3 subpopulations have <italic>E</italic><sub>a</sub> values (2.2&#x02013;2.5 kcal/mol) greater than
those of slow-decaying subpopulations P<sub>r</sub> 2, 4, and 5 (&#x0223c;0.9
kcal/mol) (Figure S1G,H of the <xref rid="notes-2" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref>). There is thus an inverse correlation between relaxation time and
activation energy in WT Cph1&#x00394;, despite the direct correlation
between relaxation time and temperature arising from standard Arrhenius
behavior. This indicates that the observed rate constants for excited-state
decay in WT Cph1&#x00394; are largely determined by the Arrhenius pre-exponential
coefficient, <italic>A</italic>, instead of <italic>E</italic><sub>a</sub>. These data thus confirm standard Arrhenius behavior of the
microscopic subpopulations while also demonstrating that there is
not a simple correlation between excited-state decay and excited-state
activation energy.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec4"><title>Discussion</title><p>In this report, we have
characterized the forward reaction of the
model cyanobacterial phytochrome Cph1&#x00394; providing new insight
into the temperature- and excitation wavelength-dependent static and
ultrafast photodynamic properties. These studies provide compelling
support for a heterogeneous P<sub>r</sub> ground state in Cph1&#x00394;,
in which a blue-shifted, fluorescent population is in equilibrium
with a photoactive population peaking at longer wavelengths. Our results
therefore corroborate solid-state NMR<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref30">30</xref></sup> and fluorescence<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19">19</xref></sup> measurements, although such previous
studies were performed on samples held at much lower temperatures.
We also show that interconversion between these two forms of Cph1&#x00394;
is accompanied by a change in heat capacity, indicative of a structural
rearrangement with a change in buried nonpolar surface area.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref40">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref41">41</xref></sup> The &#x00394;<italic>C</italic><sub><italic>p</italic></sub> for WT
Cph1&#x00394; is significantly lower than that observed for protein
unfolding<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref41">41</xref></sup> and that observed for the pB-to-pG
transition in photoactive yellow protein (PYP), which is known to
involve a partial loss of structure.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref42">42</xref></sup> The
rearrangement of Cph1&#x00394; thus seems likely to involve a large-scale
conformational change rather than denaturation or loss of secondary
structure. Such structural heterogeneity is a challenging issue for
crystallographic analysis because of the constraints associated with
crystallization, and the potential for selection of a conformation(s)
that preferentially crystallizes.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref30">30</xref></sup></p><p>It presently is unclear whether other phytochromes show similar
behavior. Temperature dependence has been reported in static measurements;
in both oat phytochrome A<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref43">43</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref44">44</xref></sup> and the bacteriophytochrome
Agp1,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref45">45</xref></sup> effects that are somewhat similar
to those reported for Cph1&#x00394;. The temperature dependence of the
ultrafast photodynamics of plant phytochromes has not yet been analyzed.
However, previous studies of the excitation wavelength dependence
in Cph1&#x00394; have produced conflicting interpretations: an initial
PP study with single-wavelength detection produced results similar
to ours, with slower dynamics at shorter wavelengths.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref22">22</xref></sup> A more recent study by van Thor and coworkers with broadband
detection resolved sequential EADS with the same spectra trends we
report in the crossover region, although these data were interpreted
differently since they were unable to resolve the kinetic differences
the DEWI-PP approach extracts.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref23">23</xref></sup> The P<sub>r</sub> state of phytochromes has also been examined using vibrational
methods. In particular, a femtosecond resonance Raman study of Cph1&#x00394;
was interpreted in terms of complete photoisomerization on the excited-state
surface due to rapid formation of Lumi-R bands with a time constant
faster than that of excited-state decay.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref></sup> Such an interpretation requires a homogeneous population, so our
results call this conclusion into question.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref31">31</xref></sup> Similarly, Raman intensity analysis was used to model the absorption
band of Cph1&#x00394; in solution or in crystals as a single homogeneous
population.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref></sup> This analysis used values
of the homogeneous broadening constant, &#x00393;, significantly higher
than those that have been reported for other proteins, and hole-burning
experiments were not conducted to provide independent support for
this &#x00393; value. We have performed two independent ultrafast measurements,
and the successful fitting of both ultrafast inverse Arrhenius effects
and static temperature effects provides powerful additional evidence
of our target model.</p><p>In addition to its implications for the
interpretation of spectroscopic
studies, our work provides new insight into the means by which phytochromes
partition the excited-state population between fluorescence and photochemistry.
The red-shifted subpopulations must have a chromophore configuration
and/or protein&#x02013;chromophore interactions slightly different
from those of the blue-shifted subpopulations. Moreover, the difference
in heat capacity between the two categories implies the existence
of two distinct configurations of the protein. Mutations such as Y<sub>176</sub>H would thus seem to change the equilibrium between these
configurations. Such configurational heterogeneity has physiological
implications, as well. Indeed, the YH mutation in plant phytochromes
from <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> has been shown to confer light-independent
constitutive signaling phenotypes consistent with a signaling-active
protein conformation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref46">46</xref></sup> and the ability
to bind to phytochrome-interacting transcription factors in the absence
of light.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref47">47</xref></sup> Further engineering of phytochrome
will ultimately benefit from elucidation of the protein&#x02013;chromophore
interactions that determine partitioning between potentially signaling-active
and -inactive subpopulations.</p></sec></body><back><notes id="notes-2" notes-type="si"><title>Supporting Information Available</title><p>Details of global analysis
target model construction, SVD analysis fit over the full temperature
range and Arrhenius analysis based on the target model, temperature-
and excitation-dependent transient absorption data and their species-associated
spectra, with the target model concentration profile. This material
is available free of charge via the Internet at <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org">http://pubs.acs.org</uri>.</p></notes><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sifile1"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="bi500108s_si_001.pdf"><caption><p>bi500108s_si_001.pdf</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><notes id="NOTES-d2773e1521-autogenerated" notes-type="conflict-of-interest"><p>The authors declare no
competing financial interest.</p></notes><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>Dr. Mikas
Vengris (Light Conversion Ltd.) is acknowledged
for the donation of the global and target analysis software package.</p></ack><glossary id="dl1"><def-list><title>Abbreviations</title><def-item><term>Cph1&#x00394;</term><def><p>PAS-GAF-PHY photosensory
core module of Cph1</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>WT</term><def><p>wild type</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>YH</term><def><p>Y<sub>176</sub>H mutant</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CBD</term><def><p>chitin-binding domain</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CD</term><def><p>circular dichroism</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>EADS</term><def><p>evolution-associated difference spectrum</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SADS</term><def><p>species-associated
difference spectra</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DEWI-PP</term><def><p>dual-excitation wavelength interleaved pump&#x02013;probe</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ESI</term><def><p>excited-state intermediate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ESA</term><def><p>excited-state absorption</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SE</term><def><p>stimulated emission</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GAF</term><def><p>domain name derived
from cGMP phosphodiesterase/adenylyl cyclase/FhlA</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GSA</term><def><p>ground-state absorbance</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RcaE</term><def><p>regulator of chromatic
adaptation E</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NOPA</term><def><p>noncollinear optical parametric amplifier</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PAS</term><def><p>Per-ARNT-Sim</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PCB</term><def><p>phycocyanobilin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>P<sub>r</sub></term><def><p>red-absorbing ground state
of red/far-red phytochromes</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>P<sub>fr</sub></term><def><p>far-red-absorbing photoproduct state of red/far-red
phytochromes</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>&#x003a6;</term><def><p>total photocycle quantum yield</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>&#x003a6;<sub>Lumi</sub></term><def><p>quantum yield of generating
Lumi-R<sub>f</sub></p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PYP</term><def><p>photoactive yellow protein.</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit1"><name><surname>Rockwell</surname><given-names>N. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>Y. S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lagarias</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Phytochrome Structure and Signaling
Mechanisms</article-title>. <source>Annu. Rev. Plant Biol.</source>
<volume>57</volume>, <fpage>837</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>858</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16669784</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit2"><name><surname>Auldridge</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Forest</surname><given-names>K. T.</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Bacterial Phytochromes:
More Than Meets the Light</article-title>. <source>Crit. Rev. Biochem.
Mol. Biol.</source>
<volume>46</volume>, <fpage>67</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>88</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21250783</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit3"><name><surname>Franklin</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Quail</surname><given-names>P. H.</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Phytochrome Functions
in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> Development</article-title>. <source>J. Exp. Bot.</source>
<volume>61</volume>, <fpage>11</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>24</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19815685</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit4"><name><surname>Piatkevich</surname><given-names>K. D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Subach</surname><given-names>F. V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Verkhusha</surname><given-names>V. V.</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Engineering of Bacterial Phytochromes
for Near-Infrared Imaging, Sensing, and Light-Control in Mammals</article-title>. <source>Chem. Soc. Rev.</source>
<volume>42</volume>, <fpage>3441</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3452</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23361376</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit5"><name><surname>Shu</surname><given-names>X. K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Royant</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>M. Z.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Aguilera</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lev-Ram</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Steinbach</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Tsien</surname><given-names>R. Y.</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Mammalian Expression of Infrared
Fluorescent Proteins Engineered from a Bacterial Phytochrome</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>324</volume>, <fpage>804</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>807</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19423828</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit6"><name><surname>Auldridge</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Satyshur</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Anstrom</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Forest</surname><given-names>K. T.</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Structure-guided
Engineering Enhances a Phytochrome-based Infrared Fluorescent Protein</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>287</volume>, <fpage>7000</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7009</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22210774</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit7"><name><surname>Sineshchekov</surname><given-names>V. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Frances</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>White</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Fluorescence and Photochemical Characterization
of Phytochrome in De-Etiolated Pea Mutant Lip</article-title>. <source>J. Photochem. Photobiol., B</source>
<volume>28</volume>, <fpage>47</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>51</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit8"><name><surname>Anders</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>von Stetten</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mailliet</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kiontke</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sineshchekov</surname><given-names>V. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hildebrandt</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Essen</surname><given-names>L. O.</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Spectroscopic and
Photochemical Characterization of the Red-Light Sensitive Photosensory
Module of Cph2 from <italic>Synechocystis</italic> PCC
6803</article-title>. <source>Photochem. Photobiol.</source>
<volume>87</volume>, <fpage>160</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>173</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21091956</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit9"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>P. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Freer</surname><given-names>L. H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Rockwell</surname><given-names>N. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lagarias</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>D. S.</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Femtosecond Photodynamics of the
Red/Green Cyanobacteriochrome
NpR6012g4 from <italic>Nostoc punctiforme</italic>.
1. Forward Dynamics</article-title>. <source>Biochemistry</source>
<volume>51</volume>, <fpage>608</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>618</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22148715</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit10"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>P. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Freer</surname><given-names>L. H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Rockwell</surname><given-names>N. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lagarias</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>D. S.</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Femtosecond Photodynamics
of the Red/Green Cyanobacteriochrome
NpR6012g4 from <italic>Nostoc punctiforme</italic>.
2. Reverse Dynamics</article-title>. <source>Biochemistry</source>
<volume>51</volume>, <fpage>619</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>630</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22148731</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit11"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>P. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Freer</surname><given-names>L. H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Rockwell</surname><given-names>N. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lagarias</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>D. S.</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Second-Chance Forward
Isomerization Dynamics of the
Red/Green Cyanobacteriochrome NpR6012g4 from <italic>Nostoc
punctiforme</italic></article-title>. <source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source>
<volume>134</volume>, <fpage>130</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>133</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22107125</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit12"><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lagarias</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Harnessing Phytochrome&#x02019;s
Glowing Potential</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source>
<volume>101</volume>, <fpage>17334</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>17339</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15548612</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="cit13"><person-group person-group-type="allauthors"><name><surname>Glazer</surname><given-names>A. N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Phycobiliproteins</article-title>. In <source>Chemicals from Microalgae</source> (<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group>, Ed.) pp <fpage>261</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>280</lpage>, <publisher-name>Taylor &#x00026; Francis
Inc.</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit14"><name><surname>Holzwarth</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Venuti</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Braslavsky</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Schaffner</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>The Phototransformation
Process in Phytochrome. 1. Ultrafast Fluorescence Component and Kinetic-Models
for the Initial Pr &#x02192; Pfr Transformation Steps in Native Phytochrome</article-title>. <source>Biochim. Biophys. Acta</source>
<volume>1140</volume>, <fpage>59</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>68</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit15"><name><surname>Dasgupta</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Frontiera</surname><given-names>R. R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>K. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lagarias</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mathies</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Ultrafast
Excited-State Isomerization in Phytochrome Revealed by Femtosecond
Stimulated Raman Spectroscopy</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad.
Sci. U.S.A.</source>
<volume>106</volume>, <fpage>1784</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1789</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19179399</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit16"><name><surname>Toh</surname><given-names>K. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Stojkovic</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>van Stokkum</surname><given-names>I. H. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Moffat</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kennis</surname><given-names>J. T. M.</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Proton-Transfer
and Hydrogen-Bond Interactions Determine Fluorescence Quantum Yield
and Photochemical Efficiency of Bacteriophytochrome</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source>
<volume>107</volume>, <fpage>9170</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9175</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20435909</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit17"><name><surname>Spillane</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Dasgupta</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lagarias</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mathies</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Homogeneity of Phytochrome
Cph1&#x00394; Vibronic Absorption Revealed by Resonance Raman Intensity
Analysis</article-title>. <source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source>
<volume>131</volume>, <fpage>13946</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>13948</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19739629</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit18"><name><surname>Mailliet</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Psakis</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Feilke</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sineshchekov</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Essen</surname><given-names>L.-O.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Spectroscopy and a
High-Resolution
Crystal Structure of Tyr263 Mutants of Cyanobacterial Phytochrome
Cph1&#x00394;</article-title>. <source>J. Mol. Biol.</source>
<volume>413</volume>, <fpage>115</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>127</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21888915</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit19"><name><surname>Sineshchekov</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Koppel</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Esteban</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lamparter</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Fluorescence
Investigation of the Recombinant Cyanobacterial Phytochrome (Cph1&#x00394;)
and Its C-terminally Truncated Monomeric Species (Cph1&#x00394;2): Implication
for Holoprotein Assembly, Chromophore-Apoprotein Interaction and Photochemistry</article-title>. <source>J. Photochem. Photobiol., B</source>
<volume>67</volume>, <fpage>39</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>50</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12007466</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit20"><name><surname>Essen</surname><given-names>L. O.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mailliet</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The Structure of a Complete Phytochrome
Sensory Module in the Pr Ground State</article-title>. <source>Proc.
Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source>
<volume>105</volume>, <fpage>14709</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14714</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18799745</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit21"><name><surname>Lamparter</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mittmann</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gartner</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Borner</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hartmann</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Characterization of Recombinant Phytochrome from the
Cyanobacterium <italic>Synechocystis</italic></article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source>
<volume>94</volume>, <fpage>11792</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11797</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9342316</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit22"><name><surname>Heyne</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Herbst</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Stehlik</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Esteban</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lamparter</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Diller</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Ultrafast Dynamics of Phytochrome
from the Cyanobacterium <italic>Synechocystis</italic>, Reconstituted with Phycocyanobilin and Phycoerythrobilin</article-title>. <source>Biophys. J.</source>
<volume>82</volume>, <fpage>1004</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1016</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11806940</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit23"><name><surname>Fitzpatrick</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lincoln</surname><given-names>C. N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>van Wilderen</surname><given-names>L. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>van Thor</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Pump-Dump-Probe
and Pump-Repump-Probe Ultrafast Spectroscopy Resolves Cross Section
of an Early Ground State Intermediate and Stimulated Emission in the
Photoreactions of the Pr Ground State of the Cyanobacterial Phytochrome
Cph1&#x00394;</article-title>. <source>J. Phys. Chem. B</source>
<volume>116</volume>, <fpage>1077</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1088</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22098118</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit24"><name><surname>van
Wilderen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>I. P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Towrie</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>van Thor</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Mid-Infrared
Picosecond Pump-Dump-Probe and Pump-Repump-Probe Experiments to Resolve
a Ground-State Intermediate in Cyanobacterial Phytochrome Cph1&#x00394;</article-title>. <source>J. Phys. Chem. B</source>
<volume>113</volume>, <fpage>16354</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>16364</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19950906</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit25"><name><surname>van
Thor</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ronayne</surname><given-names>K. L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Towrie</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Formation of the Early
Photoproduct Lumi-R of Cyanobacterial Phytochrome Cph1&#x00394; Observed
by Ultrafast Mid-Infrared Spectroscopy</article-title>. <source>J. Am.
Chem. Soc.</source>
<volume>129</volume>, <fpage>126</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>132</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17199291</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit26"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Linke</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>von Haimberger</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Matute</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Schmieder</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Heyne</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Real-Time Tracking
of Phytochrome&#x02019;s Orientational Changes During Pr Photoisomerization</article-title>. <source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source>
<volume>134</volume>, <fpage>1408</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1411</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22229806</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit27"><name><surname>van
Thor</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Borucki</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Crielaard</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Otto</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lamparter</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hellingwerf</surname><given-names>K. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Heyn</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Light-Induced Proton Release and Proton Uptake Reactions
in the Cyanobacterial Phytochrome Cph1&#x00394;</article-title>. <source>Biochemistry</source>
<volume>40</volume>, <fpage>11460</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11471</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11560494</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit28"><name><surname>Rohmer</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Bongards</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Neugebauer</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gartner</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Matysik</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Phytochrome as Molecular
Machine: Revealing Chromophore Action during the Pfr &#x02192; Pr Photoconversion
by Magic-Angle Spinning NMR Spectroscopy</article-title>. <source>J.
Am. Chem. Soc.</source>
<volume>132</volume>, <fpage>4431</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4437</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20205422</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit29"><name><surname>Mroginski</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>von Stetten</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Escobar</surname><given-names>F. V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Strauss</surname><given-names>H. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kaminski</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Scheerer</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gunther</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Murgida</surname><given-names>D. H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Schmieder</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Bongards</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gartner</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mailliet</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Essen</surname><given-names>L. O.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hildebrandt</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Chromophore Structure of Cyanobacterial
Phytochrome Cph1&#x00394; in the Pr State: Reconciling Structural and
Spectroscopic Data by QM/MM Calculations</article-title>. <source>Biophys.
J.</source>
<volume>96</volume>, <fpage>4153</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4163</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19450486</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit30"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Psakis</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mailliet</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gartner</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Matysik</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Two Ground
State Isoforms and a Chromophore
D-Ring Photoflip Triggering Extensive Intramolecular Changes in a
Canonical Phytochrome</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci.
U.S.A.</source>
<volume>108</volume>, <fpage>3842</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3847</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21325055</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit31"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>C.-W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gottlieb</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>P. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Rockwell</surname><given-names>N. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lagarias</surname><given-names>J. C. L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>D. S.</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Reactive Ground-State
Pathways Are Not Ubiquitous in
Red/Green Cyanobacteriochromes</article-title>. <source>J. Phys. Chem.
B</source>
<volume>117</volume>, <fpage>11229</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11238</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23725062</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit32"><name><surname>Wilhelm</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Piel</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Riedle</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Sub-20-fs
Pulses Tunable Across the
Visible from a Blue-Pumped Single-Pass Noncollinear Parametric Converter</article-title>. <source>Opt. Lett.</source>
<volume>22</volume>, <fpage>1494</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1496</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18188279</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit33"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Laurence</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hollars</surname><given-names>C. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Saykally</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lagarias</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Huser</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Single-Molecule Dynamics of Phytochrome-Bound
Fluorophores Probed by Fluorescence Correlation Spectroscopy</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source>
<volume>103</volume>, <fpage>11136</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11141</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16844775</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit34"><name><surname>Agmon</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Kinetics of
Switchable Proton Escape from a Proton-Wire within Green Fluorescence
Protein</article-title>. <source>J. Phys. Chem. B</source>
<volume>111</volume>, <fpage>7870</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7878</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17569555</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit35"><name><surname>Nozaki</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Iwata</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Tokutomi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kandori</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Unique Temperature
Dependence in the Adduct Formation Between FMN and Cysteine S-H Group
in the LOV2 Domain of Adiantum Phytochrome3</article-title>. <source>Chem. Phys. Lett.</source>
<volume>410</volume>, <fpage>59</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>63</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit36"><name><surname>Zaccai</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Biochemistry:
How Soft is a Protein? A Protein Dynamics Force Constant Measured
by Neutron Scattering</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>288</volume>, <fpage>1604</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1607</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10834833</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="cit37"><person-group person-group-type="allauthors"><name><surname>Holzwarth</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Data Analysis of Time-Resolved
Measurements</article-title>. In <source>Biophysical Techniques in
Photosynthesis</source> (<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Amesz</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Hoff</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name></person-group>, Eds.) pp <fpage>75</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>92</lpage>, <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Dordrecht, The Netherlands</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit38"><name><surname>van
Stokkum</surname><given-names>I. H. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>D. S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>van Grondelle</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Global and
Target Analysis of Time-Resolved Spectra</article-title>. <source>Biochim.
Biophys. Acta</source>
<volume>1657</volume>, <fpage>82</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>104</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15238266</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit39"><name><surname>Demchenko</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The Red-Edge
Effects: 30 Years of Exploration</article-title>. <source>Luminescence</source>
<volume>17</volume>, <fpage>19</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>42</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11816059</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit40"><name><surname>Prabhu</surname><given-names>N. V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sharp</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Heat Capacity in
Proteins</article-title>. <source>Annu.
Rev. Phys. Chem.</source>
<fpage>521</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>548</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15796710</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit41"><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>A. D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>K. P.</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Protein Structure
and the Energetics of Protein Stability</article-title>. <source>Chem.
Rev.</source>
<volume>97</volume>, <fpage>1251</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1267</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11851450</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit42"><name><surname>VanBrederode</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hoff</surname><given-names>W. D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>VanStokkum</surname><given-names>I. H. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Groot</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hellingwerf</surname><given-names>K. J.</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Protein
Folding Thermodynamics Applied to the Photocycle of the Photoactive
Yellow Protein</article-title>. <source>Biophys. J.</source>
<volume>71</volume>, <fpage>365</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>380</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8804619</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit43"><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gensch</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Remberg</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gartner</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Braslavsky</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Schaffner</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>The Complexity of the Pr to Pfr Phototransformation
Kinetics is an Intrinsic Property of Native Phytochrome</article-title>. <source>Photochem. Photobiol.</source>
<volume>68</volume>, <fpage>754</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>761</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit44"><name><surname>Sineshchekov</surname><given-names>V. A.</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Phytochrome
A: Functional Diversity and Polymorphism</article-title>. <source>Photochem.
Photobiol. Sci.</source>
<volume>3</volume>, <fpage>596</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>607</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15170491</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit45"><name><surname>Njimona</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lamparter</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Temperature Effects on <italic>Agrobacterium</italic> Phytochrome Agp1</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>e25977</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22043299</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit46"><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>Y.-S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lagarias</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Light-Independent Phytochrome Signaling Mediated by
Dominant GAF Domain Tyrosine Mutants of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> Phytochromes in Transgenic Plants</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>19</volume>, <fpage>2124</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2139</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17660358</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit47"><name><surname>Galvao</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kothadia</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Haskel</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Decker</surname><given-names>P. V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Van Buskirk</surname><given-names>E. K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Photoactivated Phytochromes Interact with HEMERA and Promote Its
Accumulation to Establish Photomorphogenesis in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Genes Dev.</source>
<volume>26</volume>, <fpage>1851</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1863</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22895253</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>