<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Microbiol</journal-id><journal-title>BMC Microbiology</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2180</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">11737862</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">60989</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1471-2180-1-29</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>RNA triphosphatase is essential in <italic>Schizosaccharomyces pombe</italic> and <italic>Candida albicans</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pei</surname><given-names>Yi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>y-pei@ski.mskc.org</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schwer</surname><given-names>Beate</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>bschwer@med.cornell.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Saiz</surname><given-names>Julia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>j-saiz@ski.mskccc.org</email></contrib><contrib id="A4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>Robert P</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>r-fisherr@ski.mskcc.org</email></contrib><contrib id="A5" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shuman</surname><given-names>Stewart</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>s-shuman@ski.mskcc.org</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Molecular Biology and Cell Biology Programs, Sloan-Kettering Institute, New York, NY 10021, USA</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Department of Microbiology and Immunology, Weill Medical College of Cornell University, New York, NY 10021, USA</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2001</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>11</month><year>2001</year></pub-date><volume>1</volume><fpage>29</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2180/1/29"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>5</day><month>10</month><year>2001</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>20</day><month>11</month><year>2001</year></date></history><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2001 Pei et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd. Verbatim copying and redistribution of this article are permitted in any medium for any non-commercial purpose, provided this notice is preserved along with the article's original URL. For commercial use, contact info@biomedcentral.com</copyright-statement><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>The first two steps in the capping of cellular mRNAs are catalyzed by the enzymes RNA triphosphatase and RNA guanylyltransferase. Although structural and mechanistic differences between fungal and mammalian RNA triphosphatases recommend this enzyme as a potential antifungal target, it has not been determined if RNA triphosphatase is essential for the growth of fungal species that cause human disease.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>We show by classical genetic methods that the triphosphatase (Pct1) and guanylyltransferase (Pce1) components of the capping apparatus in the fission yeast <italic>Schizosaccharomyces pombe</italic> are essential for growth. We were unable to disrupt both alleles of the <italic>Candida albicans</italic> RNA triphosphatase gene <italic>CaCET1</italic>, implying that the RNA triphosphatase enzyme is also essential for growth of <italic>C. albicans</italic>, a human fungal pathogen.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Our results provide the first genetic evidence that cap synthesis is essential for growth of an organism other than <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> and they validate RNA triphosphatase as a target for antifungal drug discovery.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>The m<sup>7</sup>GpppN cap structure is a defining feature of eukaryotic mRNA and is required for mRNA stability and efficient translation. The cap is formed by three enzymatic reactions: the 5' triphosphate end of the nascent pre-mRNA is hydrolyzed to a diphosphate by RNA triphosphatase; the diphosphate end is capped with GMP by RNA guanylyltransferase; and the GpppN cap is methylated by RNA (guanine-7-) methyltransferase [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>].</p><p>Although the three capping reactions are universal in eukaryotes, there is a surprising diversity in the genetic organization of the capping enzymes as well as a complete divergence in the structure and catalytic mechanism of the RNA triphosphatase component in "lower" versus "higher" eukaryotic species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Metazoans and plants have a two-component capping system consisting of a bifunctional triphosphatase-guanylyltransferase polypeptide and a separate methyltransferase polypeptide, whereas fungi contain a three-component system consisting of separate triphosphatase, guanylyltransferase, and methyltransferase gene products. The primary structures and biochemical mechanisms of the fungal and mammalian guanylyltransferases and cap methyltransferases are conserved. However, the atomic structures and catalytic mechanisms of the fungal and mammalian RNA triphosphatases are completely different [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. Thus, it has been suggested that RNA triphosphatase is a promising target for antifungal drug discovery [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>].</p><p>The triphosphatase (Cet1), guanylyltransferase (Ceg1), and methyltransferase (Abd1) components of the capping apparatus are essential for cell growth in the budding yeast <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. Mutations of the RNA triphosphatase Cet1 that abrogate catalytic activity <italic>in vitro</italic> are lethal <italic>in vivo</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]; thus, it is reasonable to think that pharmacological inhibition of Cet1 function <italic>in vivo</italic> would impede cell growth. The key question is whether RNA triphosphatase is a valid drug target in other fungal species besides <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> (which is not a human pathogen) and whether a mechanism-based inhibitor of one fungal RNA triphosphatase could be expected to display broad spectrum activity against triphosphatases from other fungal species.</p><p>To address these issues, we have characterized the RNA triphosphatases of two other fungi, including the human pathogen <italic>Candida albicans</italic> and the fission yeast <italic>Schizosaccharomyces pombe</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. The fungal triphosphatases, <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> Cet1, <italic>C. albicans</italic> CaCet1 and <italic>S. pombe</italic> Pct1, belong to a new family of metal-dependent phosphohydrolases that embraces the triphosphatase components of DNA virus and protozoan mRNA capping systems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. The defining features of the metal-dependent RNA triphosphatases are two glutamate-containing motifs that are required for catalysis and comprise the metal-binding site in the crystal structure of <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> Cet1. The yeast triphosphatase has a novel tertiary structure in which the active site is situated within a topologically closed hydrophilic tunnel composed of 8 antiparallel &#x003b2; strands, which are conserved in CaCet1 and Pct1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. Mutational analysis of Cet1 has identified 15 individual side chains within the tunnel that are important for Cet1 function <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. Each of the 8 strands contributes at least one functional group to the active site. Mutational analysis of the <italic>Candida</italic> triphosphatase suggested strongly that the tunnel fold and the constituents of the active site are similar, if not identical, in Cet1 and CaCet1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>].</p><p>Here we address the critical question of whether RNA triphosphatase is essential for cell growth in fungal species other than <italic>S. cerevisiae.</italic> This is not a straw-man issue, given that <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> encodes two homologous RNA triphosphatases (Cet1 and Cth1), of which only Cet1 is essential for capping and cell viability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. We use classical genetic approaches to show that the respective genes encoding RNA triphosphatase and RNA guanylyltransferase are essential in <italic>S. pombe.</italic> Using a novel method of Enloe et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>] to test gene function in diploid <italic>C. albicans,</italic> we were unable to disrupt both copies of the <italic>CaCET1</italic> gene, signifying that RNA triphosphatase is also essential in that species, a significant human pathogen. Based on these findings, and the presence of a Cet1 homolog in the <italic>Apergillus fumigatus</italic> proteome, we conclude that RNA triphosphatase is a valid target for antifungal drug development.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>RNA Triphosphatase and RNA Guanylyltransferase are Essential in <italic>S. pombe</italic></title><p><italic>S. pombe</italic> RNA triphosphatase Pct1 is a 303-amino acid polypeptide with a homodimeric quaternary structure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. The <italic>pct1</italic><sup>+</sup> gene contains a single intron within the open reading frame [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. <italic>S. pombe</italic> RNA guanylyltransferase Pce1 is a 402-amino acid monomeric protein [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>]; there are no introns within the <italic>pce1</italic><sup>+</sup> gene. Although recombinant Pct1 and Pce1 enzymes have been purified and characterized biochemically, and shown to function in cap formation when expressed in <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>], there have been no antecedent genetic studies of the essentiality of Pct1 or Pce1 in fission yeast. Here we constructed <italic>pct1&#x00394;</italic> and <italic>pce1&#x00394;</italic> plasmids containing 5' and 3' flanking genomic sequences in which the entire triphosphatase or guanylyltransferase coding sequence was deleted and replaced by the kanamycin resistance gene [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. The <italic>pct1::kanMX</italic> and <italic>pce1::kanMX</italic> constructs were transformed separately into a diploid strain of <italic>S. pombe</italic> and chromosomal integrants containing one copy of the wild-type gene and one of <italic>pct1::kanMX</italic> or <italic>pce1::kanMX</italic> were selected on medium containing G418. Correct integration was confirmed by diagnostic PCR amplification of genomic DNA from the heterozygotes. We then sporulated the heterozygotes, dissected tetrads, and scored for spore viability and the presence of the <italic>kanMX</italic> marker. We found for both knock-outs that 20 out of 20 tetrads yielded only 2 viable spores and all of the viable haploids were G418-sensitive, i.e., none contained the <italic>pct1::kanMX</italic> or <italic>pce1::kanMX</italic> alleles. We conclude that the RNA triphosphatase and RNA guanylyltransferase genes are essential for cell growth in <italic>S. pombe.</italic></p></sec><sec><title>Plasmid-based complementation of <italic>pct1&#x00394;</italic> and <italic>pct1&#x00394;</italic></title><p>The <italic>pct1</italic><sup>+</sup> and <italic>pce1</italic><sup>+</sup> cDNAs were cloned separately into the <italic>S. pombe</italic> expression vector pREP41X (<italic>LEU2 ars1</italic><sup>+</sup>) so as to place them under the control of the <italic>nmt1*</italic> promoter. We also cloned the intron-containing chromosomal <italic>pct1</italic><sup>+</sup> gene into the same expression vector. The plasmids were introduced into heterozygous <italic>pct1</italic><sup>+</sup>/<italic>pct1::kanMX</italic> or <italic>pce1</italic><sup>+</sup>/<italic>pce1::kanMX</italic> diploids. The Leu<sup>+</sup> diploid transformants were selected and then sporulated. A random population of <italic>Leu</italic><sup>+</sup> haploids was tested for G418-resistance or sensitivity (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). We found that half of the Leu<sup>+</sup> haploids derived from a <italic>pct1</italic><sup>+</sup>/<italic>pct1::kanMX</italic> strains containing a plasmid with either the <italic>pct1</italic><sup>+</sup> cDNA or <italic>pct1</italic><sup>+</sup> gene (with intron) also contained the <italic>pct1::kanMX</italic> chromosomal allele and were resistant to G418. Similarly, half of the Leu<sup>+</sup> haploids derived from a <italic>pce</italic><sup>+</sup>/<italic>pce1::kanMX</italic> strain containing the <italic>pce1</italic><sup>+</sup> plasmid were resistant to G418. In contrast, none of the Leu<sup>+</sup> haploids derived from <italic>pct1</italic><sup>+</sup>/<italic>pct1::kanMX</italic> or <italic>pce1</italic><sup>+</sup>/<italic>pce1::kanMX</italic> strains containing the control <italic>LEU2</italic> plasmid vector lacking an insert were G418-resistant. These results show that the <italic>pct1&#x00394;</italic> and <italic>pce1&#x00394;</italic> strains are viable if the chromosomal deletions are complemented by an extrachromosomal triphosphatase or guanylyltransferase gene. There was no apparent difference in complementation of <italic>pct1&#x00394;</italic> by the intron-containing <italic>pct1</italic><sup>+</sup> gene versus the <italic>pct1</italic><sup>+</sup> cDNA.</p><p>Although the plasmid-encoded capping enzyme genes are under the control of a regulated <italic>nmt1*</italic> promoter, which can be repressed by inclusion of 5 &#x003bc;g/ml thiamine in the growth medium [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>], we observed that the growth of the plasmid-dependent strains was not affected by exogenous thiamine. We suspect that expression levels of the Pct1 or Pce1 enzymes in these strains exceeded a threshold required for cell viability.</p></sec><sec><title>Test of CaCET1 Essentiality in <italic>C. albicans</italic></title><p><italic>Candida albicans</italic> strains are diploid and do not undergo meiotic division. Thus, the classical approach of allelic disruption in diploid cells followed by sporulation and segregation analysis of haploids is not applicable to the analysis of gene function in <italic>C. albicans.</italic> Tests of gene essentiality in <italic>Candida</italic> necessitate serial disruption of both alleles using two different selection markers. If the gene of interest is nonessential, a homozygous diploid disruptant can be isolated. However, if the gene is essential, it will be impossible to disrupt both alleles. Mitchell and colleagues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>] have developed a single-transformation method to test gene function in diploid <italic>C. albicans</italic> that entails the following steps, which we have applied to the <italic>CaCET1</italic> gene encoding RNA triphosphatase [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>].</p><p>First we constructed a deletion allele plasmid containing 5' and 3' genomic sequence flanking the target <italic>CaCET1</italic> gene and an intervening marker cassette (<italic>ura3&#x00394;3'-ARG4-ura3&#x00394;5',</italic> referred to as <italic>UAU1</italic>) composed of the <italic>C. albicans ARG4</italic> gene flanked by overlapping 5' and 3' fragments of the <italic>URA3</italic> gene. This construct deletes the coding sequence for amino acids 206 to 506 of the 520-aa CaCet1 polypeptide. The deleted segment contains the catalytic domain essential for triphosphatase activity <italic>in vitro</italic> and for complementation of the <italic>cet1&#x00394;</italic> strain of <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. Second, we introduced the linearized deletion allele into a diploid <italic>C. albicans ura3/ura3 arg4/arg4</italic> strain and selected for Arg<sup>+</sup> transformants. Correct insertion via homologous recombination into one copy of the <italic>CaCET1</italic> gene, resulting in <italic>cacet1::UAU1</italic> (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>), was confirmed by Southern blotting of genomic DNA digested with diagnostic restriction endonucleases. For example, a probe specific for the 5' end of the <italic>CaCET1</italic> gene (probe A in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>) hybridized to a single 4.4 kbp <italic>Bgl</italic>II fragment after restriction digestion of total DNA from the parental diploid strain, whereas the heterozygote contained an additional 2.7-kbp fragment derived from scission at a novel <italic>Bgl</italic>II site located within the <italic>ARG4</italic> component of the <italic>UAU1</italic> insert of the disrupted <italic>cacet1::UAU1</italic> allele (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A</xref>, lane P versus lane H). The 2.7-kbp fragment was also detected with an <italic>ARG4</italic>-specific probe (not shown). We found that the heterozygous <italic>CaCET1/cacet1::UAU1</italic> strain displayed normal growth and morphology (not shown).</p><p>Third, we grew 54 independent liquid cultures of the heterozygotes in nonselective medium and then selected for cells that were Arg<sup>+</sup> and Ura<sup>+</sup>. Uracil prototrophy requires restitution of the integrity of the disrupted <italic>ura3</italic> gene of the <italic>UAU1</italic> cassette by recombination between the overlapping regions of the <italic>ura3&#x00394;3'</italic> and <italic>ura3&#x00394;5'</italic> fragments with excision of the intervening <italic>ARG4</italic> gene [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. If <italic>CaCET1</italic> were nonessential, then recombination of <italic>UAU1</italic> into the second copy of <italic>CaCET1</italic> (to generate <italic>cacet1::UAU1/cacet1::UAU1</italic>) followed by excisional recombination of <italic>ARG4</italic> in one allele to restore <italic>URA3</italic> (generating <italic>cacet1::UAU1/cacet1::URA3</italic>) would result in the selected Arg<sup>+</sup> Ura<sup>+</sup> phenotype with complete loss of the wild-type <italic>CaCET1</italic> locus. However, if <italic>CaCET1</italic> is essential for growth, then all of the Arg<sup>+</sup> Ura<sup>+</sup> isolates will have three copies of the <italic>CaCET1</italic> locus (<italic>cacet1::UAU1/cacet1:: URA3/CaCET1</italic>).</p><p>We used Southern blotting to determine the genotype of one randomly selected Arg<sup>+</sup> Ura<sup>+</sup> derivative from each of the 54 separate cultures of the heterozygote diploids. The blots were probed with a 5' specific <italic>CaCET1</italic> fragment (probe A in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>), which detects both the wild-type <italic>CaCET1</italic> allele and the <italic>cacet1::UAU1</italic> allele, and with a 3'-specific <italic>CaCET1</italic> fragment (probe B in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>) derived from the segment deleted during construction of the <italic>cacet1::UAU1</italic> disruption cassette. Note that probe A hybridized to a single 4.4-kbp <italic>Bgl</italic>II fragment in both the parental diploid strain and the heterozygote (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B</xref>, lanes P and H), thereby verifying that it did not detect the disrupted allele. We found that 54/54 Arg<sup>+</sup> Ura<sup>+</sup> isolates retained the wild-type <italic>CaCET1</italic> locus (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> and data not shown), implying that <italic>CaCET1</italic> is an essential gene. All 54 isolates also retained the <italic>cacet1::UAU1</italic> allele that was present in the heterozygote (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A</xref> and data not shown) and they acquired a new ~5-kbp <italic>Bgl</italic>II fragment that hybridized to 5'-specific <italic>CaCET1</italic> probe (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A</xref> and data not shown). The novel <italic>Bgl</italic>II fragment migrated identically in 53/54 of the strains analyzed. Recombination within <italic>UAU1</italic> to regenerate <italic>URA3</italic> eliminates the <italic>Bgl</italic>II site and results in a <italic>cacet1::URA3</italic> locus that would yield an ~5-kbp fragment upon digestion with <italic>Bgl</italic>II (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). Therefore, we surmise that the vast majority of the events leading to the Arg<sup>+</sup> Ura<sup>+</sup> phenotype entailed allelic triplications. This conclusion is supported by additional Southern analyses of <italic>Sca</italic>I digests and <italic>Eco</italic>RI/<italic>Pst</italic>I digests of genomic DNA from the parental diploid, the heterozygotes, and the 54 Arg<sup>+</sup> Ura<sup>+</sup> segregants (data not shown).</p><p>We conducted in parallel an analysis of the function of the <italic>C. albicans CES1/ZDS1</italic> gene, which encodes a protein homologous to the product of the <italic>S. cerevisiae CES1/ZDS1</italic> gene isolated by us and others in various suppressor screens [[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>] and references therein]. We found that 3/26 Arg<sup>+</sup> Ura<sup>+</sup> segregants emanating from a <italic>CES1/ces1::UAU1</italic> heterozygote were homozygous for disruption at both loci (<italic>ces1::UAU1/ces1::URA3</italic>) and had lost the wild-type <italic>CES1/ZDS1</italic> allele [B. Schwer, unpublished]. This frequency of homozygosity at a nonessential locus is similar to that reported by Mitchell's group (2 out of 30) for homozygous disruption of the <italic>C. albicans CDC25</italic> gene [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. These results confirm that the single-transformation test can, in our hands, be used to identify a nonessential gene and they underscore the inference from the data presented here that RNA triphosphatase is essential for growth of <italic>C. albicans.</italic></p></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>Previous genetic analyses establishing the essentiality of cap formation were performed in the budding yeast <italic>S. cerevisiae.</italic> It remained to be seen whether the homologs from other fungal species are also essential for viability. It is not a foregone conclusion that essentiality or dispensability of a gene product in <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> can be extrapolated to pathogenic fungi. For example, Cdc25 is not essential in <italic>C. albicans</italic> whereas its homolog is essential in <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. Conversely, the enzyme DNA topoisomerase I is nonessential in <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> and <italic>S. pombe,</italic> but essential for viability in the pathogenic fungus <italic>Cryptococcus neoformans</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>].</p><p>Here we have shown that the RNA triphosphatases Pct1 and CaCet1 are essential for viability of <italic>S. pombe</italic> and <italic>C. albicans,</italic> respectively The conclusion that CaCet1 is essential is based on a finding that none of the 54 independent isolates in the single-transformation test were homozygous for <italic>cacet1&#x00394;;</italic> our interpretation is consistent with criteria established by Mitchell and colleagues for inference of essentiality using this genetic approach. De Backer et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>] had previously generated a single allele knockout in <italic>C. albicans</italic> of the guanylyltransferase component of the capping apparatus (Cgt1) using the URA-blaster technique and noted a variety of pleiotrophic effects on stress response, hygromycin sensitivity, and colony morphology in the <italic>CGT1/cgt1&#x00394;</italic> heterozygote, but they found that the heterozygote was just as virulent as the wild-type strain in animal models of systemic candidiasis. They were unable to recover a homozygous <italic>cgt1&#x00394;/cgt1&#x00394;</italic> isolate after a second transformation with the <italic>URA3</italic> disruption cassette after testing 13 transformants. Although their sample size was not large, their data, together with the present findings, indicate that the triphosphatase and guanylyltransferase are both essential for viability of <italic>C. albicans.</italic></p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>RNA triphosphatase is an attractive therapeutic target for fungal infections because: (i) the active site structure and catalytic mechanism of fungal RNA triphosphatase are completely different from the RNA triphosphatase domain of the metazoan capping enzyme and (ii) metazoans encode no identifiable homologs of the fungal RNA triphosphatases. Thus, a mechanism-based inhibitor of fungal RNA triphosphatase should be highly selective for the fungal pathogen and have minimal effect on the human or animal host. This scenario is plausible <italic>only</italic> if RNA triphosphatase is essential for growth of pathogenic fungi that cause human disease (e.g., <italic>Candida albicans, Aspergillus fumigatus, Cryptococcus neoformans, Pneumocystis carinii,</italic> etc.). The finding that the RNA triphosphatase CaCet1 is essential in the pathogenic fungus <italic>C. albicans</italic> provides impetus for the discovery of compounds that inhibit CaCet1 activity. Searches of public genome databases indicate that <italic>Aspergillus fumigatus</italic> (a major invasive pathogen in humans, with severe morbidity and mortality) encodes a homolog of Cet1, as does <italic>Neurospora crassa.</italic> Thus, we suspect that all fungal species will have metal-dependent RNA triphosphatases resembling those of <italic>S. cerevisiae, C. albicans</italic> and <italic>S. pombe.</italic></p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Methods and materials</title><sec><title>Gene disruption in <italic>S. pombe</italic></title><p>We used a modified version of the long flanking homology PCR technique [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>] to produce <italic>pct1&#x00394;</italic> and <italic>pce1&#x00394;</italic> gene disruption cassettes in which the open reading frames were replaced by the <italic>kanMX</italic> gene. For each gene, a set of four primers was synthesized: LI, a 20-mer corresponding to the sense-strand sequence of the 5'-flanking region ~1.2 kb upstream of the translation start codon of <italic>pct1</italic><sup>+</sup> or <italic>pce1</italic><sup>+</sup>; L2, a 40-mer in which 20 bases were identical to the 5' sequence of pFA6a-KanMX4 (GCTTCAGCTGGCGGCCGCGT) and 20 bases were identical to the antisense strand sequence immediately 5' of the translation start site of <italic>pct1</italic><sup>+</sup> or <italic>pce1</italic><sup>+</sup>; L3, a 40-mer in which 20 bases were identical to the 3' sequence of pFA6a-KanMX4 (AGTGGCCTATGCGGCCGCGG) and 20 bases corresponded to the sense-strand sequence immediately 3' of the stop codon of <italic>pct1</italic><sup>+</sup> or <italic>pce1</italic><sup>+</sup>; L4, a 20-mer corresponding to the antisense-strand sequence of the 3'-flanking region ~1 kb downstream of stop codon of <italic>pct1</italic><sup>+</sup> or <italic>pce1</italic><sup>+</sup>. In the first-stage PCR, a 5'-flanking fragment was synthesized using <italic>S. pombe</italic> genomic DNA as the template and LI plus L2 as primers. The 3' flanking fragment was synthesized using primers L3 and L4. In the second-stage PCR, aliquots of the purified products from the first amplification (0.1&#x02013;0.2 &#x003bc;g) were mixed with 0.5 &#x003bc;g of <italic>Not</italic>I-digested pFA6a-kanMX4 and amplification synthesis was primed with the LI and L4 oligonucleotides. The products of the second PCR amplification were gel-purified and subcloned into pGEM-T (Promega). The recombinants were selected on LB agar medium containing 100 &#x003bc;g/ml ampicillin and 60 &#x003bc;g/ml kanamycin. The pPCT1&#x00394; and pPCE1&#x00394; plasmid constructs were confirmed by restriction enzyme digestion and partial sequencing. The <italic>pct1::kanMX</italic> cassette was PCR-amplified from the pPCT1&#x00394; plasmid using primers LI and L4. The <italic>pce1::kanMX</italic> cassette was excised from PCE1&#x00394; by digestion with <italic>Aat</italic>II and <italic>Nde</italic>I. The cassette fragments were gel-purified and then used to transform diploid <italic>S. pombe.</italic></p><p>The <italic>S. pombe</italic> diploid strain was generated by crossing two heterothallic strains FY527(ura4-D18<italic> leuI-32 ade6-M216 his3-DI h</italic><sup>-</sup>) and <italic>FY528</italic>(<italic>ura4-D18 leuI-32 ade6-M210 his3-D1 h</italic><sup>+</sup>) on ME plates at room temperature. After 24 h, the cells were streaked onto medium lacking adenine to select for diploids. The Ade<sup>+</sup> diploids were verified by staining with phloxin B and a single diploid colony was picked and incubated in 100 ml of YE medium to prepare competent <italic>S. pombe</italic> cells. The transformations were performed using the lithium acetate method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. The integrants were selected at 30&#x000b0;C on YE plates containing 200 &#x003bc;g/ml G418. Single colonies were restreaked on YE agar containing G418. Genomic DNA was prepared from individual isolates and the integration of the <italic>pct1::kanMX</italic> or <italic>pce1::kanMX</italic> cassettes into the correct locus was tested by PCR using diagnostic primers. The heterozygous diploids were sporulated on ME plates at room temperature. Tetrads were dissected from single asci and the spores were incubated at 30&#x000b0;C. All viable haploids were tested for growth on YES agar and YES agar containing 200 &#x003bc;g/ml G418.</p></sec><sec><title><italic>S. pombe</italic> expression vectors for RNA triphosphatase and guanylyltransferase</title><p>The cDNA encoding Pct1 was amplified from plasmid pET-PCT1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>] using primers that introduced an <italic>Xho</italic>I site immediately upstream of the translation start codon and a <italic>Bam</italic>HI site immediately downstream of the stop codon. The intron-containing chromosomal <italic>pct1</italic><sup>+</sup> gene was amplified from total <italic>S. pombe</italic> genomic DNA. The intron-less <italic>pce1</italic><sup>+</sup> gene was amplified from plasmid pl32-PCE1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. The PCR products were digested with <italic>Xho</italic>I and <italic>Bam</italic>HI and then inserted into the <italic>S. pombe</italic> expression vector pREP41X (<italic>LEU2 ars1</italic><sup>+</sup>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. The inserts were sequenced to exclude the acquisition of unwanted mutations during the amplification and cloning steps. Expression of the capping enzymes from these plasmids is driven by the <italic>nmt1*</italic> promoter [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. The plasmids were transformed into heterozygous <italic>pct1</italic><sup>+</sup>/<italic>pct1::kanMX</italic> or <italic>pce1</italic><sup>+</sup>/<italic>pct1::kanMX</italic> diploids using the lithium acetate method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. The <italic>Leu</italic><sup>+</sup> diploid transformants were then sporulated on ME plates at room temperature. A loopful of cells was inoculated into 500 &#x003bc;l of sterile water and the mixture was incubated overnight at 28&#x000b0;C with 10 &#x003bc;l of &#x003b2;-glucuronidase (Sigma G7770). The spores were plated on EMM(-Leu) agar medium and incubated at 30&#x000b0;C. Individual colonies were then restreaked onto YES agar and on YES agar containing 200 &#x003bc;g/ml G418. Growth was scored after incubation for 5 to 7 days at 30&#x000b0;C.</p></sec><sec><title>Gene disruption in <italic>C. albicans</italic></title><p>The <italic>CaCET1</italic> gene was disrupted by insertion of a <italic>UAU1</italic> cassette [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. We first constructed plasmid pKS-5'3'CaCET1, in which a 665-bp PCR fragment derived from the 5' end of the <italic>CaCET1</italic> gene (from nucleotides -50 to +615 of the open reading frame, with the A residue of the ATG translation start codon defined as position +1) was cloned between the <italic>Kpn</italic>I and <italic>Xba</italic>I sites of pBluescript <italic>KS</italic><sup>+</sup> and a 720-bp fragment extending from position +1518 of the 1560-nt <italic>CaCET1</italic> coding sequence into the 3' flanking genomic region was inserted between the <italic>Sac</italic>I and <italic>Sac</italic>II sites of pBluescript KS<sup>+</sup> The 3.8-kbp <italic>UAU1</italic> gene was excised from pBME101 with <italic>Xba</italic>I and <italic>Sac</italic>II and inserted between the <italic>Xba</italic>I and <italic>Sac</italic>II sites of pKS-5'3'CaCET1 to yield pCaCET1::UAU1. This DNA was linearized with <italic>Kpn</italic>I and <italic>Sac</italic>I and then transformed into the diploid <italic>C. albicans</italic> strain BWP17 using the lithium acetate method. We selected 25 <italic>Arg</italic><sup>+</sup> transformants and analyzed them by Southern blotting for integration of the <italic>UAU1</italic> cassette into one of the two <italic>CaCET1</italic> chromosomal loci to yield the heterozygote <italic>CaCET1/cacet1::UAU1</italic> configuration depicted in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>. Briefly, genomic DNA was isolated from the 25 <italic>Arg</italic><sup>+</sup> strains, then digested with <italic>Sca</italic>I (which cuts neither <italic>CaCET1</italic> nor <italic>UAU1</italic>). The digests were resolved by agarose gel-electrophoresis and transferred to membranes, which were probed with a radiolabeled DNA corresponding to the 5' segment of <italic>CaCET1</italic> (probe A in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). Whereas probe A hybridized to a single 3.8-kbp <italic>Sca</italic>I fragment in the parental BWP17 strain, the probe detected two fragments in the heterozygote &#x02013; a 3.8-kbp fragment corresponding to the wild-type <italic>CaCET1</italic> locus and an ~7.5-kbp fragment corresponding to <italic>cacet1::UAU1</italic> (data not shown). This analysis identified 16/25 of the Arg<sup>+</sup> transformants as <italic>CaCET1/cacet1::UAU1</italic> heterozygotes. Recombination rates at the <italic>UAU1</italic> gene in the heterozygote were determined as described by Enloe et al [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. Ura<sup>+</sup> segregants arose at a rate of 5 x 10<sup>-5</sup> per division and Arg<sup>+</sup> Ura<sup>+</sup> segregants arose at rate of 8 x 10<sup>-9</sup> per division.</p><p>The sixteen <italic>CaCET1/cacet1::UAU1</italic> heterozygotes were streaked to YPD agar and grown for 3 days at 30&#x000b0;C. A total of 54 single colonies derived from the 16 heterozygotes were inoculated into separate YPD liquid cultures. After growth to saturation, aliquots of the cultures were plated on SD(-Arg-Ura) agar medium. Genomic DNA was prepared from one Arg<sup>+</sup> Ura<sup>+</sup> segregant from each culture and subjected to restriction digestion and Southern analysis.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Dr. Aaron Mitchell for plasmid pBME101 and <italic>C. albicans</italic> strain BWP17. This work was supported by NIH grant GM52470 to SS and BS.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shuman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure, mechanism, and evolution of the mRNA capping apparatus.</article-title><source>Prog Nucleic Acid Res Mol Biol</source><year>2000</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>40</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name><surname>Shuman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure and mechanism of yeast RNA triphosphatase: an essential component of the mRNA capping apparatus.</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1999</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>533</fpage><lpage>543</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10589681</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Changela</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Shuman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mondragon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure and mechanism of the RNA triphosphatase component of mammalian mRNA capping enzyme.</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>2001</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>2575</fpage><lpage>2586</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11350947</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shibagaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hagata</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mizumoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>mRNA capping enzyme: isolation and characterization of the gene encoding mRNA guanylyltransferase subunit from <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae.</italic></article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1992</year><volume>267</volume><fpage>9521</fpage><lpage>9528</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1315757</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsukamoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Shibagaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Imajoh-Ohmi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Murakoshi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gotoh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Mizumoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation and characterization of the yeast mRNA capping enzyme &#x025a1; subunit gene encoding RNA 5'-triphosphatase, which is essential for cell viability.</article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Res Comm</source><year>1997</year><volume>239</volume><fpage>116</fpage><lpage>122</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9345280</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Shuman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Yeast mRNA cap methyltransferase is a 50-kilodalton protein encoded by an essential gene.</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>1995</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>4167</fpage><lpage>4174</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7623811</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name><surname>Pei</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shuman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Yeast and viral RNA 5' triphosphatases comprise a new nucleoside triphosphatase family.</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1998</year><volume>273</volume><fpage>34151</fpage><lpage>34156</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9852075</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pei</surname><given-names>YHCK</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Shuman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mutational analyses of yeast RNA triphosphatases highlight a common mechanism of metal-dependent NTP hydrolysis and a means of targeting enzymes to pre-mRNAs <italic>in vivo</italic> by fusion to the guanylyltransferase component of the capping apparatus.</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1999</year><volume>274</volume><fpage>28865</fpage><lpage>28874</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10506129</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bisaillon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shuman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure-function analysis of the active site tunnel of yeast RNA triphosphatase.</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2001</year><volume>276</volume><fpage>17261</fpage><lpage>17266</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11279161</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pei</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Lehman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Shuman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of <italic>Candida albicans</italic> RNA triphosphatase and mutational analysis of its active site.</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2000</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>1885</fpage><lpage>1892</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10756187</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lehman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Saha</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Shuman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of the mRNA capping apparatus of <italic>Candida albicans.</italic></article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2001</year><volume>276</volume><fpage>1857</fpage><lpage>1864</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11035009</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pei</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hausmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shuman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of <italic>Schizosaccharomyces pombe</italic> RNA triphosphatase.</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2001</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>387</fpage><lpage>396</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11139608</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name><surname>Shuman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A yeast-like mRNA capping apparatus in <italic>Plasmodium falciparum.</italic></article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2001</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>3050</fpage><lpage>3055</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11248030</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Shuman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RNA triphosphatase component of the mRNA capping apparatus of <italic>Paramecium bursaria Chlorella</italic> virus 1.</article-title><source>J Virol</source><year>2001</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>1744</fpage><lpage>1750</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11160672</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Takagi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Buratowski</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> RNA 5'-triphosphatase related to mRNA capping enzyme.</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1999</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>2182</fpage><lpage>2188</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Enloe</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Diamond</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A single-transformation gene function test in diploid <italic>Candida albicans.</italic></article-title><source>J Bacterial</source><year>2000</year><volume>182</volume><fpage>5730</fpage><lpage>5736</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wach</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PCR-synthesis of marker cassettes with long flanking homology regions for gene disruptions in <italic>S. cerevisiae.</italic></article-title><source>Yeast</source><year>1996</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>259</fpage><lpage>265</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8904338</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gietz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>St Jean</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Schiestl</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improved method for high efficiency transformation of intact yeast cells.</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1992</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>1425</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1561104</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Forsburg</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of <italic>Schizosaccharomyces pombe</italic> expression systems.</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1993</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>2955</fpage><lpage>2956</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8332516</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shuman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Covalent catalysis in nucleotidyl transfer reactions: essential motifs in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> RNA capping enzyme are conserved in <italic>Schizosaccharomyces pombe</italic> and viral capping enzymes and among polynucleotide ligases.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>1994</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>12046</fpage><lpage>12050</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7991582</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hausmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Shuman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An essential function of <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> RNA triphosphatase Cet1 is to stabilize RNA guanylyltransferase Ceg1 against thermal inactivation.</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2001</year><volume>276</volume><fpage>36116</fpage><lpage>36124</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11463793</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamada-Okabe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mio</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsui</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kashim</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Arisawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamada-Okabe</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation and characterization of the <italic>Candida albicans</italic> gene for mRNA 5' triphosphatase: association of mRNA 5' triphosphatase and mRNA 5' guanylyltransferase activities is essential for the function of mRNA 5' capping enzyme in vivo.</article-title><source>FEBS Lett</source><year>1998</year><volume>435</volume><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9755857</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Linder</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Shuman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of deletion mutations in the yeast Ces1 protein on cell growth and morphology and on high copy suppression of mutations in mRNA capping enzyme and translation initiation factor 4A.</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1998</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>803</fpage><lpage>809</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9443973</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Del Poeta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tofaletti</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Rude</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>Dykstra</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Heitman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Perfect</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Topoisomerase I is essential in <italic>Cryptococcus neoformans:</italic> role in pathobiology and as an antifungal target.</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>1999</year><volume>152</volume><fpage>167</fpage><lpage>178</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10224251</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>DeBacker</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>de Hoogt</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Froyen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Odds</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name><name><surname>Simons</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Contreras</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Luyten</surname><given-names>WHM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Single allele knock-out of <italic>Candida albicans CGT1</italic> leads to unexpected resistance to hygromycin B and elevated temperature.</article-title><source>Microbiology</source><year>2000</year><volume>146</volume><fpage>353</fpage><lpage>365</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10708374</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list><sec sec-type="display-objects"><title>Figures and Tables</title><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><italic>Genotype of the CaCET1/cacet1::UAU1 heterozygote strain of C. albicans.</italic> Illustrated in cartoon form are the configurations of the wild-type <italic>CaCET1</italic> and the <italic>cacet1::UAU1</italic> chromosomal loci in the Arg<sup>+</sup> heterozygous diploids. The positions of pertinent restriction sites and the <italic>CaCET1</italic> 5'-specific (A) and 3'-specific (B) hybridization probes are shown. Also shown is the configuration of the triplicated <italic>cacet1::URA2</italic> allele in the Arg<sup>+</sup> Ura<sup>+</sup> segregants.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2180-1-29-1"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><italic>Southern blot analysis.</italic> DNA isolated from the parental diploid strain (lane P), one of the Arg<sup>+</sup> heterozygotes (isolate #19; lane H), and fourteen independent Arg<sup>+</sup> Ura<sup>+</sup> segregants were digested with <italic>Bgl</italic>II and resolved by agarose gel electrophoresis. A photograph of the ethidium bromide-stained gel is shown in <italic>panel C.</italic> The positions and sizes (kbp) of DNA size markers are indicated on the <italic>right.</italic> The DNA was transferred to a Hybond membrane, which was serially hybridized to <sup>32</sup>P-labeled DNA probes A (<italic>panel A</italic>) and B (<italic>panel B</italic>) derived from the 5' and 3' segments of the <italic>CaCET1</italic> gene, respectively.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2180-1-29-2"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Plasmid-based Complementation of <italic>pct1&#x00394;</italic> and <italic>pce1&#x00394;</italic></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="center">Strain</td><td align="center">Plasmid</td><td align="center">G418 resistant</td><td align="center">G418 sensitive</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><italic>pct1</italic><sup>+</sup>/<italic>pct1::kanMX</italic></td><td align="left">pREP41X</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">24</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">pREP41X-<italic>pct1</italic><sup>+</sup> (cDNA)</td><td align="center">21</td><td align="center">19</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">pREP41X-<italic>pct1</italic><sup>+</sup></td><td align="center">22</td><td align="center">18</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>pce1</italic><sup>+</sup>/<italic>pce1::kanMX</italic></td><td align="left">pREP41X</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">24</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">pREP41X-<italic>pce1</italic><sup>+</sup></td><td align="center">22</td><td align="center">18</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec></back></article>


