<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Res Notes</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Res Notes</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Research Notes</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1756-0500</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24673808</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3986815</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1756-0500-7-189</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1756-0500-7-189</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Relevance of the two-component sensor protein CiaH to acid and oxidative stress responses in <italic>Streptococcus pyogenes</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A1"><name><surname>Tatsuno</surname><given-names>Ichiro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>tatsuno@med.nagoya-cu.ac.jp</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A2"><name><surname>Isaka</surname><given-names>Masanori</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>isaka@med.nagoya-cu.ac.jp</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A3"><name><surname>Okada</surname><given-names>Ryo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>aslan087@gmail.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A4"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Yan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>zhangyan0522@gmail.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A5"><name><surname>Hasegawa</surname><given-names>Tadao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>tadaoh@med.nagoya-cu.ac.jp</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Bacteriology, Nagoya City University Graduate School of Medical Sciences, 1 Kawasumi Mizuho-cho Mizuho-ku, Nagoya 467-8601, Japan</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>3</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><fpage>189</fpage><lpage>189</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>26</day><month>9</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>17</day><month>3</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2014 Tatsuno et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Tatsuno et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1756-0500/7/189"/><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>The production of virulence proteins depends on environmental factors, and two-component regulatory systems are involved in sensing these factors. We previously established knockout strains in all suspected two-component regulatory sensor proteins of the <italic>emm1</italic> clinical strain of <italic>S. pyogenes</italic> and examined their relevance to acid stimuli in a natural atmosphere. In the present study, their relevance to acid stimuli was re-examined in an atmosphere containing 5% CO<sub>2</sub>.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>The <italic>spy1236</italic> (which is identical to <italic>ciaH</italic><sub><italic>py</italic></sub>) sensor knockout strain showed significant growth reduction compared with the parental strain in broth at pH&#x000a0;6.0, suggesting that the Spy1236 (CiaH<sub>py</sub>) two-component sensor protein is involved in acid response of <italic>S. pyogenes</italic>. CiaH is also conserved in <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic>, and it has been reported that deletion of the gene for its cognate response regulator (<italic>ciaR</italic><sub><italic>pn</italic></sub>) made the pneumococcal strains more sensitive to oxidative stress. In this report, we show that the <italic>spy1236</italic> knockout mutant of <italic>S. pyogenes</italic> is more sensitive to oxidative stress than the parental strain.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>These results suggest that the two-component sensor protein CiaH is involved in stress responses in <italic>S. pyogenes</italic>.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p><italic>Streptococcus pyogenes</italic>, is a Gram-positive bacterium that infects the upper respiratory tract, including the tonsils and pharynx, and is responsible for post-infection diseases such as rheumatic fever and glomerulonephritis. <italic>S. pyogenes</italic> also causes severe invasive diseases including necrotizing fasciitis and streptococcal toxic shock syndrome (STSS) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>].</p><p><italic>S. pyogenes</italic> is exclusively a human pathogen and it possesses many virulence factors that help it to resist host defense systems. The production of these factors is precisely regulated in response to host environmental conditions, such as different infection sites or host immune system induction levels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. In prokaryotes, the regulation of protein production in response to fluctuating environmental conditions depends primarily on two-component regulatory systems, which consist of a sensor histidine kinase and its cognate response regulator [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. Thirteen two-component regulatory systems have been described in <italic>S. pyogenes</italic>, of which the CovRS system (also known as the CsrRS system) mediates the control of several virulence factors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. Analysis of the other two-component regulatory systems is still incomplete. In addition, most experiments have been performed from the viewpoint of the response regulators. Therefore, it is still unclear which signals the sensor proteins sense.</p><p>In a previous study, we focused on the sensor proteins of two-component regulatory systems, establishing 13 types of sensor knockout mutants, analyzing their involvement in the acid response in a &#x0201c;natural&#x0201d; atmosphere, and proposing that the Spy1622 two-component sensor protein is involved in sensing acid stimuli [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. In contrast to the natural atmosphere used in our previous study, an atmosphere containing 5% CO<sub>2</sub> is often used to culture <italic>S. pyogenes</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. The CO<sub>2</sub> concentration in deeper tissues is higher than its concentration at the epithelial surface of the host [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. This can cause certain genes&#x02014;for example, the gene encoding M protein&#x02014;to be stimulated by carbon dioxide [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>]. Therefore, it is possible that the genes involved in the acid response are also stimulated differently under natural atmospheric conditions than they are in an atmosphere containing 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. In the present study, we reanalyzed the involvement of 13 sensor proteins in the acid response in an atmosphere containing 5% CO<sub>2</sub>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title><italic>S. pyogenes</italic> strains</title><p>Streptococcal strains 1529, MDYK, and MDN were isolated from Japanese patients with STSS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]. <italic>S. pyogenes</italic> (GAS) strain SF370, which is currently the most prevalent database reference isolate (accession number NC_002737), was provided by J. J. Ferretti [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]. As shown in Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>, 13 sensor knockout mutants derived from the strain 1529 have previously been constructed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. These strains were cultured in either brain&#x02013;heart infusion (E-MC62, EIKEN Chemical Co., Tokyo, Japan) supplemented with 0.3% yeast extract (BD, Sparks, MD, USA) broth (BHI-Y), or Todd Hewitt broth (BD) supplemented with 0.3% yeast extract broth (TH-YE), unless otherwise stated.</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Analysis of the growth of 13 sensor knockout strains cultured in acidic media (pH&#x000a0;6.0) in an atmosphere containing 5% CO</bold><sub><bold>2</bold></sub><bold>.</bold> The CFU/ml after 23&#x000a0;h, broth culture of wild-type strain 1529 and its derived sensor knockout strains are shown. Viable counts were performed on BHI-Y and sheep blood agar plates. At least three independent experiments were performed. The error bars indicate the standard error of the mean (SEM).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1756-0500-7-189-1"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Culture conditions for growth assay</title><p>Streptococcal strains were cultured using a previously described strategy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>], with certain modifications. In brief, an aliquot of frozen bacterial stock solution that had been stored at &#x02212;80&#x000b0;C was inoculated into the TH-YE broth and cultured overnight (about for 18&#x000a0;h) at 37&#x000b0;C without agitation. A 70&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L sample of the overnight culture was added to fresh TH-YE broth (4&#x000a0;mL, pH&#x000a0;7.6 or 6.0), cultured in an atmosphere containing 5% CO<sub>2</sub> for 23&#x000a0;h, and then the viable cells were counted by plating onto blood agar and BHI-Y agar plates. The experiments were repeated at least three times, independently.</p></sec><sec><title>Production of <italic>spy1236</italic> knockout strains</title><p>We constructed an <italic>S. pyogenes</italic> strain 1529&#x00394;<italic>spy1236</italic> as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. Strains MDYK&#x00394;<italic>spy1236</italic> and MDN&#x00394;<italic>spy1236</italic> were constructed using the same strategy. To construct a plasmid for <italic>spy1236</italic> complementation (pLZ-spy1236), the DNA fragment was amplified using oligonucleotide primers 1236-n2 (5<sup>&#x02032;</sup>-GTGGTTGACTTAGCTCGAAA-3<sup>&#x02032;</sup>) and 1236-c2 (5<sup>&#x02032;</sup>-AAAATTCATTGAACCTACAC-3<sup>&#x02032;</sup>), strain 1529 genomic DNA as template, and PrimeSTAR HS DNA polymerase (Takara, Ohtsu, Japan). Digestion with <italic>Pvu</italic>II produced a fragment containing <italic>spy1236</italic>, which was treated with T4 polynucleotide kinase and ligated into the <italic>Sma</italic>I site of the plasmid pLZ12-Km2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>BLAST analysis</title><p>The Basic Local Alignment Search Tool (BLAST) was used for homology search (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/">http://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec><title>The sensitivity of &#x00394;<italic>spy1236</italic> mutants and derivative strains to H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub></title><p>Assays were performed as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]. In brief, aliquots of bacterial cultures grown to an OD<sub>660</sub> of ~0.3 were exposed to 61&#x000a0;mM H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> for 15&#x000a0;min at room temperature. Viable cells were counted by plating onto blood agar and BHI-Y agar plates before and after exposure to H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, and the result was expressed as percent survival.</p></sec><sec><title>Plasmids having <italic>htrA</italic> gene</title><p>Plasmids pLZ-htrA<sub>forward</sub> and pLZ-htrA<sub>reverse</sub> were constructed as described in Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>: Figure S1. In brief, a DNA fragment encoding the <italic>htrA</italic> gene was amplified using oligonucleotide primers htrA-F3 (5<sup>&#x02032;</sup>-CATTACTTTTTACACAATTTATCCACAAGT-3<sup>&#x02032;</sup>) and htrA-R1 (5<sup>&#x02032;</sup>-GTAGGTCTATCAATAATTCTTTTGTCATAA-3<sup>&#x02032;</sup>), strain1529 genomic DNA as template, and <italic>TaKaRa Ex Taq</italic> DNA polymerase (Takara). The PCR product was cloned into the pGEM&#x000ae;-T Easy vector (Promega, Madison, WI, USA). The resulting plasmid was digested with <italic>Eco</italic>RI and ligated into the <italic>Eco</italic>RI site of the plasmid pLZ12-Km2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>] to yield pLZ-htrA<sub>forward</sub> and pLZ-htrA<sub>reverse</sub>. In pLZ-htrA<sub>forward</sub> and pLZ-htrA<sub>reverse</sub>, the <italic>htrA</italic> genes were cloned in opposite directions.</p></sec><sec><title>Quantitative RT-PCR (qRT-PCR)</title><p>Total RNA was extracted from bacterial cells grown as described above for the H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> sensitivity assay. The purity and concentration of the RNA were determined by gel electrophoresis and spectrophotometry, respectively. Extracted total RNA was employed as the template for random-primed first-strand cDNA synthesis using a High Capacity cDNA Reverse Transcription Kit with RNAase Inhibitor (Applied Biosystems, Darmstadt, Germany) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. It was also used without reverse transcription, as a control to assess genomic DNA contamination. The cDNA and the control were then used as templates for quantitative RT-PCR (qRT-PCR) (real-time 7900HT PCR machine; Applied Biosystems) using the Sybr green detection system (Applied Biosystems). Primers for the genes of interest and the internal control gene <italic>gyrA</italic> are shown in Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>. PCR conditions included incubation at 50&#x000b0;C for 2&#x000a0;min, followed by incubation at 95&#x000b0;C for 10&#x000a0;min, and finally 40-cycles of amplification (95&#x000b0;C for 15&#x000a0;s and 60&#x000b0;C for 1&#x000a0;min). The signal was standardized to that of the <italic>gyrA</italic> gene, where the cycle threshold (CT) was determined automatically using a real-time 7900HT PCR software (Applied Biosystems) after 40&#x000a0;cycles. Changes in the levels of gene expression were calculated using the &#x00394;&#x00394;C<sub><italic>T</italic></sub> method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]. Each assay was repeated using at least three independent RNA samples. Product specificity was evaluated using both melting-curve analysis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>] and 2% agarose gels.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Sequences of primers used in qRT-PCR</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead valign="top"><tr><th align="left"><bold>Primer</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Sequence (5</bold><sup>
<bold>&#x02032;</bold>
</sup><bold>-3</bold><sup>
<bold>&#x02032;</bold>
</sup><bold>)</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">GyrA-1584&#x000a0;F<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">ACGTGGCGTCCAAGGAACT<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">GyrA-1709R<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">TGCTAAGCTTTCAACCGATAGACA<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">HtrA-F4<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">ATCGACGGAGCTAAACGAATTG<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">HtrA-R4<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">TCAGCTCCAACTAATTCACCAACA<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Nrd-F<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">ACAGTAGACAAGCTGAAGACGGC<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Nrd-R<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">AGCGAGTATGACACTGTTCACATTC<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Emm1-31&#x000a0;F<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">TGCTACTCCAGCTGTTGCCATA<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Emm1-98R<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">ACAGGTGAAACAGCTAACCCATTC<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">MGAS5005 polA-F<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">GCGGGCAAAACCACCTT<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">MGAS5005 polA-R</td><td align="left">GCGCGACCCGCCTTATA</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Primers were designed by using Primer Express&#x000ae; software version 3.0 and 2.0, and with technical support of life technologies Japan.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Survival times were analyzed by using nonparametric Mann&#x02013;Whitney U analysis and unpaired <italic>t</italic> test. <italic>P</italic> values of &#x0003c;0.05 for both analyses were considered statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results and discussion</title><sec><title>Analysis of the effect of sensor proteins on the growth of bacteria cultured at pH&#x000a0;7.6 or 6.0</title><p>To test the effect of <italic>S. pyogenes</italic> sensor proteins on growth under acidic pH conditions, we first used the previously established knockout mutants lacking all 13 suspected sensor proteins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. We cultured the parental and derived knockout strains in a medium with the pH adjusted to 6.0, and in an atmosphere containing 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. As shown in Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref> and Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>, the CFU (colony forming units)/ml for overnight cultures of strain 1529&#x00394;<italic>spy337</italic> (<italic>covS</italic>) and 1529&#x00394;<italic>spy1236</italic> were lower than that of the parental strain 1529. However, the CFU/ml for overnight cultures of strain 1529&#x00394;<italic>spy1622</italic> was not lower than that of the parental strain 1529 under this experimental condition.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><bold>Growth of </bold><bold>
<italic>spy1236 </italic>
</bold><bold>knockout mutant in acidic (pH&#x000a0;6.0) media in an atmosphere containing 5% CO</bold><sub>
<bold>2</bold>
</sub></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead valign="top"><tr><th align="left"><bold>Strains</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>OD</bold><sub>
<bold>660</bold>
</sub></th><th align="left"><bold>Av. CFU/mL</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>(pH7.6)</bold><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">1529wt<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.906&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.009<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">3.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7 &#x000d7; 10<sup>8</sup><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">1529&#x00394;<italic>spy1236</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.927&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.025<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6 &#x000d7; 10<sup>8</sup><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>(pH6.0)</bold><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">1529wt<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.662&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.009<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">4.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.6 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1529&#x00394;<italic>spy1236</italic></td><td align="left">0.571&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.039</td><td align="left">2.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.0 &#x000d7; 10<sup>4</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>The experiment was performed as described in Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>. At least three independent experiments were performed and they always yielded essentially the same results. Values expressed are the means (&#x000b1;SEM).</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>In this study, we focused on Spy1236 more than CovS, for the following three reasons. First, we have already analyzed 1529&#x00394;<italic>covS</italic> and have showed that 1529&#x00394;<italic>covS</italic> had lower growth ability than the parental wild type strain 1529 even at pH&#x000a0;7.6 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. Therefore, the lower growth ability of the <italic>covS</italic> mutated strain shown in Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref> may not have been caused by the fact that the medium was adjusted to pH&#x000a0;6.0. Second, CFU/ml (or OD<sub>660</sub>) for overnight cultures of strain 1529&#x00394;<italic>spy1236</italic> was similar to that of the parental strain 1529, when cultured in a medium with pH adjusted to 7.6 and in an atmosphere containing 5% CO<sub>2</sub> (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). Finally, BLAST analysis showed that Spy1236 (436 amino acids) shares 58% identity with CiaH of <italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic> (referred to as CiaH<sub>m</sub>). It is known that the CiaH<sub>m</sub> sensor kinase is involved in a response to acid stress in <italic>S. mutans</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>].</p><p>In order to further investigate the effect of Spy1236 sensor kinase on growth under acidic conditions, we next established a strain in which the s<italic>py1236</italic> knockout was complemented using an appropriate plasmid, and performed the same experiments at pH&#x000a0;6.0 and 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. As shown in Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>, <italic>spy1236</italic> cloned into a plasmid vector (pLZ-spy1236) complemented the lower growth ability of 1529&#x00394;<italic>spy1236</italic>. These results suggested that the lower growth level of the <italic>spy1236</italic> mutant was Spy1236-dependent, at least in this strain.</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Analysis of the growth of wild-type, </bold><bold><italic>spy1236 </italic></bold><bold>knockout, and complemented strains cultured in acidic (pH&#x000a0;6.0) media in an atmosphere containing 5% CO</bold><sub><bold>2</bold></sub><bold>.</bold> The CFU/ml after 23&#x000a0;h, broth culture of wild-type strain 1529 and its derived strains are shown. Viable counts were performed on BHI-Y and sheep blood agar plates. At least three independent experiments were performed and they always yielded essentially the same results. The error bars indicate the standard error of the mean.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1756-0500-7-189-2"/></fig><p>To examine the effects related to strain specificity, we established additional <italic>spy1236</italic> knockout strains derived from strains MDYK and MDN (MDYK&#x00394;<italic>spy1236</italic> and MDN&#x00394;<italic>spy1236</italic>, respectively). When the same experiments were performed at pH&#x000a0;6.0 and 5% CO<sub>2</sub>, the CFU/ml for overnight cultures of MDYK&#x00394;<italic>spy1236</italic> and MDN&#x00394;<italic>spy1236</italic> were lower than those of the parental strains (Figures&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>a and c). In addition, the CFU/ml for overnight cultures of MDYK&#x00394;<italic>spy1236</italic> (pLZ-spy1236) and MDN&#x00394;<italic>spy1236</italic> (pLZ-spy1236), in which the <italic>spy1236</italic> deletions were complemented with pLZ-spy1236, were higher than those for MDYK&#x00394;<italic>spy1236</italic> (pLZ12-km2) and MDN&#x00394;<italic>spy1236</italic> (pLZ12-km2), which harbor a control vector, respectively (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>b and d). Thus, Spy1236 (also referred to as CiaH<sub>py</sub>) may be involved in the response to acid stress in some <italic>S. pyogenes</italic> strains, as it is in <italic>S. mutans</italic>, in an atmosphere containing 5% CO<sub>2</sub>.</p><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>Analysis of the growth of wild-type, </bold><bold><italic>spy1236 </italic></bold><bold>knockout and complemented strains cultured in acidic media (pH&#x000a0;6.0) in an atmosphere containing 5% CO</bold><sub><bold>2</bold></sub><bold>.</bold> The experiment was performed as described in Figures&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>. At least three independent experiments were performed and they always yielded essentially the same results. The error bars indicate the standard error of the mean. <bold>(a)</bold> The CFU/ml broth culture of wild-type strain MDYK and its derived strain MDYK&#x00394;<italic>spy1236</italic> are shown. <bold>(b)</bold> The CFU/ml culture of MDYK&#x00394;<italic>spy1236</italic> (pLZ-spy1236) and MDYK&#x00394;<italic>spy1236</italic> (pLZ12-Km2) grown in a broth supplemented with 62.5&#x000a0;mg/mL kanamycin are shown. Viable counts were performed on BHI-Y agar plates supplemented with 125&#x000a0;mg/mL kanamycin. <bold>(c)</bold> The CFU/ml broth culture of wild-type strain MDN and its derived strain MDN&#x00394;<italic>spy1236</italic> are shown. <bold>(d)</bold> The CFU/ml culture of MDN&#x00394;<italic>spy1236</italic> (pLZ-spy1236) and MDN&#x00394;<italic>spy1236</italic> (pLZ12-Km2) grown in a broth supplemented with 62.5&#x000a0;mg/mL kanamycin are shown. Viable counts were performed on BHI-Y agar plates supplemented with 125&#x000a0;mg/mL kanamycin.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1756-0500-7-189-3"/></fig><p>Meanwhile, the empty-vector complementation resulted in the increased acid-resistance compared to the mutant strain (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). Kanamycin added to the complementation assay might induce some stress responses including the acid-resistance.</p></sec><sec><title>Sensitivity of the <italic>spy1236</italic> knockout strains to oxidative stress</title><p>The CiaH sensor kinase is also conserved in <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic> (51% identical with Spy1236 by BLAST analysis). Ibrahim <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>] showed that deletion of the gene encoding the cognate response regulator CiaR<sub>pn</sub> made a pneumococcal strain more sensitive to oxidative stress. Therefore, we were interested to learn whether the Spy1236 sensor kinase is involved in the response to oxidative stress, and performed essentially the same experiments using <italic>S. pyogenes</italic> &#x00394;<italic>spy1236</italic> mutants as were previously done using <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]<italic>.</italic> As shown in Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>a, 1529&#x00394;<italic>spy1236</italic> was significantly more sensitive to hydrogen peroxide than the parental strain 1529, and the complemented strain 1529&#x00394;<italic>spy1236</italic> (pLZ-spy1236) was more resistant to hydrogen peroxide than 1529&#x00394;<italic>spy1236</italic> (pLZ12-Km2, the control vector) (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>b). To examine the effects related to strain specificity, we also performed this experiment in strain MDYK. The knockout strain MDYK&#x00394;<italic>spy1236</italic> was more sensitive to hydrogen peroxide than its parental strain, MDYK (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>c). Thus, the CiaH<sub>py</sub> sensor kinase of <italic>S. pyogenes</italic> may contribute to oxidative stress tolerance.</p><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><bold>H</bold><sub><bold>2</bold></sub><bold>O</bold><sub><bold>2 </bold></sub><bold>sensitivity assays for 1529</bold>&#x00394;<bold><italic>spy1236 </italic></bold><bold>and MDYK</bold>&#x00394;<bold><italic>spy1236 </italic></bold><bold>strains.</bold> H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> sensitivity assays were performed for wild-type 1529 and 1529<bold>&#x00394;</bold><italic>spy1236</italic> strains <bold>(a)</bold>, 1529<bold>&#x00394;</bold><italic>spy1236</italic> (pLZ-<italic>spy1236</italic>) and 1529<bold>&#x00394;</bold><italic>spy1236</italic> (pLZ-12-Km2) strains <bold>(b)</bold>, or wild-type MDYK and MDYK<bold>&#x00394;</bold><italic>spy1236</italic> strains <bold>(c)</bold>. 1529&#x00394;<italic>spy1236</italic> (pLZ-<italic>spy1236</italic>) and 1529&#x00394;<italic>spy1236</italic> (pLZ-12-Km2) strains were grown in broth supplemented with 62.5 mg/mL kanamycin. H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (61 mM) was added to 1-mL aliquots of culture grown to an OD<sub>660</sub> of ~0.3. After 15 min at room temperature (~22&#x000b0;C), viable counts were performed on BHI-Y and sheep blood agar plates before and after the addition of peroxide, and the percentages of survival were calculated. The BHI-Y agar plates were supplemented with 125 mg/mL kanamycin for the 1529&#x00394;<italic>spy1236</italic> (pLZ-<italic>spy1236</italic>) and 1529&#x00394;<italic>spy1236</italic> (pLZ-12-Km2) strains. Values expressed are the means (&#x000b1; SEM) of three independent experiments.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1756-0500-7-189-4"/></fig><p>The percent survival of 1529&#x00394;<italic>spy1236</italic> (pLZ12-Km2) (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>b) seems to be similar to that of wild-type strain 1529 (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>a). One of the differences in their experimental settings is that 1529&#x00394;<italic>spy1236</italic> (pLZ12-Km2) was grown in broth supplemented with kanamycin. This might induce some stress responses to increase the survival rate of the 1529&#x00394;<italic>spy1236</italic> (pLZ12-Km2). At least, we did not find a potential region to confer the ability, when the pLZ12-Km2 sequence was analyzed using BLAST.</p></sec><sec><title>Contribution of the CiaH sensor kinase to oxidative stress tolerance may not be mediated via HtrA</title><p>Ibrahim <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>] also demonstrated that the contribution of the CiaH<sub>pn</sub> sensor kinase to oxidative stress tolerance was mediated by the HtrA protein in <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic>, based on the following evidence: (i) the sensitivity of the <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic> strain D39&#x00394;<italic>ciaR</italic> to oxidative stress can be restored by complementation with HtrA, and (ii) the expression of <italic>htrA</italic> in the CiaR-null mutant was down-regulated. HtrA, also known as DegP or DO protease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>], is a stress-induced serine protease that manifests both general molecular chaperone and proteolytic activities, and switches from chaperone to protease in a temperature-dependent manner [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>]. HtrA is also conserved in <italic>S. pyogenes</italic> and is known to be essential for oxidative tolerance in <italic>S. pyogenes</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. Therefore, we were interested to learn whether the contribution of the Spy1236 (CiaH<sub>py</sub>) sensor kinase to oxidative stress tolerance was also mediated by the HtrA protein in <italic>S. pyogenes</italic> (HtrA<sub>py</sub>). We first attempted to determine whether the sensitivity of the 1529&#x00394;<italic>spy1236</italic> strain to oxidative stress could be restored by complementation with HtrA<sub>py</sub>; i.e., to investigate whether the first evidence shown in <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic> is also true in <italic>S. pyogenes</italic>. For this purpose, <italic>htrA</italic><sub><italic>py</italic></sub> of <italic>S. pyogenes</italic> was cloned into pLZ12-Km2 to yield pLZ-htrA<sub>forward</sub> and pLZ-htrA<sub>reverse</sub> (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>: Figure S1). The <italic>htrA</italic><sub><italic>py</italic></sub> gene is cloned into pLZ-htrA<sub>reverse</sub> in the direction opposite to that in pLZ-htrA<sub>forward</sub>. When pLZ-htrA<sub>forward</sub> was introduced into 1529&#x00394;<italic>spy1236,</italic> the sensitivity of the resultant strain 1529&#x00394;<italic>spy1236</italic> (pLZ-htrA<sub>forward</sub>) to hydrogen peroxide was not significantly different than that of 1529&#x00394;<italic>spy1236</italic> (control vector) (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>a). This may have resulted from the insufficient expression of HtrA<sub>py</sub> by the pLZ-htrA<sub>forward</sub> contained within 1529&#x00394;<italic>spy1236</italic>. In addition, we hypothesized that level of HtrA expression from pLZ-htrA<sub>reverse</sub> was greater than that from pLZ-htrA<sub>forward</sub> (See Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>: Figure S1 for detailed explanation). As shown in Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref> (b), 1529&#x00394;<italic>spy1236</italic> having pLZ-htrA<sub>reverse</sub> was more resistant to hydrogen peroxide than 1529&#x00394;<italic>spy1236</italic> having pLZ12-Km2 (control vector). This result suggests that the overexpression of <italic>htrA</italic> may contribute the oxidative tolerance in that <italic>spy1236</italic> mutant.</p><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><bold>H</bold><sub><bold>2</bold></sub><bold>O</bold><sub><bold>2 </bold></sub><bold>sensitivity assay for 1529</bold>&#x00394;<bold><italic>spy1236 </italic></bold><bold>with the overexpression of </bold><bold><italic>htrA</italic></bold><bold>.</bold> H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> sensitivity assays were performed for 1529<bold>&#x00394;</bold><italic>spy1236</italic> (pLZ-<italic>htrA</italic><sub>forward</sub>) <bold>(a)</bold> or 1529<bold>&#x00394;</bold><italic>spy1236</italic> (pLZ-<italic>htrA</italic><sub>reverse</sub>) strains <bold>(b)</bold>. Bacteria were grown in broth supplemented with 62.5 mg/mL kanamycin. H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (61 mM) was added to 1-mL aliquots of culture grown to an OD<sub>660</sub> of ~0.3. After 15 min at room temperature (~25&#x000b0;C), viable counts were performed as described in Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>. Values expressed are the means (&#x000b1; SEM) of three independent experiments.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1756-0500-7-189-5"/></fig><p>Next, we attempted to investigate the down-regulation of HtrA in the CiaH-null mutant; i.e., to determine whether the second evidence shown in <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic> is also true in <italic>S. pyogenes</italic>. For this purpose, expression of <italic>htrA</italic><sub><italic>py</italic></sub> was measured using qRT-PCR. Surprisingly, expression of <italic>htrA</italic><sub><italic>py</italic></sub> was not decreased in strains 1529&#x00394;<italic>spy1236</italic> and MDYK&#x00394;<italic>spy1236,</italic> compared with the parental strains 1529 and MDYK (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>a and b). Therefore, we could not conclude that the contribution of the Spy1236 sensor kinase to oxidative stress tolerance was mediated by the HtrA protein in <italic>S. pyogenes.</italic> This result evoked further questions about what mediates control of oxidative stress tolerance by Spy1236 in <italic>S. pyogenes.</italic> In addition to HtrA, probably, there are at least two systems (NrdR- and PolA1-dependent, respectively) for oxidative stress tolerance in <italic>S. pyogenes.</italic> NrdR is a transcription factor first described in <italic>Streptomyces coelicolor</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>] that regulates the expression of ribonucleotide reductase genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>]. The ribonucleotide reductase genes are involved in the proliferation of <italic>Salmonella</italic> Typhymurium inside macrophages [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>]. PolA1, a putative DNA polymerase I, has been reported to contribute to peroxide stress defenses in <italic>S. pyogenes</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>]. Therefore, we measured the expression of <italic>nrdR</italic> and <italic>polA1</italic> (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>a and b), and observed that their expression levels were slightly decreased in strains 1529&#x00394;<italic>spy1236</italic> and MDYK&#x00394;<italic>spy1236,</italic> compared with the parental strains (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>a and b).</p><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><bold>Expression levels of Spy1236-regulated genes evaluated using qRT-PCR. (a)</bold> Expression in 1529&#x00394;<italic>spy1236</italic> mutant relative to that in the wild-type strain (1529). <bold>(b)</bold> Expression in MDYK&#x00394;<italic>spy1236</italic> mutant relative to that in the wild-type strain (MDYK). Error bars represent the SEM of at least three biological repeats.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1756-0500-7-189-6"/></fig><p>Thus, the contribution of Spy1236 (CiaH<sub>py</sub>) sensor kinase to oxidative stress tolerance may not be mediated via HtrA in <italic>S. pyogenes</italic> (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref>: Figure S2). If this hypothesis is true, what factor mediates the contribution of Spy1236 to the tolerance? The slightly decreased expression of <italic>polA1</italic> (and/or <italic>nrdR</italic>) may be insufficient to explain why <italic>spy1236</italic> mutant that the expression of <italic>htrA</italic> is increased is lower than the parental wild type in the oxidative tolerance ability. Our next experiments will attempt to identify a Spy1236 regulon.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>In this study, we have demonstrated that the CiaH<sub>py</sub> sensor kinase of <italic>S. pyogenes</italic> is involved in the response to acid and/or oxidative stresses, as are the related sensor kinases in <italic>S. mutans</italic> and/or <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic>. However, an important subject remains to be solved; i.e., it is still unclear how the CiaR/H<sub>py</sub> two-component regulatory system is involved in the virulence of <italic>S. pyogenes</italic>, whereas the CiaR/H two-component regulatory systems in <italic>S. mutans</italic> and <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic> are already known to be involved in regulating virulence. At least using a mouse infection model, the virulence of &#x00394;<italic>spy1236</italic> mutants is not significantly different from that of the parental <italic>S. pyogenes</italic> strains (Tatsuno <italic>et al</italic>., unpublished results). However the infection model seems to investigate the middle to late, but not the early stages of infection, because more than 10<sup>7</sup>&#x000a0;CFU of bacteria are inoculated into each mouse (10&#x02013;12&#x000a0;g) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>], and this number is equivalent to &#x0003e;10<sup>10</sup>&#x000a0;CFU in a human. Therefore, the CiaH<sub>py</sub> sensor kinase of <italic>S. pyogenes</italic> may not be important for virulence in the late stage of the infection, whereas it is still possible that CiaH<sub>py</sub> confers some benefits to <italic>S. pyogenes</italic> in earlier infection stages, as proposed for the CovS sensor kinase in a previous study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>].</p><p>The present and previous studies suggested that CO<sub>2</sub> condition is important for the triggering the function of Spy1236, but not of Spy1622 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. There are some helpful reports to discuss the potential mechanism about why CO<sub>2</sub> is required for triggering Spy1236 regulatory function [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>]. M1 and PrtF1/SfbI are both fibronectin binding proteins, which are required for <italic>S. pyogenes</italic> invasion of mammalian cells. PrtF1/SfbI expression is enhanced in an O<sub>2</sub>-rich environment, while M1 expression is greater at higher CO<sub>2</sub> partial pressure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>]. It has been explained that the differential regulation of these two Fn-binding proteins in high O<sub>2</sub> or high CO<sub>2</sub> may allow <italic>S. pyogenes</italic> to adapt to several different <italic>in vivo</italic> environments, such as those on the skin, on mucosal surfaces, and within the tonsils. When <italic>S. pyogenes</italic> encounters acid stress at the epithelial surface of the host, the bacterium might need the expression of different genes, compared with the genes required when exposed to acid and/or oxidative stresses in deeper tissues. If this hypothesis is true, the Spy1236 regulon should be different from a Spy1622 regulon. Although CovR was already found to influence transcription of 15% of all chromosomal genes using DNA microarrays [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>], such analysis has not been adopted for the other two-component systems in <italic>S. pyogenes</italic>. Our next experiments will attempt to identify the Spy1236 and the Spy1622 regulons.</p><p>Not only the present study but also previous studies have not ever determine whether CiaH directly senses acidic signal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>]. Although the established method to address this question does not exist as far as we know, if the phosphorylation status or regulatory activity of cognate response regulator, or the expression of Spy1236-regulated genes is demonstrated, they may provide some answers to the question.</p><sec><title>Availability of supporting data</title><p>There are three supporting data of Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>: Figure S1, Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref>: Figure S2, and Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3">3</xref>: Figure S3.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Abbreviations</title><p>BHI-Y: Brain-heart infusion yeast; TH-YE: Todd Hewitt yeast.</p></sec><sec><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>IT conceived the study. IT, RO, and TH designed and performed the experimental work with help by YZ and MI. All authors contributed to the data analysis. IT wrote the original manuscript. TH helped to produce the final manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S1"><caption><title>Additional file 1: Figure S1</title><p>Schematic representations of the pLZ-htrA<sub>forward</sub> and pLZ-htrA<sub>reverse</sub> plasmids used for overexpression of the <italic>htrA</italic> gene in <italic>S. pyogenes</italic>.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1756-0500-7-189-S1.ppt"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S2"><caption><title>Additional file 2: Figure S2</title><p>Hypothetical working model for the response to oxidative stress mediated by the two-component system Spy1236-1237. HtrA is regulated by systems other than Spy1236 in <italic>S. pyogenes</italic>. Dotted arrows indicate hypothetical pathways.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1756-0500-7-189-S2.ppt"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S3"><caption><title>Additional file 3: Figure S3</title><p>Expression levels of <italic>htrA</italic> and <italic>polA1</italic> in 1529&#x00394;<italic>spy1236</italic> (pLZ-htrA<sub>reverse</sub>) relative to those in 1529&#x00394;<italic>spy1236</italic> (pLZ-htrA<sub>forward</sub>) evaluated using qRT-PCR. The expression of <italic>htrA</italic> in 1529&#x00394;<italic>spy1236</italic> (pLZ-htrA<sub>reverse</sub>) was 1.5 (&#x000b1; 0.1) times that in 1529&#x00394;<italic>spy1236</italic> (pLZ- htrA<sub>forward</sub>), while the expression of <italic>polA1</italic> in 1529&#x00394;<italic>spy1236</italic> (pLZ-htrA<sub>reverse</sub>) was 0.94 (&#x000b1; 0.08) times that in 1529&#x00394;<italic>spy1236</italic> (pLZ- htrA<sub>forward</sub>). Error bars represent the SEM of four experiments.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1756-0500-7-189-S3.ppt"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><sec><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We thank Keisuke Iwamoto, Hiroshi Tsuge, Yukumi Kato, and Hideyuki Matsui for technical assistance and Dr. Hiroyuki Abe for the helpful advice. This study was supported by JSPS KAKENHI Grant numbers 21790425 and 24590531, a Grant-in-Aid for Research in Nagoya City University, a grant from Ohyama Health Foundation, and a grant from the 24<sup>th</sup> General Assembly of the Japanese Association of Medical Sciences (Medical Science Promotion Fund). The authors would like to thank Enago (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.enago.jp">http://www.enago.jp</ext-link>) for the English language review.</p></sec><ref-list><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cone</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Woodard</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlievert</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomory</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><article-title>Clinical and bacteriologic observations of a toxic shock-like syndrome due to Streptococcus pyogenes</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>1987</year><volume>317</volume><fpage>146</fpage><lpage>149</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJM198707163170305</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3299086</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hoge</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Talkington</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Breiman</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>MacNeill</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Englender</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><article-title>The changing epidemiology of invasive group A streptococcal infections and the emergence of streptococcal toxic shock-like syndrome. A retrospective population-based study</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>1993</year><volume>269</volume><fpage>384</fpage><lpage>389</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.1993.03500030082037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8418346</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Facklam</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Breiman</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><article-title>Changing epidemiology of group A streptococcal infection in the USA</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>1990</year><volume>336</volume><fpage>1167</fpage><lpage>1171</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0140-6736(90)92777-F</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1978035</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><article-title>Invasive group A streptococcal infections: the past, present and future</article-title><source>Pediatr Infect Dis J</source><year>1994</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>561</fpage><lpage>566</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00006454-199406000-00033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8078755</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hasegawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hashikawa</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Torii</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Factors determining prognosis in streptococcal toxic shock-like syndrome: results of a nationwide investigation in Japan</article-title><source>Microbes Infect</source><year>2004</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1073</fpage><lpage>1077</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.micinf.2004.06.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15380776</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Agarwal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Agarwal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pancholi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Pancholi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><article-title>Role of serine/threonine phosphatase (SP-STP) in Streptococcus pyogenes physiology and virulence</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2011</year><volume>286</volume><fpage>41368</fpage><lpage>41380</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M111.286690</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21917918</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Musser</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Shelburne</surname><given-names>SA</given-names><suffix>3rd</suffix></name><article-title>A decade of molecular pathogenomic analysis of group A Streptococcus</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><year>2009</year><volume>119</volume><fpage>2455</fpage><lpage>2463</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI38095</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19729843</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kreikemeyer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>McIver</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Podbielski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Virulence factor regulation and regulatory networks in Streptococcus pyogenes and their impact on pathogen-host interactions</article-title><source>Trends Microbiol</source><year>2003</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>224</fpage><lpage>232</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0966-842X(03)00098-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12781526</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stock</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name><name><surname>Goudreau</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name><article-title>Two-component signal transduction</article-title><source>Annu Rev Biochem</source><year>2000</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>183</fpage><lpage>215</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.biochem.69.1.183</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10966457</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sumby</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitney</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Graviss</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>DeLeo</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><name><surname>Musser</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><article-title>Genome-wide analysis of group a streptococci reveals a mutation that modulates global phenotype and disease specificity</article-title><source>PLoS Pathog</source><year>2006</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>e5</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.0020005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16446783</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wessels</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><article-title>Identification of csrR/csrS, a genetic locus that regulates hyaluronic acid capsule synthesis in group A Streptococcus</article-title><source>Mol Microbiol</source><year>1998</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>209</fpage><lpage>219</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2958.1998.01057.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9786197</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bernish</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>van de Rijn</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><article-title>Characterization of a two-component system in Streptococcus pyogenes which is involved in regulation of hyaluronic acid production</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1999</year><volume>274</volume><fpage>4786</fpage><lpage>4793</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.274.8.4786</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9988717</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Federle</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>McIver</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><article-title>A response regulator that represses transcription of several virulence operons in the group A streptococcus</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>1999</year><volume>181</volume><fpage>3649</fpage><lpage>3657</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10368137</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Heath</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>DiRita</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Barg</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name><surname>Engleberg</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><article-title>A two-component regulatory system, CsrR-CsrS, represses expression of three Streptococcus pyogenes virulence factors, hyaluronic acid capsule, streptolysin S, and pyrogenic exotoxin B</article-title><source>Infect Immun</source><year>1999</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>5298</fpage><lpage>5305</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10496909</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Engleberg</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Heath</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rivera</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>DiRita</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name><article-title>Spontaneous mutations in the CsrRS two-component regulatory system of Streptococcus pyogenes result in enhanced virulence in a murine model of skin and soft tissue infection</article-title><source>J Infect Dis</source><year>2001</year><volume>183</volume><fpage>1043</fpage><lpage>1054</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/319291</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11237829</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ichikawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Minami</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Isaka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tatsuno</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasegawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><article-title>Analysis of two-component sensor proteins involved in the response to acid stimuli in Streptococcus pyogenes</article-title><source>Microbiology</source><year>2011</year><volume>157</volume><fpage>3187</fpage><lpage>3194</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/mic.0.050534-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21873405</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tatsuno</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Okada</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Isaka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasegawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><article-title>Partial loss of CovS function in Streptococcus pyogenes causes severe invasive disease</article-title><source>BMC Res Notes</source><year>2013</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>126</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1756-0500-6-126</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23537349</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Koller</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Manetti</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kreikemeyer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lembke</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Margarit</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Grandi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Podbielski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Typing of the pilus-protein-encoding FCT region and biofilm formation as novel parameters in epidemiological investigations of Streptococcus pyogenes isolates from various infection sites</article-title><source>J Med Microbiol</source><year>2010</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>442</fpage><lpage>452</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/jmm.0.013581-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20007764</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>DiRita</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mekalanos</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><article-title>Genetic regulation of bacterial virulence</article-title><source>Annu Rev Genet</source><year>1989</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>455</fpage><lpage>482</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.ge.23.120189.002323</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2694940</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Caparon</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Geist</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name><surname>Perez-Casal</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><article-title>Environmental regulation of virulence in group A streptococci: transcription of the gene encoding M protein is stimulated by carbon dioxide</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>1992</year><volume>174</volume><fpage>5693</fpage><lpage>5701</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1512202</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hasegawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Okamoto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamimura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tatsuno</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Hashikawa</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Yabutani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Isaka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Minami</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Detection of invasive protein profile of Streptococcus pyogenes M1 isolates from pharyngitis patients</article-title><source>APMIS</source><year>2010</year><volume>118</volume><fpage>167</fpage><lpage>178</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-0463.2009.02574.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20132182</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tatsuno</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Isaka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Minami</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasegawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><article-title>NADase as a target molecule of in vivo suppression of the toxicity in the invasive M-1 group A Streptococcal isolates</article-title><source>BMC Microbiol</source><year>2010</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>144</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2180-10-144</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20470439</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ferretti</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>McShan</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ajdic</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Savic</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Savic</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyon</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Primeaux</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sezate</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Suvorov</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Kenton</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name><surname>Najar</surname><given-names>FZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Clifton</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Roe</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>McLaughlin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><article-title>Complete genome sequence of an M1 strain of Streptococcus pyogenes</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2001</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>4658</fpage><lpage>4663</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.071559398</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11296296</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Suvorov</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferretti</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><article-title>Physical and genetic chromosomal map of an M type 1 strain of Streptococcus pyogenes</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>1996</year><volume>178</volume><fpage>5546</fpage><lpage>5549</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8808951</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Okada</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Tatsuno</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanski</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Caparon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasakawa</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><article-title>Streptococcus pyogenes protein F promotes invasion of HeLa cells</article-title><source>Microbiology</source><year>1998</year><volume>144</volume><fpage>3079</fpage><lpage>3086</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/00221287-144-11-3079</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9846743</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerr</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>McCluskey</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><article-title>Control of virulence by the two-component system CiaR/H is mediated via HtrA, a major virulence factor of Streptococcus pneumoniae</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>2004</year><volume>186</volume><fpage>5258</fpage><lpage>5266</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.186.16.5258-5266.2004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15292127</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Eguchi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kubo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsunaga</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Igarashi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Utsumi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><article-title>Development of an antivirulence drug against Streptococcus mutans: repression of biofilm formation, acid tolerance, and competence by a histidine kinase inhibitor, walkmycin C</article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>2011</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>1475</fpage><lpage>1484</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.01646-10</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21282451</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lemme</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sztajer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner-Dobler</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><article-title>Characterization of mleR, a positive regulator of malolactic fermentation and part of the acid tolerance response in Streptococcus mutans</article-title><source>BMC Microbiol</source><year>2010</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>58</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2180-10-58</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20178568</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Miyoshi-Akiyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikebe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Uchiyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirikae</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawamura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><article-title>Use of DNA arrays to identify a mutation in the negative regulator, csrR, responsible for the high virulence of a naturally occurring type M3 group A streptococcus clinical isolate</article-title><source>J Infect Dis</source><year>2006</year><volume>193</volume><fpage>1677</fpage><lpage>1684</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/504263</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16703511</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Biswas</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Drake</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Erkina</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Biswas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>Involvement of sensor kinases in the stress tolerance response of Streptococcus mutans</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>2008</year><volume>190</volume><fpage>68</fpage><lpage>77</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.00990-07</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17965153</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name><name><surname>Sutherland</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sisson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Mai</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><article-title>Global transcriptional analysis of acid-inducible genes in Streptococcus mutans: multiple two-component systems involved in acid adaptation</article-title><source>Microbiology</source><year>2009</year><volume>155</volume><fpage>3322</fpage><lpage>3332</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/mic.0.031591-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19608608</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Seol</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Woo</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ichihara</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ha</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><article-title>Protease Do is essential for survival of Escherichia coli at high temperatures: its identity with the htrA gene product</article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><year>1991</year><volume>176</volume><fpage>730</fpage><lpage>736</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0006-291X(05)80245-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2025286</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Spiess</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Beil</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehrmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>A temperature-dependent switch from chaperone to protease in a widely conserved heat shock protein</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1999</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>339</fpage><lpage>347</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(00)80743-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10319814</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Bolken</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeller</surname><given-names>GO</given-names></name><name><surname>Hruby</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><article-title>Conserved DegP protease in gram-positive bacteria is essential for thermal and oxidative tolerance and full virulence in Streptococcus pyogenes</article-title><source>Infect Immun</source><year>2001</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>5538</fpage><lpage>5545</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.69.9.5538-5545.2001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11500427</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Borovok</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorovitz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Yanku</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schreiber</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gust</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Chater</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Aharonowitz</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><article-title>Alternative oxygen-dependent and oxygen-independent ribonucleotide reductases in Streptomyces: cross-regulation and physiological role in response to oxygen limitation</article-title><source>Mol Microbiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>1022</fpage><lpage>1035</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2004.04325.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15522084</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Case</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><name><surname>Akers</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>CT406 encodes a chlamydial ortholog of NrdR, a repressor of ribonucleotide reductase</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>2011</year><volume>193</volume><fpage>4396</fpage><lpage>4404</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.00294-11</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21725017</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Panosa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Roca</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibert</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><article-title>Ribonucleotide reductases of Salmonella typhimurium: transcriptional regulation and differential role in pathogenesis</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2010</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>e11328</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0011328</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20593029</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Toukoki</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gryllos</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><article-title>PolA1, a putative DNA polymerase I, is coexpressed with PerR and contributes to peroxide stress defenses of group A Streptococcus</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>2013</year><volume>195</volume><fpage>717</fpage><lpage>725</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.01847-12</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23204468</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dedhar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cleary</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><article-title>Paxillin phosphorylation: bifurcation point downstream of integrin-linked kinase (ILK) in streptococcal invasion</article-title><source>Cell Microbiol</source><year>2007</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1519</fpage><lpage>1528</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1462-5822.2007.00889.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17298394</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hyland</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Cleary</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><article-title>Protein F1 and Streptococcus pyogenes resistance to phagocytosis</article-title><source>Infect Immun</source><year>2007</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>3188</fpage><lpage>3191</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.01745-06</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17371855</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fogg</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Okada</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Geist</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanski</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Caparon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Regulation of host cell recognition in Streptococcus pyogenes</article-title><source>Dev Biol Stand</source><year>1995</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>137</fpage><lpage>144</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8586164</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Smoot</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Migliaccio</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Virtaneva</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sturdevant</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Porcella</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Federle</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Musser</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><article-title>Virulence control in group A Streptococcus by a two-component gene regulatory system: global expression profiling and in vivo infection modeling</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2002</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>13855</fpage><lpage>13860</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.202353699</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12370433</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>