<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Braz J Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Braz. J. Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bjm</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">bjm</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Brazilian Journal of Microbiology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1517-8382</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1678-4405</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Sociedade Brasileira de Microbiologia</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24031365</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3769713</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S1517-838220090002000020</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S1517-838220090002000020</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Medical Microbiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Research Paper</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Candidiasis in pediatric patients with cancer interned in a university hospital</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>De Carvalho Parahym</surname><given-names>Ana Maria Rabelo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>De Melo</surname><given-names>Luciana Resende Bandeira</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>De Morais</surname><given-names>Vera L&#x000fa;cia Lins</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Neves</surname><given-names>Rejane Pereira</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="au1"><label>1</label><institution>Departamento de Micologia, Centro de Ci&#x000ea;ncias Biol&#x000f3;gicas, Universidade Federal de Pernambuco</institution>, <addr-line>Recife, PE</addr-line>, <country>Brasil</country></aff><aff id="au2"><label>2</label><institution>Hospital Universit&#x000e1;rio Oswaldo Cruz, Pronto de Socorro Cardiol&#x000f3;gico</institution>, <addr-line>Recife, PE</addr-line>, <country>Brasil</country></aff><aff id="au3"><label>3</label><institution>Hospital Universit&#x000e1;rio Oswaldo Cruz, Centro de Oncologia</institution>, <addr-line>Recife, PE</addr-line>, <country>Brasil</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><sup>*</sup>Corresponding Author. Mailing address: R. Major Armando de Souza Melo, 42/204, Boa Viagem, Recife, PE, Brasil. 51030-180. Fax: (+5581) 21268482. E-mail: <email>aana_mrc@hotmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>Apr-Jun</season><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>1</day><month>6</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>40</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>321</fpage><lpage>324</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>02</day><month>1</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>09</day><month>3</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>03</day><month>5</month><year>2009</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; Sociedade Brasileira de Microbiologia</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2009</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/"><license-p>All the content of the journal, except where otherwise noted, is licensed under a <underline>Creative Commons License</underline></license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Fungi are common causes of infection in immunocompromised patients. <italic>Candida</italic> species are frequently involved in these cases. In order to investigate candidiasis in pediatric patients with cancer, clinical samples were collected from one hundred and twenty two patients interned in the Oswaldo Cruz University Hospital in Recife, Brazil. Yeasts were isolated from thirty-four clinical samples. The species isolated were: <italic>Candida albicans</italic> (fourteen isolates), <italic>C. parapsilosis</italic> (nine isolates), <italic>C. guilliermondii</italic> (two isolates) and <italic>C. tropicalis</italic> (two isolates). We found that candidemia was most frequent in patients with malignant hematology and that <italic>C. parapsilosis</italic> infections caused the highest mortality.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd><italic>Candida</italic> spp.</kwd><kwd>fungi infection</kwd><kwd>candidaemia</kwd><kwd>pediatric patient</kwd><kwd>cancer</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Fungal infection is an important cause of morbidity and mortality in immunocompromised pediatric cancer patients (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19">19</xref>). The underlying disease, neutropenia and other risk factors, substantially alter the epidemiology of infection allowing the development of opportunistic infectious processes at some point during the immunosuppressive therapy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">24</xref>).</p><p>The risk of fungal infection in patients with cancer is also a function of the balance between the integrity of host defence mechanisms and the intensity of exposure to potentially pathogenic microorganisms in the host&#x02019;s environment (especially hospital pathogens) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">26</xref>). Although anti-fungal drugs are administered at the start of chemotherapy this prophylaxis is often ineffective (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">20</xref>). In addition, the use of wide spectrum antibiotics, treatment with corticosteroids and cytostatic substances, and invasive surgical procedures often predispose children to the development of fungal infections (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">16</xref>).</p><p>The main opportunistic infectious agents are <italic>Candida</italic> species present in the gastrointestinal tract (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">12</xref>). <italic>Candida</italic> species produce infections that range from non&#x02013;life-threatening muco-cutaneous illnesses to invasive processes that may involve virtually any organ in the body (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref>). For example, epithelial cells of the buccal mucosa are very sensitive to chemotherapeutic drugs which may predispose the patient to candidiasis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">15</xref>). Fungal septicemia is frequently associated with a primary buccal infections (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">7</xref>).</p><p>Since fungal infections are common in patients with cancer and lead to poor prognostic, the present study had the objective of evaluating the epidemiology of <italic>Candida</italic> infection in oncologic pediatric patients in the Oswaldo Cruz University Hospital / Pediatric Oncology Center, Recife, Brazil.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><p>This study was carried out between March 2006 and July 2007. The samples were collected according to the physicians request from 122 patients with cancer who were treated with radiotherapy and chemotherapy and that showed clinical manifestations of fungal infection such as fever, macular erythematous rash in the inguinal region, difficulty and burning when urinating, ulcerative lesions with white and cream deposits in the oral cavity. We collected blood samples from all neutropenic patients who had persistent fever and were not responding to antibiotics. All patients received prophylactic antifungal therapy with fluconazole 200 mg/day for five to ten days.</p><p>All samples were collected over a period of three consecutive days. Venous blood samples were collected aseptically in central and peripheral vein by venipuncture into VACUTAINER&#x000ae; tubes using EDTA anticoagulant. Oral samples were obtained by swabbing the palatal and buccal mucosa. Urine specimens were collected in aseptic tubes after the urinary catheter had been removed and samples taken from the inguinal region. All samples were processed immediately after collection by standard methods for mycological diagnosis (direct examination and isolation in culture) at the Medical Mycology Laboratory, Federal University of Pernambuco, Recife, Brazil.</p><p>The direct examination was performed on the fresh samples (without clarification and staining) or clarified with 20% potassium hydroxide solution when necessary. For isolation, spreading was performed on the surface of Sabouraud agar with 0.5 mg of yeast extract/L and 50 mg chloranphenicol/L, and then incubated at between 30&#x000ba;C and 35&#x000ba;C in an aerobic atmosphere for 15 days. After isolation and culture purification, identification was achieved using recognized macroscopic, microscopic, and physiologic features according to the criteria described by Barnett et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref>) and Hoog et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>) and VITEK 120 test methods.</p></sec><sec><title>RESULTS</title><p>Diagnostic identification was based on both the presence of yeast cells (and some times pseudohyphae and true hyphae) in direct examination (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>) and the isolation of the causal agent in pure culture. The isolates ferment and assimilate carbohydrates and assimilate ammonium sulfate, which distinguishes it from other members of the genus <italic>Candida.</italic></p><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Direct examination revealed yeast cells in blood-1000x (A) hyphae hyaline and yeast cells in inguinal region (B), oral secretion (C) and urine (D) -400x.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="bjm-40-321-g001"/></fig><p>Candidiasis occurred in 28 patients, 21 of these had candidaemia, five oral candidiasis and candidaemia, one urinary infection and candidaemia and one inguinal candidiasis. Yeast colonies were isolated in 27 samples from blood, five from oral cavity and one from urine and inguinal region. This analysis yielded a distribution of 14 instances of <italic>Candida albicans</italic>, nine of <italic>C. guilliermondii</italic>, nine of <italic>C. parapsilosis</italic> and two of <italic>C. tropicalis</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>). Death rates due to infection by these species were 50%, 11%, 56% and 50% respectively.</p><table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Yeast isolated from cultures in Oswaldo Cruz University Hospital/ Pediatric Oncology Center in the period of March of 2006 the July of 2007.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="none"><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Yeast species</bold></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Localization</bold></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>N&#x000b0; of isolates</bold></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Total n&#x000b0; (% of total n&#x000b0;)</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Candida albicans</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blood</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.59%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oral cavity</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.71%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inguinal region</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.94%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urine</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,94%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>C. parapsilosis</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blood</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26,47%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>C. guilliermondii</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blood</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26,47%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>C. tropicalis</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blood</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,88%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Systemic blood infection was the most prevalent fungal infection and of the 27 samples of blood positive for fungi 17 (63%) came from patients with malignant hematology and 10 (37%) from patients with solid tumors. Thus candidaemia was more common in patients with malignant hematology.</p></sec><sec><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>Oral candidiasis represents a problem for children with cancer due to the possibility of a systemic infection that may be life threatening. However, it has been reported that the use of preventive therapy before the establishment of chemotherapy may decrease the incidence of oral candidiasis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">22</xref>). In our patients, preventive therapy with oral fluconazole also reduced the incidence of oral candidiaisis.</p><p>About 10 to 15% of urinary tract hospital infections are due to <italic>Candida</italic> spp., and its prevalence is increasing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27">27</xref>). Importantly, in all relevant studies candiduria was detected prior to development of candidemia indicating a probable ascending route of infection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25">25</xref>). In our study the same <italic>Candida</italic> species was detected in the urine and blood of one patient indicating the occurrence of candiduria as possible route of systemic infection.</p><p>Although <italic>C. albicans</italic> remains the most common pathogen in oropharyngeal, urine and cutaneous candidiasis, non-albicans species are increasingly associated with invasive candidiasis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref>). These epidemiologic changes are attributable to a combination of factors, such as the use of fluconazole prophylaxis, changes in patient demographics and underlying diseases, and use of therapeutic strategies that may pose unique risks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">17</xref>).</p><p>For example, <italic>C. guilliermondii</italic> is rarely isolated in fungaemia cases but is emerging as a cause of candidaemia in cancer patients (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref>). This yeast was often isolated in our study with a high incidence in cancer patients. <italic>C. parapsilosis</italic> is the second most common species found in patients with candidaemia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">8</xref>). The reasons for the rising incidence of <italic>C. parapsilosis</italic> candidaemia are not completely known, although venous catheters and parenteral nutrition have been recognized as specific risk factors and have a poor prognosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">2</xref>). In our study all patients with this infection were using venous catheters and parenteral nutrition. Possibly the large number of deaths caused by this infection occurred because of the constant use of such instruments that have become recurring sources of infection resulting in a poor prognosis for the patient. The presence of yeast in the blood may be associated with the use of venous catheters and, in many cases the same yeast species was isolated in blood culture and in the microbiological examination of the catheter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref>).</p><p>Patients with cancer are commonly affected by fungal infections. However, in patients with malignant hematology these are more frequently due to the aggressive anti-neoplastic therapy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">26</xref>). In our research we found the same result.</p><p>In conclusion, fungal bloodstream infections are most common in pediatric patients with cancer. <italic>C. albicans</italic> is the most common etiologic agent. <italic>C. guilliermondii</italic> and <italic>C</italic>. <italic>parapsilosis</italic> are more common in bloodstream infections in patients with cancer. <italic>C. parapsilosis</italic> causes greatest mortality in candidaemia episodes. <italic>C. guilliermondii</italic> fungaemia is rare but is frequently seen in cancer patients and candidaemia is most frequently observed in patients with malignant hematology.</p></sec></body><back><sec><title>RESUMO</title><sec><title>Candid&#x000ed;ases em pacientes pedi&#x000e1;tricos com c&#x000e2;ncer internados em um hospital universit&#x000e1;rio</title><p>Os fungos s&#x000e3;o causas comuns de infec&#x000e7;&#x000f5;es em pacientes imunocomprometidos e esp&#x000e9;cies de <italic>Candida</italic> s&#x000e3;o freq&#x000fc;entemente envolvidas nesses casos. A fim de investigar infec&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o f&#x000fa;ngica em pacientes pedi&#x000e1;tricos com c&#x000e2;ncer, amostras cl&#x000ed;nicas foram coletadas de cento e vinte dois pacientes internados no Hospital Universit&#x000e1;rio Oswaldo Cruz em Recife, Brasil. Leveduras foram isoladas de trinta e quatro amostras cl&#x000ed;nicas. As leveduras isoladas foram: <italic>Candida albicans</italic> (catorze isolados), <italic>C. parapsilosis</italic> (nove isolados), <italic>C. guilliermondii</italic> (dois isolados) e <italic>C. tropicalis</italic> (dois isolados). Descobrimos que candidemia foi mais freq&#x000fc;ente em doentes com hematologias malignas e que <italic>C. parapsilosis</italic> apresentou maior mortalidade.</p><p><bold>Palavras chave</bold>: <italic>Candida</italic> spp., infec&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o f&#x000fa;ngica, candidemia, paciente pedi&#x000e1;trico, c&#x000e2;ncer.</p></sec></sec><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="b1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alberth</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Majoros</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kovalecz</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Borb&#x000e1;s</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Szegedi</surname><given-names>I.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000e1;rton</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiss</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Significance of oral <italic>Candida</italic> infections in children with c&#x000e2;ncer</article-title><source>Pathol. Oncol. Res.</source><year>2006</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>237</fpage><lpage>241</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17189988</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Almirante</surname><given-names>B.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez</surname><given-names>B.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cuenca-Estrella</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Planes</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Almela</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mensa</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanchez</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayats</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gimenez</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pere Saballs</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fridkin</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez-Tudela</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Warnock</surname><given-names>D.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pahissa</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidemiology and predictors of mortality in cases of <italic>Candida</italic> bloodstream infections: results from population-based surveillance, Barcelona, Spain, from 2002 to 2003.</article-title><source>J. Clin. Microbiol.</source><year>2005</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>1829</fpage><lpage>1835</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15815004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>&#x000c1;lvarez-Lerma</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nolla-Salas</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Le&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Palomar</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jord&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carrasco</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bobillo</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Candiduria in critically ill patients admitted to intensive care medical units.</article-title><source>Intensive Care. Med.</source><year>2003</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>1069</fpage><lpage>1076</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12756441</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barnett</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Paine</surname><given-names>R.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yarrow</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Yeasts: Characteristics and Identification.</source><year>2000</year><publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc><publisher-name>CambridgeUniversity Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="b5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Binelli</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moretti</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Assis</surname><given-names>R.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauaia</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Menezes</surname><given-names>P.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Geiger</surname><given-names>D.C.P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mikami</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyaji</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barone</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Investigation of the possible association between nosocomial candiduria and candidaemia.</article-title><source>Clin. Microbiol. Infec.</source><year>2006</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>538</fpage><lpage>543</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16700702</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Castro</surname><given-names>T.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coutinho</surname><given-names>H.D.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gedeon</surname><given-names>C.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Santana</surname><given-names>W.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Souza</surname><given-names>L.B.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mecanismos de resist&#x000ea;ncia da <italic>Candida</italic> Sp. Wwa antif&#x000fa;ngicos.</article-title><source>Infarma</source><year>2006</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>10</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Childers</surname><given-names>N.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stinnett</surname><given-names>E.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>J.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Castleberry</surname><given-names>R.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dasanayake</surname><given-names>A.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oral complications in children with cancer.</article-title><source>Oral Surg. Oral Med. Oral Pathol.</source><year>1993</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>47</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8419873</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Slavinski</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lott</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arthington-Skaggs</surname><given-names>B.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brandt</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Webb</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Currier</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Flowers</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fridkin</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hajjeh</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidemiologic and molecular characterization of an outbreak of <italic>Candida parapsilosis</italic> bloodstream infections in a community hospital.</article-title><source>J. Clin. Microbiol.</source><year>2004</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>4468</fpage><lpage>4472</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15472295</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Hoog</surname><given-names>G.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guarro</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gene</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Figueras</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Atlas of clinical fungi.</source><year>2000</year><publisher-loc>Utrecht/R&#x000e9;us</publisher-loc><publisher-name>The Netherlands, Centraalbureau voor Schimmelcultures, Universitat Rovira i Virgili,</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="b10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Diekema</surname><given-names>D.J.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Messer</surname><given-names>S.A.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brueggemann</surname><given-names>A.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidemiology of candidemia: 3-year results from the emerging infections and the epidemiology of Iowa organisms study.</article-title><source>J. Clin. Microbiol.</source><year>2002</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>1298</fpage><lpage>1302</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11923348</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Durango</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hern&#x000e1;ndez</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zapata</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sierra</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pe&#x000f1;a</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aristiz&#x000e1;bal</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alzate</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x000f3;pez</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Posada</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Colonizaci&#x000f3;n por especies de <italic>Candida</italic> en orofaringe y tracto gastrointestinal en ni&#x000f1;os.</article-title><source>Infection</source><year>2002</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>156</fpage><lpage>61</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eggimann</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Garbino</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pittet</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidemiology of <italic>Candida</italic> species infections in critically ill non-immunosuppressed patients.</article-title><source>Lancet. Infect. Dis.</source><year>2003</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>685</fpage><lpage>702</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14592598</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names>A.C.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sousa J&#x000fa;nior</surname><given-names>F.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Oliveira</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Calich</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Milan</surname><given-names>E.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of <italic>Candida</italic> species in umbilical catheters implanted in Newborns in Natal, Brazil.</article-title><source>Braz. J. Microbiol.</source><year>2007</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>104</fpage><lpage>107</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghannoum</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Candida</italic> biofilms: antifungal resistance and emerging therapeutic options.</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Invest. Drugs.</source><year>2004</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>186</fpage><lpage>97</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lockhart</surname><given-names>P.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonis</surname><given-names>S.T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relationship of oral complications to peripheral blood leukocyte and platelet counts in patients receiving cancer chemothe-rapy.</article-title><source>Oral. Surg. Oral. Med. Oral. Pathol.</source><year>1979</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>28</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">313547</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lopez Sastre</surname><given-names>J.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coto</surname><given-names>C.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernandez</surname><given-names>C.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neonatal sepsis of nosocomial origin: an epidemiological study from the Grupo de Hospitales</article-title><source>Castrillo. J. Perinat. Med.</source><year>2002</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>157</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marr</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Invasive <italic>Candida</italic> infections: the changing epidemiology.</article-title><source>Oncology (Williston Park, N.Y.)</source><year>2004</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>14</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nucci</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Anaissie</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Revisiting the source of candidaemia: skin or gut?</article-title><source>Clin. Infect. Dis.</source><year>2001</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>1959</fpage><lpage>1967</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11702290</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>Y.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Effmann</surname><given-names>E.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Godwin</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pulmonary infections in immunocompromised hosts: the importance of correlating the conventional radiologic appearance with the clinical setting.</article-title><source>Radiology</source><year>2000</year><volume>217</volume><fpage>647</fpage><lpage>56</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11110924</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paganini</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>B.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosanova</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Risk factors for nosocomial candidaemia: a case-control study in children.</article-title><source>J. Hosp. Infect.</source><year>2002</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>304</fpage><lpage>308</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12014905</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pappas</surname><given-names>P.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rex</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sobel</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Filler</surname><given-names>S.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dismukes</surname><given-names>W.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>T.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Guidelines for Treatment of Candidiasis.</article-title><source>Clin. Infec. Dis.</source><year>2004</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>161</fpage><lpage>89</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14699449</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rojas de Morales</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zambrano</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rivera</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Navas</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaparro</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernardonni</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rivera</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fonseca</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tirado</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oral-disease prevention in children with cancer: testing preventive protocol effectiveness.</article-title><source>Med. Oral.</source><year>2001</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>326</fpage><lpage>334</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11694865</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blitz</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shafran</surname><given-names>S.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of current management on morbidity and mortality in hospitalized adults with funguria.</article-title><source>J. Infect.</source><year>2004</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>248</fpage><lpage>252</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15337343</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soni</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagstaff</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fungal infection.</article-title><source>Curr. Anaesth. Crit. Care.</source><year>2005</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>231</fpage><lpage>241</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Talluri</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marella</surname><given-names>V.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shirazian</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wise</surname><given-names>G.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immune response in patients with persistent candiduria and occult candidemia</article-title><source>J. Urol.</source><year>1999</year><volume>162</volume><fpage>1361</fpage><lpage>1364</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10492197</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vento</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cainelli</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Infections in patients with cancer undergoing chemotherapy: aetiology, prevention, and treatment</article-title><source>Lancet. Oncol.</source><year>2003</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>595</fpage><lpage>604</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14554236</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weinberger</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sweet</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leibovici</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pitlik</surname><given-names>S.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Samra</surname><given-names>Z.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Correlation between candiduria and departmental antibiotic use.</article-title><source>J. Hosp. infect.</source><year>2003</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>183</fpage><lpage>186</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12623318</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>