<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Case Rep Endocrinol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Case Rep Endocrinol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CRIM.ENDOCRINOLOGY</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Case Reports in Endocrinology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2090-6501</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2090-651X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Hindawi Publishing Corporation</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23320206</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3534206</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2012/529730</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A Rare Corticotroph-Secreting Tumor with Coexisting Prolactin and Growth Hormone Staining Cells</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kannan</surname><given-names>Subramanian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Staugaitis</surname><given-names>Susan M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Weil</surname><given-names>Robert J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hatipoglu</surname><given-names>Betul</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><sup>1</sup>Department of Endocrinology, Diabetes and Metabolism, Cleveland Clinic Foundation, 9500 Euclid Avenue Desk F20, Cleveland, OH 44195, USA</aff><aff id="I2"><sup>2</sup>Departments of Anatomic Pathology and Neurosciences, Cleveland Clinic Foundation, 9500 Euclid Avenue Desk NC30, Cleveland, OH 44195, USA</aff><aff id="I3"><sup>3</sup>Division of Brain Tumor and Neuro-Oncology Center, Cleveland Clinic Foundation, 9500 Euclid Avenue Desk ND40, Cleveland, OH 44195, USA</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">*Subramanian Kannan: <email>kannans@ccf.org</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other"><p>Academic Editors: E. Hershkovitz and H. Kang</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>17</day><month>12</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>2012</volume><elocation-id>529730</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>10</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>29</day><month>11</month><year>2012</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2012 Subramanian Kannan et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Pituitary adenomas can express and secrete different hormones. Expression of pituitary hormones in nonneoplastic pituitary cells is regulated by different transcription factors. Some pituitary adenomas show plurihormonal expression. The most commonly reported plurihormonal adenomas are composed of somatotrophs, lactotrophs, thyrotrophs and gonadotrophs. Pituitary adenomas composed of both corticotroph and somatolactotroph secreting cells are not common because transcription factors regulating the expression of these hormones are different. We report a rare case of pituitary adenoma with concomitant corticotroph, prolactin, and growth hormone staining cells, review literature on similar cases, and discuss possible biological mechanisms underlying these plurihormonal tumors.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><title>1. Case Summary</title><p>A 52-year-old grocery store manager presented with symptoms of fatigue, poor libido, and erectile dysfunction for a two-year period. Onset was insidious and some of his symptoms were partially relieved by testosterone gel that was prescribed to him by his primary care doctor. He noted a 50&#x02009;lb weight gain in a period of 6 months that prompted him to see an endocrinologist. In addition to the fatigue, he noted increasing muscle pain and proximal weakness over the past 6 months. He complained of increased ring and shoe size but it was difficult to clarify whether this was related to his generalized weight gain or specifically to his acral enlargement. On review of symptoms, he noted easy bruisability but denied breast enlargement or galactorrhea. His hypertension was well controlled with two medications and was not diagnosed with glucose intolerance. Clinical exam revealed a morbidly obese male with BMI of 48. His obesity was truncal, and he had disproportionately thin proximal musculature. Abdomen exam revealed 1&#x02009;cm purple striae. His facial features were suggestive of cushingoid appearance. He did not have any definitive physical signs of acromegaly. His preoperative labs are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tab1">Table 1</xref>, which were was conclusive for Cushing's syndrome. He had mild elevation of prolactin (PRL), insulin-like growth factor (IGF-1) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tab1">Table 1</xref>). GH nadir after a 75&#x02009;g glucose challenge was 0.36&#x02009;ng/mL. MRI of the sella showed a pituitary microadenoma (5&#x02009;mm) with a normal appearing stalk (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>). Inferior petrosal sinus sampling confirmed the presence of pituitary source of ACTH hypersecretion. The patient underwent trans-sphenoidal resection of an unencapsulated tumor. The rest of the pituitary was carefully scrutinized with no evidence for additional tumors.</p><p>Histology of the resected tissue revealed one piece of tissue measuring 1&#x02009;mm<sup>2</sup> and that was composed of an adenoma with abundant relatively eosinophilic cytoplasm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2(a)</xref>). In addition, there were several smaller pieces of adenoma each measuring 0.2&#x02009;mm in greatest dimension. These cells had less abundant and more basophilic cytoplasm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2(b)</xref>). Immunohistochemistry was performed using antibodies to PRL, GH, ACTH, TSH, LH, and FSH. All of the cells in the larger adenoma were immunoreactive with antibodies to PRL (A0569, Dako), and rare cells were positive to GH (A0570, Dako, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2(c)</xref>). The cells of the small pieces of adenoma were ACTH positive (RB-9217-P0, Thermo-Fisher, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2(d)</xref>). There was no overlap between the prolactin-positive and ACTH-positive cells. No cells labeled with antibodies to FSH (M3504, Dako), LH (M3502, Dako), or TSH (112A-18, Cell Marque). The patient was supplemented with hydrocortisone postoperatively. His PRL and IGF-1 levels normalized (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tab2">Table 2</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>2. Discussion</title><p>Pituitary adenomas can express and secrete different hormones. Expression of pituitary hormones in nonneoplastic pituitary cells is regulated by different transcription factors. Pituitary-specific positive transcription factor 1 (PIT-1) regulates expression of GH, PRL, and TSH, and the steroidogenic factor 1 (STF-1) and endothelial transcription factor GATA 2 regulate expression of LH and FSH. ACTH expression is regulated by tumor homeobox transcription factor19 (TBX 19, also known as TPIT) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">9</xref>]. Some pituitary adenomas show plurihormonal expression. The most commonly reported plurihormonal adenomas coexpress growth hormone (GH), prolactin (PRL), and/or thyroid stimulating hormone (TSH) or luteinizing hormone (LH) and follicle-stimulating (FSH) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">10</xref>]. In view of the transcription factors that regulate the synthesis of the individual hormones, this finding is not surprising.</p><p>Plurihormonal tumors are either monomorphous (different hormones expressed from a single cell type or plurimorphous (different hormonal expression from different cells) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">11</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">13</xref>]. Our review of the literature (English language only) revealed few case reports of plurihormonal tumors with concomitant presence of ACTH and PRL/GH staining tumor cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">14</xref>]. Details of clinical presentation and staining pattern of eight cases are listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tab2">Table 2</xref>. In contrast to the previously published cases, where the tumor was a macroadenoma and the predominant clinical presentation was acromegaly, our patient had a microadenoma and dominant clinical presentation was Cushing's disease.</p><p>Diagnosis of plurihormonal tumors relies on immunohistochemistry demonstrating significant and specific immunoreactivity to unrelated hormones using specific antisera. The case we report clearly had two histologically distinct populations of cells with evidence of different immunohistochemical hormonal expression. We have excluded the common pitfalls for misdiagnosis of plurihormonality. The histology of the specimen removed from the patient in our case showed only adenoma and did not include any tissue recognizable as entrapped normal adenohypophysis. The pattern of immunoreactivity for ACTH, PRL, and GH in the specimen was nonoverlapping and supports the interpretation that the antibodies used for detection were specific (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>). It is impossible to conclude whether the expression of PRL and GH in one portion of the specimen influenced the clinical presentation of our patient. Although our patient did have marginally elevated PRL and IGF-1 levels, their clinical significance is uncertain.</p><p>The pathogenesis of plurimorphous plurihormonal tumors is hypothesized to be as a result of neoplastic transformation of two different cell lines or transdifferentiation of a once tumor cell line into a different hormone-producing cell line [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">15</xref>]. The possibility of tumors developing from noncommitted stem cells in the pituitary also has been suggested [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">15</xref>]. We did not perform an electron microscopy or a transcription factor analysis in our case, which limits further speculation on the original tumor cell line. Further work is required to elucidate the role of specific factors and the molecular mechanisms contributing to normal and abnormal pituitary development.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Conflict of Interests</title><p>The authors have no conflict of interests.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="B13"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arita</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Uozumi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuwabara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A case of pituitary adenoma producing both growth hormone (GH) and adrenocorticotropic hormone (ACTH)</article-title><source><italic>Endocrinologia Japonica</italic></source><year>1991</year><volume>38</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>271</fpage><lpage>278</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0026334872</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1665412</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blevins</surname><given-names>LS</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name><surname>Madoff</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Laws</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Wand</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Case report: acromegaly and Cushing&#x02019;s disease in a patient with synchronous pituitary adenomas</article-title><source><italic>American Journal of the Medical Sciences</italic></source><year>1992</year><volume>304</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>294</fpage><lpage>297</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0026448626</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1442869</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Apel</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Asa</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A composite somatotroph-corticotroph pituitary adenoma</article-title><source><italic>Endocrine Pathology</italic></source><year>1994</year><volume>5</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>240</fpage><lpage>246</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0000471175</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kovacs</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Horvath</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Stefaneanu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pituitary adenoma producing growth hormone and adrenocorticotropin: a histological, immunocytochemical, electron microscopic, and in situ hybridization study</article-title><source><italic>Journal of Neurosurgery</italic></source><year>1998</year><volume>88</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1111</fpage><lpage>1115</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0031842052</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9609310</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mazarakis</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kontogeorgos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kovacs</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Horvath</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Borboli</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Piaditis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Composite somatotroph&#x02014;ACTH-immunoreactive pituitary adenoma with transformation of hyperplasia to adenoma</article-title><source><italic>Pituitary</italic></source><year>2001</year><volume>4</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>215</fpage><lpage>221</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0035470203</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12501971</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kageyama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nigawara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamata</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A multihormonal pituitary adenoma with growth hormone and adrenocorticotropic hormone production, causing acromegaly and Cushing disease</article-title><source><italic>American Journal of the Medical Sciences</italic></source><year>2002</year><volume>324</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>326</fpage><lpage>330</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0036949418</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12495300</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsuchiya</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohta</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshimoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Doi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Izumiyama</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirata</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A case of acromegaly associated with subclinical Cushing&#x02019;s disease</article-title><source><italic>Endocrine Journal</italic></source><year>2006</year><volume>53</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>679</fpage><lpage>685</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-33750629963</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16926523</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamane</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Oda</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Combined acromegaly and subclinical Cushing disease related to high-molecular-weight adrenocorticotropic hormone: case report</article-title><source><italic>Journal of Neurosurgery</italic></source><year>2009</year><volume>110</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>369</fpage><lpage>373</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-62649104760</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18991502</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B1"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Melmed</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pathogenesis of pituitary tumors</article-title><source><italic>Nature Reviews Endocrinology</italic></source><year>2011</year><volume>7</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>257</fpage><lpage>266</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McComb</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bayley</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Horvath</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kovacs</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kourides</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Monomorphous plurihormonal adenoma of the human pituitary. A histologic, immunocytologic and ultrastructural study</article-title><source><italic>Cancer</italic></source><year>1984</year><volume>53</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1538</fpage><lpage>1544</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0021349795</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6141845</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Al-Brahim</surname><given-names>NYY</given-names></name><name><surname>Asa</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>My approach to pathology of the pituitary gland</article-title><source><italic>Journal of Clinical Pathology</italic></source><year>2006</year><volume>59</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1245</fpage><lpage>1253</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-33846046438</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17142570</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Asa</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ezzat</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The pathogenesis of pituitary tumors</article-title><source><italic>Annual Review of Pathology</italic></source><year>2009</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>126</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-66149120642</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Asa</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Practical pituitary pathology: what does the pathologist need to know?</article-title><source><italic>Archives of Pathology and Laboratory Medicine</italic></source><year>2008</year><volume>132</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1231</fpage><lpage>1240</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-49449100984</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18684022</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salehi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Syro</surname><given-names>LV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Plurihormonality in pituitary adenomas associated with acromegaly</article-title><source><italic>Endocrine Pathology</italic></source><year>2006</year><volume>17</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>291</fpage><lpage>296</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-33847112413</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17308366</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kovacs</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Horvath</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Asa</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Stefaneanu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pituitary cells producing more than one hormone: human pituitary adenomas</article-title><source><italic>Trends in Endocrinology and Metabolism</italic></source><year>1989</year><volume>1</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>104</fpage><lpage>107</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0024307326</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18411100</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="fig1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Pituitary MRI (post-contrast) showing microadenoma (thick arrow).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="CRIM.ENDOCRINOLOGY2012-529730.001"/></fig><fig id="fig2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Pathology images of the tumor. (a) H&#x00026;E stain of the larger tumor tissue showing abundant eosinophilic cytoplasm. (b) H&#x00026;E stain of the smaller tissue showing abundant basophilic cytoplasm. (c) Immunohistochemistry: all of the cells in the larger adenoma were immunoreactive with antibodies to prolactin, and rare cells (Inset) were growth hormone positive. (d) Immunohistochemistry: cells of the small pieces of adenoma were ACTH positive.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="CRIM.ENDOCRINOLOGY2012-529730.002"/></fig><table-wrap id="tab1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Hormonal profile pre- and postoperatively. </p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal range</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Preoperative</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Postoperative</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Testosterone (Total)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">300&#x02013;890&#x02009;pg/mL</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">195</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Testosterone (Free)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47&#x02013;244&#x02009;pg/mL</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cortisol (AM)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4&#x02013;26.9&#x02009;mcg/dL</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACTH (AM)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8&#x02013;42&#x02009;pg/mL</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IGF-1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61&#x02013;285&#x02009;ng/mL</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">323</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">241</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prolactin</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1&#x02013;17.7&#x02009;ng/mL</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Free T4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8&#x02013;1.8&#x02009;ng/dL</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cortisol (LDDST*)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;1.8&#x02009;mcg/dL</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;1.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Salivary cortisol (midnight)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;50&#x02009;ng/dL</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">114</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02009;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GH (Basal)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01&#x02013;0.97&#x02009;ng/mL</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GH (75&#x02009;g glucose load&#x02014;30&#x02009;min)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02009;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02009;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GH (75&#x02009;g glucose load&#x02014;60&#x02009;min)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02009;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02009;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GH (75&#x02009;g glucose load&#x02014;120&#x02009;min)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02009;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02009;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>*LDDST: Low-dose dexamethasone suppression test.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="tab2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Case reports of concomitant ACTH and GH/PRL secreting tumors described in the literature.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Author and year</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age/sex</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Size of adenoma</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dominant clinical presentation</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acromegaly evaluation</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cushings evaluation</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pattern of stains</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arita et al. 1991 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">1</xref>]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29/F</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6&#x02009;cm</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acromegaly and Cushing's</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GH 92&#x02009;ng/mL<break/></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACTH 94&#x02009;pg/mL</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diffuse GH stainings and focal ACTH staining in the tumor tissue</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blevins et al. 1992 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">2</xref>]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40/F</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3&#x02009;cm </td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acromegaly and Cushing's</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GH 22&#x02009;ng/mL<break/>Nonsuppression of GH with OGTT<break/></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UFC 731&#x02009;nmol/d (66&#x02013;298)<break/>Nonsuppression of UFC with 2&#x02009;mg Dexamethasone</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Two discrete cell groups each staining diffusely for GH and ACTH, respectively</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Apel et al. 1994 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">3</xref>]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76/F</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2&#x02009;cm</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acromegaly</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GH 13.7&#x02009;ng/mL (&#x0003c;5)<break/>IGF-1 464&#x02009;ng/L (116&#x02013;270)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACTH 6.5&#x02009;pmol/L (&#x0003c;22)<break/>PRL 25.8&#x02009;mcg/L (&#x0003c;17.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Two discrete areas of GH and ACTH staining</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kovacs et al. 1998 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">4</xref>]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62/M</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;1&#x02009;cm**</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acromegaly</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GH 13.7&#x02009;ng/mL (&#x0003c;5)<break/>IGF-1: 973&#x02009;ng/L (48&#x02013;275)<break/></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not available</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Majority of cells displayed variable positivity for GH, whereas the minority of adenoma cells were strongly stain for ACTH; occasional cells positive for PRL</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Mazarakis et al. 2001 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">5</xref>]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53/M</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5&#x02009;cm</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acromegaly</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GH 17.5&#x02009;ng/mL<break/>IGF-1 934&#x02009;ng/mL</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACTH 29&#x02009;pg/mL (&#x0003c;52)<break/>No hypercortisolism documented</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chromophobic tumor, immunoreactive for GH focally admixed with hyperplastic PAS positive, and ACTH immunoreactive cells showing the electron microscopic features characteristic of corticotrophs</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kageyama et al. 2002 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">6</xref>]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45/F</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2&#x02009;cm</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acromegaly</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GH 20.9&#x02009;ng/mL (&#x0003c;3.1)<break/>IGF-1 650&#x02009;ng/mL (46&#x02013;282)<break/></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACTH 91&#x02009;pg/mL (&#x0003c;60)<break/>Urine-free cortisol 403&#x02009;mcg/d (40&#x02013;140)<break/>LDST-Cortisol Nonsuppression<break/>HDST-cortisol suppression</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 distinct types of tumor cells, with either diffuse but faint GH-positive cells or sparse but distinct ACTH-stained cells; few PRL positive cells detected as well</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tsuchiya et al. 2006 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">7</xref>]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54/M</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2&#x02009;cm</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acromegaly</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GH: 31.5&#x02009;ng/mL (&#x0003c;0.6)<break/>IGF-1: 493&#x02009;ng/mL (106&#x02013;398)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACTH: 53&#x02009;pg/mL (7&#x02013;56)<break/>UFC: 45.6&#x02009;mcg/d (&#x0003c;80.3)<break/>LDST-Cortisol Nonsuppression<break/>HDST-cortisol suppression<break/></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diffuse GH and PRL staining and focal ACTH staining in the tumor tissue</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oki et al. 2009 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">8</xref>]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36/M</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;1&#x02009;cm**</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acromegaly</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GH 6.33&#x02009;ng/mL <break/>IGF-1: 1361.3&#x02009;ng/mL (67&#x02013;318)<break/></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACTH 91.7&#x02009;pg/mL<break/>LDST-Cortisol Nonsuppression<break/>HDST-cortisol suppression</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tumor cells with diffuse strong GH stain and focal staining with ACTH and TSH</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>**Clear evidence of macroadenoma on the MRI images, size details not provided in the case reports.</p></fn><fn><p>Values in parenthesis indicate normal ranges.</p></fn><fn><p>UFC: urine-free cortisol.</p></fn><fn><p>LDST: low-dose dexamethasone test (0.5 or 1&#x02009;mg).</p></fn><fn><p>HDST: high-dose dexamethasone test (8&#x02009;mg).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></floats-group></article>