<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Clin Infect Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Clin. Infect. Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">cid</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">cid</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Clinical Infectious Diseases: An Official Publication of the Infectious Diseases Society of America</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1058-4838</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1537-6591</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26063722</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4551004</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cid/civ431</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">civ431</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Articles and Commentaries</subject></subj-group><series-title>Editor's choice</series-title></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Partial Failure of Milk Pasteurization as a Risk for the Transmission of <italic>Campylobacter</italic> From Cattle to Humans</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names>Anand M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Balasegaram</surname><given-names>Sooria</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Willis</surname><given-names>Caroline</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wimalarathna</surname><given-names>Helen M. L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Maiden</surname><given-names>Martin C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>Noel D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af5">5</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af6">6</xref></contrib><aff id="af1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Operations Directorate</addr-line></aff><aff id="af2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Field Epidemiology Services</addr-line></aff><aff id="af3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Food, Water and Environment Laboratory</addr-line>, <institution>Public Health England</institution></aff><aff id="af4"><label>4</label><addr-line>Department of Zoology</addr-line></aff><aff id="af5"><label>5</label><addr-line>National Institute for Health Research Health Protection Research Unit in Gastrointestinal Infections</addr-line>, <institution>University of Oxford</institution></aff><aff id="af6"><label>6</label><institution>Warwick Medical School, University of Warwick, United Kingdom</institution></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp>Correspondence: Noel D. McCarthy, BA, MB, BCh, BAO, MSc, MPH, DPhil, Department of Zoology, University of Oxford, Oxford OX1 3PS, UK (<email>noel.mccarthy@zoo.ox.ac.uk</email>).</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>15</day><month>9</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>6</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>10</day><month>6</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>61</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>903</fpage><lpage>909</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>27</day><month>1</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>8</day><month>4</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the Infectious Diseases Society of America.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="civ431.pdf"/><abstract abstract-type="precis"><p>An outbreak investigation identified a plausible transmission route that may contribute to the large and poorly characterized human disease burden of <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> from cattle and demonstrated an approach to testing this hypothesis through integration of genomic analysis in surveillance.</p></abstract><abstract><p><bold><italic>Background.</italic></bold>&#x02003;Cattle are the second most common source of human campylobacteriosis. However, routes to account for this scale of transmission have not been identified. In contrast to chicken, red meat is not heavily contaminated at point of sale. Although effective pasteurization prevents milk-borne infection, apparently sporadic infections may include undetected outbreaks from raw or perhaps incompletely pasteurized milk.</p><p><bold><italic>Methods.</italic></bold>&#x02003;A rise in <italic>Campylobacter</italic> gastroenteritis in an isolated population was investigated using whole-genome sequencing (WGS), an epidemiological study, and environmental investigations.</p><p><bold><italic>Results.</italic></bold>&#x02003;A single strain was identified in 20 cases, clearly distinguishable from other local strains and a reference population by WGS. A case-case analysis showed association of infection with the outbreak strain and milk from a single dairy (odds ratio, 8; Fisher exact test <italic>P</italic> value = .023). Despite temperature records indicating effective pasteurization, mechanical faults likely to lead to incomplete pasteurization of part of the milk were identified by further testing and examination of internal components of dairy equipment.</p><p><bold><italic>Conclusions.</italic></bold>&#x02003;Here, milk distribution concentrated on a small area, including school-aged children with low background incidence of campylobacteriosis, facilitated outbreak identification. Low-level contamination of widely distributed milk would not produce as detectable an outbreak signal. Such hidden outbreaks may contribute to the substantial burden of apparently sporadic <italic>Campylobacter</italic> from cattle where transmission routes are not certain. The effective discrimination of outbreak isolates from a reference population using WGS shows that integrating these data and approaches into surveillance could support the detection as well as investigation of such outbreaks.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd><italic>Campylobacter</italic></kwd><kwd>cattle</kwd><kwd>milk</kwd><kwd>whole-genome sequencing</kwd><kwd>pasteurization</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="funding-1"><funding-source>National Institute for Health Research <named-content content-type="funder-id">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100000272</named-content></funding-source></award-group><award-group id="funding-2"><funding-source>NIHR</funding-source></award-group><award-group id="funding-3"><funding-source>Public Health England <named-content content-type="funder-id">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100002141</named-content></funding-source></award-group><award-group id="funding-4"><funding-source>UK Food Standards Agency and Defra</funding-source></award-group><award-group id="funding-5"><funding-source>NIHR</funding-source></award-group></funding-group></article-meta></front><body><p><related-article related-article-type="article-reference" id="d35e255" vol="61" page="910" ext-link-type="pmc"><bold>(See the Editorial Commentary by Osterholm on pages 910&#x02013;1.)</bold></related-article></p><p><italic>Campylobacter</italic> is the commonest cause of bacterial gastroenteritis in humans, with chicken and cattle the first and second most common sources, respectively [<xref rid="CIV431C1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="CIV431C3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Population genetic models have attributed 39% [<xref rid="CIV431C2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] and 18%&#x02013;38% [<xref rid="CIV431C1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] of human infection in the United Kingdom to ruminant (cattle or sheep) sources, and 20%&#x02013;30% in New Zealand [<xref rid="CIV431C3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>], with cattle identified as the main ruminant source. High prevalence and concentration of <italic>Campylobacter</italic> on chicken contrasts with low prevalence and concentration on red meat at retail [<xref rid="CIV431C4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="CIV431C5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], and transmission routes to humans from ruminants are unclear despite the ruminant-associated burden of well over 100 000 cases per year in England alone [<xref rid="CIV431C2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="CIV431C6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>].</p><p>Although detected <italic>Campylobacter</italic> outbreaks in England have included some from raw milk sources [<xref rid="CIV431C7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="CIV431C8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], especially locally distributed, this pattern has changed with near-universal pasteurization of milk. Identified outbreaks are now mostly associated with foods containing chicken liver prepared by the catering industry [<xref rid="CIV431C9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. In the United States, the decline has been less marked; 1 ruminant-associated <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> subtype has been found in outbreaks linked to unpasteurized milk, in addition to 56 apparently sporadic cases where source of infection was generally unknown [<xref rid="CIV431C10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Among apparently sporadic cases of <italic>Campylobacter</italic> in Minnesota, 6% (407) reported consuming raw milk compared with 2.3% among the general population. Raw milk consumption was estimated by extrapolation to have caused &#x0003e;12 000 cases in this population from 2001 to 2010 [<xref rid="CIV431C11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. The occurrence of so many raw milk&#x02013;associated cases in Minnesota, in the absence of detected outbreaks, may be a feature of the difficulty of detecting outbreaks for a widely distributed food [<xref rid="CIV431C12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], especially if outbreaks are small and the distribution diffuse [<xref rid="CIV431C7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="CIV431C8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="CIV431C13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. More generally, <italic>Campylobacter</italic> outbreaks have mainly been identified in socially or geographically defined groups [<xref rid="CIV431C7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="CIV431C9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], despite a biology of persistence but not growth on foods [<xref rid="CIV431C14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="CIV431C15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], so that distributed outbreaks might be expected to be more common.</p><p>The combination of a large burden of human campylobacteriosis originating from cattle, unexplained transmission routes from this source, and evidence that a large burden of apparently sporadic unpasteurized milk&#x02013;associated disease can occur without detected outbreaks [<xref rid="CIV431C11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] raises the question of whether imperfectly pasteurized milk might also cause undetected outbreaks that contribute to human campylobacteriosis. If pasteurization in large-volume, widely distributed supplies reduces risk substantially, but sometimes incompletely (eg, due to partial failures), the resulting low-level distributed contamination would be likely to produce even more diffuse outbreaks than with raw milk. Current human disease surveillance would not provide a robust form of monitoring to detect these outbreaks.</p><p>When bacterial subtyping has been applied to milk-borne <italic>Campylobacter</italic> outbreaks, a single or dominant subtype has usually been identified [<xref rid="CIV431C10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="CIV431C16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="CIV431C19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], including 1 recent family farm outbreak where isolates from family members, cattle feces, and milk tanks were shown to be almost identical [<xref rid="CIV431C20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] by whole-genome sequence (WGS) multilocus sequence typing (wgMLST) [<xref rid="CIV431C21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="CIV431C22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. This shows that milk-borne outbreaks are at least sometimes due to a single strain. Preliminary work suggests that WGS analysis can detect distributed <italic>Campylobacter</italic> outbreaks [<xref rid="CIV431C21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], even though preceding molecular methods have not been effective for detecting outbreaks of this diverse pathogen [<xref rid="CIV431C23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="CIV431C24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>].</p><p>Here we describe an outbreak due to unidentified inadequate pasteurization at a dairy supplying a local population. Localized exposure of an age group in which this infection is rare allowed detection of a cluster likely to have been missed if distribution were across a wider population. Identification of the source of infection involved integration of WGS data, other epidemiological data, and environmental investigation showing the benefits of triangulating WGS data with more familiar forms of epidemiological information [<xref rid="CIV431C25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. We also used this example to test whether integration of genome sequencing in surveillance could detect epidemiologically related cases occurring in a less demographically distinct group.</p><sec sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title>METHODS</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Epidemiological Methods</title><sec id="s2a1"><title>Case Definition</title><p>The outbreak control team case definition included any laboratory-confirmed case of <italic>Campylobacter</italic> gastroenteritis at a laboratory serving the population of a small island, identified during October 2011, with onset after 29 September, without preceding foreign travel, and where the isolate was sensitive to ciprofloxacin and erythromycin.</p><p>Subsequently, an outbreak strain case definition to allow case-case analysis used the criteria of allele differences at &#x02264;12 of the genetic loci used in <italic>Campylobacter</italic> wgMLST analysis [<xref rid="CIV431C21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Cases in households where another case had occurred &#x02265;3 days earlier were considered as secondary to allow repeat analysis excluding probable and possible secondary cases.</p></sec><sec id="s2a2"><title>Case Information</title><p>A standard questionnaire for gastrointestinal illness applied by the local public health authorities gathered information on symptoms, onset time, and food and other exposures in the week preceding onset. This was later modified to examine milk consumption in more detail. Cases, or parents of child cases, were interviewed in person or by telephone. Information obtained was recorded on the case management system used by English public health authorities.</p></sec><sec id="s2a3"><title>Microbiological Methods for Human Samples</title><p>Stool specimens submitted to the hospital laboratory serving the island population were cultured for <italic>Campylobacter</italic> species using British standard methods. Once an outbreak was suspected, available isolates, which are usually discarded, were retained for genome sequencing. DNA was extracted and sequencing performed on the Illumina Hi-Seq platform as described elsewhere [<xref rid="CIV431C21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s2a4"><title>Food Chain Investigation</title><p>The milk supply chain for schools was later investigated given the concentration of infection among school-aged children and frequent reports by these cases of school milk consumption.</p></sec><sec id="s2a5"><title>Food Microbiology and Biochemistry</title><p>Milk samples were taken from the dairy milk tank and after bottling and analyzed at the Food Water and Environmental Microbiology Laboratory, Porton Down, for alkaline phosphatase (according to International Organization for Standardization 11816&#x02013;1:2006) to test for adequacy of pasteurization [<xref rid="CIV431C26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], Enterobacteriaceae using the TEMPO automated most probable number technique [<xref rid="CIV431C27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], and for the presence of <italic>Campylobacter</italic> using Health Protection Agency Standard Procedure F21.</p></sec><sec id="s2a6"><title>Bioinformatics Analysis</title><p>The 23 available isolates from the laboratory catchment population were analyzed with a reference population comprising 65 contemporaneous isolates from an ongoing genomic surveillance project in Oxfordshire, United Kingdom (isolates cultured between 29 September and 22 October) given evidence for seasonal but limited geographical variation in <italic>Campylobacter</italic> subtypes in England [<xref rid="CIV431C28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="CIV431C30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. The Genome Comparator tool was used within BIGSdb [<xref rid="CIV431C31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] to perform wgMLST analysis [<xref rid="CIV431C22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] using the 1643 genetic loci validated for this form of analysis [<xref rid="CIV431C21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Pairwise differences were estimated among outbreak and reference population isolates to discriminate clusters against a background population.</p><p>Following the identification of an outbreak strain as described above, a more challenging discriminatory task was set, to separate outbreak isolates from a reference population with the same standard 7-locus MLST [<xref rid="CIV431C32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>] as the outbreak strain (ST21). This used all ST21 isolates from Oxfordshire isolated during September, October, and November (n = 29) as a surrogate to test the capacity of genome sequencing to distinguish the outbreak cluster from a wider background population. This evaluation compared the distributions of pairwise differences between (1) each pair of outbreak strain isolates, (2) each pair of reference population isolates, and (3) each outbreak strain isolate and each reference isolate. Genome sequences for all isolates used in the analyses are accessible on the pubMLST/Campylobacter database.</p></sec><sec id="s2a7"><title>Case-Case Analysis</title><p>Following confirmation of an outbreak strain, a case-case analysis [<xref rid="CIV431C33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>] was undertaken comparing outbreak strain cases with all other isolates from the island population that had different genome sequences or had not been genome sequenced, from people without a history of foreign travel. Odds ratios (ORs) and 95% confidence intervals (CIs) were estimated by logistic regression and exact logistic regression implemented in Stata 12, and statistical significance was tested using Fisher exact test.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>RESULTS</title><sec id="s3a"><title>Descriptive Epidemiology</title><p>Forty-eight <italic>Campylobacter</italic>-positive samples were reported by the hospital laboratory in October vs an average of 15 during October over the previous 4 years. Eleven were excluded as cases due to symptom onset prior to 29 September (n = 6), foreign travel (n = 2), or antibiotic resistance (n = 3).</p><p>Twenty-nine of the 37 cases were in the primary and preschool age range of 1&#x02013;11 years (78%). The other 8 were aged &#x02265;24 years. Onset dates were mainly (32 of 37) between 29 September and 5 October, peaking on Saturday, 1 October (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="CIV431F1">1</xref>). Cases in schoolchildren were distributed unevenly among 12 schools. Two schools accounted for 52% (15) of cases in the primary and preschool age range.
<fig id="CIV431F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Epidemic curve of cases of <italic>Campylobacter</italic> per day identifying those meeting the original outbreak case definition (probable) and the outbreak strain case definition (confirmed). Abbreviation: EH, environmental health.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="civ43101"/></fig></p><p>Diarrhea was reported by all 33 cases for whom symptom information was available, with abdominal pain reported by 88%, fever 70%, and bloody diarrhea 52%. Two children were hospitalized for 1 day each.</p></sec><sec id="s3b"><title>Human Sample Microbiology</title><p>Twenty-three isolates were available for genome sequencing. Complete data were available at 1319 genetic loci for all of these and the reference population isolates. Genes were missing or alleles incomplete in 1 or more isolates at an additional 324 loci. Some allelic variation among isolates was evident at all 1319 loci with complete data. A cluster of 20 of the 23 isolates in the outbreak catchment area were almost identical, with differences of &#x02264;4 (mean, 1.3) on all pairwise comparisons. The other 3 isolates from the area were not similar to this cluster, each differing at &#x02265;1132 loci from all members of the cluster and from each other (mean, 1190). Extraction of 7-locus MLST [<xref rid="CIV431C32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>] showed that the cluster of 20 isolates shared the 7-locus ST21 genotype and the other 3 were 1 each of ST42, ST257, and ST353. The 65 reference population isolates differed at &#x02265;56 loci from each strain in the outbreak cluster.</p><p>Analysis comparing the cluster of 20 against the related ST21 reference population showed 1577 shared loci. Identical alleles were present at 602 in all reference and outbreak isolates, whereas 975 showed allelic variation. The pattern of pairwise differences among each population and between the 2 is shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="CIV431F2">2</xref>. The cluster of 20 isolates showed a range of 0&#x02013;8 and mean of 4 pairwise differences ( &#x0201c;within-cluster&#x0201d; differences); comparing each isolate in the cluster with each in the reference population showed differences at between 20 and 668 loci, with a mean of 295 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="CIV431F2">2</xref>).
<fig id="CIV431F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Distribution of pairwise differences between ST21 isolates in an identified cluster of 20 isolates (blue), between isolates in this cluster and a geographically separate but temporally similar reference population of ST21 isolates (red), and within the reference population (green) across 1577 loci.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="civ43102"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s3c"><title>Food Chain Tracing</title><p>One dairy supplied milk to all local authority primary schools in the area, to nurseries offering government-funded milk to children &#x0003c;5 years old, and to a small proportion of the wider market including hotels, care homes, and household doorstep deliveries of milk.</p></sec><sec id="s3d"><title>Dairy Inspection and Milk Testing</title><p>Temperature thermographs on pasteurization tanks did not identify pasteurization process failure. No basis for postpasteurization contamination was identifiable on review of the packaging process and bottle storage. <italic>Campylobacter</italic> was not isolated from the milk samples taken from the dairy. Seventeen of 22 samples (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="CIV431TB1">1</xref>) exceeded the alkaline phosphatase level of 350 mU/L specified in European legislation (Commission Regulation [EC] 1664/2006), indicating either failed pasteurization or contamination with raw milk after pasteurization. Enterobacteriaceae counts exceeded the criteria specified for pasteurized milk in European microbiological criteria (EC 2073/2005 as amended in EC 365/2010).
<table-wrap id="CIV431TB1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Phosphatase Test Results on Milk Samples Before and After Repair of the Pasteurizer</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Date of Sample</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Type of Sample and Alkaline Phosphatase Result<sup>a</sup>, mU/L<hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Whole Milk</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Skimmed Milk</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 October</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bottle: 24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 October</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tank: <bold>517</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tank: <bold>627</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">First bottle on line: <bold>578</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">First bottle on line: 337</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Last bottle on line: 65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 October</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tank: <bold>722</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tank: <bold>627</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bottles: 225, <bold>365</bold>, 250</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bottles: <bold>625, 639, 639</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 October</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bottles: <bold>906, 880, 837, 903</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bottles: <bold>608, 601, 632, 539</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Pasteurizer repaired overnight 20&#x02013;21 October</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;21 October</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bottles: 20, 20, 16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bottles: &#x0003c;10, &#x0003c;10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;22 October</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bottles: 22, 16, 18, 12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bottles: &#x0003c;10, 12, 12, &#x0003c;10, &#x0003c;10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;27 October</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bottles: 25, 25, 29, 25, 44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bottles: 22, 54, 42, 27</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn1"><p><sup>a</sup> Counts exceeding regulatory standards (350 mU/L) are shown in bold.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p>Inspection of the pasteurizer by an engineer, in the light of milk-test results, identified problems with heat exchanger plates, rubber gaskets, and an internal control mechanism on a steam control valve. These could have led to the failure of pasteurization for some of the milk passing through the pasteurizer, although most may have reached pasteurization temperatures. The regeneration heat exchanger and hot water set plates were replaced, and the pasteurizer was recalibrated. Subsequent phosphatase tests on 23 samples were within normal limits (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="CIV431TB1">1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s3e"><title>Reported Risk Factors and Association With the Outbreak Strain</title><p>Of the 29 cases aged 0&#x02013;11 years, 27 interviews were completed, including 23 school-aged children. Twenty-one parents of school-aged cases reported school milk consumption by their children in the week before illness. Consumption of school lunches was reported by 17 cases and participation in school swimming by 8 cases. Case-case analysis of the association between milk consumption and illness is summarized in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="CIV431TB2">2</xref> (OR, 8.0 [95% CI, 1.4&#x02013;45.8]). Excluding 5 cases that are considered likely to be household secondary infections, all cases for whom an exposure history was available had consumed milk (OR, 11.7 estimated by exact logistic regression).
<table-wrap id="CIV431TB2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Association Between Illness With the Confirmed Outbreak Strain and Milk Consumption From the Implicated Dairy</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="char" span="1"/><col align="char" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cases</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Milk</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No Milk</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic> Value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">Analysis of all cases with available data<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Confirmed case</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4&#x02013;45.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.023</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Not confirmed</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">Excluding probable secondary cases<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Confirmed case</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4&#x02013;undefined</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.010</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Not confirmed</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn2"><p>Abbreviations: CI, confidence interval; OR, odds ratio.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn3"><p><sup>a</sup> Three individuals were not interviewed or did not give information on exposure to milk.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn4"><p><sup>b</sup> Five cases occurred in family members of cases and may have been secondary cases.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>The distribution of milk from a dairy with pasteurization failures to an insular community, served by a single microbiology laboratory, and including school-aged populations, supported the detection of an epidemiological signal for this outbreak. A combination of descriptive epidemiology, genomic epidemiology, and environmental investigation identified the likely source of infection. Combination of exposure histories and WGS data allowed testing of the hypothesis generated using case-case analysis [<xref rid="CIV431C33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Although no single analysis or form of data was conclusive, the combination allows relatively firm inference on the source and process issues that led to human infection. Misclassification of cases with unavailable isolates as controls might have weakened the observed associations but would not have created a false-positive association. A cohort or case-control study would have been useful in confirming this inference and testing for possible effects of confounding that was not possible in our small case-case analysis, particularly if evidence was needed to support enforcement. The main peak of the outbreak was short-lived, which was compatible with infection from a single day's delivery of milk. Additionally, illness did not appear to be evenly distributed across school attendees and other populations exposed to milk from the dairy. This suggests that contamination may have affected only a portion of the milk from the dairy, and for only a limited time. Later tests on dairy milk were negative for <italic>Campylobacter</italic> although showing biochemical evidence for pasteurization failure.</p><p>Most reported <italic>Campylobacter</italic> outbreaks are small and detected in defined communities. Some have been larger, with 1 outbreak associated with pasteurized milk believed to have been contaminated after pasteurization, causing an estimated 1644 cases among prisoners in California, but this was nonetheless in a defined group [<xref rid="CIV431C17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Noninstitutional outbreaks linked to pasteurization failures have been described where a community distribution was relatively local [<xref rid="CIV431C34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, <xref rid="CIV431C35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] or where the outbreak was very large (affecting 3500 individuals) and mainly concentrated in schoolchildren [<xref rid="CIV431C16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="CIV431C36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. In some incidents, increased awareness of risk due to identified pasteurization failures may have contributed to outbreak detection [<xref rid="CIV431C34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, <xref rid="CIV431C35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] and, as in the present outbreak, interventions may have contributed to a short duration or the avoidance of recurrence. Reports of recurrent pasteurization failures but only single, time-limited outbreaks [<xref rid="CIV431C34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, <xref rid="CIV431C35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] fit with our later milk samples testing negative for <italic>Campylobacter</italic> even though phosphatase tests suggested incomplete pasteurization of at least some milk. Contamination of raw milk with <italic>Campylobacter</italic> appears to be uncommon and mainly associated with fecal contamination [<xref rid="CIV431C19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="CIV431C37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>, <xref rid="CIV431C38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>].</p><p>Neither the outbreak that we report nor other literature describes the type of diffuse outbreaks that might be anticipated from low-level <italic>Campylobacter</italic> contamination of milk given that it is a product that is typically processed in bulk and widely distributed, and that this pathogen can survive in refrigerated milk for 3 weeks [<xref rid="CIV431C39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>] but could not grow [<xref rid="CIV431C14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="CIV431C15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] in these conditions. It may be that modern large-scale production of pasteurized milk provides complete protection, or that the protection is sometimes &#x0003c;100% but that wide distribution networks for milk make it difficult to detect outbreaks following minor levels of contamination and partial pasteurization failure so that they are lost into the background of apparently sporadic cases. The large burden of unexplained cattle origin human infection highlights the importance of obtaining evidence to identify which of these explanations is correct.</p><p>Critically, this investigation and our past work [<xref rid="CIV431C21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] show that the integration of WGS into the surveillance of <italic>Campylobacter</italic> infection will allow the detection of single-strain outbreaks, or those where a single strain is dominant. The 20 outbreak isolates showed allele differences at &#x02264;8 loci on pairwise comparison, with a mean of 4 locus differences, across 1577 loci analyzed. These levels of difference are equivalent to the differences seen between 2 isolates from the same patient and do not appear to occur among isolates with no epidemiological relationship [<xref rid="CIV431C21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. As a single or dominant subtype has typically been reported for milk-borne <italic>Campylobacter</italic> outbreaks when subtyping has been undertaken [<xref rid="CIV431C10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="CIV431C16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="CIV431C20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], these outbreaks may be particularly detectable by genomic approaches. This contrasts with outbreaks due to poultry liver&#x02013;containing foods that often contain multiple strains [<xref rid="CIV431C40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, <xref rid="CIV431C41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Taken together, this suggests that the integration of these data and techniques into routine surveillance of <italic>Campylobacter</italic> could detect diffusely distributed outbreaks that do not produce an epidemiological signal in time and space and which are currently likely to be missed, as well as supporting their further investigation. The investigation of these outbreaks may allow identification of the pathways of the extensive human infection that comes from the cattle <italic>Campylobacter</italic> reservoir and support control measures against this large burden of disease. However, such detection of multiple, relatively small, epidemiologically related clusters may be a double-edged sword. On one hand, small, well-investigated clusters can provide insight into overall risk factors for infectious disease to support control [<xref rid="CIV431C42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]; on the other hand, the difficulties of identifying sources in small outbreaks, especially if cases are diffusely distributed, will limit the practicality or utility of investigating all such clusters. Identifying which leads to follow may be critical to our effective application of these novel technologies.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Notes</title><p><bold><italic>Acknowledgments.</italic></bold>&#x02003;We thank the members of the outbreak control team set up to investigate and manage the outbreak, and Lt Col Ewan Cameron for coordinating actions arising from the outbreak control team meetings.</p><p><bold><italic>Disclaimer.</italic></bold>&#x02003;The views expressed are those of the authors and not necessarily those of the National Health Service, the <funding-source>National Institute for Health Research</funding-source> (<funding-source>NIHR</funding-source>), the Department of Health, or Public Health England.</p><p><bold><italic>Financial support.</italic></bold>&#x02003;This work was supported by core UK government public health funding through <funding-source>Public Health England</funding-source>. Part of this work was supported by a grant from the European Community's Seventh Framework Program (FP7/2007-2013) under grant agreement 278864 in the framework of the European Union Patho-NGen-Trace project. The reference datasets used were generated and made publicly available by the University of Oxford, supported by funding from the <funding-source>UK Food Standards Agency and Defra</funding-source>.</p><p><bold><italic>Potential conflicts of interest.</italic></bold>&#x02003;N. D. M. has received institutional funding from the <funding-source>NIHR</funding-source> and the UK Food Standards Agency and Defra. M. C. M. has received institutional funding from the UK Food Standards Agency and Defra. All other authors report no potential conflicts.</p><p>All authors have submitted the ICMJE Form for Disclosure of Potential Conflicts of Interest. Conflicts that the editors consider relevant to the content of the manuscript have been disclosed.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="CIV431C1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sheppard</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dallas</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Strachan</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title><italic>Campylobacter</italic> genotyping to determine the source of human infection</article-title>. <source>Clin Infect Dis</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>48</volume>:<fpage>1072</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19275496</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIV431C2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gabriel</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Leatherbarrow</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Tracing the source of campylobacteriosis</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>e1000203</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18818764</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIV431C3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mullner</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Spencer</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Assigning the source of human campylobacteriosis in New Zealand: a comparative genetic and epidemiological approach</article-title>. <source>Infect Genet Evol</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>1311</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19778636</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIV431C4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Turnbull</surname><given-names>PCB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title><italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> and <italic>Salmonella</italic> in raw red meats. A Public Health Laboratory Service survey</article-title>. <source>J Hyg (Lond)</source>
<year>1982</year>; <volume>88</volume>:<fpage>29</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>37</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20475890</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIV431C5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hollis</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cornelius</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nicol</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hudson</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Prevalence, numbers, and subtypes of <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> and <italic>Campylobacter coli</italic> in uncooked retail meat samples</article-title>. <source>J Food Prot</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>70</volume>:<fpage>566</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>73</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17388043</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIV431C6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tam</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Viviani</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Longitudinal study of infectious intestinal disease in the UK (IID2 study): incidence in the community and presenting to general practice</article-title>. <source>Gut</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>61</volume>:<fpage>69</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>77</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21708822</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIV431C7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frost</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gillespie</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Public health implications of <italic>Campylobacter</italic> outbreaks in England and Wales, 1995&#x02013;9: epidemiological and microbiological investigations</article-title>. <source>Epidemiol Infect</source>
<year>2002</year>; <volume>128</volume>:<fpage>111</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12002527</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIV431C8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pebody</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wall</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Outbreaks of <italic>Campylobacter</italic> infection: rare events for a common pathogen</article-title>. <source>Commun Dis Rep CDR Rev</source>
<year>1997</year>; <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>R33</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9080726</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIV431C9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gormley</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Little</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rawal</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gillespie</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lebaigue</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Adak</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A 17-year review of foodborne outbreaks: describing the continuing decline in England and Wales (1992&#x02013;2008)</article-title>. <source>Epidemiol Infect</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>139</volume>:<fpage>688</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>99</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20696086</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIV431C10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sahin</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fitzgerald</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stroika</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Molecular evidence for zoonotic transmission of an emergent, highly pathogenic <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> clone in the United States</article-title>. <source>J Clin Microbiol</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>50</volume>:<fpage>680</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22189122</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIV431C11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Scheftel</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Raw milk consumption among patients with non-outbreak-related enteric infections, Minnesota, USA, 2001&#x02013;2010</article-title>. <source>Emerg Infect Dis</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>38</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>44</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24520559</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIV431C12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tauxe</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Molecular subtyping and the transformation of public health</article-title>. <source>Foodborne Pathog Dis</source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>4</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16602974</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIV431C13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sails</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Swaminathan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fields</surname><given-names>PI</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Utility of multilocus sequence typing as an epidemiological tool for investigation of outbreaks of gastroenteritis caused by <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic></article-title>. <source>J Clin Microbiol</source>
<year>2003</year>; <volume>41</volume>:<fpage>4733</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14532212</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIV431C14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alter</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Scherer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Stress response of <italic>Campylobacter</italic> spp. and its role in food processing</article-title>. <source>J Vet Med B Infect Dis Vet Public Health</source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>53</volume>:<fpage>351</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17010037</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIV431C15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The physiology of <italic>Campylobacter</italic> species and its relevance to their role as foodborne pathogens</article-title>. <source>Int J Food Microbiol</source>
<year>2002</year>; <volume>74</volume>:<fpage>177</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>88</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11981968</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIV431C16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Willis</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Skirrow</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Josephs</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title><italic>Campylobacter enteritis</italic> associated with the consumption of free school milk</article-title>. <source>J Hyg (Lond)</source>
<year>1981</year>; <volume>87</volume>:<fpage>155</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>62</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6895230</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIV431C17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jay-Russell</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mandrell</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Using major outer membrane protein typing as an epidemiological tool to investigate outbreaks caused by milk-borne <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> isolates in California</article-title>. <source>J Clin Microbiol</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>51</volume>:<fpage>195</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>201</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23115263</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIV431C18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kembrey</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A milk-borne campylobacter outbreak following an educational farm visit</article-title>. <source>Epidemiol Infect</source>
<year>1996</year>; <volume>117</volume>:<fpage>457</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>62</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8972669</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIV431C19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Orr</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lightfoot</surname><given-names>NF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sisson</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Direct milk excretion of <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> in a dairy cow causing cases of human enteritis</article-title>. <source>Epidemiol Infect</source>
<year>1995</year>; <volume>114</volume>:<fpage>15</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>24</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7867733</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIV431C20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Revez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schott</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kivisto</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hanninen</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Genomic variation between <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> isolates associated with milk-borne-disease outbreaks</article-title>. <source>J Clin Microbiol</source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>52</volume>:<fpage>2782</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24850348</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIV431C21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cody</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jansen van Rensburg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Real-time genomic epidemiology of human <italic>Campylobacter</italic> isolates using whole genome multilocus sequence typing</article-title>. <source>J Clin Microbiol</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>51</volume>:<fpage>2526</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>34</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23698529</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIV431C22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maiden</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>van Rensburg</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bray</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>MLST revisited: the gene-by-gene approach to bacterial genomics</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>728</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>36</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23979428</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIV431C23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gerner-Smidt</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hise</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kincaid</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>PulseNet USA: a five-year update</article-title>. <source>Foodborne Pathog Dis</source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>9</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>19</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16602975</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIV431C24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hedberg</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Besser</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Limitations of pulsed-field gel electrophoresis for the routine surveillance of <italic>Campylobacter</italic> infections</article-title>. <source>J Infect Dis</source>
<year>2001</year>; <volume>184</volume>:<fpage>242</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11424025</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIV431C25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>An epidemiological view of microbial genomic data</article-title>. <source>Lancet Infect Dis</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>104</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23347622</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIV431C26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Angelino</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Christen</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Penfield</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Beattie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Residual alkaline phosphatase activity in pasteurized milk heated at various temperatures--measurement with the fluorophos and Scharer rapid phosphatase tests</article-title>. <source>J Food Prot</source>
<year>1999</year>; <volume>62</volume>:<fpage>81</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9921835</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIV431C27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Owen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Willis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lamph</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Evaluation of the TEMPO((R)) most probable number technique for the enumeration of Enterobacteriaceae in food and dairy products</article-title>. <source>J Appl Microbiol</source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>109</volume>:<fpage>1810</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20649835</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIV431C28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cody</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wimalarathna</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>A longitudinal 6-year study of the molecular epidemiology of clinical <italic>Campylobacter</italic> isolates in Oxfordshire, United Kingdom</article-title>. <source>J Clin Microbiol</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>50</volume>:<fpage>3193</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>201</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22814466</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIV431C29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dingle</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cody</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peto</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Maiden</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Extended sequence typing of <italic>Campylobacter</italic> spp., United Kingdom</article-title>. <source>Emerg Infect Dis</source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>1620</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18826829</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIV431C30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gillespie</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lawson</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Molecular epidemiology of human <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> shows association between seasonal and international patterns of disease</article-title>. <source>Epidemiol Infect</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>140</volume>:<fpage>1102</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21859502</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIV431C31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jolley</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Maiden</surname><given-names>MCJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>BIGSdb: scalable analysis of bacterial genome variation at the population level</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>595</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21143983</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIV431C32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dingle</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Colles</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wareing</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Multilocus sequence typing system for <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic></article-title>. <source>J Clin Microbiol</source>
<year>2001</year>; <volume>39</volume>:<fpage>14</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>23</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11136741</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIV431C33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Giesecke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Case-case comparisons to study causation of common infectious diseases</article-title>. <source>Int J Epidemiol</source>
<year>1999</year>; <volume>28</volume>:<fpage>764</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10480708</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIV431C34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fahey</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gunneburg</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Adak</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Majid</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kaczmarski</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>An outbreak of <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> enteritis associated with failed milk pasteurisation</article-title>. <source>J Infect</source>
<year>1995</year>; <volume>31</volume>:<fpage>137</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>43</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8666844</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIV431C35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A milk-borne outbreak of <italic>Campylobacter</italic> infection</article-title>. <source>J Hyg (Lond)</source>
<year>1980</year>; <volume>84</volume>:<fpage>415</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7052223</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIV431C36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Milk-borne campylobacter infection</article-title>. <source>Br Med J (Clin Res Ed)</source>
<year>1981</year>; <volume>282</volume>:<fpage>1374</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIV431C37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Waterman</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bramley</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A search for the source of <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> in milk</article-title>. <source>J Hyg (Lond)</source>
<year>1984</year>; <volume>93</volume>:<fpage>333</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6501879</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIV431C38"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Humphrey</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title><italic>Campylobacter</italic> and <italic>Salmonella</italic> contamination of unpasteurized cows&#x02019; milk on sale to the public</article-title>. <source>J Appl Bacteriol</source>
<year>1988</year>; <volume>65</volume>:<fpage>463</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3072328</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIV431C39"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blaser</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hardesty</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Powers</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Survival of <italic>Campylobacter fetus</italic> subsp. <italic>jejuni</italic> in biological milieus</article-title>. <source>J Clin Microbiol</source>
<year>1980</year>; <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>309</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>13</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6892819</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIV431C40"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abid</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wimalarathna</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Duck liver-associated outbreak of campylobacteriosis among humans, United Kingdom, 2011</article-title>. <source>Emerg Infect Dis</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>1310</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23876233</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIV431C41"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Forbes</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gormley</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dallas</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title><italic>Campylobacter</italic> immunity and coinfection following a large outbreak in a farming community</article-title>. <source>J Clin Microbiol</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>47</volume>:<fpage>111</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19005146</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIV431C42"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Briggs</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Boxall</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Van Santen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chalmers</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Approaches to the detection of very small, common, and easily missed outbreaks that together contribute substantially to human <italic>Cryptosporidium</italic> infection</article-title>. <source>Epidemiol Infect</source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>142</volume>:<fpage>1869</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>76</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24690264</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>