<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">DNA Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">DNA Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">dnares</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">dnares</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>DNA Research: An International Journal for Rapid Publication of Reports on Genes and Genomes</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1340-2838</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1756-1663</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24568933</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4131831</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/dnares/dsu003</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">dsu003</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Full Papers</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Complete Genome Sequence of <italic>Enterococcus mundtii</italic> QU 25, an Efficient <sc>l</sc>-(+)-Lactic Acid-Producing Bacterium</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shiwa</surname><given-names>Yuh</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="AN1">&#x02020;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yanase</surname><given-names>Hiroaki</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hirose</surname><given-names>Yuu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Satomi</surname><given-names>Shohei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Araya-Kojima</surname><given-names>Tomoko</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>Satoru</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zendo</surname><given-names>Takeshi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chibazakura</surname><given-names>Taku</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shimizu-Kadota</surname><given-names>Mariko</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yoshikawa</surname><given-names>Hirofumi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sonomoto</surname><given-names>Kenji</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af4">4</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib><aff id="af1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Genome Research Center</addr-line>, <institution>NODAI Research Institute, Tokyo University of Agriculture</institution>, <addr-line>1-1-1 Sakuragaoka, Setagaya-ku, Tokyo 156&#x02013;8502</addr-line>, <country>Japan</country></aff><aff id="af2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Department of Bioscience</addr-line>, <institution>Tokyo University of Agriculture</institution>, <addr-line>1-1-1 Sakuragaoka, Setagaya-ku, Tokyo 156-8502</addr-line>, <country>Japan</country></aff><aff id="af3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Electronics-Inspired Interdisciplinary Research Institute (EIIRIS)</addr-line>, <institution>Toyohashi University of Technology</institution>, <addr-line>Toyohashi 441-8580</addr-line>, <country>Japan</country></aff><aff id="af4"><label>4</label><addr-line>Laboratory of Microbial Technology, Division of Applied Molecular Microbiology and Biomass Chemistry, Department of Bioscience and Biotechnology, Faculty of Agriculture</addr-line>, <institution>Graduate School, Kyushu University</institution>, <addr-line>6-10-1 Hakozaki, Higashi-ku, Fukuoka 812-8581</addr-line>, <country>Japan</country></aff><aff id="af5"><label>5</label><addr-line>Department of Environmental Science</addr-line>, <institution>Musashino University</institution>, <addr-line>3-3-3 Ariake, Koto-ku, Tokyo 135-0063</addr-line>, <country>Japan</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel. +81 92-642-3019. Fax. +81 92-642-3019. Email: <email>sonomoto@agr.kyushu-u.ac.jp</email></corresp><fn id="AN1"><label>&#x02020;</label><p>Present address: Iwate Tohoku Medical Megabank Organization, Iwate Medical University, 2-1-1 Nishitokuta, Yahaba-cho, Shiwa-gun, Iwate 028-3694, Japan.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="fn1"><p>Edited by Dr Naotake Ogasawara</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>8</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>24</day><month>2</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>24</day><month>2</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>21</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>369</fpage><lpage>377</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>18</day><month>11</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>1</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author 2014. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of Kazusa DNA Research Institute.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact <email>journals.permissions@oup.com</email></license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="dsu003.pdf"/><abstract><p><italic>Enterococcus mundtii</italic> QU 25, a non-dairy bacterial strain of ovine faecal origin, can ferment both cellobiose and xylose to produce <sc>l</sc>-lactic acid. The use of this strain is highly desirable for economical <sc>l</sc>-lactate production from renewable biomass substrates. Genome sequence determination is necessary for the genetic improvement of this strain. We report the complete genome sequence of strain QU 25, primarily determined using Pacific Biosciences sequencing technology. The <italic>E. mundtii</italic> QU 25 genome comprises a 3 022 186-bp single circular chromosome (GC content, 38.6%) and five circular plasmids: pQY182, pQY082, pQY039, pQY024, and pQY003. In all, 2900 protein-coding sequences, 63 tRNA genes, and 6 rRNA operons were predicted in the QU 25 chromosome. Plasmid pQY024 harbours genes for mundticin production. We found that strain QU 25 produces a bacteriocin, suggesting that mundticin-encoded genes on plasmid pQY024 were functional. For lactic acid fermentation, two gene clusters were identified&#x02014;one involved in the initial metabolism of xylose and uptake of pentose and the second containing genes for the pentose phosphate pathway and uptake of related sugars. This is the first complete genome sequence of an <italic>E. mundtii</italic> strain. The data provide insights into lactate production in this bacterium and its evolution among enterococci.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd><italic>Enterococcus mundtii</italic></kwd><kwd>xylose</kwd><kwd><sc>l</sc>-lactic acid</kwd><kwd>mundticin</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><label>1.</label><title>Introduction</title><p>Optically pure lactic acid is necessary for the production of the bioplastic polylactic acid. The use of cellulosic biomass instead of food crops should lower the cost for commercial production of this green plastic. <italic>Enterococcus mundtii</italic> QU 25 is a non-dairy bacterial strain that was originally isolated from ovine faeces.<sup><xref rid="DSU003C1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> Unlike most lactic acid bacteria, strain QU 25 can ferment both cellobiose and xylose to produce <sc>l</sc>-lactic acid.<sup><xref rid="DSU003C1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="DSU003C2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> This strain metabolizes a mixture of glucose and cellobiose simultaneously without apparent carbon catabolite repression (CCR),<sup><xref rid="DSU003C1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> and it produces optically pure <sc>l</sc>-lactate (&#x02265;99.9%) with a yield of 1.41 mol/mol xylose consumed, without by-products such as acetic acid or ethanol.<sup><xref rid="DSU003C1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="DSU003C2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> Moreover, high productivity of <sc>l</sc>-lactic acid in an open repeated batch fermentation system under non-sterile conditions was demonstrated.<sup><xref rid="DSU003C3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> Therefore, the use of strain QU 25 is highly desirable for the economical production of <sc>l</sc>-lactate from renewable biomass substrates. Furthermore, determination of the genome sequence of this bacterium is necessary to generate optimized, recombinant strains for commercial use.</p><p>Draft genome sequences of microorganisms can be obtained rapidly and cost-effectively by using second-generation sequencing technologies. Owing to its relatively short read length of second-generation platforms (100&#x02013;700 bp), obtaining a complete genome sequence requires additional costs and time-consuming finishing steps such as scaffolding and gap closing. By comparison, third-generation single molecule real time (SMRT) sequencing technology developed by Pacific Biosciences (PacBio) can produce considerably long sequences (&#x0223c;23 kb). Complete genome sequencing using only PacBio sequence data was recently reported.<sup><xref rid="DSU003C4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup></p><p>To date, there have been only two draft genome sequences available for <italic>E. mundtii</italic> (strains CRL1656<sup><xref rid="DSU003C5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> and ATCC 882). Here, we report the complete genome sequence of strain QU 25, whose chromosome sequence was determined using only PacBio sequence data. This is the first complete genome sequence of an <italic>E. mundtii</italic> strain. The data reveal useful insights on lactic acid fermentation in this bacterium, as well as phylogenetic relationships with other <italic>Enterococcus</italic> species.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><label>2.</label><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="s2a"><label>2.1.</label><title>Culture conditions and preparation of genomic DNA for sequencing</title><p><italic>Enterococcus mundtii</italic> QU 25 cells were grown to mid-log phase in GM17.<sup><xref rid="DSU003C6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> Cells from 100-ml culture were harvested, suspended in 25 ml of a solution containing 2 g of polyethylene glycol 2000, 62.5 mg of egg white lysozyme, and 5 mM Tris&#x02013;hydrochloride (pH 8.0), and incubated for 60 min at 37&#x000b0;C. After centrifugation, the cells were resuspended in 12.5 ml of TES buffer (50 mM Tris&#x02013;hydrochloride [pH 7.6], 20 mM sodium ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid, and 25% sucrose), treated with 8 &#x000b5;g/ml of ribonuclease A for 60 min at 37&#x000b0;C, and then lysed with heat at 60&#x000b0;C for 2 h in the presence of 40 &#x000b5;g/ml of proteinase K and 1.7% sodium dodecyl sulphate. Total DNA was extracted gently from the lysate with PCI mixture (phenol, chloroform, and isoamyl alcohol in a ratio of 25 : 24 : 1, respectively) three times and precipitated with ethanol.</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><label>2.2.</label><title>Genome sequencing</title><p>For PacBio RS sequencing, two types of SMRTbell DNA template libraries were created with 1- and 10-kb sheared genomic DNA, and prepared using the standard PacBio RS sample preparation methods with C2 chemistry specific to each insert size. The 10-kb library was sequenced on eight SMRT cells with a 1 &#x000d7; 120-min collection protocol, generating 189 953 post-filtered continuous long reads (CLRs; mean length, 3702 bp; maximum length 20 405 bp; &#x0223c;234&#x000d7; coverage). The 1-kb library was sequenced on eight SMRT cells with a 2 &#x000d7; 55-min collection protocol, generating 258 068 post-filtered circular consensus sequences (CCS; mean length, 660 bp; &#x0223c;57&#x000d7; coverage).</p><p>For the second-generation Roche/454 sequencing, a 1.6-kb fragment library was sequenced using the GS-FLX+ system. A total of 302 056 reads (mean length, 455 bp; &#x0223c;34&#x000d7; coverage) was generated and assembled using Newbler (ver. 2.6). To estimate the plasmid copy number, a 500-bp paired-end library was sequenced using the Illumina Genome Analyzer IIx, generating 76-bp paired-end reads (48 724 736 reads, &#x0223c;1234&#x000d7; coverage). The copy number of plasmid per chromosome was estimated based on the coverage ratio between the corresponding contig and the chromosome contig using CLC Genomics workbench 6 (CLC bio, Aarhus, Denmark).</p></sec><sec id="s2c"><label>2.3.</label><title>Error correction, assembly, and optical mapping</title><p>The error correction of CLRs was performed using the command pacBioToCA.<sup><xref rid="DSU003C7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> CCS (57&#x000d7; length coverage) reads were used for correction. After error correction, we selected reads named PacBio-corrected Reads (PBcRs) for assembly. Assembly was performed using Celera Assembler (ver. 7.0).<sup><xref rid="DSU003C8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> To confirm the correctness of the assembly, DNA from QU 25 cells was digested using <italic>Nco</italic>I and a whole-genome optical map (OpGen, Inc., Gaithersburg, MD, USA) was generated.<sup><xref rid="DSU003C9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup></p></sec><sec id="s2d"><label>2.4.</label><title>Genome analysis</title><p>At first, the genome sequence was automatically annotated using the MiGAP, Microbial Genome Annotation Pipeline (<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="www.migap.org">www.migap.org</uri>) with the g-MiGAP level. In the pipeline, open reading frames (ORFs) were identified using MetaGeneAnnotator,<sup><xref rid="DSU003C10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> and genes for tRNAs and rRNAs were identified by tRNAscan-SE and RNAmmer, respectively.<sup><xref rid="DSU003C11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> Predicted ORFs were annotated using BLASTP searches against other <italic>Enterococcus</italic> genomes, and National Center of Biological Information (NCBI) nr<sup><xref rid="DSU003C12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> with an <italic>E</italic>-value of 1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;10</sup>. Additional annotation was performed using InterProScan<sup><xref rid="DSU003C13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> and KEGG pathway analyses.<sup><xref rid="DSU003C14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> Regions containing prophage were predicted by a phage search tool, PHAST (<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://phast.wishartlab.com/">http://phast.wishartlab.com/</uri>)<sup><xref rid="DSU003C15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> and further manual inspection. The insertion sequence (IS) was detected by ISsaga.<sup><xref rid="DSU003C16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> CRISPR loci were detected by CRISPRfinder.<sup><xref rid="DSU003C17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> For comparative genomes of other <italic>Enterococcus</italic> spp., a draft genome sequence of <italic>E. mundtii</italic> ATCC 882 was obtained from the Broad Institute website (<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://olive.broadinstitute.org/genomes/ente_mund_atcc882.1">https://olive.broadinstitute.org/genomes/ente_mund_atcc882.1</uri>). In addition, complete genome sequences of five <italic>Enterococcus</italic> spp. with (<italic>E. casseliflavus</italic> EC20<sup><xref rid="DSU003C18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup>: NC_021023; <italic>E. faecalis</italic> V583<sup><xref rid="DSU003C19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup>: NC_004668, NC_004669, NC_004670, and NC_004671; <italic>E. faecium</italic> Aus0004<sup><xref rid="DSU003C20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup>: NC_017022, NC_017023, NC_017024, and NC_017032; <italic>E. faecium</italic> DO<sup><xref rid="DSU003C21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup>: NC_017960, NC_017961, NC_017962, and NC_017963; <italic>E. hirae</italic> ATCC 9790<sup><xref rid="DSU003C22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup>: NC_015845 and NC_018081) were obtained from the NCBI website for genome comparisons. GenomeMatcher<sup><xref rid="DSU003C23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> and In Silico Molecular Cloning Genomics Edition (IMC-GE) software (In Silico Biology, Japan) were also used for intra- and inter-QU 25 genome comparisons.</p></sec><sec id="s2e"><label>2.5.</label><title>Vancomycin resistance assay</title><p><italic>Enterococcus mundtii</italic> QU 25 was propagated in MRS medium (Oxoid, Basingstoke, UK) at 30&#x000b0;C for 12 h as a pre-culture. One hundred microliters of pre-culture were inoculated in 10 ml of MRS medium containing various concentrations of vancomycin (2&#x02013;100 &#x000b5;g/ml, Sigma, St. Louis, MO, USA). After incubation at 30&#x000b0;C for 24 h, the minimum concentration of vancomycin that resulted in the absence of growth was considered to be the minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC).</p></sec><sec id="s2f"><label>2.6.</label><title>Bacteriocin activity assay</title><p><italic>Lactobacillus sakei</italic> JCM 1157<sup>T</sup> and <italic>E. faecalis</italic> JCM 5803<sup>T</sup> were employed as indicator strains for bacteriocin activity. Taken together with <italic>E. mundtii</italic> QU 25, <italic>E. mundtii</italic> QU 2 (mundticin producer)<sup><xref rid="DSU003C24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> and JCM 8731<sup>T</sup> (non-bacteriocin producer) were tested as positive and negative controls, respectively. The three <italic>E. mundtii</italic> strains were also used as indicator strains for cross- and self-immunity. All strains were propagated in MRS medium at 30&#x000b0;C for 12&#x02013;18 h before use. Strains QU 25, QU 2, and JCM 8731<sup>T</sup> were cultured in MRS medium at 30&#x000b0;C for 12 h for bacteriocin production. Bacteriocin activity assay was performed by the spot-on-lawn method, as described previously.<sup><xref rid="DSU003C25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> Briefly, 10 &#x000b5;l of each cell-free culture supernatant were spotted onto a double-layered agar plate containing 5 ml of Lactobacilli Agar AOAC (BD, Sparks, MD, USA) inoculated with an overnight culture of an indicator strain as an upper layer, and 10 ml of MRS medium supplemented with 1.2% agar as a bottom layer. After overnight incubation at appropriate temperatures for indicator strains, bacterial lawns were checked for inhibition zones.</p></sec><sec id="s2g"><label>2.7.</label><title>Catalase and haemolysin activity assays</title><p>Strain QU 25 was tested for catalase activity by two methods. First, cells cultured in MRS liquid medium at 30&#x000b0;C for 12 h were collected by centrifugation and examined for catalase activity by the addition of 3% hydrogen peroxide solution. Secondly, colonies formed on the sheep blood-containing agar plates (Eiken Chemical, Tokyo, Japan) after incubation at 30&#x000b0;C for 24 h were examined by the addition of 3% hydrogen peroxide solution. Generation of oxygen bubbles was considered to be indicative of catalase activity. Colonies formed on blood agar plates were also examined for haemolysin activity. Discolouration or clearing of blood agar in the vicinity of the colonies was regarded as haemolysis.</p></sec><sec id="s2h"><label>2.8.</label><title>Nucleotide sequence accession numbers</title><p>The complete genome sequence for <italic>E. mundtii</italic> QU 25 was deposited in GenBank/DDBJ/EMBL under accession numbers AP013036&#x02013;AP013041.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><label>3.</label><title>Results and discussion</title><sec id="s3a"><label>3.1.</label><title>Genome summary</title><p>To determine the full genome sequence of <italic>E. mundtii</italic> QU 25, we combined two sequencing platforms: PacBio and Roche/454. As a result, the complete chromosome sequence of <italic>E. mundtii</italic> QU 25 was determined using only PacBio RS sequencing. This technology generates two types of sequences: CLRs and CCS reads.<sup><xref rid="DSU003C26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> The read length of CLRs can reach up to 23 kb; however, the average base accuracy is only 82.1&#x02013;84.4%.<sup><xref rid="DSU003C7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> CCS reads are consensus sequences obtained from multiple passes on a single sequence with relatively short lengths (&#x0223c;2 kb) and a low error rate.<sup><xref rid="DSU003C27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup> The PBcR algorithm can improve read accuracy of CLRs from 80% to over 99.9% by using CCS reads.<sup><xref rid="DSU003C7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup></p><p>Error correction of CLRs was done using high-accuracy sequences of CCS with the PBcR algorithm.<sup><xref rid="DSU003C7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> After error correction, the resulting 6806 PBcRs of at least 7-kb length (mean length, 8517 bp; maximum length, 16 733 bp; &#x0223c;20&#x000d7; coverage) were assembled, generating five contigs. Comparison between the <italic>Nco</italic>I digest of the whole-genome optical map and <italic>in silico</italic>-generated physical maps of contigs showed that the largest contig (3 Mb) was mapped onto the chromosome, confirming the correctness of the assembly (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DSU003F1">1</xref>A). Thus, we concluded that the remaining four contigs were plasmids. The presence of the 2.5-kb plasmid, which had been detected as an extrachromosomal element by agarose gel electrophoresis (data not shown), was not included in the five contigs generated by PacBio, due to its assembly threshold of 7-kb read length. Therefore, we adapted one contig produced using Roche/454.
<fig id="DSU003F1" position="float"><label>Figure&#x000a0;1.</label><caption><p>Analysis of the <italic>Enterococcus mundtii</italic> QU 25 complete genome. (A) Linearized <italic>Nco</italic>I-digested whole-genome optical map of QU 25 compared with the <italic>in silico</italic>-derived <italic>Nco</italic>I-digest map, demonstrating correct chromosome assembly. (B) Genome map of the QU 25 strain. In the outermost circle, three prophages of phiEmqu1, phiEmqu2, and phiEmqu3, replication origin (<italic>dnaA</italic>), and terminus (<italic>dif</italic>) are shown. In the second circle, the ORFs transcribed in a clockwise manner are shown as bars. The third circle shows ORFS transcribed in a counter-clockwise manner. The fourth to ninth circles depict the results of ortholog analyses (BLASTP <italic>E</italic>-value &#x02264;1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;10</sup>) with <italic>E. mundtii</italic> ATCC 882, <italic>E. faecium</italic> DO, <italic>E. faecium</italic> Aus0004, <italic>E. hirae</italic> ATCC 9790, <italic>E. casseliflavus</italic> EC20, and <italic>E. faecalis</italic> V583, respectively. The extent of homology relative to QU 25 is depicted using a heat map of arbitrarily chosen bins. The colour scheme and percentage identity for orthologs are as follows: red, orthologs with &#x0003e;90% identity; green, 70&#x02013;90% identity; blue, 50&#x02013;70% identity; and black, &#x0003c;50% identity. The 10th circle shows the positions of rRNA operons. The last two (innermost) circles represent G + C content (purple &#x0003e;39.5% average; green &#x0003c;39.5% average; range from 32 to 47%) and G + C skew, both calculated for a 10-kb window with 1-kb stepping.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="dsu00301"/></fig></p><p>The genome of QU 25 comprises a single circular chromosome of 3 022 186 bp (GC content, 38.6%) and five circular plasmids: pQY182, pQY082, pQY039, pQY024, and pQY003, with lengths of 181 920, 82 213, 38 528, 23 629, and 2584 bp, and GC contents of 36.2, 35.8, 33.8, 35.3, and 38.9%, respectively (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="DSU003TB1">1</xref> and Fig.&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DSU003F1">1</xref>B). Coordinates on the genome were designated as bp starting from the first nucleotide of the start codon of <italic>dnaA.</italic> We confirmed the likely location of the replication terminus by identifying a single <italic>dif</italic> sequence (ACTTTGTATAATATATATTATGTAAACT, position 1 449 088 to 1 449 115) that aligns with the shift in GC skew (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DSU003F1">1</xref>B). A total of 2900 protein-coding sequences (CDS), 63 tRNA genes, and 6 rRNA operons were predicted in the QU 25 chromosome.
<table-wrap id="DSU003TB1" position="float"><label>Table&#x000a0;1.</label><caption><p>General features of the <italic>Enterococcus mundtii</italic> QU 25 genome</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="char" char=" " span="1"/><col align="char" char=" " span="1"/><col align="char" char=" " span="1"/><col align="char" char=" " span="1"/><col align="char" char=" " span="1"/><col align="char" char=" " span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Features</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chromosome</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pQY182</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pQY082</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pQY039</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pQY024</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pQY003</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Size (bp)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 022 186</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">181 920</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">82 213</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 528</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 629</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2584</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G + C content (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of rRNA operons</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of tRNA genes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CDS (protein coding)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2900</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">178</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">82</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average of CDS length (bp)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">884</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">813</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">818</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">850</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">903</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">436</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estimated copy number of replicon</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="s3b"><label>3.2.</label><title>Genomic comparisons with other <italic>Enterococcus</italic> species</title><p>From the phylogeny based on 16S rRNA sequences, <italic>E. mundtii</italic> was closely related to <italic>E. hirae</italic> and <italic>E. faecium</italic>, while <italic>E. casseliflavus</italic> and <italic>E. faecalis</italic> were more distantly related to <italic>E. mundtii.</italic><sup><xref rid="DSU003C28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup> To investigate the taxonomic position of <italic>E. mundtii</italic> QU 25 based on genome-wide comparisons, we first carried out ortholog analysis with the draft genome of <italic>E. mundtii</italic> ATCC 882 and five complete genomes of other <italic>Enterococcus</italic> spp., including two <italic>E. faecium</italic> strains (DO and Aus0004), <italic>E. hirae</italic> ATCC 9790, <italic>E. casseliflavus</italic> EC20, and <italic>E. faecalis</italic> V583 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/dnares/dsu003/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S1</ext-link> and Fig.&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DSU003F1">1</xref>B). The results were consistent with the phylogeny based on 16S rRNA. While <italic>E. mundtii</italic> ATCC 882 showed the highest similarity to QU 25 as anticipated, two other species (<italic>E. faecium</italic> DO and Aus0004, and <italic>E. hirae</italic> ATCC 9790) showed moderate degrees of similarity, while <italic>E. casseliflavus</italic> EC20 and <italic>E. faecalis</italic> V583 were the least similar. DNA dot plot analysis showed the centre diagonal line between QU 25, the two <italic>E. faecium</italic> strains, and <italic>E. hirae</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DSU003F2">2</xref>), indicating that not only each of the genes but also their genome structures (or gene orders) were related. There were gene regions unique to the QU 25 strain (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DSU003F1">1</xref>B). Except for prophages, the 9-kb region (positions 1 359 588&#x02013;1 368 963) includes five hypothetical proteins and a cell wall-anchored protein with a LPXTG motif.
<fig id="DSU003F2" position="float"><label>Figure&#x000a0;2.</label><caption><p>Dot plots comparing the chromosomal organization among the six <italic>Enterococcus</italic> species. Dot plots were generated using BLASTN and GenomeMatcher software. This figure appears in colour in the online version of <italic>DNA Research</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="dsu00302"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s3c"><label>3.3.</label><title>Mobile genetic elements</title><p>Three chromosomal regions were identified as prophage loci. Their positions are indicated in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DSU003F1">1</xref>B and are named phiEmqu1 (38.7 kb; positions 806 547&#x02013;845 215), phiEmqu2 (47.9 kb; positions 2 327 297&#x02013;2 375 151), and phiEmqu3 (40.8 kb; positions 2 556 843&#x02013;2 597 594). Sixty, 70, and 54 phage-related genes were identified in these regions, respectively (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/dnares/dsu003/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S2</ext-link>). Prophages phiEmqu1 and phiEmqu3 contained several putative genes involved in DNA replication. However, no genes for DNA synthesis were found in the largest prophage phiEmqu2, suggesting that it is replication-defective. As shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DSU003F1">1</xref>B, the locations of <italic>ori</italic> (<italic>dnaA</italic>) and <italic>ter</italic> (<italic>dif</italic>) were not exactly opposite each other. The <italic>dif</italic> motif, which is strongly associated with replication termini,<sup><xref rid="DSU003C29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup> was &#x0223c;60 kb off the exact opposite position of <italic>ori</italic> (<italic>dnaA</italic>). Phage-mediated replicore imbalance has been observed in <italic>E. faecium</italic> Aus0004.<sup><xref rid="DSU003C20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> Thus, the replicore balance of QU 25 could be disrupted by the insertion of phiEmqu2 and/or phiEmqu3.</p><p>Clustered regularly interspaced short palindromic repeats (CRISPRs) are involved in a recently discovered interference pathway that protects cells from bacteriophages and conjugative plasmids. Approximately 40% of sequenced bacterial genomes and &#x0223c;90% of genomes from archaea contain at least one CRISPR locus.<sup><xref rid="DSU003C30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> No CRISPR loci were detected in the QU 25 genome. Many insertion sequence elements (ISEs) have been found in enterococci. The relatively closed species, such as <italic>E. mundtii</italic> ATCC 882, <italic>E. faecium</italic> DO and Aus0004 strains, and <italic>E. hirae</italic> ATCC 9790, have 21, 180, 76, and 14 ISEs and transposase-related genes, respectively. At least 13 different ISEs were detected in the QU 25 genome, ranging in copy number from 1 to 5, representing 33 distinct copies and distributed around the chromosome and plasmids (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/dnares/dsu003/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S3</ext-link>). The most frequently observed ISE type was the ISL3 family.</p></sec><sec id="s3d"><label>3.4.</label><title>Plasmids</title><p><italic>Enterococcus</italic> spp. have been reported to possess a number of plasmids that often confer resistance to antimicrobials and particular heavy metals, and serve to enhance virulence and/or DNA repair mechanisms.<sup><xref rid="DSU003C31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="DSU003C34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup> In strain QU 25, the plasmid copy number per chromosome was estimated by observing the distribution of read coverage of the Illumina sequence read, which indicated one copy of pQY182, pQY082, pQY039, and pQY024, and five copies of pQY003 (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="DSU003TB1">1</xref>). BLASTN analyses showed that these five plasmids were similar to those of <italic>E. mundtii</italic>, <italic>E. faecium</italic>, <italic>E. hirae</italic>, or <italic>E. faecalis</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/dnares/dsu003/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S4</ext-link>).</p><p>Plasmid pQY182 harbours genes that encode a two-component regulatory system, a cellulose 1,4-beta-cellobiosidase, a toxin&#x02013;antitoxin system, and several proteins with DNA repair functions. Plasmid pQY082 harbours duplicated regions of 8.3 kb, which include the IS1675 transposase, <italic>ubiD</italic> family decarboxylase, two cell surface proteins, and two proteins with unknown functions (EMQU_3088-3094 and EMQU_3155-3160 with 99% similarity). pQY082 also harbours genes that encode several proteins with DNA repair functions and a toxin&#x02013;antitoxin system. Toxin&#x02013;antitoxin systems have been frequently reported in <italic>E. faecium</italic> strains,<sup><xref rid="DSU003C35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup> and the QU 25 chromosome additionally has at least four such systems. Plasmid pQY039 contains several genes for a DNA damage-inducible protein and a gene encoding a toxin&#x02013;antitoxin system. Plasmid pQY024 also harbours genes for a DNA damage-inducible protein, a toxin&#x02013;antitoxin system, and mundticin KS genes (see Discussion later). Plasmid pQY003 only harbours genes with unknown function, except for the replication initiation protein.</p></sec><sec id="s3e"><label>3.5.</label><title>Vancomycin resistance</title><p>Because many <italic>Enterococcus</italic> isolates show vancomycin resistance which has been associated with hospital-acquired infections, we tested the sensitivity of QU 25 to this antibiotic for the safety of industrial use. The results showed that the vancomycin MIC for QU 25 was &#x0003e;2 &#x000b5;g/ml, indicating that this strain is vancomycin-sensitive. Several known genes involved in vancomycin resistance (<italic>vanA</italic>, <italic>vanB</italic>, <italic>vanX</italic>, <italic>vanH</italic>, <italic>vanR</italic>, and <italic>vanS</italic>)<sup><xref rid="DSU003C36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup> were not detected in the QU 25 genome and also in plasmids.</p></sec><sec id="s3f"><label>3.6.</label><title>Bacteriocin activity and self- and cross-immunity</title><p>Bacteriocins are ribosomally synthesized bacterial peptides or proteins that show antimicrobial activity, generally against species that are closely related to bacteriocin producers.<sup><xref rid="DSU003C24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> Mundticin is one of the bacteriocins produced by some <italic>E. mundtii</italic> strains. It is significant to clarify whether QU 25 produces mundticin or not for the resistivity to contamination in a large-scale culture. Three genes, such as <italic>munA</italic> (mundticin precursor), <italic>munB</italic> (ATP-binding cassette [ABC] transporter), and <italic>munC</italic> (mundticin KS immunity protein), are responsible for mundticin production in <italic>E. mundtii</italic> NERI 7393.<sup><xref rid="DSU003C37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup> The gene cluster containing these three genes was identified on plasmid pQY024, and <italic>munA</italic> (EMQU_3203; 100% nucleotide sequence identity), <italic>munB</italic> (EMQU_3204; 99.56% nucleotide sequence identity), and <italic>munC</italic> (EMQU_3205; 98.99% nucleotide sequence identity) showed high homology with corresponding genes in strain NERI 7393.</p><p>To examine whether the gene cluster for mundticin synthesis was functional, QU 25 was tested for bacteriocin production. QU 25 and <italic>E. mundtii</italic> QU 2 showed bacteriocin activity against three indicator strains (<italic>L. sakei</italic> JCM 1157<sup>T</sup>, <italic>E. faecalis</italic> JCM 5803<sup>T</sup>, and <italic>E. mundtii</italic> JCM 8731<sup>T</sup>), none of which showed inhibitory activity (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="DSU003TB2">2</xref>). QU 25 and QU 2 showed no activity against each other (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="DSU003TB2">2</xref>), which indicated that these strains have self- and cross-immunity against their bacteriocins. Bacteriocin-producing strains are known to have immunity (tolerance) to their own bacteriocins and to bacteriocins with similar structures. Collectively, these results strongly suggest that QU 25 produces a bacteriocin with similar characteristics to mundticin produced by QU 2.
<table-wrap id="DSU003TB2" position="float"><label>Table&#x000a0;2.</label><caption><p>Bacteriocin activity and immunity of <italic>Enterococcus mundtii</italic> strains</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Indicator strain</th><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Bacteriocin producer<hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>E. mundtii</italic> QU 25</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>E. mundtii</italic> QU 2</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>E. mundtii</italic> JCM 8731<sup>T</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>E. mundtii</italic> QU 25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>E. mundtii</italic> QU 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>E. mundtii</italic> JCM 8731<sup>T</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>E. faecalis</italic> JCM 5803<sup>T</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>L. sakei</italic> JCM 1157<sup>T</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbnfn1"><p>+, growth inhibition of indicator strains; &#x02212;, no inhibition of indicator strains.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="s3g"><label>3.7.</label><title>Haemolysin activity</title><p>Haemolysin is one of the putative enterococcal virulence factors,<sup><xref rid="DSU003C20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> so it is important to test the haemolysin activity for the safety of industrial use in a large-scale culture. Four putative haemolysin genes (haemolysin, haemolysin III, haemolysin A, and &#x003b1;-haemolysin) were identified (EMQU_0190 and EMQU_0948, EMQU_0449, EMQU_0841, and EMQU_1982, respectively). We tested haemolysin activity and no changes to the blood agar in the vicinity of the colonies were observed (data not shown), suggesting that these putative haemolysin genes in QU 25 might be inactive or silent under the tested culture conditions.</p></sec><sec id="s3h"><label>3.8.</label><title>Metabolic pathways for lactic acid fermentation</title><p>QU 25 was previously reported to have two different pathways for xylose metabolism: the phosphoketolase (PK) pathway and the pentose phosphate (PP)/glycolytic pathway in low xylose concentrations.<sup><xref rid="DSU003C2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="DSU003C38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></sup> When QU 25 was grown in high xylose concentrations, PK activity was not detected. However, higher transaldolase and transketolase activities were detected<sup><xref rid="DSU003C2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>, indicating that strain QU 25 would utilize the PP/glycolytic pathway, not the PK pathway, as the main pathway for lactic acid fermentation.</p><p>Genes for xylose metabolism in the QU 25 chromosome were located in a 22-kb region (positions 2 904 895&#x02013;2 926 710 bp) in two gene clusters: one involved in the initial metabolism of xylose and uptake of pentose, and the other involved in the PP/glycolytic pathway and uptake of related sugars (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DSU003F3">3</xref>). The first gene cluster contained <italic>xylR</italic> (EMQU_2811; xylose repressor), <italic>xylA</italic> (EMQU_2810; xylose isomerase), <italic>xynB</italic> (EMQU_2809; xylan beta-1,4-xylosidase; additionally, there is another <italic>xynB</italic> gene [EMQU_2642] outside of this cluster), <italic>xylB</italic> (EMQU_2805; <sc>d</sc>-xylulose kinase), putative xylose transporter genes annotated as <sc>l</sc>-arabinose and <sc>d</sc>-ribose ABC transporter (EMQU_2806-2808), and a hypothetical protein (EMQU_2804), the N- and C-terminal regions of DNA mismatch repair protein (EMQU_2803 and EMQU_2802, respectively, which were thought as pseudogenes), ABC transporter ATP-binding protein (EMQU_2801), and its permease (EMQU_2800). Since pentose transporters have been shown to be promiscuous,<sup><xref rid="DSU003C39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup>
<sc>d</sc>-xylose would likely be transported by these gene products in QU 25.
<fig id="DSU003F3" position="float"><label>Figure&#x000a0;3.</label><caption><p>Gene clusters involved in the initial metabolism of xylose and the PP/glycolytic pathway in <italic>E. mundtii</italic> QU 25. Numbers below arrows indicate feature code (EMQU_XXXX).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="dsu00303"/></fig></p><p>The second gene cluster contains genes for the PP/glycolytic pathway, including a transketolase (EMQU_2812) and a transaldolase (EMQU_2814). Furthermore, this cluster contains an allulose-6-phosphate 3-epimerase gene (EMQU_2813), genes for a fructose-like phosphotransferase system (EMQU_2815-2819), and a putative transcriptional regulator (EMQU_2820). Transketolase is a key enzyme in the PP/glycolytic pathway, and the QU 25 chromosome additionally harbours one transketolase gene (EMQU_1275). Since allulose-6-phosphate 3-epimerase catalyses the conversion of <sc>d</sc>-allulose-6-phosphate to <sc>d</sc>-fructose-6-phosphate, this enzyme and the fructose transporters may supply various ketoses to the PP/glycolytic pathway. For genes involved in the PK pathway, PK (EMQU_1837), acetate kinase (EMQU_2620), phosphotransacetylase (EMQU_2119), acetaldehyde dehydrogenase (EMQU_2205), and alcohol dehydrogenase (EMQU_1129, EMQU_1829, and EMQU_2109) were dispersed throughout the chromosome.</p><p>To get insights into the lactic acid fermentation characteristics of strain QU 25, we performed the comparative analysis on the presence of key enzymes related to lactic acid fermentation from xylose using KO (KEGG Orthology) gene assignment (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/dnares/dsu003/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S5</ext-link>). Two clinical isolates of <italic>E. faecium</italic> (DO and Aus0004) and <italic>E. hirae</italic> ATCC 9790 lack genes necessary for the metabolism of xylose (transaldolase, PK, xylulokinase, and xylose isomerase). Another clinical isolate, <italic>E. faecalis</italic> V583, lacks genes for transketolase, transaldolase, and PK. Thus, it is most unlikely that these strains metabolize xylose. <italic>E. casseliflavus</italic> EC20 has genes for PK, xylulokinase, and xylose isomerase, so that this strain can metabolize xylose by the PK pathway. It also has two complete genes for transketolase, but lacks transaldolase for the PP/glycolytic pathway. However, Kato <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref rid="DSU003C40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup> reported that <italic>Lactococcus lactis</italic> IO-1, which can utilize xylose, also lacks the gene for transaldolase and is presumed to have an alternative PP/glycolytic pathway. Therefore, EC20 might metabolize xylose also by the PP/glycolytic pathway. Two <italic>E. mundtii</italic> strains (QU 25 and ATCC 882) have two genes of full-length transketolase and all other genes necessary for the xylose metabolism by the two pathways. The results of our genomic analysis coincide with the description on their phenotype about xylose metabolism in Bergey's Manual (p. 599, Table&#x000a0;116).<sup><xref rid="DSU003C28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup> From these results, remarkable genomic features related to lactic acid fermentation in QU 25 still remain unclear, and the analysis of transcriptional regulation of these genes could help its clarification.</p><p>QU 25 was able to metabolize a mixture of glucose and cellobiose simultaneously without apparent CCR.<sup><xref rid="DSU003C1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> In Gram-positive bacteria, the roles of catabolite control protein A (CcpA) and seryl-phosphorylated form of histidine-containing protein (P-Ser-HPr) in CCR have been well studied.<sup><xref rid="DSU003C41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></sup> Genes encoding CcpA (EMQU_1943), HPr (EMQU_0954), and HPr kinase/phosphorylase (EMQU_1951) were also found in the QU 25 genome. The mechanism by which CCR is prevented in the presence of glucose is still unknown.</p><p>Strain QU 25 shows a predominant production of <sc>l</sc>-(+)-lactate when grown at high concentrations of cellobiose and xylose, whereas <sc>d</sc>-lactic acid was not detected in the culture broth.<sup><xref rid="DSU003C1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="DSU003C2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> However, two <sc>l</sc>-lactate dehydrogenase genes (<sc>l</sc>-LDH; EMQU_1380 and EMQU_2714) and one <sc>d</sc>-lactate dehydrogenase gene (<sc>d</sc>-LDH; EMQU_2453) were identified. Potentially, little or no <sc>d</sc>-LDH was expressed under these culture conditions. Lactate racemase, another gene involved in <sc>d</sc>-lactic acid formation,<sup><xref rid="DSU003C42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup> was not found in the QU 25 genome.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s4"><label>4.</label><title>Conclusions</title><p>We have highlighted the phylogenetic relationship of <italic>E. mundtii</italic> QU 25 with related enterococcal species and characterized mobile genetic elements, including multiple prophages and ISEs, plasmids, and genes for metabolic pathways for lactic acid fermentation in this strain. In addition, we have demonstrated that QU 25 has bacteriocin activity. The complete <italic>E. mundtii</italic> QU 25 genome sequence described here may be an important resource in the genetic engineering of recombinant strains for optimized production of lactic acid.</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Supplementary data</title><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/dnares/dsu003/-/DC1">Supplementary data are available at www.dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Funding</title><p>This study was supported by <funding-source id="cs1" rid="cn1">the MEXT-Supported Program for the Strategic Research Foundation at Private Universities, 2008-2012</funding-source> (<award-id id="cn1" rid="cs1">S0801025</award-id>).</p></sec>
<sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
<title>Supplementary Material</title>
<supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
<caption>
<title>Supplementary Data</title>
</caption>
<media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_21_4_369__index.html"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"
xlink:href="supp_dsu003_dsu003supp_table1.doc"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"
xlink:href="supp_dsu003_dsu003supp_table2.doc"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"
xlink:href="supp_dsu003_dsu003supp_table3.doc"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"
xlink:href="supp_dsu003_dsu003supp_table4.doc"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"
xlink:href="supp_dsu003_dsu003supp_table5.doc"/>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Pacific Biosciences, Inc. (Menlo Park, CA, USA) and Tomy Digital Biology Co., Ltd (Tokyo, Japan) for PacBio sequencing and assembly, and Hitachi Solutions, Ltd (Tokyo, Japan) for optical mapping. We also thank Y. Kanesaki for helpful discussions.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="DSU003C1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abdel-Rahman</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tashiro</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zendo</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shibata</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonomoto</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation and characterisation of lactic acid bacterium for effective fermentation of cellobiose into optically pure homo <sc>l</sc>-(+)-lactic acid</article-title><source>Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>1039</fpage><lpage>49</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21061005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DSU003C2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abdel-Rahman</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tashiro</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zendo</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanada</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shibata</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonomoto</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efficient homofermentative <sc>l</sc>-(+)-lactic acid production from xylose by a novel lactic acid bacterium, <italic>Enterococcus mundtii</italic> QU 25</article-title><source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>1892</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21193678</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DSU003C3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abdel-Rahman</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tashiro</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zendo</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonomoto</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improved lactic acid productivity by an open repeated batch fermentation system using <italic>Enterococcus mundtii</italic> QU 25</article-title><source>RSC Adv.</source><year>2013</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>8437</fpage><lpage>45</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="DSU003C4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chin</surname><given-names>C.-S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>D.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marks</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Nonhybrid, finished microbial genome assemblies from long-read SMRT sequencing data</article-title><source>Nat. Methods</source><year>2013</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>563</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23644548</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DSU003C5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Magni</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Espeche</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Repizo</surname><given-names>G.D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Draft genome sequence of <italic>Enterococcus mundtii</italic> CRL1656</article-title><source>J. Bacteriol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>194</volume><fpage>550</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22207752</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DSU003C6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Machii</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zendo</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Chemically defined media and auxotrophy of the prolific l-lactic acid producer <italic>Lactococcus lactis</italic> IO-1</article-title><source>J. Biosci. Bioeng.</source><year>2013</year><volume>115</volume><fpage>481</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23287501</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DSU003C7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koren</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schatz</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Walenz</surname><given-names>B.P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Hybrid error correction and de novo assembly of single-molecule sequencing reads</article-title><source>Nat. Biotechnol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>693</fpage><lpage>700</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22750884</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DSU003C8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Delcher</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Koren</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Aggressive assembly of pyrosequencing reads with mates</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2008</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>2818</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18952627</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DSU003C9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nagarajan</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Read</surname><given-names>T.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pop</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Scaffolding and validation of bacterial genome assemblies using optical restriction maps</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2008</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>1229</fpage><lpage>35</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18356192</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DSU003C10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Noguchi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Taniguchi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MetaGeneAnnotator: detecting species-specific patterns of ribosomal binding site for precise gene prediction in anonymous prokaryotic and phage genomes</article-title><source>DNA Res.</source><year>2008</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>387</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18940874</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DSU003C11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sugawara</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohyama</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurokawa</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microbial genome annotation pipeline (MiGAP) for diverse users</article-title><year>2009</year><conf-name>The 20th International Conference on Genome Informatics (GIW2009) Poster and Software Demonstrations (Yokohama)</conf-name><comment>S001-1-2</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="DSU003C12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Benson</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Database resources of the National Center for Biotechnology Information</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2007</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>D5</fpage><lpage>D12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17170002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DSU003C13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zdobnov</surname><given-names>E.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Apweiler</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>InterProScan&#x02014;an integration platform for the signature-recognition methods in InterPro</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2001</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>847</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11590104</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DSU003C14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moriya</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Okuda</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshizawa</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanehisa</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>KAAS: an automatic genome annotation and pathway reconstruction server</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2007</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>W182</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17526522</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DSU003C15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>K.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dennis</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wishart</surname><given-names>D.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PHAST: a fast phage search tool</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2011</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>W347</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21672955</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DSU003C16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Varani</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Siguier</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gourbeyre</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Charneau</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandler</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ISsaga is an ensemble of web-based methods for high throughput identification and semi-automatic annotation of insertion sequences in prokaryotic genomes</article-title><source>Genome Biol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>R30</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21443786</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DSU003C17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grissa</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vergnaud</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pourcel</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CRISPRFinder: a web tool to identify clustered regularly interspaced short palindromic repeats</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2007</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>W52</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17537822</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DSU003C18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>K.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carniol</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Manson</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>High-quality draft genome sequences of 28 <italic>Enterococcus</italic> sp. isolates</article-title><source>J. Bacteriol.</source><year>2010</year><volume>192</volume><fpage>2469</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20207762</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DSU003C19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paulsen</surname><given-names>I.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Banerjei</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>G.S.A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Role of mobile DNA in the evolution of vancomycin-resistant <italic>Enterococcus faecalis</italic></article-title><source>Science</source><year>2003</year><volume>299</volume><fpage>2071</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12663927</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DSU003C20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>M.M.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seemann</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bulach</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparative analysis of the first complete <italic>Enterococcus faecium</italic> genome</article-title><source>J. Bacteriol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>194</volume><fpage>2334</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22366422</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DSU003C21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Galloway-Pe&#x000f1;a</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sillanpaa</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Complete genome sequence of <italic>Enterococcus faecium</italic> strain TX16 and comparative genomic analysis of <italic>Enterococcus faecium</italic> genomes</article-title><source>BMC Microbiol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>135</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22769602</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DSU003C22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gaechter</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wunderlin</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidheini</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Solioz</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome sequence of <italic>Enterococcus hirae</italic> (<italic>Streptococcus faecalis</italic>) ATCC 9790, a model organism for the study of ion transport, bioenergetics, and copper homeostasis</article-title><source>J. Bacteriol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>194</volume><fpage>5126</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22933757</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DSU003C23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ohtsubo</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikeda-Ohtsubo</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagata</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsuda</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>GenomeMatcher: a graphical user interface for DNA sequence comparison</article-title><source>BMC Bioinformatics</source><year>2008</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>376</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18793444</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DSU003C24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zendo</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eungruttanagorn</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujioka</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identification and production of a bacteriocin from <italic>Enterococcus mundtii</italic> QU 2 isolated from soybean</article-title><source>J. Appl. Microbiol.</source><year>2005</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>1181</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16238749</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DSU003C25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ennahar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Asou</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zendo</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonomoto</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishizaki</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biochemical and genetic evidence for production of enterocins A and B by <italic>Enterococcus faecium</italic> WHE 81</article-title><source>Int. J. Food Microbiol.</source><year>2001</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>291</fpage><lpage>301</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11764194</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DSU003C26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>S.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>D.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Advantages of single-molecule real-time sequencing in high-GC content genomes</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>e68824</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23894349</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DSU003C27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Travers</surname><given-names>K.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chin</surname><given-names>C.-S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rank</surname><given-names>D.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eid</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>S.W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A flexible and efficient template format for circular consensus sequencing and SNP detection</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2010</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>e159</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20571086</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DSU003C28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whitman</surname><given-names>W.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodfellow</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#x000e4;mpfer</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Bergey's Manual of Systematic Bacteriology</source><year>2012</year><edition>2 edition</edition><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer Publishing Company</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="DSU003C29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hendrickson</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>J.G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mutational bias suggests that replication termination occurs near the dif site, not at Ter Sites</article-title><source>Mol. Microbiol.</source><year>2007</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>42</fpage><lpage>56</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17376071</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DSU003C30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marraffini</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sontheimer</surname><given-names>E.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CRISPR interference: RNA-directed adaptive immunity in bacteria and archaea</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Genet.</source><year>2010</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20125085</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DSU003C31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arias</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Panesso</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>K.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>L.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>B.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cotransfer of antibiotic resistance genes and a hylEfm-containing virulence plasmid in <italic>Enterococcus faecium</italic></article-title><source>Antimicrob. Agents Chemother.</source><year>2009</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>4240</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19667280</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DSU003C32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garcia-Migura</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasman</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>L.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Presence of pRI1: a small cryptic mobilizable plasmid isolated from <italic>Enterococcus faecium</italic> of human and animal origin</article-title><source>Curr. Microbiol.</source><year>2009</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18830745</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DSU003C33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garcia-Migura</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liebana</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>L.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transposon characterization of vancomycin-resistant <italic>Enterococcus faecium</italic> (VREF) and dissemination of resistance associated with transferable plasmids</article-title><source>J. Antimicrob. Chemother.</source><year>2007</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>263</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17561499</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DSU003C34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hasman</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kempf</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chidaine</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Copper resistance in <italic>Enterococcus faecium</italic>, mediated by the tcrB gene, is selected by supplementation of pig feed with copper sulfate</article-title><source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source><year>2006</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>5784</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16957194</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DSU003C35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moritz</surname><given-names>E.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hergenrother</surname><given-names>P.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Toxin-antitoxin systems are ubiquitous and plasmid-encoded in vancomycin-resistant enterococci</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2007</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>311</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17190821</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DSU003C36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pootoolal</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Neu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>G.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Glycopeptide antibiotic resistance</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Pharmacol. Toxicol.</source><year>2002</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>381</fpage><lpage>408</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11807177</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DSU003C37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kawamoto</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shima</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Biochemical and genetic characterization of mundticin KS, an antilisterial peptide produced by <italic>Enterococcus mundtii</italic> NFRI 7393</article-title><source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source><year>2002</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>3830</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12147478</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DSU003C38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abdel-Rahman</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tashiro</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonomoto</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recent advances in lactic acid production by microbial fermentation processes</article-title><source>Biotechnol. Adv.</source><year>2013</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>877</fpage><lpage>902</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23624242</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DSU003C39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Utilization of <sc>d</sc>-ribose through <sc>d</sc>-xylose transporter</article-title><source>FEMS Microbiol. Lett.</source><year>1998</year><volume>163</volume><fpage>255</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9673030</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DSU003C40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shiwa</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oshima</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Complete genome sequence of <italic>Lactococcus lactis</italic> IO-1, a lactic acid bacterium that utilizes xylose and produces high levels of <sc>l</sc>-lactic acid</article-title><source>J. Bacteriol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>194</volume><fpage>2102</fpage><lpage>3</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22461545</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DSU003C41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Carbon catabolite control of the metabolic network in <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic></article-title><source>Biosci. Biotechnol. Biochem.</source><year>2009</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>245</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19202299</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DSU003C42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goffin</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deghorain</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mainardi</surname><given-names>J.-L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Lactate racemization as a rescue pathway for supplying <sc>d</sc>-lactate to the cell wall biosynthesis machinery in <italic>Lactobacillus plantarum</italic></article-title><source>J. Bacteriol.</source><year>2005</year><volume>187</volume><fpage>6750</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16166538</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>