<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="abstract"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">EJNMMI Phys</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">EJNMMI Phys</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>EJNMMI Physics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2197-7364</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer International Publishing</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Cham</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26501636</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4545852</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">55</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/2197-7364-1-S1-A48</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Meeting Abstract</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A fully automated and reproducible level-set segmentation approach for generation of MR-based attenuation correction map of PET images in the brain employing single STE-MR imaging modality</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Kazerooni</surname><given-names>Anahita Fathi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff102"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff103"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Aarabi</surname><given-names>Mohammad Hadi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff102"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff103"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ay</surname><given-names>Mohammadreza</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff102"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff104"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rad</surname><given-names>Hamidreza Saligheh</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff102"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff103"/></contrib><aff id="Aff102"><label/>Quantitative MR Imaging and Spectroscopy Group, Research Center for Cellular and Molecular Imaging, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran </aff><aff id="Aff103"><label/>Department of Medical Physics and Biomedical Engineering, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran </aff><aff id="Aff104"><label/>Medical Imaging Systems Group, Research Center for Cellular and Molecular Imaging, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>7</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>29</day><month>7</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>7</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>1</volume><issue>Suppl 1</issue><elocation-id>A48</elocation-id><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; Kazerooni et al; licensee Springer 2014</copyright-statement><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This article is published under license to BioMed Central Ltd. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2014</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Generating MR-based attenuation correction map (<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>-map) for quantitative reconstruction of PET images still remains a challenge in hybrid PET/MRI systems, mainly because cortical bone structures are indistinguishable from proximal air cavities in conventional MR images. Recently, development of short echo-time (STE) MR imaging sequences, has shown promise in differentiating cortical bone from air. However, on STE-MR images, the bone appears with discontinuous boundaries. Therefore, segmentation techniques based on intensity classification, such as thresholding or fuzzy C-means, fail to homogeneously delineate bone boundaries, especially in the presence of intrinsic noise and intensity inhomogeneity. Consequently, they cannot be fully automatized, must be fine-tuned on the case-by-case basis, and require additional morphological operations for segmentation refinement. To overcome the mentioned problems, in this study, we introduce a new fully automatic and reproducible STE-MR segmentation approach exploiting level-set in a clustering-based intensity inhomogeneity correction framework to reliably delineate bone from soft tissue and air.</p><p>MR images were acquired on a clinical 1.5T MRI System, MAGNETOM Avanto, using a FLASH 3D pulse sequence with <italic>TE</italic>=1.1<italic>ms</italic>, <italic>TR</italic>=12<italic>ms</italic>, <italic>flip angle</italic>=18&#x000b0;, <italic>voxel size</italic>=1.2&#x000d7;1.2&#x000d7;2<italic>mm</italic><sup>3</sup>.</p><p>For segmentation of the STE-MR images into three regions, consisting of bone, air and soft tissue, a region-based level-set segmentation algorithm was applied. In this technique, k-means clustering is applied to estimate the intensity properties of each region for bias field correction simultaneously with the level-set segmentation. This algorithm incorporates both intensity and spatial information to define continuous boundaries.</p><p>The quantitative assessment outcomes of the segmentation performance yielded an average of 89%, 82%, 91%, and 73% for the accuracy, sensitivity, specificity and dice scores in bone segmentation, respectively.</p><p>The results suggest that the proposed fully automatic segmentation approach can reliably discriminate bony structures from the neighboring air and soft tissue in STE-MR images, which is suitable for generating accurate <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>-maps in clinical PET/MR applications.</p></body></article>