<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Environ Health Perspect</journal-id><journal-title>Environmental Health Perspectives</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0091-6765</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">8319629</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">1567053</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Detection and comparison of DNA adducts after in vitro and in vivo diesel emission exposures.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gallagher</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>George</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kohan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shank</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lewtas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, Research Triangle Park, NC 27711.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>3</month><year>1993</year></pub-date><volume>99</volume><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>228</lpage><abstract><p>Development of methods to evaluate certain classes of polycyclic aromatic compounds (PAC) detected in complex mixtures to which humans are exposed would greatly improve the diagnostic potential of 32P-postlabeling analysis. Identification of DNA adduct patterns or specific exposure-related marker adducts would strengthen associations between observed DNA adducts and exposures to different environmental pollutants (e.g., kerosene, cigarette smoke, coke oven, and diesel). We have compared diesel-modified DNA adduct patterns in various in vitro and in vivo rodent model systems and compared them to DNA reactive oxidative and reductive metabolites of 1-nitropyrene. The formation of nitrated polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbon (nitrated PAH) DNA adducts, derived from the metabolism of diesel extract constituents, was enhanced relative to other PAH-derived DNA adducts via xanthine oxidase-catalyzed nitroreduction. These adducts were detectable only by the butanol extraction version of the postlabeling analysis. Five major DNA adducts were detected in human lymphocytes treated in vitro with diesel extract. A major adduct detected in human lymphocytes treated in vitro with diesel extract comigrated with a major adduct detected in lymphocyte DNA treated with benzo[a]pyrene (BaP) alone. Other adducts that co-migrated with the major BaP-derived adducts were detected in skin and lung DNA isolated from rodents topically treated with (50 mg) diesel extract and the major adduct detected in calf thymus DNA treated with rat liver S9 and diesel particle extract. Postlabeling of lung DNA isolated from rodents exposed via lung inhalation for 24 months to diesel combustion emissions resulted in the formation of a major nuclease-P1-sensitive DNA adduct that did not co-migrate with the major BaP-diol epoxide adduct.(ABSTRACT TRUNCATED AT 250 WORDS)</p><sec sec-type="scanned-figures"><title>Images</title><fig id="F1"><label>FIGURE 1. a</label><graphic xlink:href="envhper00412-0207-a" xlink:role="226"/></fig><fig id="F2"><label>FIGURE 1. b</label><graphic xlink:href="envhper00412-0207-b" xlink:role="226"/></fig><fig id="F3"><label>FIGURE 1. c</label><graphic xlink:href="envhper00412-0207-c" xlink:role="226"/></fig><fig id="F4"><label>FIGURE 2.</label><graphic xlink:href="envhper00412-0208-a" xlink:role="227"/></fig><fig id="F5"><label>FIGURE 3.</label><graphic xlink:href="envhper00412-0208-b" xlink:role="227"/></fig></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><supplementary-material content-type="scanned-pages"><graphic xlink:href="envhper00412-0206.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="225" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="envhper00412-0207.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="226" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="envhper00412-0208.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="227" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/><graphic xlink:href="envhper00412-0209.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="228" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/></supplementary-material></body></article>

