<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="abstract" xml:lang="en"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Extrem Physiol Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Extrem Physiol Med</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Extreme Physiology &#x00026; Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2046-7648</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4580773</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2046-7648-4-S1-A160</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/2046-7648-4-S1-A160</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Meeting Abstract</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Repeated determination of convective and radiative heat transfer coefficients using 32 zones thermal manikin</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A1"><name><surname>Fojtl&#x000ed;n</surname><given-names>Milo&#x00161;</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>fojtlin@eu.fme.vutbr.cz</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A2"><name><surname>Fi&#x00161;er</surname><given-names>Jan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A3"><name><surname>J&#x000ed;cha</surname><given-names>Miroslav</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Thermodynamics and Environmental Engineering, Energy Institute, Faculty of mechanical engineering, Brno University of Technology, Czech Republic</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>9</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>4</volume><issue>Suppl 1</issue><supplement><named-content content-type="supplement-title">15th International Conference on Environmental Ergonomics (ICEE XV)</named-content><named-content content-type="supplement-sponsor">Publication of this supplement was funded by the Energy Institute.</named-content></supplement><fpage>A160</fpage><lpage>A160</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2015 Fojtl&#x000ed;n et al.;</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Fojtl&#x000ed;n et al.;</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.extremephysiolmed.com/content/4/S1/A160"/><conference><conf-date>28 June-3 July 2015</conf-date><conf-name>15th International Conference on Environmental Ergonomics (ICEE XV)</conf-name><conf-loc>Portsmouth, UK</conf-loc></conference></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Average European citizens spend 80 % to 90 % of their workday time indoors, in buildings or vehicles [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Owing to this fact, building design in terms of thermal comfort, air quality, and low energy demands is important. In addition, many independent studies provide evidence of improper thermal environment and the negative influence of this on the human body, e.g. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. However, such situations can be tackled, in the future, using modern computational methods. To do so there is a need for anatomically detailed heat transfer coefficients that quantify heat flux from a human body. A lot of research has been done in order to investigate heat transfer coefficients in various body postures, wind speeds and wind directions, e.g. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. On the other hand, there has not been any emphasis given to measurement reproducibility. A thermal manikin was involved to determine convective and radiative heat transfer coefficients in a sitting and standing posture repeatedly.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><p>Presented study involves the state-of-the-art thermal manikin (Newton). The manikin imitates human metabolic heat production, measures combined dry heat flux from its surface and also its surface temperature. To separate convective and radiative heat flux portion a low emissivity coating was applied to the surface of the manikin. Next, the manikin was placed into a calibration box that was built inside a climatic chamber to achieve uniform environment (t<sub>amb </sub>= t<sub>rad </sub>= 24 &#x000b0;C &#x000b1; 0.2 &#x000b0;C, w = 0.05 m.s<sup>-1</sup>). Manikin's constant temperature control mode was set to 34 &#x000b0;C, as it is a reasonable approximation of a real human skin temperature in neutral thermal conditions. The measurement time schedule consisted of a period of the manikin preheating (1.5 to 3 h) and data logging (1 h). Each case was repeated three times.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p>Results of the research are presented via average values of convective and radiative heat transfer coefficients in a complete overview of 32 zones. Data of sitting and standing positions with 95% confidence error bars are available. The lowest values of convective heat transfer coefficients (h<sub>c</sub>) are found on the chest (3.3 W.m<sup>-2</sup>.K<sup>-1</sup>). The highest h<sub>c </sub>were indicated on the limbs (feet 6.6 W.m<sup>-2</sup>.K<sup>-1</sup>). Generally, h<sub>c </sub>values of the sitting manikin were slightly higher than those of the standing. Opposite logic applies in the case of radiative heat transfer coefficients (h<sub>r</sub>) where the (h<sub>r</sub>) maximum is on the back (5.5 W.m<sup>-2</sup>.K<sup>-1</sup>). Due to the manikin's hair, the lowest h<sub>r </sub>value was determined at the manikin's head (3 W.m<sup>-2</sup>.K<sup>-1</sup>).</p></sec><sec><title>Discussion and conclusion</title><p>The results are compared with results of two independent authors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. Normally, differences among the authors in the mean coefficient values vary up to 1 W.m<sup>-2</sup>.K<sup>-1 </sup>per segment. Extremes are found on the head, feet, seat, and back, where different conditions and geometry apply due to the different manikins involved. The trends of the results are mostly complying. In addition, thanks to the confidence bars we are also able to indicate systematic errors in measurements (lower limbs). To sum up, we have proven reproducibility of the method used, yet in a limited scale.</p></sec><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The research was supported by the project LO1202 NETME CENTRE PLUS with the financial support from the Ministry of Education, Youth and Sports of the Czech Republic under the "National Sustainability Programme I". The authors gratefully acknowledge the support from the project No. FSI-S-14-2355 of the BUT.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>OFFICE FOR OFFICIAL PUBLICATIONS OF THE EUROPEAN COMMUNITIES</collab><article-title>How Europeans spend their time</article-title><source>Luxemburg: European Communities</source><year>2004</year><fpage>132</fpage><comment>s.ISBN 92-894-7235-9</comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><name><surname>Ailu</surname><given-names>CHEN</given-names></name><name><surname>victor</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname></name><article-title>Human health and thermal comfort of Office workers in Singapore</article-title><year>2012</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>172</fpage><lpage>178</lpage><comment>December</comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>PARSON</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><source>Human Thermal Environments</source><year>2003</year><publisher-name>Taylor &#x00026; Francis</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><name><surname>De</surname><given-names>DEAR</given-names></name><etal/><article-title>Convective and radiative heat transfer coefficients for individual human body segments</article-title><source>Int J Biometeorol</source><year>40</year><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>156</lpage><comment>ISB &#x000b4;97</comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Quintela</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/><article-title>Analysis of sensible heat exchanges from a thermal manikin</article-title><source>Eur J Appl Physiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>663</fpage><lpage>668</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00421-004-1132-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15185082</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>AVM</given-names></name><etal/><source>Journal of Wind Energy Ind. Aerodynamics</source><year>2014</year><volume>132</volume><fpage>66</fpage><lpage>76</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Kurazumi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/><source>Radiative and convective heat transfer coefficients of the human body in natural convection</source><volume>43</volume><issue>2008</issue><publisher-name>Elsevier Ltd.: Building and Environment</publisher-name><fpage>2142</fpage><lpage>2153</lpage></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>