<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="review-article" xml:lang="EN"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">FEMS Microbiol Rev</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">fmr</journal-id><journal-title>Fems Microbiology Reviews</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0168-6445</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1574-6976</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Blackwell Publishing Ltd</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17696886</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2040187</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-6976.2007.00080.x</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Review Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><italic>Carnobacterium:</italic> positive and negative effects in the environment and in foods</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Leisner</surname><given-names>J&#x000f8;rgen J</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Laursen</surname><given-names>Birgit Groth</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pr&#x000e9;vost</surname><given-names>Herv&#x000e9;</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Drider</surname><given-names>Djamel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dalgaard</surname><given-names>Paw</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="au1"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Veterinary Pathobiology, Faculty of Life Sciences, University of Copenhagen</institution><addr-line>Copenhagen, Denmark</addr-line></aff><aff id="au2"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Seafood Research, Danish Institute for Fisheries Research, Technical University of Denmark</institution><addr-line>Lyngby, Denmark</addr-line></aff><aff id="au3"><label>3</label><institution>UMR INRA-1014 SECALIM, Ecole Nationale d'Ing&#x000e9;nieurs des Techniques des Industries Agricoles et Alimentaires (ENITIAA)</institution><addr-line>Nantes, France</addr-line></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Orejas</surname><given-names>Ram&#x000f3;n D&#x000ed;az</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold>Correspondence:</bold> J&#x000f8;rgen J. Leisner, Department of Veterinary Pathobiology, Faculty of Life Sciences, University of Copenhagen, Gr&#x000f8;nneg&#x000e5;rdsvej 15, DK-1870 Frederiksberg C., Denmark. Tel.: +45 35332768; fax: +45 35332757;e-mail: <email>jjl@life.ku.dk</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>9</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><month>8</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><volume>31</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>592</fpage><lpage>613</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>26</day><month>3</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>11</day><month>6</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>6</month><year>2007</year></date></history><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2007 The Authors Journal compilation &#x000a9; 2007 Federation of European Microbiological Societies Published by Blackwell Publishing Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2007</copyright-year><abstract><p>The genus <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> contains nine species, but only <italic>C. divergens</italic> and <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> are frequently isolated from natural environments and foods. They are tolerant to freezing/thawing and high pressure and able to grow at low temperatures, anaerobically and with increased CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations. They metabolize arginine and various carbohydrates, including chitin, and this may improve their survival in the environment. <italic>Carnobacterium divergens</italic> and <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> have been extensively studied as protective cultures in order to inhibit growth of <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic> in fish and meat products. Several carnobacterial bacteriocins are known, and parameters that affect their production have been described. Currently, however, no isolates are commercially applied as protective cultures. Carnobacteria can spoil chilled foods, but spoilage activity shows intraspecies and interspecies variation. The responsible spoilage metabolites are not well characterized, but branched alcohols and aldehydes play a partial role. Their production of tyramine in foods is critical for susceptible individuals, but carnobacteria are not otherwise human pathogens. <italic>Carnobacterium maltaromaticum</italic> can be a fish pathogen, although carnobacteria are also suggested as probiotic cultures for use in aquaculture. Representative genome sequences are not yet available, but would be valuable to answer questions associated with fundamental and applied aspects of this important genus.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd><italic>Carnobacterium</italic></kwd><kwd>natural environment</kwd><kwd>antimicrobial properties</kwd><kwd>food spoilage</kwd><kwd>food safety</kwd><kwd>probiotics</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Carnobacteria are ubiquitous lactic acid bacteria (LAB) isolated from cold and temperate environments. More importantly from a practical viewpoint, they also frequently predominate in a range of foods, including fish, meat, and some dairy products. In this regard, they have been extensively studied in the last two decades as protective cultures, to inhibit pathogenic and spoilage microorganisms, and as potential spoilage bacteria in chilled seafood and meat products. In addition, owing to their presence in the aqueous environment, their importance as fish pathogens or probiotic cultures in the aquaculture industry has been examined.</p><p>The genus <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> currently consists of nine species, but only two of these, <italic>Carnobacterium divergens</italic> and <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> (formerly <italic>C. piscicola</italic>) are frequently encountered in the environment and in foods (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>). This review concerns the importance of these two species in dairy, meat and fish products and in the aquatic environment. The taxonomy and methods for isolation and identification of carnobacteria are not described. It is, however, important to note that older studies frequently used carbohydrate fermentation patterns to distinguish between <italic>C. divergens</italic> and <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic>. These methods are now considered less reliable than molecular methods, and results relying on phenotypic criteria must be interpreted with caution (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b74">Hammes &#x00026; Hertel, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b104">Laursen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Compilation of <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> species and known sources<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf1-1">*</xref></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Isolated from</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Species</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Isolation frequency</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Food products</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Environment</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>C. alterfunditum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Very low</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not reported</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Live fish, polar lakes/sea, deep sea sediment</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>C. divergens</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dairy, meat, fish, shrimp</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intestine of live fish, <italic>Sphagnum</italic> pond (U)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf1-1">*</xref>, alpine permafrost (U)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>C. funditum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Very low</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not reported</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Polar lakes/sea, intestine of live fish, marine sponge</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>C. gallinarum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Meat</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Live fish</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>C. inhibens</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Very low</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not reported</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Atlantic salmon</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf1-2">&#x02020;</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dairy, meat, fish, shrimp</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Live/diseased fish, moth larval midgut, polar sea, deep sea (U), cold and alkaline tufa columns, Japanese lakes (U), <italic>Sphagnum</italic> pond (U)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>C. mobile</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Meat, shrimp</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Live fish</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>C. pleistocenium</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Very low</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not reported</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Permafrost tunnel</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>C. viridans</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Very low</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Meat</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not reported</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Carnobacterium</italic> spp.<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf1-3">&#x02021;</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">See<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf1-3">&#x02021;</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Andean wetlands (U), Canadian oil sands tailing pond (U), cow rumen (U), deep sea (U), polar areas, pufferfish organs (U), spent mushroom compost, pig effluent-impacted environment (U), watershed polluted with horse manure</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tf1-1"><label>*</label><p>References are quoted in the text except for unpublished (U) studies that include the following accession numbers (EF090688; AM269906; AB248932; AB248935; AB260993; AM711880; EF420230; AY244979; AM111051; DQ778093; DQ337521; DQ337531). In some cases (EF090688, AM269906, AB260993), the source of the sequence was listed as <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> sp. However, comparison of the 16S rRNA gene sequences with additional carnobacterial 16S rRNA gene sequences in the databases (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov</ext-link>) allowed us to allocate these sequences to specific carnobacterial species.</p></fn><fn id="tf1-2"><label>&#x02020;</label><p>Formerly <italic>C. pisciciola</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b136">Mora <italic>et al.</italic> (2003)</xref>. Two human clinical isolates of this species are known, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28">Chmela&#x00159;<italic>et al.</italic> (2002)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b219">Xu <italic>et al.</italic> (1997)</xref>; and AF113133. Two clinical isolates of <italic>C. divergens</italic> have also been described (AY650920).</p></fn><fn id="tf1-3"><label>&#x02021;</label><p>Examples of habitats described for cultured and noncultured samples. Sequences for samples obtained from foods are, with a few exceptions [e.g. milk (EF204312)], allocated to known species.</p></fn><fn><p>NA, not applicable.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Distribution in the natural environment and foods</title><sec><title>Natural environment</title><p>Among the nine reported species of <italic>Carnobacterium</italic>, only two species, <italic>C. divergens</italic> and <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic>, are frequently isolated from various sources (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>). Four species, <italic>C. alterfunditum</italic>, <italic>C. funditum</italic>, <italic>C. gallinarum</italic> and <italic>C. mobile</italic>, have been isolated a few times from at most three sources (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>). Three species, <italic>C. inhibens</italic>, <italic>C. pleistocenium</italic> and <italic>C. viridans</italic>, have only been isolated from one source (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b90">J&#x000f6;born <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b81">Holley <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b156">Pikuta <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>), but it should be noted that <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> spp. related to, for example, <italic>C. inhibens</italic> have been described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b191">Simpson <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>). <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> spp. appear to have both the temperate and polar aquatic environments as habitats including live fish (see also &#x02018;Carnobacteria as pathogenic organisms and/or probiotic cultures&#x02019;), marine sponges (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b115">Li &#x00026; Liu, 2006</xref>), Antarctic lakes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b58">Franzmann <italic>et al.</italic>, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">Bratina <italic>et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>), Arctic and Antarctic sea water as well as the deep sea (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b59">Galkin <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b70">Groudieva <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b143">Newberry <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b209">Toffin <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b103">Lauro <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>), aquous alkaline tufa columns from Greenland (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b184">Schmidt <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>), and freshwater habitats from the temperate clima zone, including a <italic>Sphagnum</italic> pond (Leisner <italic>et al.</italic>, unpublished results) and rivers in the northwest region of Spain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b64">Gonz&#x000e1;lez <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>). Although <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> and/or <italic>C. divergens</italic> have been isolated from tropical fish products, including smoked surubim, a Brazilian tropical freshwater fish (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">Alves <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>), and from vacuum-packed tuna caught in the Indian Ocean and processed in Sri Lanka (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b54">Emborg <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>), it cannot, at least in the latter case, be excluded that this is due to contamination associated with repackaging in Denmark.</p><p>The presence of carnobacteria has also been demonstrated in the terrestrial environment, including a field treated with whey (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b33">Coombs &#x00026; Brenchley, 1999</xref>), Canadian winter soil (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b214">Walker <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>), permafrost ice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b156">Pikuta <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b94">Katayama <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>), a compost pile (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b148">Ntougias <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>), a collapsed horse manure pile (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b191">Simpson <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>), the larval midgut of a moth species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b187">Shannon <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>), and other sources (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>). It appears that the temperate/polar aquatic and terrestrial environments are both natural habitats.</p><p><italic>Carnobacterium divergens</italic> and <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> possess traits that may play a role in their survival in these surroundings. One study has reported that a <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> sp. soil isolate related to <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> survived 48 serial freeze&#x02013;thaw cycles better than <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> and an <italic>Enterococcus</italic> sp. soil isolate, but worse than a few other soil isolates, including an <italic>Acinetobacter</italic> sp. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b214">Walker <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). Indeed, these organisms may survive freezing for considerable periods of time, as witnessed by the isolation of a <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> sp. preserved in a permafrost ice wedge for 25 000 years (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b94">Katayama <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). Additional data on the abilities of carnobacteria to grow at low temperatures and to survive frozen storage is available for food products. Also, a cold-active &#x003b2;-galactosidase from <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> and a cold-adapted alanine dehydrogenase from a <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> sp. related to <italic>C. alterfunditum</italic> have been reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32">Coombs &#x00026; Brenchley, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b59">Galkin <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>). Some carnobacterial isolates originate from natural high-pressure habitats (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b103">Lauro <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>), and additional data on resistance to pressure have been reported for high-pressure-processed foods. It has not been described how other physical/chemical parameters such as salt content, atmosphere and pH affect survival and growth of these organisms in the natural environment.</p><p>With respect to energy-yielding substrates, one species, <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic>, expresses chitinase activity (Leisner &#x00026; Ingmer, unpublished data). This may facilitate adherence to and survival on zooplankton as suggested for enterococci (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b189">Signoretto <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>), and also explain the isolation of this species from the midgut of the larval stage of a species of moth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b187">Shannon <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>). Interestingly, the arginine deiminase pathway is expressed by the most frequently encountered species, <italic>C. divergens</italic>, <italic>C. gallinarum</italic>, <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> and <italic>C. mobile</italic> (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29">Collins <italic>et al.</italic>, 1987</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b110">Leisner <italic>et al.</italic>, 1994b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b183">Schillinger &#x00026; Holzapfel, 1995</xref>) but not by <italic>C. inhibens</italic> or <italic>C. viridans</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b90">J&#x000f6;born <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">Collins <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b81">Holley <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>). Arginine is not a substrate that results in growth of <italic>C. alterfunditum</italic> and <italic>C. funditum</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b58">Franzmann <italic>et al.</italic>, 1991</xref>), and information is not available for <italic>C. pleistocenium</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b154">Pikuta <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>). This amino acid may represent an additional energy source for growth and survival when carbohydrates are scarce, and it may offer protection against acid stress, as described for <italic>Enterococcus faecalis</italic> and related species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b120">Marquis <italic>et al.</italic>, 1987</xref>). Finally, carnobacteria are able to catabolize a range of carbohydrates, although there are considerable interspecies and intraspecies heterogeneities. Examples of sources of such carbohydrates include animals (e.g. chitin and, to some extent, lactose, although the targets of the lactose hydrolytic activity shown by carnobacteria may instead be byproducts of plant sugar polymers and saccharides adsorbed to humic acid substances in the soil) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32">Coombs &#x00026; Brenchley, 2001</xref>), plants (e.g. salicin and sucrose), fungi (e.g. chitin and trehalose), prokaryotes (<italic>N</italic>-acetylglucosamine), and living organisms in general (ribose) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b190">Shaw &#x00026; Harding, 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b98">Lai &#x00026; Manchester, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b178">Rudi <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>). The importance of these abilities for growth and survival in the environment deserves further study. The genome sizes of <italic>C. alterfunditum</italic>, <italic>C. divergens</italic> and <italic>C. pleistocenium</italic> strains and a <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> sp. AT7 deep sea isolate have been estimated to be 2.9, 3.2, 3.2 and 2.4 Mb, respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b41">Daniel, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b156">Pikuta <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>), and for the AT7 isolate, the data are reported in a database described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b116">Liolios (2006)</xref>. These sizes are relatively large in comparison to many other LAB, suggesting that carnobacterial genomes may encode a range of genes that makes them well adapted to deal with environmental challenges.</p><p>Even if carnobacteria are well adapted to temperate or polar aqueous environments, this does not always provide improved ability to survive as compared to other bacteria. Thus, the actual abilities of strains of <italic>C. divergens</italic> and <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> isolated from a <italic>Sphagnum</italic> pond to survive in water from this source were not improved as compared to related gram-positive bacteria originating from other sources (Leisner <italic>et al.</italic>, unpublished data). At present, therefore, the precise mechanisms by which <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> spp. persist in the natural environment and their underlying genetics are not known. Finally, it should be noted that the environments from which carnobacteria can be isolated are not always as extreme as they appear at first sight. Thus, <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> spp. isolated from Lake Vanda, Antarctica were found at a depth of 61 m, where the temperature was <italic>c</italic>. 15&#x02013;20&#x000b0;C (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">Bratina <italic>et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Dairy, fish and meat products</title><p>High concentrations of bacteria (&#x0003e;10<sup>6</sup>&#x02013;10<sup>7</sup> CFU g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) in food are typically required before their activity is sufficient to influence the sensory properties of a product. For this to happen, occurrence and growth kinetics are the key parameters, and databases, including ComBase, are available to determine the effect of food storage conditions and product characteristics on growth of specific bacteria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b126">McMeekin <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). However, information on carnobacteria has not yet been included in such databases.</p><p><italic>Carnobacterium maltaromaticum</italic> and another <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> sp. have been isolated from milk (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b133">Miller <italic>et al.</italic>, 1974</xref>; EF204312), and they, in addition to <italic>C. divergens</italic>, have been detected in soft cheeses, including mold-ripened brie (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b135">Milli&#x000e8;re <italic>et al.</italic>, 1994</xref>), mozzarella (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b137">Morea <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>), Camembert (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23">Cailliez-Grimal <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>) and other types (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b134">Milli&#x000e8;re &#x00026; Lefebvre, 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">Cailliez-Grimal <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). The high concentration of <italic>C. divergens</italic> in the curd of mozzarella, exposed to 10&#x02013;37&#x000b0;C during processing, is in agreement with the maximum growth temperature (40&#x000b0;C) of this species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29">Collins <italic>et al.</italic>, 1987</xref>).</p><p>The occurrence of <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> in dairy products (and other foods) is most likely underreported. This is due to the common use of acetate containing media, particularly MRS agar (Oxoid CM361) or Rogosa agar (Oxoid CM0627), for enumeration of LAB (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b44">de Man <italic>et al.</italic>, 1960</xref>). Growth of <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> is inhibited by acetate, and both MRS and Rogosa agar media significantly underestimate concentrations in food (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b106">Leblanc <italic>et al.</italic>, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b177">Sakala <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b74">Hammes &#x00026; Hertel, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b203">Susiluoto <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28">Chenoll <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>).</p><p><italic>Carnobacterium divergens</italic> and <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> are present in seafood and are able to grow to high concentrations in different fresh and lightly preserved products. Studies of naturally contaminated products suggest which storage conditions and product characteristics select for carnobacteria as compared to the other bacteria present in seafood. For chilled fresh seafood, we have found no reports where <italic>C. divergens</italic> and <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> dominated the microbial communities in aerobically stored products, but this has been reported for modified atmosphere-packed (MAP) coalfish, cod, pollack, rainbow trout, salmon, shrimp, swordfish and tuna (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b124">Mauguin &#x00026; Novel, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b106">Leblanc <italic>et al.</italic>, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b53">Emborg <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b54">2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b57">Franzetti <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b178">Rudi <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>). After frozen storage (&#x02212;20 to &#x02212;30&#x000b0;C for 5&#x02013;8 weeks), <italic>C. divergens</italic> and <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> seem to be particularly prominent in chilled MAP fish, as has been reported for cod, garfish, salmon, and tuna (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b71">Guldager <italic>et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b53">Emborg <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b54">2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b40">Dalgaard <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). In addition to freezing, these carnobacteria are relatively resistant to high-pressure processing and are found in high concentrations in vacuum-packed and chilled squid mantle and cold-smoked salmon previously treated with 200&#x02013;400 MPa for 15&#x02013;20 min (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b150">Paarup <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b99">Lakshmanan &#x00026; Dalgaard, 2004</xref>). In vacuum-packed cold-smoked or sugar-salted (&#x02018;gravad&#x02019;) seafood with 3&#x02013;7% NaCl in the water phase and a pH of 5.8&#x02013;6.5, high concentrations of <italic>C. divergens</italic> and <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> are particularly common, as reported for halibut, rainbow trout, salmon, surubim, and tuna (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b86">Jeppesen &#x00026; Huss, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b109">Leisner <italic>et al.</italic>, 1994a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b155">Pilet <italic>et al.</italic>, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b113">Leroi <italic>et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b117">Lyhs <italic>et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b118">2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b153">Paludan-M&#x000fc;ller <italic>et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b210">Truelstrup Hansen &#x00026; Huss, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b92">J&#x000f8;rgensen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b66">Gonz&#x000e1;lez-Rodr&#x000ed;guez <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">Alves <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b52">Emborg &#x00026; Dalgaard, 2006</xref>). High concentrations of <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> are also reported in salted lumpfish roe, and it has been isolated from frozen, smoked mussels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">Basby <italic>et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b205">Tahiri <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>). Finally, for cooked seafood, high concentrations of <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> have been detected in MAP shrimp after storage at 2&#x02013;8&#x000b0;C (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b129">Mejlholm <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>). Both <italic>C. divergens</italic> and <italic>C. mobile</italic> were isolated from cooked and brined MAP shrimps (with NaCl, benzoic acid, citric acid and sorbic acid) after storage at 2&#x02013;8&#x000b0;C (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b39">Dalgaard <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b104">Laursen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>). Clearly, carnobacteria are common in chilled fresh and lightly preserved seafood, but at higher storage temperatures (15&#x02013;25&#x000b0;C), other species, including <italic>Enterococcus</italic> spp., more frequently dominate the spoilage microbial community of seafood (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b39">Dalgaard <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>).</p><p><italic>Carnobacterium divergens</italic> and <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> are able to grow in meat products at temperatures as low as 2 to &#x02212;1.5&#x000b0;C (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b127">McMullen &#x00026; Stiles, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b177">Sakala <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b91">Jones, 2004</xref>), and they are frequently predominant members (up to 50%<italic>C. divergens</italic> and up to 26%<italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> of the gram-positive or LAB isolates obtained) of the microbial community of raw meat (beef, pork, lamb, and poultry). The two species are found irrespective of whether products have been stored aerobically, vacuum packaged, or subjected to modified atmospheres, including gas compositions of CO<sub>2</sub>/N<sub>2</sub> (%) ranging from 10 : 90 to 80 : 20 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b190">Shaw &#x00026; Harding, 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b68">Grant &#x00026; Patterson, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b127">McMullen &#x00026; Stiles, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">Barakat <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b177">Sakala <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b203">Susiluoto <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b91">Jones, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">Bj&#x000f6;rkroth <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b104">Laursen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b215">Vihavainen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). One study demonstrated the presence of <italic>C. divergens</italic> in beef stored in air but not in MAP beef with increased concentrations of O<sub>2</sub> (20&#x02013;40%) in addition to CO<sub>2</sub> (40%) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b55">Ercolini <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). The growth of <italic>C. funditum</italic> is impaired by oxygen (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b58">Franzmann <italic>et al.</italic>, 1991</xref>), and it will be of interest to study further whether addition of O<sub>2</sub> to the gas composition of modified atmospheres consistently inhibits growth of carnobacteria, as has been observed for some other bacteria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b54">Emborg <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>).</p><p>Further studies are needed in order to determine whether differences in the presence of carnobacteria in meat are due to variations in storage conditions or variations in contamination levels at the processing plants. The source of carnobacteria in meat products is most probably the processing plant, as these organisms have not been isolated from the gastrointestinal system or skin of chicken, cattle, pigs or sheep, except for one unpublished study (cow rumen, AY244979). Thus, the source of contamination of broiler carcasses by <italic>C. divergens</italic> and <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> was shown to be the air in the processing plant and not incoming broiler chickens (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b213">Vihavainen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). In fact, two studies confirmed that <italic>C. divergens</italic> and <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> present in the raw material were eliminated or reduced in number by cooking of a processed meat product, ham (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b179">Samelis <italic>et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b180">2000</xref>).</p><p><italic>Carnobacterium divergens</italic> and <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> have, however, been detected in a variety of processed meat products, including the cured pork product bacon (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b188">Shaw &#x00026; Harding, 1984</xref>), ham (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">Borch &#x00026; Molin, 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b84">Jack <italic>et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>), a Danish processed pork product (&#x02018;rullep&#x000f8;lse&#x02019;) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b104">Laursen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref> and unpublished results), various Spanish processed meat products (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27">Chenoll <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>), cooked poultry meat (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">Barakat <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>), pressure-treated (408&#x02013;888 MPa) chicken (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b149">O'Brien &#x00026; Marshall, 1996</xref>), and irradiated pork and chicken (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b68">Grant &#x00026; Patterson, 1991</xref>). On a few occasions, <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> has even been isolated from fermented sausages (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b182">Schillinger &#x00026; L&#x000fc;cke, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b102">Larrouture-Thiveyrat <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>); as noted by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b74">Hammes &#x00026; Hertel (2003)</xref>, this contrasts with the usual nonaciduric habitats of carnobacteria. Other <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> spp. isolated from processed meat products include <italic>C. gallinarium</italic> (irradiated chicken) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b207">Thornley, 1957</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29">Collins <italic>et al.</italic>, 1987</xref>), <italic>C. mobile</italic> (cooked turkey) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27">Chenoll <italic>et al</italic>,. 2007</xref>) and <italic>C. viridans</italic> (vacuum-packed Bologna sausage) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b81">Holley <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>). Although these organisms are frequently isolated from processed meat products, it has been suggested that they are rarely present in high numbers, and that terminal spoilage of cooked, cured meats is primarily caused by aciduric LAB (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b180">Samelis, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28">Chenoll <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>).</p><p>Finally, a <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> sp. has also been isolated from egg contents, and it was shown that this isolate had a similar ability to penetrate the eggshell and contaminate the whole egg as various other gram-positive and gram-negative bacteria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b45">De Reu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>).</p><p>Transmission routes for carnobacteria from the natural environment into food-manufacturing plants and further on to dairy, fish and meat products are not known to any extent. Knowledge on this topic is essential to evaluate if species and intraspecific clusters that differ in spoilage ability (as discussed later) also have different colonization abilities. Such knowledge would also illuminate the feasibility of using the production of metabolites, especially tyramine, by <italic>C. divergens</italic> and <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> as an index of microbial spoilage of specific fish and meat products (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b50">Edwards <italic>et al.</italic>, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b36">Dainty &#x00026; Mackey, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b109">Leisner <italic>et al.</italic>, 1994a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b37">Dainty, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b92">J&#x000f8;rgensen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b53">Emborg <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b105">Laursen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Functional properties of carnobacteria</title><sec><title>Bacteriocins and antimicrobial properties</title><p>Carnobacteria with the ability to produce antimicrobial peptides, bacteriocins, are commonly encountered in foods (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b114">Lewus <italic>et al.</italic>, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b35">Coventry <italic>et al.</italic>, 1997</xref>). The characterized carnobacterial bacteriocins belong to class I and class II [e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b46">Drider <italic>et al.</italic> (2006)</xref> for bacteriocin nomenclature]. So far, only one class I bacteriocin (lantibiotic), UI149, has been reported to be produced by <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b200">Stoffels <italic>et al.</italic>, 1992a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b201">b</xref>). In contrast, ten amino acid-sequenced bacteriocins belong to class II, and most of these more specifically to class IIa, which comprises small pediocin-like peptides (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>). The inhibition spectrum of carnobacterial class IIa bacteriocins includes <italic>Listeria</italic>, and antimicrobial activity is exerted by pore formation, dissipation of membrane potential, and leakage of internal low molecular weight substances (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b202">Suzuki <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b46">Drider <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="tbl2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Bacteriocins produced by carnobacteria</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Species</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bacteriocin (class)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-1">*</xref></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unprocessed precursor/ mature chain<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-2">&#x02020;</xref></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Location of gene</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Accession number</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">References</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cm</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-3">&#x02021;</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carnobacteriocin A (IIc)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>cbnA</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71/53</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plasmid</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P38578</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b217">Worobo <italic>et al.</italic> (1994)</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Piscicolin 61<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-4">&#x000a7;</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b79">Holck <italic>et al.</italic> (1994)</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carnobacteriocin BM1 (IIa)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>cbnBM1</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61/43</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chromosome</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P38579</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b157">Quadri <italic>et al.</italic> (1994)</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carnobacteriocin B1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-4">&#x000a7;</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Piscicocin V1b<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-4">&#x000a7;</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">Bhugaloo-Vial <italic>et al.</italic> (1996)</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carnocin CP51<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-4">&#x000a7;</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b75">Herbin <italic>et al.</italic> (1997)</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carnobacteriocin B2 (IIa)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>cbnB2</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66/48</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plasmid</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P38580</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b157">Quadri <italic>et al.</italic> (1994)</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b216">Wang <italic>et al.</italic> (1999)</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carnocin CP52<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-4">&#x000a7;</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b75">Herbin <italic>et al.</italic> (1997)</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A9b<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-4">&#x000a7;</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b145">Nilsson <italic>et al.</italic> (2002)</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Piscicolin 126 (IIa)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>pisA</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62/44</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chromosome</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P80569</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b84">Jack <italic>et al.</italic> (1996)</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Piscicocin V1a<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-4">&#x000a7;</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">Bhugaloo-Vial <italic>et al.</italic> (1996)</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b72">Gursky <italic>et al.</italic> (2006)</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Piscicocin CS526 (IIa)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">X/&#x02265;43</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b221">Yamazaki <italic>et al.</italic> (2005)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cd</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Divercin V41 (IIa)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>dvn41</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66/43</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chromosome</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAA11804</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b130">M&#x000e9;tivier <italic>et al.</italic> (1998)</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Divergicin M35 (IIa)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">X/43</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P84962</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b203">Tahiri <italic>et al.</italic> (2004)</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Divergicin A (IIc)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>dvnA</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75/46</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plasmid</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAZ29031</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b218">Worobo <italic>et al.</italic> (1995)</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b211">van Belkum &#x00026; Stiles (2006)</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Divergicin 750 (IIc)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>dvn750</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63/34</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plasmid</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2209292A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b80">Holck <italic>et al.</italic> (1996)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Carnobacterium</italic> sp.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carnocin H (II)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Partial sequence<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-5">&#x000b6;</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">Blom <italic>et al.</italic> (2001)</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carnocin UI149 (I)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Partial sequence<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-6">&#x02225;</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P36960</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b199">Stoffels <italic>et al.</italic> (1992b)</xref></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tf2-1"><label>*</label><p>Classification of bacteriocins based on review by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b46">Drider <italic>et al.</italic> (2006)</xref>.</p></fn><fn id="tf2-2"><label>&#x02020;</label><p>Numbers of amino acids.</p></fn><fn id="tf2-3"><label>&#x02021;</label><p><italic>Carnobacterium divergens (Cd)</italic>, <italic>Carnobacterium maltaromaticum (Cm)</italic>.</p></fn><fn id="tf2-4"><label>&#x000a7;</label><p>Synonyms.</p></fn><fn id="tf2-5"><label>&#x000b6;</label><p>Approximately 75 amino acids.</p></fn><fn id="tf2-6"><label>&#x02225;</label><p>35&#x02013;37 amino acids.</p></fn><fn><p>ND, not determined.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Class IIa bacteriocins are ribosomally synthesized as inactive prepeptides that are modified by posttranslational cleavage of the N-terminal peptide leader at a double-glycine site in order to release mature and active cationic peptides. Carnobacterial class IIa bacteriocins (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>) have similar amino acid sequences, with a YGNGV(X)C(X)<sub>4</sub>C motif (X denotes any amino acid) near the N-terminus of the mature peptide. Two cysteine residues form a disulfide bond in the N-terminal region, and there is an amphipathic &#x003b1;-helix near the C-terminus. The N-terminal region is relatively hydrophilic and conserved, whereas the C-terminus is hydrophobic and diverse. To establish the structure&#x02013;activity relationships of carnobacterial bacteriocins, the structures of carnobacteriocin B2 and divercin V41 were modified (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b161">Quadri <italic>et al.</italic>, 1997a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">Bhugaloo-Vial <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>). Thus, amino acid substitutions closer to the N-terminus in carnobacteriocin B2 drastically reduced or eliminated antimicrobial activity, whereas this was not so for substitutions close to the C-terminal part (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b159">Quadri <italic>et al.</italic>, 1997a</xref>). Divercin V41 contains a second disulfide bond located in the C-terminal region (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b130">M&#x000e9;tivier <italic>et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>). When the C-terminal region of divercin V41 was separated from the N-terminus by endoproteinase Asp-N, only the C-terminal fragment was active. After trypsin cleavage next to lysine at position 42 or disulfide reduction, the C-terminus lost its inhibitory activity. These results suggested that both hydrophobicity and folding imposed by this second disulfide bond were essential for antilisterial activity of the C-terminal hydrophobic peptide (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">Bhugaloo-Vial <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>). Chemical oxidation of tryptophan residues by <italic>N</italic>-bromosuccinimide showed that these residues were crucial for inhibitory activity, as modification of any one of them rendered divercin V41 inactive (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">Bhugaloo-Vial <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>). The three-dimensional structure of carnobacteriocin B2, its precursor and the corresponding immunity protein have been solved by nuclear magnetic resonance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b218">Wang <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b195">Sprules <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b198">b</xref>). These are, at present, the only reported carnobacterial protein structures.</p><p>Carnobacterial class II bacteriocins that contain a double-glycine-type leader peptide are transported by a dedicated ATP-binding cassette (ABC) transport system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b46">Drider <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). In contrast, divergicin A does not require a secretion protein, as the transport depend on the general cellular secretion (sec) pathway (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b218">Worobo <italic>et al.</italic>, 1995</xref>).</p><p>The genes involved in carnobacterial bacteriocin production are generally clustered in operons. In the simplest case, corresponding to the sec-dependent divergicin A, the bacteriocin operon is composed of only the structural gene followed downstream by the gene encoding an immunity protein that protects the cell from is own bacteriocin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b218">Worobo <italic>et al</italic>, 1995</xref>). Production of class IIa bacteriocins requires four genes as a minimum, including genes encoding bacteriocin, immunity protein, ABC of transport protein and its membrane-bound accessory protein. Genes for bacteriocin production may be encoded on the chromosome or on plasmids (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>). <italic>Carnobacterium maltaromaticum</italic> LV17 produces at least three class II bacteriocins. Carnobacteriocins A and B2 are encoded on different but compatible plasmids, pCP49 (72 kb) and pCP40 (61 kb), respectively. The carnobacteriocin BM1 structural gene and its immunity gene are localized on the chromosome. Activation and export of carnobacteriocin BM1 depend on genes located on plasmid pCP40 encoding carnobacteriocin B2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b162">Quadri <italic>et al.</italic>, 1997b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b176">Rohde &#x00026; Quadri, 2006</xref>). For carnobacteriocins BM1 and B2, a peptide-pheromone dependent quorum-sensing mode caused by the bacteriocin itself or an autoinducer peptide is involved in the regulation of bacteriocin production by two- and three-component signal transduction systems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b181">Saucier <italic>et al.</italic>, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b97">Kleerebezem <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b147">Nilsson <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b176">Rohde &#x00026; Quadri, 2006</xref>). The components of this regulatory system consist of an induction factor, a histidine protein kinase, and a response regulator. Four carnobacterial bacteriocin operons including genes for immunity proteins and regulatory proteins involved in bacteriocin expression and secretion have been sequenced (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">Fig. 1</xref>).</p><fig id="fig01" position="float"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Gene loci involved in carnobacteriocins B2, BM1, A, piscicolin 126 and divercin V41 production and immunity. First line, left: carnobacteriocin B2 locus (plasmid pCP40, accession number L47121). First line, right: carnobacteriocin BM1 chromosomal locus (L29058). Second line: carnobacteriocin A locus (plasmid pCP49, AF207838). Third line: piscicolin 126 chromosomal locus (AF275938). Fourth line: divercin V41 chromosomal locus (AJ224003). Genes <italic>cbnB2</italic>, <italic>cbnBM1</italic>, <italic>cbnA</italic>, <italic>pisA</italic> and <italic>dvn41</italic> encode the precursor bacteriocins (colored in black). Genes <italic>cbiB2</italic>, <italic>cbiBM1</italic>, <italic>cbiA</italic>, <italic>pisI</italic>, <italic>dvnT2</italic> and <italic>dvnI</italic> encode immunity proteins (colored in white). Genes <italic>cbnT</italic>, <italic>cbaT</italic>, <italic>pisT</italic> and <italic>dvnT1</italic> encode ABC transporter (italic hatching). Genes <italic>cbnD</italic>, <italic>cbaC</italic> and <italic>pisE</italic> encode transporter accessory protein (vertical hatching). The loci of carnobacteriocins B2, A and piscicolin 126 contain the <italic>cbnS</italic>&#x02013;<italic>cbnK</italic>&#x02013;<italic>cbnR</italic>, <italic>cbaX</italic>&#x02013;<italic>cbaK</italic>&#x02013;<italic>cbaR</italic> and <italic>pisN</italic>&#x02013;<italic>pisK</italic>&#x02013;<italic>pisR</italic> three-component regulatory system gene clusters, respectively (colored in gray). Only histidine protein kinase and response regulator protein encoded by <italic>dvnK</italic>&#x02013;<italic>dvnR</italic> are found in the divercin locus (colored in gray).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmr0031-0592-f1"/></fig><p>External parameters also affect bacteriocin production. Thus, increasing concentrations of NaCl (2&#x02013;7%) reduced production of A9b/B2 bacteriocin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b76">Himelbloom <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b147">Nilsson <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>), increasing the temperature from below 19 to 25&#x000b0;C inhibited production of piscicolin 126 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b72">Gursky <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>), and reducing the pH from 6.5 to 5.5 inhibited production of carnobacteriocins BM1 and B2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">Ahn &#x00026; Stiles, 1990</xref>). Acetate (A9b bacteriocin) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b145">Nilsson <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>) or the presence of a bacteriocin-sensitive strain belonging to the same genus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b192">Sip <italic>et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>) induced bacteriocin production. It is clear that, in order to apply carnobacterial bacteriocins for the biopreservation of foods, detailed knowledge of the factors that influence production of the bacteriocin is necessary. Finally, it should be noted that the bacteriocinogenic activity may be lost, as shown for a <italic>C. divergens</italic> divercin V41-producing strain that retained only partial activity after being subjected to spray-drying (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b190">Silva <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>).</p><p>Interest in applying carnobacterial bacteriocins in foods and feeds has been directed towards inhibiting <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl3">Table 3</xref>) and spoilage microorganisms, to extend the shelf-life of lightly preserved seafood (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b51">Einarsson &#x00026; Lauzon, 1995</xref>). These attempts have generally, but not always [e.g. regarding prevention of spoilage, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b51">Einarsson &#x00026; Lauzon (1995)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b175">Roller <italic>et al.</italic> (2002)</xref>], met with success, although diversity in sensitivity of the target organism has been observed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">Brillet <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>). However, the occurrence of resistant <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> target organisms has led to the suggestion that bacteriocin-negative LAB may be more suitable for practical use as bioprotective agents against <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> in ready-to-eat foods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b148">Nilsson <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b212">Vermeiren <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). Indeed, <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> is inhibited by carnobacterial cultures that do not produce bacteriocins, and this is partly due to glucose depletion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">Buchanan &#x00026; Bagi, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b146">Nilsson <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b147">2005</xref>). One study also reported a successful application of cultures with no demonstrated bacteriocinogenic activity for extension of the shelf-life of vacuum-packed cold-smoked salmon (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b112">Leroi <italic>et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>). This effect was not, however, observed for a <italic>C. divergens</italic> strain that was unable to produce the class IIa divercin V41 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b162">Richard <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="tbl3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Applications of antagonistic strains of <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> spp. against <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf3-1">*</xref> in dairy, meat or fish food and feed products</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Product (Species)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mechanism</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Dairy</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02002;UHT milk (<italic>Cm</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bacteriocin, other?</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">Buchanan &#x00026; Klawitter (1992)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02002;Whole milk (<italic>Cm</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Piscicolin 126</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b215">Wan <italic>et al.</italic> (1997)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02002;Camembert cheese (<italic>Cm</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Piscicolin 126</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b215">Wan <italic>et al.</italic> (1997)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Fish and shellfish</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02002;Cold-smoked salmon (<italic>Cd</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Divercin V41</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b47">Duffes <italic>et al.</italic> (1999a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b48">b</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31">Connil <italic>et al.</italic> (2002)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02002;Cold-smoked salmon (<italic>Cm</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Piscocin V1, bacteriocin</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b47">Duffes <italic>et al.</italic> (1999a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b48">b</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02002;Cold-smoked salmon (<italic>Cm</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carnobacteriocin B2, other</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b148">Nilsson <italic>et al.</italic> (1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b146">2004</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02002;Cold-smoked salmon (<italic>Cm</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Piscicocin CS526, other?</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b220">Yamazaki <italic>et al.</italic> (2003)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02002;Pasteurized crabmeat (<italic>Cm</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bacteriocin, other?</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">Buchanan &#x00026; Klawitter (1992)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Meat</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02002;Beef steaks (<italic>Cm</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bacteriocinogenic substance</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b185">Sch&#x000f6;bitz <italic>et al.</italic> (1999)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02002;Canned dog food (<italic>Cm</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bacteriocin, other?</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">Buchanan &#x00026; Klawitter (1992)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02002;Cooked chicken (<italic>Cm</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bacteriocin, other</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">Campos <italic>et al.</italic> (1997)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02002;Frankfurters (<italic>Cm</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bacteriocin, other?</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">Buchanan &#x00026; Klawitter (1992)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02002;Ham paste (<italic>Cm</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Piscolin 126</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b84">Jack <italic>et al.</italic> (1996)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02002;Ground meat (<italic>Cm</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Piscolin CS526 (freeze dried)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">Azuma <italic>et al.</italic> (2007)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02002;Sterile raw ground beef (<italic>Cm</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bacteriocin, other?</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">Buchanan &#x00026; Klawitter (1992)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Vegetables</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02002;Canned creamed corn (<italic>Cm</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bacteriocin, other?</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">Buchanan &#x00026; Klawitter (1992)</xref></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tf3-1"><label>*</label><p>Studies using <italic>Listeria innocua</italic> as target organism e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b175">Roller <italic>et al.</italic> (2002)</xref> have not been included in the table.</p></fn><fn><p><italic>Cd</italic>, <italic>Carnobacterium divergens</italic>; <italic>Cm, Carnobacterium maltaromaticum</italic>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Resistance of <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> to the class IIa divergicin M35 was probably due to modification of the cell wall fatty acid composition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b139">Naghmouchi <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic> strains resistant to the class IIa divercin V41 also showed substantial differences in protein expressions as compared with the wild type strain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b49">Duffes <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>). A &#x003c3;<sup>54</sup>-dependent PTS permease of the mannose family (EII<sub>t</sub><sup>Man</sup>), which belongs to the phosphotransferase system (PTS), is responsible for sensitivity of <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> to class IIa bacteriocins. These results suggested that EII<sub>t</sub><sup>Man</sup> encoded by the <italic>mptACD</italic> operon might be a target molecule for class IIa bacteriocins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b38">Dalet <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b69">Gravesen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>). Recently, two genes coding for a glycerophosphoryl diester phosphodiesterase (<italic>GlpQ</italic>) and a protein with a putative phosphoesterase function (<italic>Pde</italic>) were identified as also being involved in the class IIa sensitivity of <italic>En. faecalis</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25">Calvez <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). Finally, it is important to note that the susceptibility of the target strain is affected by various environmental conditions such as NaCl and pH (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b107">Lebois <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>).</p><p>Another cause of concern when using carnobacteria for biopreservation is that <italic>C. divergens</italic> and <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> both produce tyramine, as discussed further below. Therefore, it has been suggested that a <italic>C. divergens</italic> strain in which the tyrosine decarboxylase gene is inactivated by mutagenesis could be used as a protective culture to prevent growth of <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> in cold-smoked salmon (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19">Brillet <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). Currently, no carnobacterial culture, bacteriocin producing or not, is commercially applied for protection against the growth of <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> or other bacterial pathogens or spoilage organisms in food.</p></sec><sec><title>Effect of catabolic activities on sensory characteristics and safety of foods</title><p>As shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl4">Table 4</xref>, the catabolic activities of carnobacteria may result in sensory spoilage of inoculated fish and meat products. Whether this is so for cheese products is not clear. In naturally contaminated products, it seems other members of the bacterial community are typically more important with regard to sensory effects, including spoilage. It is of interest that spoilage was enhanced if moderate-spoilage strains of <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> were inoculated with nonspoilage <italic>Vibrio</italic> sp. strains or the moderate-spoilage organism <italic>Brochothrix thermosphacta</italic> into cold-smoked salmon that was subsequently vacuum-packaged (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b90">Joffraud <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). However, this was not so for combinations of <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> and <italic>Photobacterium phosphoreum</italic> in this product. In addition, a spoilage synergy effect was observed for combinations of <italic>B. thermosphacta</italic> and <italic>C. divergens</italic>, <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> or <italic>C. mobile</italic> in MAP shrimp (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b131">Mejlholm <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b105">Laursen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="tbl4" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Sensory effect of <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> spp. inoculated into dairy, fish or meat products</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Food (storage conditions)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Species</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spoilage (sensory effect)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Important metabolites produced</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Dairy</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Skimmed milk</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cm</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spoiled? (Malty aroma/flavor)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Branched alcohols and aldehydes<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf4-1">*</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b133">Miller <italic>et al.</italic> (1974)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Fish and shellfish</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">&#x02002;Cold-smoked salmon</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Vacuum, 4&#x02013;8&#x000b0;C</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cd</italic>, <italic>Cm</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not or weakly spoiled (cheese/feet in some cases)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not examined</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">Brillet <italic>et al.</italic> (2005)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Vacuum, 4&#x02013;8&#x000b0;C</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cd</italic>, <italic>Cm</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not spoiled</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not examined</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b48">Duffes <italic>et al.</italic> (1999b)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;MAP or vacuum, 5&#x000b0;C</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cm</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not spoiled</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not examined</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b151">Paludan-M&#x000fc;ller <italic>et al.</italic> (1998)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Vacuum, 5&#x000b0;C</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cm</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not spoiled</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not examined</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b144">Nilsson <italic>et al.</italic> (1999)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Vacuum, 6&#x000b0;C</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cm</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not spoiled (butter, caramel, sour, fruity)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,3-Butanedione, 2,3-pentanedione</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b89">Joffraud <italic>et al.</italic> (2001)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Vacuum, 6&#x000b0;C</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cm</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not spoiled [butter/plastic, rubbery and neutral (green/cooked meat)]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not examined</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b200">Stohr <italic>et al.</italic> (2001)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Vacuum, 8&#x000b0;C</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cm</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lightly spoiled (grassy, fruity notes)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not examined</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b90">Joffraud <italic>et al.</italic> (2006)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Shrimp (MAP, 5&#x000b0;C)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cd</italic>, <italic>Cm</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spoiled (chlorine, chemical, malty, nutty, sour)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ornithine, ammonia, acetic acid, alcohols, aldehydes, ketones, 2,4,6-trimethylpyridine</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b129">Mejlholm <italic>et al.</italic> (2005)</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b105">Laursen <italic>et al.</italic> (2006)</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cm</italic> (L)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf4-2">&#x02020;</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not spoiled (grass/hay, weak chlorine)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ornithine, ammonia, acetic acid, alcohols, aldehydes, ketones</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b105">Laursen <italic>et al.</italic> (2006)</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cmo</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not spoiled (yogurt-like)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Organic acids, alcohols, ketones</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b105">Laursen <italic>et al.</italic> (2006)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Meat</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">&#x02002;Beef</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Vacuum, 2&#x000b0;C</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cm</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not spoiled/spoiled<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf4-3">&#x02021;</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not examined</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b111">Leisner <italic>et al.</italic> (1995)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Vacuum, 4&#x000b0;C, normal pH</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cd</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not indicated (butter, acid)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not examined</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">Borch <italic>et al.</italic> (1996)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Vacuum, 4&#x000b0;C, high pH</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cd</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not indicated (acid, slightly sulfurous)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not examined</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">Borch <italic>et al.</italic> (1996)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;In air, 7&#x000b0;C</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cm</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spoiled</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not examined</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b111">Leisner <italic>et al.</italic> (1995)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Cured bologna (4 or 9&#x000b0;C)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cv</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Green discoloration</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Presumably by H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b153">Peirson <italic>et al.</italic> (2003)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ham, cooked, sliced (vacuum, 5 or 7&#x000b0;C)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cm</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spoiled</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Branched alcohols and aldehydes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">Budde <italic>et al.</italic> (2003)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Cooked, minced sausage (24&#x02013;15&#x000b0;C)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cm</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sausage/fatty odor</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b1;-Ketoisocaproic acid, hydroxy-&#x003b1;-ketoisocaproic acid, 3-methylbutanoic acid</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b102">Larrouture-Thiveyrat <italic>et al.</italic> (2003)</xref></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tf4-1"><label>*</label><p>2-Methylpropanal, 2-methylpropanol, 3-methylbutanal, 3-methylbutanol (both ham and milk) and 2-methylbutanal (ham). For milk, the production of these compounds was determined in a laboratory medium and not milk <italic>per se</italic>.</p></fn><fn id="tf4-2"><label>&#x02020;</label><p>Phenotypical cluster L (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b104">Laursen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>).</p></fn><fn id="tf4-3"><label>&#x02021;</label><p>Spoilage observed at an initial density of log 4 CFU cm<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> but not at log 2 CFU cm<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>.</p></fn><fn><p><italic>Cd</italic>, <italic>Carnobacterium divergens</italic>; <italic>Cm</italic>, <italic>Carnobacterium maltaromaticum</italic>; <italic>Cmo, Carnobacterium mobile</italic>; <italic>Cv</italic>, <italic>Carnobacterium viridans</italic>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>We will first focus on catabolic reactions with carbohydrates and/or organic acids as substrates and with pyruvic acid as an intermediate metabolite. Respiration might occur in the presence of hematin, as shown for <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b128">Meisel <italic>et al.</italic>, 1994</xref>), and, indeed, this species consumes substantial proportions of oxygen during exponential growth under aerobic conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">Borch &#x00026; Molin, 1989</xref>). <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> spp. are, however, considered to be homofermentative organisms that produce lactic acid from glucose. The presence of the glycolytic pathway in <italic>C. divergens</italic> has been demonstrated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b43">de Bruyn <italic>et al.</italic>, 1987</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b42">1988</xref>). It can be debated whether carnobacteria should instead be considered facultative or atypical heterofermentative organisms, as <italic>C. divergens</italic> and <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> are able to utilize ribose and gluconic acid as substrates for growth, and may produce acetic acid, formic acid, and CO<sub>2</sub> (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b190">Shaw &#x00026; Harding, 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b43">de Bruyn <italic>et al.</italic>, 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">Borch &#x00026; Molin, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b108">Leisner, 1992</xref>) as end-products of some secondary decarboxylation/dissimilation reactions of pyruvic acid (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b43">de Bruyn <italic>et al.</italic>, 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b183">Schillinger &#x00026; Holzapfel, 1995</xref>). Indeed, carnobacteria were initially described as heterofermenters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29">Collins <italic>et al.</italic>, 1987</xref>). Acetic acid production by <italic>C. divergens</italic> and <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> can be substantial during growth in laboratory media under aerobic conditions or in MAP shrimp, and quantitatively it can exceed lactic acid production (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">Borch &#x00026; Molin, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b105">Laursen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). Production of acetic acid by <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> is also increased relative to lactic acid if glucose is substituted by ribose (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b108">Leisner, 1992</xref>). Furthermore, <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> can produce large amounts of ethanol from glucose and ribose during growth in a shrimp extract under anaerobic conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b108">Leisner, 1992</xref>).</p><p>Acetoin can be generated by <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> from pyruvic acid (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">Borch &#x00026; Molin, 1989</xref>), and this reaction is also found for <italic>C. divergens</italic> and <italic>C. gallinarum</italic> but not for <italic>C. alterfunditum</italic>, <italic>C. funditum</italic>, <italic>C. inhibens</italic> and <italic>C. viridance</italic>, according to reactions in the Voges&#x02013;Proskauer test (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">Collins <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b81">Holley <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>). <italic>Carnobacterium mobile</italic> gives variable reactions, and information is not available for <italic>C. pleistocenium</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29">Collins <italic>et al.</italic>, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b156">Pikuta <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>). The factors affecting acetoin production are not well known, but production is increased by resting cells of <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> in the presence of hematin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b128">Meisel <italic>et al.</italic>, 1994</xref>). In addition, two out of four strains of <italic>C. divergens</italic> and <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> isolated from mozzarella cheese were reported to be able to metabolize citric acid, but the potential sensory role of this reaction, e.g. by production of acetoin and diacetyl, was not examined (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b137">Morea <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>). Production of diacetyl and 2,3-pentanedione by <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> during growth in cold-smoked salmon resulted in a butter-like odor but not in spoilage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b89">Joffraud <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl4">Table 4</xref>). In conclusion, even, if carbohydrate catabolism by carnobacteria appears to result in a diverse number of metabolites, these have generally a limited effect on the sensory attributes of foods. H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> may be produced by <italic>C. divergens</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">Borch &#x00026; Molin, 1989</xref>), and formation of this compound by <italic>C. viridans</italic> has been associated with spoilage in the form of green discoloration of cured Bologna ham (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl4">Table 4</xref>).</p><p>Whether carnobacteria possess proteolytic activities of potential importance for taste in products such as cheese is not known, and this deserves further investigation. In contrast, metabolites resulting from the degradation of amino acids certainly cause sensory effects in foods (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl4">Table 4</xref>). Generation of branched alcohols and aldehydes (2-methyl-1-butanal, 2-methyl-1-butanol, 3-methyl-1-butanal, 3-methyl-1-butanol, 2-methylpropanal, and 2-methylpropanol) by transamination, decarboxylation and reduction of the amino acids valine, leucine and isoleucine appears to be particularly important. Production of some of these compounds, such as 3-methyl-1-butanal, is strain or species dependent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b100">Larrouture <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>). Production by a <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> strain of 3-methylbutanal, 3-methylbutanol and 3-methylbutanoic acid from leucine was, in general, increased at pH values of 6.5 or higher and in the presence of increased concentrations of &#x003b1;-ketoisocaproic acid and glucose (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b101">Larrouture-Thiveyrat &#x00026; Montel, 2003</xref>). This strain affected the odor and reduced the leucine content of a sausage mince, but a clear causal relationship was not demonstrated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b102">Larrouture-Thiveyrat <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>). Production by <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> of alcohols and aldehydes from valine, leucine and/or isoleucine resulted in a malty, green aroma in skimmed milk and shrimp, and has also caused spoilage of cured ham (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl4">Table 4</xref>). The association between the presence of these compounds and spoilage is, however, not always straightforward, as production of 3-methyl-1-butanal and/or 3-methyl-1-butanol in shrimp by certain <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> strains did not result in malty off-flavors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b105">Laursen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>).</p><p>Production of NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> from arginine as a result of its catabolism catalyzed by the arginine deaminase pathway (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b110">Leisner <italic>et al.</italic>, 1994b</xref>) may, in theory, cause spoilage of shrimp or squid that contain high levels of free arginine (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">Asakawa <italic>et al.</italic>, 1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b77">Hirano <italic>et al.</italic>, 1992</xref>). <italic>Carnobacterium maltaromaticum</italic> and <italic>C. divergens</italic> but not <italic>C. mobile</italic> were able to produce NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> in MAP shrimp, but this was not the cause of spoilage of this product (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b105">Laursen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>).</p><p>Production of indole from the amino acid tryptophan is also a potential cause of spoilage, although <italic>C. divergens</italic>, <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> and <italic>C. mobile</italic> are all unable to carry out this reaction in standard laboratory media (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b105">Laursen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). It has, however, been observed that <italic>C. divergens</italic> and strains belonging to a major phenotypic cluster of <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> were able to use tryptophan as a substrate during growth in MAP shrimp (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b105">Laursen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). Whether this resulted in generation of indole was not examined.</p><p>Production of tyramine from tyrosine is the only known metabolic reaction by <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> spp. that constitutes a cause of concern regarding food safety. Not all carnobacterial species possess this ability, as <italic>C. mobile</italic> does not produce tyramine during growth in shrimp, and variation exists among different strains and phenotypic clusters of <italic>C. divergens</italic> and <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> for amounts of tyramine produced (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b109">Leisner <italic>et al.</italic>, 1994a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b121">Masson <italic>et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">Bover-Cid &#x00026; Holzapfel, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b105">Laursen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). Tyramine production by one <italic>C. divergens</italic> strain was at its maximum during the stationary growth phase and at a low initial pH in the presence of 0.6% glucose, whereas NaCl (10%) was inhibitory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b122">Masson <italic>et al.</italic>, 1997</xref>). Regardless of strain variation and the effects of environmental parameters, tyramine production by <italic>C. divergens</italic> and/or <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> has been reported in a range of foods, including meat (up to 28 mg kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b50">Edwards <italic>et al.</italic>, 1987</xref>), a meat&#x02013;fat mixture (up to 121 mg kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b123">Masson <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>), cold-smoked salmon (up to <italic>c</italic>. 370 mg kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b48">Duffes <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b92">J&#x000f8;rgensen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31">Connil <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">Brillet <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>), frozen and thawed salmon (up to 40&#x02013;60 mg kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b53">Emborg <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>), and shrimp (up to 20&#x02013;60 mg kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b105">Laursen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). These levels have no adverse effects on most consumers, but for sensitive individuals, e.g. with reduced monoamine oxidase activity due to medication or hereditary deficiency, very little tyramine can cause migraine headaches, and an intake of no more than 5 mg of tyramine per meal has been recommended (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b125">McCabe, 1986</xref>). Typical consumption of fish and meat products is 50&#x02013;150 g per meal. As described above, <italic>C. divergens</italic> and/or <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> are able to form <italic>c</italic>. 20&#x02013;370 mg tyramine kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> in these products, corresponding to <italic>c</italic>. 1&#x02013;55 mg of tyramine per meal. Consequently, tyramine formation by carnobacteria in specific foods can represent a hazard for sensitive individuals who might suffer migraine headaches. This risk for sensitive individuals can be minimized by restricting their consumption of fish and meat to products that are newly processed, i.e. that are not close to the declared shelf-life expiry day.</p><p>Growth of <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> spp. in food products may result in accumulation of a range of volatile alcohols, ketones, hydrocarbons, and other compounds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b105">Laursen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). The metabolic reactions leading to these products have not been studied in detail for <italic>Carnobacterium</italic>, in contrast to the situation for other LAB (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b193">Smit <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>), but may be a result of NAD+-generating reactions or nonenzymatic reactions. Several ketones have characteristic odors, but whether they contribute to spoilage off-flavors as a result of carnobacterial metabolic activity is not well understood. With regard to lipids, <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> has been reported to hydrolyze tributyrin, a triglyceride with butyrate as fatty acid (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b152">Papon &#x00026; Talon, 1988</xref>), but it is not known whether this lipase activity contributes to flavor changes of dairy, fish and meat products. <italic>Carnobacterium divergens</italic> and <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> were not able to limit oxidation of linoleic acid during growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b204">Talon <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>). This indicates that these species may not prevent quality deterioration of meat products by lipid oxidation. Finally, <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> has been shown to cause a softer texture of salmon fillets when inoculated in high numbers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b138">Morzel <italic>et al.</italic>, 1997</xref>).</p><p>It is worth noting that interspecies and intraspecies differences exist regarding carnobacterial spoilage capacity. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b105">Laursen <italic>et al.</italic> (2006)</xref> showed that <italic>C. mobile</italic> and a minor phenotypic cluster of <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> did not spoil MAP shrimp, in contrast to what was seen with <italic>C. divergens</italic> and the major phenotypic cluster of <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic>. It would be of interest to examine whether similar heterogeneities exist for <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> spp. growing in other dairy, fish and meat products. As environmental parameters readily affect the metabolism of carbohydrates and amino acids, it is not surprising that product-specific and storage-specific conditions also play important roles. The ability of two <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> strains to relatively rapidly spoil meat during growth under aerobic conditions at 7&#x000b0;C but not or only after a long storage period in vacuum packs at 2&#x000b0;C serves as an example (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl4">Table 4</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b111">Leisner <italic>et al.</italic>, 1995</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Carnobacteria as pathogenic organisms and/or probiotic cultures</title><p>Two human clinical cases caused by opportunistic infection with <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> and a <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> sp. have been described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b221">Xu <italic>et al.</italic>, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27">Chmelar <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>). Two clinical isolates of <italic>C. divergens</italic> have also been obtained (accession number AY650920). Carnobacteria are not known members of the human gastrointestinal microbial community, unlike several other LAB. The exceptions are an unpublished study reporting an uncultured <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> sp. clone from cow rumen (AY244976) and two studies demonstrating the presence of carnobacteria in pig and horse effluent-impacted environments (DQ337521; DQ337531) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b191">Simpson <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>). Nevertheless, it is safe to conclude that the presence of <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> spp. in food does not present a risk factor for human illness, except for the production of the biogenic amine, tyramine, as discussed previously. Neither do <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> spp. appear to present a risk for nocosomial infections in hospitals and similar institutions, although they have, in one instance, been isolated from contaminated blood plasma (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b206">Thornley &#x00026; Sharpe, 1959</xref>).</p><p>The presence of virulence factors in carnobacteria is not well documented. Thus <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> strains isolated from diseased fish lacked hemolytic and phospholipolytic activities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b74">Hammes &#x00026; Hertel, 2003</xref>). <italic>Carnobacterium viridans</italic> shows, however, &#x003b2;-hemolytic activity on sheep blood agar (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b81">Holley <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>). Although several isolates of carnobacteria produce bacteriocins, none of these compounds has been reported to exert a cytolytic activity as shown for the <italic>En. faecalis</italic> class I-related bacteriocin cytolysin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b63">Gilmore <italic>et al.</italic>, 1994</xref>). Regarding chemotherapeutic agents, fish pathogenic strains of <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> were resistant to several of the agents widely used in aquaculture, such as oxytetracycline, quinolones, nitrofurans and potentiated sulfonamides, but sensitive to erythromycin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b133">Michel <italic>et al.</italic>, 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">Baya <italic>et al.</italic>, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b208">Toranzo <italic>et al.</italic>, 1993a</xref>). This species is not resistant to lysozyme from salmonid eggs, which supports the idea that it is not vertically transmitted, at least in this fish species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b222">Yousif <italic>et al.</italic>, 1994</xref>). Finally, it should be noted that two clinical isolates of <italic>C. divergens</italic> have been reported to possess a gene encoding a new class of penicillinase (AY650920). It will be of interest to further explore the distribution of this enzyme among carnobacterial species as well as its functionality.</p><p>It has been documented that some strains of <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> are pathogenic for several fish species, including Australian salmonids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b82">Humphrey <italic>et al.</italic>, 1987</xref>), carp (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b131">Michel <italic>et al.</italic>, 1986</xref>), rainbow trout (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b78">Hiu <italic>et al.</italic>, 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">Baya <italic>et al.</italic>, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b197">Starliper <italic>et al.</italic>, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b208">Toranzo <italic>et al.</italic>, 1993a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b209">b</xref>), striped bass and channel catfish (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">Baya <italic>et al.</italic>, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b209">Toranzo <italic>et al.</italic>, 1993b</xref>), and salmon (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b78">Hiu <italic>et al.</italic>, 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b133">Michel <italic>et al.</italic>, 1986</xref>). Pathologic effects vary, and include, for example, septicemia, peritonitis, exophthalmia, accumulation of ascitic fluid, and hemorrhages. In most (but not all) instances, the virulence appears, however, to be low and only causes problems in fish undergoing severe stress, e.g. due to spawning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b133">Michel <italic>et al.</italic>, 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b197">Starliper <italic>et al.</italic>, 1992</xref>). It is, therefore, not surprising that <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> and <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic>-like strains are also found in the intestine or gills of healthy fish, including Arctic charr (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b167">Ring&#x000f8;<italic>et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b167">2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b165">Ring&#x000f8; &#x00026; Olsen, 1999</xref>), Atlantic cod (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b188">Seppola <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b173">Ring&#x000f8;<italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>), Atlantic salmon (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b164">Ring&#x000f8; &#x00026; Holzapfel, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b166">Ring&#x000f8;<italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b167">2001</xref>), brown bullhead (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">Baya <italic>et al.</italic>, 1991</xref>), trout (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b64">Gonz&#x000e1;lez <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b196">Spanggaard <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b158">Pond <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>), and various freshwater fish (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b64">Gonz&#x000e1;lez <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b65">2000</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b170">Ring&#x000f8;<italic>et al.</italic> (2005)</xref> also summarize some of these findings.</p><p>The presence of other carnobacterial species in healthy fish has also been reported, including <italic>C. divergens</italic> [Arctic charr (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b165">Ring&#x000f8; &#x00026; Olsen, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b168">Ring&#x000f8;<italic>et al.</italic>, 2002a</xref>), Atlantic salmon, Atlantic cod and wolffish (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b167">Ring&#x000f8;<italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>), trout (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b196">Spanggaard <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b96">Kim &#x00026; Austin, 2006b</xref>), and freshwater fish (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b65">Gonz&#x000e1;lez <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>)], <italic>C. alterfunditum</italic>-like [rainbow trout (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b194">Spanggaard <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>)], <italic>C. funditum</italic>-like [Arctic charr and Atlantic cod (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b169">Ring&#x000f8;<italic>et al.</italic>, 2002b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b171">2006</xref>)], <italic>C. gallinarum</italic> [Atlantic cod (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b186">Seppola <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>)], <italic>C. inhibens</italic> [Atlantic salmon (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b88">J&#x000f6;born <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>)], <italic>C. mobile</italic>-like [Arctic charr and Atlantic cod (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b165">Ring&#x000f8; &#x00026; Olsen, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b173">Ring&#x000f8;<italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>)], and <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> spp. [Arctic charr (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b167">Ring&#x000f8;<italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>) and carp (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b73">Hagi <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>)]. Clearly, further research is necessary to clarify under what circumstances <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> spp. may be pathogenic for fish and whether the infective capability is species and clone specific.</p><p>The reported pathogenicity of <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> has not hindered research into the possibility of using other carnobacteria as probiotic cultures in aquaculture, including <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> sp. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b83">Irianto &#x00026; Austin, 2002</xref>), <italic>C. alterfunditum</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b194">Spanggaard <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>), <italic>C. divergens</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b61">Gildberg <italic>et al.</italic>, 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b62">1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b196">Spanggaard <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>), and <italic>C. inhibens</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b87">J&#x000f6;born <italic>et al.</italic>, 1997</xref>). Isolates of these species, in addition to <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic>, exhibit inhibitory activity towards bacterial fish pathogens (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b164">Ring&#x000f8; &#x00026; Holzapfel, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b67">Gram &#x00026; Ring&#x000f8;, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b172">Ring&#x000f8;<italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>). <italic>Carnobacterium divergens</italic> and <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> enhance the cellular and humoral immune responses and cytokine expression ratios of rainbow trout (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b95">Kim &#x00026; Austin, 2006a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b96">b</xref>). Use of carnobacteria as probiotics leads to increased survival of the fish in some instances [larvae of cod fry and Atlantic salmon fry (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b61">Gildberg <italic>et al.</italic>, 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b62">1997</xref>), rainbow trout (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b83">Irianto &#x00026; Austin, 2002</xref>), and salmon (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b173">Robertson <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>)], but not in others [larvae of cod fry (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b60">Gildberg &#x00026; Mikkelsen, 1998</xref>), and rainbow trout (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b194">Spanggaard <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>)]. One study showed that <italic>in vitro</italic> exposure to <italic>C. divergens</italic> did not reverse the effects of bacterial pathogens, although these were alleviated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b172">Ring&#x000f8;<italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). Additional research is necessary to validate the usefulness of carnobacteria as probiotic cultures.</p><p><italic>Carnobacterium maltaromaticum</italic> has also been reported to be pathogenic for the fruit fly, <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic>, upon injection into the thorax (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b85">Jensen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). This specific case of pathogenesis is probably best understood as a result of opportunistic infection, although <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> (but not <italic>C. divergens</italic>, <italic>C. gallinarum</italic>, <italic>C. inhibens</italic>, <italic>C. mobile</italic> or <italic>C. viridans</italic>) exerts chitinolytic acitivity (Leisner &#x00026; Ingmer, unpublished data), a feature that can be perceived as targeting the chitin-containing exoskeleton of insects. Indeed, insects may serve as a host for this species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b187">Shannon <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Genomics</title><p>The complete chromosomes of many LAB species have now been sequenced. Currently, 19 complete genome sequences of streptococci and 18 complete genome sequences of the nonpathogenic LAB representing 14 species from the order <italic>Lactobacillales</italic> are available (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b119">Makarova &#x00026; Koonin, 2007</xref>). However, no genome sequence or physical genetic map is available for <italic>Carnobacterium</italic>. The LAB have relatively small genomes for nonobligatory bacterial parasites or symbionts, ranging from <italic>c</italic>. 1.6 to <italic>c</italic>. 3 Mb. For <italic>C. divergens</italic> and <italic>C. pleistocenium</italic>, the genome size was estimated to 3.2 Mb, and for <italic>C. alterfunditum</italic> pf4<sup>T</sup>, it was estimated to be 2.9 Mb (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b41">Daniel, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b156">Pikuta <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>). At the time of writing (March 2007), there is only one <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> genome sequencing project. <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> sp. AT7, a piezophilic strain isolated from the Aleutian trench at a depth of 2500 m, is being sequenced for the Moore Foundation Marine Microbial Genome Sequencing Project with a grant to the J. Craig Venter Institute. The data already available indicate that the <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> sp. AT7 genome contains 2.4 Mb and encodes 2388 proteins (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genomesonline.org">http://www.genomesonline.org</ext-link>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b116">Liolios <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> sp. AT7 is closely related to <italic>C. alterfunditum</italic> and <italic>C. pleistocenium</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b103">Lauro <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>).</p><p>To date, knowledge on the genes and DNA sequences of <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> is comparatively sparse, concerning mostly bacteriocin-related genes in the species <italic>C. divergens</italic> and <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>) and 16S rRNA and 16S&#x02013;23S rRNA gene intergenic spacer sequences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b93">Kabadjova <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b163">Rachman <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>). Genes involved in some important carnobacterial metabolic traits have been sequenced (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl5">Table 5</xref>). The genetic information obtained is, for most sequences, derived from just one strain, and may therefore be strain specific, as shown for a number of <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b142">Nelson <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="tbl5" position="float"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Summary of known genes and DNA sequences in <italic>Carnobacterium</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf5-1">*</xref></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Function</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Species/Strain</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Accession number</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">References<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf5-2">&#x02020;</xref></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Bacteriocin immunity</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02002;To carnobacteriocin A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cm</italic>/LV17A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>cbiA</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf5-3">&#x02021;</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AF207838</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b56">Franz <italic>et al.</italic> (2000)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02002;To carnobacteriocin BM1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cm</italic>/LV17B</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>cbiBM1</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L29058</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b157">Quadri <italic>et al.</italic> (1994)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02002;To carnobacteriocin B2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cm</italic>/LV17B, CP52</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>cbiB2</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf5-3">&#x02021;</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L47121</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b158">Quadri <italic>et al.</italic> (1995)</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b75">Herbin <italic>et al.</italic> (1997)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02002;To divercin V41</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cd</italic>/V41</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>dvnT2</italic>, <italic>dvnI</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AJ224003</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b130">M&#x000e9;tivier <italic>et al.</italic> (1998)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02002;To divergicin A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cd</italic>/LV13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>dviA</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf5-3">&#x02021;</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DQ087597</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b218">Worobo <italic>et al.</italic> (1995)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02002;To piscicolin 126</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cm</italic>/JG126</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>pisI</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AF275938</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gibbs <italic>et al.</italic> (2000) (U)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf5-2">&#x02020;</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Regulation of bacteriocin expression/secretion</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02002;Carnobacteriocin A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cm</italic>/LV17A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>cbaX</italic>, <italic>K</italic>, <italic>R</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf5-3">&#x02021;</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AF207838</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b56">Franz <italic>et al.</italic> (2000)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02002;Carnobacteriocin BM1 andB2: three-component regulatory system</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cm</italic>/LV17B</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>cbnS</italic>, <italic>K</italic>,<italic>R</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf5-3">&#x02021;</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L47121</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b160">Quadri <italic>et al.</italic> (1997b)</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b97">Kleerebezem <italic>et al.</italic> (2001)</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b174">Rohde &#x00026; Quadri (2006)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02002;Divercin regulatory system</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cd</italic>/V41</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>dvnK</italic>, <italic>R</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AJ224003</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b130">M&#x000e9;tivier <italic>et al.</italic> (1998)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02002;Piscicolin 126 regulatory system</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cm</italic>/JG126</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>pisN</italic>, <italic>K</italic>, <italic>R</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AF275938</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gibbs <italic>et al.</italic> (2000) (U)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Bacteriocin ABC transporter</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02002;Carnobacteriocin A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cm</italic>/LV17A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>cbaT</italic>,<italic>C</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf5-3">&#x02021;</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AF207838</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b56">Franz <italic>et al.</italic> (2000)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02002;Carnobacteriocin BM1 and B2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cm</italic>/LV17B</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>cbnT</italic>,<italic>D</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf5-3">&#x02021;</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L47121, L29058</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quadri <italic>et al.</italic> (1997)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b97">Kleerebezem <italic>et al.</italic> (2001)</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b174">Rohde &#x00026; Quadri (2006)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02002;Divercin</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cd</italic>/V41</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>dvnT1</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AJ224003</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b130">M&#x000e9;tivier <italic>et al.</italic> (1998)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02002;Piscicolin 126</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cm</italic>/JG126</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>pisT</italic>, <italic>E</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AF275938</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gibbs <italic>et al.</italic> (2000) (U)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Metabolism</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02002;Alanine dehydrogenase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Csp</italic>/st2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ald</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AF070714</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b59">Galkin <italic>et al.</italic> (1999)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02002;ATP synthase &#x003b1;-subunit</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cd</italic>/LMG 9199<sup>T</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>atpA</italic> partial</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AJ843296</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b140">Naser <italic>et al.</italic> (2005)</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cm</italic>/LMG 9839<sup>T</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>atpA</italic> partial</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AJ843298</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b140">Naser <italic>et al.</italic> (2005)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02002;Glutamate racemase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Csp</italic>/st2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Glr</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AF263927</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Galkin <italic>et al.</italic> (2000) (U)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02002;Glycosyl hydrolases</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cm</italic>/BA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>agaA</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AF376480</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32">Coombs &#x00026; Brenchley (2001)</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>bgaC</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AF376481</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32">Coombs &#x00026; Brenchley (2001)</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>bgaB</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AF184246</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b33">Coombs &#x00026; Brenchley (1999)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02002;Homoserine dehydrogenase and aromatic amino acid aminotransferase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cm</italic>/545</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>hdhCP</italic>, <italic>araTCP</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AY029372</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Larrouture-Thiveyrat <italic>et al.</italic> (2001) (U)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02002;Penicillinase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cd</italic>/BM4489</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>cad-1</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AY650920</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Perichon <italic>et al.</italic> (2004) (U)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02002;Phenylalanyl-tRNA synthase &#x003b1;-subunit</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cm</italic>/LMG 6903<sup>T</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>pheS</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AM168425</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b141">Naser <italic>et al.</italic> (2006)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02002;Superoxide dismutase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cm</italic>/3364-01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>sodA</italic>, partial</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AM490329</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b132">Michel <italic>et al.</italic> (2007)</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cm</italic>/NCIMB 2264</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>sodA</italic>, partial</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AM490310</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b132">Michel <italic>et al.</italic> (2007)</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ci</italic>/CIP 106863<sup>T</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>sodA</italic>, partial</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AM490313</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b132">Michel <italic>et al.</italic> (2007)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02002;Tyrosine decarboxylase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cd</italic>/V41</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>tdc</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DQ336701</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">Brillet <italic>et al.</italic> (2005)</xref> (U)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34">Coton <italic>et al.</italic> (2004)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Miscellaneous</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02002;Recombinase A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cm</italic>/LMG 6903<sup>T</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>recA</italic>, partial</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AJ621690</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Felis <italic>et al.</italic> (2005) (U)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02002;RNAse RH</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Csp</italic>/st2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>rph</italic>, partial</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AF263927</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Galkin <italic>et al.</italic> (2000) (U)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02002;Theta-type plasmid</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cd</italic>/LV13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>pCD3.4</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf5-3">&#x02021;</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DQ087597</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b211">Van Belkum &#x00026; Stiles (2006)</xref></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tf5-1"><label>*</label><p>For bacteriocin structural genes, see <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>.</p></fn><fn id="tf5-2"><label>&#x02020;</label><p>U, unpublished sequence (National Center for Biotechnology Information Genome Library, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov</ext-link>).</p></fn><fn id="tf5-3"><label>&#x02021;</label><p>The sequences are encoded by plasmids.</p></fn><fn><p><italic>Cd, Carnobacterium divergens</italic>; <italic>Ci</italic>, <italic>Carnobacterium inhibens</italic>; <italic>Cm</italic>, <italic>Carnobacterium maltaromaticum</italic>; <italic>Csp</italic>, <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> sp.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Clearly, our knowledge of important phenotypes of strains and species of <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> would benefit from the availability of a complete genome sequence for a strain representative of <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic>, which is the species with most importance for the food and aquaculture industries. The most extensive study on phenotypic variation of <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> revealed that the majority of strains studied belonged to one phenotypic cluster (cluster H) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b104">Laursen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>). Thus, in our opinion, a suitable candidate for a whole genomic sequence could be either <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> LMG 22901 (isolated from pork meat), LMG 22899 (isolated from cod) or LMG 22898 (isolated from salmon), which all belong to this phenotypic cluster. LMG 22901 does not harbor plasmids (Laursen, unpublished), and therefore appears to be a prime candidate for such an endeavor.</p></sec><sec><title>Concluding remarks</title><p>We have come some way towards understanding important aspects of the presence of carnobacteria in foods and the environment, particularly concerning the genetics of carnobacterial bacteriocins and their application. However, there are important areas where knowledge on these bacteria is limited. These include the following:</p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Distribution and quantitative microbial ecology: <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> spp. have not been reported from a number of habitats, such as plants, fermented vegetable foods and the gastrointestinal system of birds and mammals, including humans, that have otherwise been associated with several genera and species of LAB. This may, in some instances, be due to faulty methodology for detecting carnobacteria. Generally, however, our quantitative understanding is limited regarding factors that influence inactivation, survival or growth of carnobacteria in various natural environments. In foods, more detailed information is available, but mathematical models for quantitative prediction of processing, product and storage effects on growth and metabolic activity, including bacteriocin and tyramine formation, awaits further development together with recording of responses in databases. In addition, further studies are needed to elucidate mechanisms underlying the relationship between environmental parameters and kinetic responses of carnobacteria.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Routes of food contamination: To reduce the negative effects of carnobacteria in foods (spoilage metabolites and tyramine), further information on routes of contamination is desirable. In fact, very little research has been performed so far concerning this aspect of carnobacteria in food.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Metabolic activity: It is known that carnobacteria, or at least <italic>C. maltaromaticum</italic> and <italic>C. divergens</italic>, have the capacity to produce a wide range of metabolites in chilled food. Further studies on the importance of these metabolites with respect to positive and negative sensory attributes of various foods are, however, needed.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Diversity: We are beginning to appreciate how interspecies and intraspecies variation determine the positive and negative effects of the presence of carnobacteria in food and the environment, but we still do not understand how such variation affects, for instance, their survival in food-processing plants and contamination of foods. The significance of such variation for their potential as fish pathogens also needs to be substantiated. This is also the case for their role as spoilage organisms in meat and fish products, with the exception of a few products such as vacuum-packed smoked salmon and cooked MAP shrimps.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Genomics: Representative genome sequences would offer a very valuable road map in order to answer many of the outstanding questions associated with this important genus.</p></list-item></list></sec><sec><title>Statement</title><p>Reuse of this article is permitted in accordance with the Creative Commons Deed, Attribution 2.5, which does not permit commercial exploitation.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="b1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plasmid-associated bacteriocin production by a strain of <italic>Carnobacterium piscicola</italic> from meat</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>1990</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>2503</fpage><lpage>2510</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2403256</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>VF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antilisterial activity of a <italic>Carnobacterium piscicola</italic> isolated from Brazilian smoked fish (Surubim [<italic>Pseudoplatystoma</italic> sp.]) and its activity against a persistant strain of <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic> isolated from Surubim</article-title><source>J Food Prot</source><year>2005</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>2068</fpage><lpage>2077</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16245709</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Asakawa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Taste-active components of the shrimp <italic>Pandalus borealis</italic></article-title><source>Nippon Shokuhin Kogyo Gakkaishi</source><year>1981</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>594</fpage><lpage>599</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Azuma</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibition of <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic> by freeze-dried piscicocin CS526 fermentate in food</article-title><source>Lett Appl Microbiol</source><year>2007</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>138</fpage><lpage>144</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17257251</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barakat</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation and characterization of <italic>Carnobacterium</italic>, <italic>Lactococcus</italic>, and <italic>Enterococcus</italic> spp. from cooked, modified atmosphere packaged, refrigerated, poultry meat</article-title><source>Int J Food Microbiol</source><year>2000</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>83</fpage><lpage>94</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11139026</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Basby</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of the microflora of lightly salted lumpfish (<italic>Cyclopterus lumpus</italic>) roe stored at 5&#x000b0;C</article-title><source>J Aquat Food Product Technol</source><year>1998</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>51</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baya</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biochemical and serological characterization of <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> spp. isolated from farmed and natural populations of striped bass and catfish</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>1991</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>3114</fpage><lpage>3120</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1781676</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhugaloo-Vial</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Purification and amino acid sequences of piscicocins V1a and V1b, two class IIa bacteriocins secreted by <italic>Carnobacterium piscicola</italic> V1 that display significantly different levels of specific inhibitory activity</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>1996</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>4410</fpage><lpage>4416</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8953713</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhugaloo-Vial</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Delineation of key amino acid side chains and peptide domains for antimicrobial properties of divercin V41, a pediocin-like bacteriocin secreted by <italic>Carnobacterium divergens</italic> V41</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>1999</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>2895</fpage><lpage>2900</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10388680</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bj&#x000f6;rkroth</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Enterococcus</italic> species dominating in fresh modified-atmosphere-packaged, marinated broiler legs are overgrown by <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> and <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> species during storage at 6&#x000b0;C</article-title><source>Int J Food Microbiol</source><year>2005</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>267</fpage><lpage>276</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15582737</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blom</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization, production and purification of carnocin H, a bacteriocin produced by <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> 377</article-title><source>Curr Microbiol</source><year>2001</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>227</fpage><lpage>231</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11683354</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Borch</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Numerical taxonomy of psychrotrophic lactic acid bacteria from prepacked meat and meat products</article-title><source>Anton Leeuw</source><year>1988</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>301</fpage><lpage>323</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Borch</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The aerobic growth and product formation of <italic>Lactobacillus</italic>, <italic>Leuconostoc</italic>, <italic>Brochothrix</italic>, and <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> in batch cultures</article-title><source>Appl Microbiol Biotech</source><year>1989</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>88</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Borch</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bacterial spoilage of meat and cured meat products</article-title><source>Int J Food Microbiol</source><year>1996</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>103</fpage><lpage>120</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8913812</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bover-Cid</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improved screening procedure for biogenic amine production by lactic acid bacteria</article-title><source>Int J Food Microbiol</source><year>1999</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10598112</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bratina</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Manganese reduction by microbes from oxic regions of the Lake Vanda (Antarctica) water column</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>1998</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>3791</fpage><lpage>3797</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9758801</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brillet</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biodiversity of <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic> sensitivity to bacteriocin-producing <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> strains and application in sterile cold-smoked salmon</article-title><source>J Appl Microbiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>1029</fpage><lpage>1037</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15479419</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brillet</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of inoculation of <italic>Carnobacterium divergens</italic> V41, a biopreservative strain against <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic> risk, on the microbiological, chemical and sensory quality of cold-smoked salmon</article-title><source>Int J Food Microbiol</source><year>2005</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>309</fpage><lpage>324</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15979753</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b19"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brillet</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Luten</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Selection of non-tyramine producing <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> strains for the biopreservation of cold-smoked salmon</article-title><source>Seafood Research from Fish to Dish</source><year>2006</year><publisher-loc>Wageningen, The Netherlands</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Wageningen Academic Publishers</publisher-name><fpage>403</fpage><lpage>410</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buchanan</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effectiveness of <italic>Carnobacterium piscicola</italic> LK5 for controlling the growth of <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic> Scott A in refrigerated foods</article-title><source>J Food Safety</source><year>1992</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>219</fpage><lpage>236</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buchanan</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microbial competition: effect of culture conditions on the suppression of <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic> Scott A by <italic>Carnobacterium piscicola</italic></article-title><source>J Food Prot</source><year>1997</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>254</fpage><lpage>261</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Budde</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Leuconostoc carnosum</italic> 4010 has the potential for use as a protective culture for vacuum-packed meats: culture isolation, bacteriocin identification, and meat application experiments</article-title><source>Int J Food Microbiol</source><year>2003</year><volume>83</volume><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>184</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12706038</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cailliez-Grimal</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantitative polymerase chain reaction used for the rapid detection of <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> species from French soft cheeses</article-title><source>FEMS Microbiol Lett</source><year>2005</year><volume>250</volume><fpage>163</fpage><lpage>169</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16009510</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cailliez-Grimal</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Carnobacterium maltaromaticum</italic>: the only <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> species in French ripened soft cheeses as revealed by polymerase chain reaction detection</article-title><source>J Dairy Sci</source><year>2007</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>1133</fpage><lpage>1138</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17297087</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Calvez</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of new genes associated with intermediate resistance of <italic>Enterococcus faecalis</italic> to divercin V41, a pediocin-like bacteriocin</article-title><source>Microbiol</source><year>2007</year><volume>153</volume><fpage>1609</fpage><lpage>1618</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Campos</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibition of <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic> by <italic>Carnobacterium piscicola</italic> in vacuum-packaged cooked chicken at refrigeration temperatures</article-title><source>J Food Safety</source><year>1997</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>151</fpage><lpage>160</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chenoll</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lactic acid bacteria associated with vacuum-packed cooked meat product spoilage: population analysis by rDNA-based methods</article-title><source>J Appl Microbiol</source><year>2007</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>498</fpage><lpage>508</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17241356</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chmela&#x00159;</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation of <italic>Carnobacterium piscicola</italic> from human pus &#x02013; Case report</article-title><source>Folia Microbiol</source><year>2002</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>455</fpage><lpage>457</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12422528</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Classification of <italic>Lactobacillus divergens</italic>, <italic>Lactobacillus piscicola</italic>, and some catalase-negative, asporogenous, rod-shaped bacteria from poultry in a new genus, <italic>Carnobacterium</italic></article-title><source>Int J System Bacteriol</source><year>1987</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>310</fpage><lpage>316</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Isobaculum melis</italic> gen. nov., sp. nov., a <italic>Carnobacterium</italic>-like organism isolated from the intestine of a badger</article-title><source>Int J System Evol Microbiol</source><year>2002</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>210</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11837304</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Connil</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Production of biogenic amines and divercin V41 in cold smoked salmon inoculated with <italic>Carnobacterium divergens</italic> V41, and specific detection of this strain by multiplex-PCR</article-title><source>J Appl Microbiol</source><year>2002</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>611</fpage><lpage>617</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11966900</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coombs</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of two new glycosyl hydrolases from the lactic acid bacterium <italic>Carnobacterium piscicola</italic> strain BA</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2001</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>5094</fpage><lpage>5099</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11679331</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coombs</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biochemical and phylogenetic analyses of a cold-active &#x003b2;-galactosidase from the lactic acid bacterium <italic>Carnobacterium piscicola</italic> BA</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>1999</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>5443</fpage><lpage>5450</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10584002</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coton</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of the gene encoding a putative tyrosine decarboxylase of <italic>Carnobacterium divergens</italic> 508. Development of molecular tools for the detection of tyramine-producing bacteria</article-title><source>Food Microbiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>125</fpage><lpage>130</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coventry</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detection of bacteriocins of lactic acid bacteria isolated from foods and comparison with pediocin and nisin</article-title><source>J Appl Microbiol</source><year>1997</year><volume>83</volume><fpage>248</fpage><lpage>258</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9281829</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dainty</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical/biochemical detection of spoilage</article-title><source>Int J Food Microbiol</source><year>1996</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8913807</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dainty</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The relationship between the phenotypic properties of bacteria from chill-stored meat and spoilage processes</article-title><source>J Appl Bacteriol Symp Suppl</source><year>1992</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>103S</fpage><lpage>114S</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dalet</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><collab>The European Listeria Genome Consortium</collab><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>H&#x000e9;chard</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A &#x003c3;<sup>54</sup>-dependent PTS permease of the mannose family is responsible for sensitivity of <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic> to mesentericin Y105</article-title><source>Microbiol</source><year>2001</year><volume>147</volume><fpage>3263</fpage><lpage>3269</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dalgaard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of lactic acid bacteria from spoilage associations of cooked and brined shrimps stored under modified atmosphere between 0&#x000b0;C and 25&#x000b0;C</article-title><source>J Appl Microbiol</source><year>2003</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>80</fpage><lpage>89</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12492927</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b40"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dalgaard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biogenic amine formation and microbial spoilage in chilled garfish (<italic>Belone belone belone</italic>) &#x02013; effect of modified atmosphere packaging and previous frozen storage</article-title><source>J Appl Microbiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>80</fpage><lpage>95</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16834594</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b41"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Daniel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sizing of the <italic>Lactobacillus plantarum</italic> genome and other lactic acid bacteria species by transverse alternating field electrophoresis</article-title><source>Curr Microbiol</source><year>1995</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>243</fpage><lpage>246</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Bruyn</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Glucose metabolism by <italic>Lactobacillus divergens</italic></article-title><source>J Gen Microbiol</source><year>1988</year><volume>134</volume><fpage>2103</fpage><lpage>2109</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3253406</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b43"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Bruyn</surname><given-names>IN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Lactobacillus divergens</italic> is a homofermentative organism</article-title><source>Syst Appl Microbiol</source><year>1987</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>173</fpage><lpage>175</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b44"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Man</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A medium for the cultivation of Lactobacilli</article-title><source>J Appl Bacteriol</source><year>1960</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>130</fpage><lpage>135</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b45"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Reu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Eggshell factors influencing eggshell penetration and whole egg contamination by different bacteria, including <italic>Salmonella enteritidis</italic></article-title><source>Int J Food Microbiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>112</volume><fpage>253</fpage><lpage>260</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16822571</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b46"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Drider</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The continuing story of class IIa bacteriocins</article-title><source>Microbiol Mol Biol Rev</source><year>2006</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>564</fpage><lpage>582</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16760314</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b47"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duffes</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibition of <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic> by <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> spp. strains in a simulated cold smoked fish system stored at 4&#x000b0;C</article-title><source>Int J Food Microbiol</source><year>1999a</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10357271</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b48"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duffes</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibition of <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic> by <italic>in situ</italic> produced and semipurified bacteriocins of <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> spp. on vacuum-packed, refrigerated cold-smoked salmon</article-title><source>J Food Prot</source><year>1999b</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>1394</fpage><lpage>1403</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10606143</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b49"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duffes</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of two-dimensional electrophoresis to study differential protein expression in divercin V41-resistant and wild-type strains of <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic></article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2000</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>4318</fpage><lpage>4324</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11010876</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b50"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Amines in fresh beef of normal pH and the role of bacteria in changes in concentration observed during storage in vacuum packs at chill temperatures</article-title><source>J Appl Bacteriol</source><year>1987</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>427</fpage><lpage>434</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3440765</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b51"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Einarsson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biopreservation of brined shrimps (<italic>Pandalus borealis</italic>) by bacteriocins from lactic acid bacteria</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>1995</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>669</fpage><lpage>676</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16534936</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b52"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Emborg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Formation of histamine and biogenic amines in cold-smoked tuna: an investigation of psychrotolerant bacteria from samples implicated in cases of histamine fish poisoning</article-title><source>J Food Prot</source><year>2006</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>897</fpage><lpage>906</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16629036</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b53"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Emborg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microbial spoilage and formation of biogenic amines in fresh and thawed modified atmosphere-packed salmon (<italic>Salmo salar</italic>) at 2&#x000b0;C</article-title><source>J Appl Microbiol</source><year>2002</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>790</fpage><lpage>799</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11966922</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b54"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Emborg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Significant histamine formation in tuna (<italic>Thunnus albacares</italic>) at 2&#x000b0;C &#x02013; effect of vacuum- and modified atmosphere-packaging on psychrotolerant bacteria</article-title><source>Int J Food Microbiol</source><year>2005</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>263</fpage><lpage>279</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15925710</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b55"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ercolini</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changes in the spoilage-related microbiota of beef during refrigerated storage under different packaging conditions</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>4663</fpage><lpage>4671</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16820458</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b56"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Franz</surname><given-names>CMAP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of the genetic locus responsible for production and immunity of carnobacteriocin A: the immunity gene confers cross-protection to enterocin B</article-title><source>Microbiology</source><year>2000</year><volume>146</volume><fpage>621</fpage><lpage>631</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10746765</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b57"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Franzetti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Carnobacterium</italic> spp. in seafood packaged in modified atmosphere</article-title><source>Ann Microbiol</source><year>2003</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>189</fpage><lpage>198</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b58"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Franzmann</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Psychrotrophic, lactic acid-producing bacteria from anoxic waters in Ace Lake, Antartica; <italic>Carnobacterium funditum</italic> sp. nov. and <italic>Carnobacterium alterfunditum</italic> sp. nov</article-title><source>Archiv Microbiol</source><year>1991</year><volume>156</volume><fpage>255</fpage><lpage>262</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b59"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Galkin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cold-adapted alanine dehydrogenases from two Antarctic bacterial strains: gene cloning, protein characterization, and comparison with mesophilic amd thermophilic counterparts</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>1999</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>4014</fpage><lpage>4020</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10473410</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b60"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gildberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of supplementing the feed to Atlantic cod (<italic>Gadus morhua</italic>) fry with lactic acid bacteria and immuno-stimulating peptides during a challenge trial with <italic>Vibrio anguillarum</italic></article-title><source>Aquaculture</source><year>1998</year><volume>167</volume><fpage>103</fpage><lpage>113</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b61"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gildberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Growth and survival of Atlantic salmon (<italic>Salmo salar</italic>) fry given diets supplemented with fish protein hydrolysate and lactic acid bacteria during a challenge trial with <italic>Aeromonas salmonicida</italic></article-title><source>Aquaculture</source><year>1995</year><volume>138</volume><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>34</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b62"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gildberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Probiotic effect of lactic acid bacteria in the feed on growth and survival of fry of Atlantic cod (<italic>Gadus morhua</italic>)</article-title><source>Hydrobiologia</source><year>1997</year><volume>352</volume><fpage>279</fpage><lpage>285</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b63"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gilmore</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic structure of <italic>Enterococcus faecalis</italic> plasmid pAD1-encoded cytolytic toxin system and its relationship to lantibiotic determinants</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>1994</year><volume>176</volume><fpage>7335</fpage><lpage>7344</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7961506</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b64"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez</surname><given-names>C-J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bacterial microflora of wild brown trout (<italic>Salmo trutta</italic>), wild pike (<italic>Esox lucius</italic>), and aquacultured rainbow trout (<italic>Oncorhynchus mykiss</italic>)</article-title><source>J Food Prot</source><year>1999</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>1270</fpage><lpage>1277</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10571316</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b65"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization and identification of lactic acid bacteria from freshwater fishes</article-title><source>Food Microbiol</source><year>2000</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>383</fpage><lpage>391</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b66"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez-Rodr&#x000ed;guez</surname><given-names>M-N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Numbers and types of microorganisms in vacuum-packed cold-smoked freshwater fish at the retail level</article-title><source>Int J Food Microbiol</source><year>2002</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>161</fpage><lpage>168</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12076034</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b67"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gram</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Holzapfel</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prospects of fish probiotics</article-title><source>Microbial Ecology in Growing Animals</source><year>2005</year><publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name><fpage>379</fpage><lpage>417</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b68"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>IR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A numerical taxonomic study of lactic acid bacteria isolated from irradiated pork and chicken packaged under various gas atmospheres</article-title><source>J Appl Bacteriol</source><year>1991</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>302</fpage><lpage>307</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2055792</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b69"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gravesen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High-level resistance to class IIa bacteriocins is associated with one general mechanism in <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic></article-title><source>Microbiol</source><year>2002</year><volume>148</volume><fpage>2361</fpage><lpage>2369</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b70"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Groudieva</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diversity and cold-active hydrolytic enzymes of culturable bacteria associated with Arctic sea ice, Spitzbergen</article-title><source>Extremophiles</source><year>2004</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>475</fpage><lpage>488</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15252724</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b71"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guldager</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Thawed cod fillets spoil less rapidly than unfrozen fillets when stored under modified atmosphere at 2&#x000b0;C</article-title><source>J Food Prot</source><year>1998</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>1129</fpage><lpage>1136</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9766063</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b72"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gursky</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Production of piscicolin 126 by <italic>Carnobacterium maltaromaticum</italic> UAL26 is controlled by temperature and induction peptide concentration</article-title><source>Arch Microbiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>186</volume><fpage>317</fpage><lpage>325</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16927067</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b73"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hagi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diversity and seasonal changes in lactic acid bacteria in the intestinal tract of cultured freshwater fish</article-title><source>Aquaculture</source><year>2004</year><volume>234</volume><fpage>335</fpage><lpage>346</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b74"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hammes</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Dworkin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The genera <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> and <italic>Carnobacterium</italic></article-title><source>The Procaryotes: An Evolving Electronic Resource for the Microbiological Community</source><year>2003</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name><fpage>320</fpage><lpage>403</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b75"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herbin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characteristics and genetic determinants of bacteriocin activities produced by <italic>Carnobacterium piscicola</italic> CP5 isolated from cheese</article-title><source>Curr Microbiol</source><year>1997</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>319</fpage><lpage>326</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9353214</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b76"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Himelbloom</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Factors affecting production of an antilisterial bacteriocin by <italic>Carnobacterium piscicola</italic> strain A9b in laboratory media and model fish systems</article-title><source>J Appl Microbiol</source><year>2001</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>506</fpage><lpage>513</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11556917</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b77"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hirano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Free amino acids, trimethylamine oxide, and betaines of the raw and boiled meats of mantis shrimp <italic>Oratosquilla oratolia</italic></article-title><source>Nippon Suisan Gakkaishi</source><year>1992</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>973</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="b78"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hiu</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Lactobacillus piscicola</italic>, a new species from salmonid fish</article-title><source>Int J System Bacteriol</source><year>1984</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>393</fpage><lpage>400</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b79"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holck</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Purification and cloning of piscicolin-61, a bacteriocin from <italic>Carnobacterium piscicola</italic> LV61</article-title><source>Curr Microbiol</source><year>1994</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>63</fpage><lpage>68</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7764997</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b80"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holck</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Divergicin 750, a novel bacteriocin produced by <italic>Carnobacterium divergens</italic> 750</article-title><source>FEMS Microbiol Lett</source><year>1996</year><volume>136</volume><fpage>163</fpage><lpage>168</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8869500</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b81"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holley</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Carnobacterium viridans</italic> sp. nov., an alkaliphilic, facultative anaerobe isolated from refrigerated, vacuum-packed bologna sausage</article-title><source>Int J System Evol Microbiol</source><year>2002</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>1881</fpage><lpage>1885</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12361300</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b82"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Humphrey</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The disease status of Australian salmonids: bacteria and bacterial diseases</article-title><source>J Fish Dis</source><year>1987</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>403</fpage><lpage>410</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b83"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Irianto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Probiotics in aquaculture</article-title><source>J Fish Dis</source><year>2002</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>633</fpage><lpage>642</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b84"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jack</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of the chemical and antimicrobial properties of piscicolin 126, a bacteriocin produced by <italic>Carnobacterium piscicola</italic> JG126</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>1996</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>2897</fpage><lpage>2903</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8702282</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b85"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Limitations in the use of <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> as a model host for Gram positive bacterial infection</article-title><source>Lett Appl Microbiol</source><year>2007</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>218</fpage><lpage>223</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17257264</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b86"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jeppesen</surname><given-names>VF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characteristics and antagonistic activity of lactic acid bacteri isolated from chilled fish products</article-title><source>Int J Food Microbiol</source><year>1993</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>305</fpage><lpage>320</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8347429</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b87"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>J&#x000f6;born</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Colonization in the fish intestinal tract and production of inhibitory substances in intestinal mucus and faecal extracts by <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> sp. strain K1</article-title><source>J Fish Dis</source><year>1997</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>383</fpage><lpage>392</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b88"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>J&#x000f6;born</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Carnobacterium inhibens</italic> sp. nov., isolated from the intestine of Atlantic salmon (<italic>Salmo salar</italic>)</article-title><source>Int J System Bacteriol</source><year>1999</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>1891</fpage><lpage>1898</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10555373</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b89"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Joffraud</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterisation of volatile compounds produced by bacteria isolated from the spoilage flora of cold-smoked salmon</article-title><source>Int J Food Microbiol</source><year>2001</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>175</fpage><lpage>184</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11428576</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b90"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Joffraud</surname><given-names>J-J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of bacterial interactions on the spoilage of cold-smoked salmon</article-title><source>Int J Food Microbiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>112</volume><fpage>51</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16949172</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b91"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Observations on the succession dynamics of lactic acid bacteria populations in chill-stored vacuum-packaged beef</article-title><source>Int J Food Microbiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>273</fpage><lpage>282</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14751682</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b92"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>J&#x000f8;rgensen</surname><given-names>LV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of biogenic amine production by single bacterial cultures and metabiosis on cold-smoked salmon</article-title><source>J Appl Microbiol</source><year>2000</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>920</fpage><lpage>934</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11123465</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b93"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kabadjova</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differentiation of closely related <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> food isolates based on 16S&#x02013;23S ribosomal DNA intergenic spacer region polymorphism</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2002</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>5358</fpage><lpage>5366</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12406725</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b94"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Katayama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phylogenetic analysis of bacteria preserved in a permafrost ice wedge for 25 000 years</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2007</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>2360</fpage><lpage>2363</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17293514</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b95"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>D-H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cytokine expression in leucocytes and gut cells of rainbow trout, <italic>Oncorhynchus mykiss</italic> Walbaum, induced by probiotics</article-title><source>Vet Immun Immunopath</source><year>2006a</year><volume>114</volume><fpage>297</fpage><lpage>304</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b96"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>D-H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Innate immune responses in rainbow trout (<italic>Oncorhynchus mykiss</italic>, Walbaum) induced by probiotics</article-title><source>Fish Shellfish Immunol</source><year>2006b</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>513</fpage><lpage>524</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16631379</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b97"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kleerebezem</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A two-component signal-transduction cascade in <italic>Carnobacterium piscicola</italic> LV17B: two signaling peptides and one sensor-transmitter</article-title><source>Peptides</source><year>2001</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>1597</fpage><lpage>1601</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11587787</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b98"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Numerical phenetic study of the genus <italic>Carnobacterium</italic></article-title><source>Anton Leeuw</source><year>2000</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>85</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b99"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lakshmanan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of high-pressure processing on <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic>, spoilage microflora and multiple compound quality indices in chilled cold-smoked salmon</article-title><source>J Appl Microbiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>398</fpage><lpage>408</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14723701</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b100"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Larrouture</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ability of meat starter cultures to catabolize leucine and evaluation of the degradation products by using an HPLC method</article-title><source>Food Microbiol</source><year>2000</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>563</fpage><lpage>570</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b101"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Larrouture-Thiveyrat</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of environmental factors on leucine catabolism by <italic>Carnobacterium piscicola</italic></article-title><source>Int J Food Microbiol</source><year>2003</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>184</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12485743</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b102"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Larrouture-Thiveyrat</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of <italic>Carnobacterium piscicola</italic> on aroma formation in sausage mince</article-title><source>Meat Sci</source><year>2003</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>423</fpage><lpage>426</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b103"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lauro</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The unique 16S rRNA genes of piezophiles reflect both phylogeny and adaptation</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2007</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>838</fpage><lpage>845</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17158629</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b104"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laursen</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Carnobacterium divergens</italic> and <italic>Carnobacterium maltaromaticum</italic> as spoilers or protective cultures in meat and seafood: phenotypic and genotypic characterization</article-title><source>Syst Appl Microbiol</source><year>2005</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>151</fpage><lpage>164</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15830808</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b105"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laursen</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Carnobacterium</italic> species: effect of metabolic activity and interaction with <italic>Brochothrixthermosphacta</italic> on sensory characteristics of modified atmosphere packed shrimp</article-title><source>J Agric Food Chem</source><year>2006</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>3604</fpage><lpage>3611</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b106"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leblanc</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Luten</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of the prevailing flora of <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> ssp. growing on CO<sub>2</sub> modified atmosphere packaged rainbow trout (<italic>Oncorhynchus mykiss</italic>) fillets</article-title><source>Seafood from Producer to Consumer. Integrated Approach to Quality</source><year>1997</year><publisher-loc>Amsterdam</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name><fpage>445</fpage><lpage>454</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b107"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lebois</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of divercin V41 combined to NaCl content, phenol (liquid smoke) concentration and pH on <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic> Scott A growth in BHI broth by an experimental design approach</article-title><source>J Appl Microbiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>931</fpage><lpage>937</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15078508</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b108"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leisner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterisation of lactic acid bacteria isolated from lightly preserved fish products and their ability to metabolise various carbohydrates and amino acids</article-title><year>1992</year><publisher-loc>Copenhagen, Denmark</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Royal Veterinary and Agricultural University</publisher-name><comment>Ph.D. thesis</comment></citation></ref><ref id="b109"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leisner</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Production of histamine and tyramine by lactic acid bacteria isolated from vacuum-packed sugar-salted fish</article-title><source>J Appl Bacteriol</source><year>1994a</year><volume>76</volume><fpage>417</fpage><lpage>423</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8005830</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b110"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leisner</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Catabolism of arginine by <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> spp. isolated from vacuum-packed sugar-salted fish</article-title><source>Curr Microbiol</source><year>1994b</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>99</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b111"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leisner</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of growth of selected lactic acid bacteria on storage life of beef stored under vacuum and in air</article-title><source>Int J Food Microbiol</source><year>1995</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>231</fpage><lpage>243</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7577360</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b112"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leroi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of inoculation with lactic acid bacteria on extending the shelf-life of vacuum-packed cold smoked salmon</article-title><source>Int J Food Sci Technol</source><year>1996</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>497</fpage><lpage>504</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b113"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leroi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Study of the microbial ecology of cold-smoked salmon during storage at 8&#x000b0;C</article-title><source>Int J Food Microbiol</source><year>1998</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>121</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9562883</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b114"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lewus</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibition of food-borne bacterial pathogens by bacteriocins from lactic acid bacteria isolated from meat</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>1991</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>1683</fpage><lpage>1688</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1908209</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b115"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z-Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Marine sponge <italic>Craniella austrialiensis</italic>-associated bacterial diversity revelation based on 16S rDNA library and biologically active Actinomycetes screening, phylogenetic analysis</article-title><source>Lett Appl Microbiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>410</fpage><lpage>416</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16965372</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b116"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liolios</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The genomes on line database (GOLD) v.2: a monitor of genome projects worldwide</article-title><source>Nucl Acids Res</source><year>2006</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>D332</fpage><lpage>D334</lpage><comment>(Database issue)</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16381880</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b117"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lyhs</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The spoilage flora of vacuum-packaged, sodium nitrite or potassium nitrate treated, cold-smoked rainbow trout stored at 4&#x000b0;C or 8&#x000b0;C</article-title><source>Int J Food Microbiol</source><year>1998</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>135</fpage><lpage>142</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9924944</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b118"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lyhs</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of lactic acid bacteria from spoiled, vacuum-packaged &#x02018;gravad&#x02019; rainbow trout using ribotyping</article-title><source>Int J Food Microbiol</source><year>2002</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>147</fpage><lpage>153</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11843406</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b119"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Makarova</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolutionary genomics of lactic acid bacteria</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>2007</year><volume>189</volume><fpage>1199</fpage><lpage>1208</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17085562</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b120"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marquis</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Arginine deiminase system and bacterial adaptation to acid environments</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>1987</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>198</fpage><lpage>200</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3103530</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b121"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Masson</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Histamine and tyramine production by bacteria from meat products</article-title><source>Int J Food Microbiol</source><year>1996</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>199</fpage><lpage>207</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8880339</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b122"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Masson</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of physico-chemical factors influencing tyramine production by <italic>Carnobacterium divergens</italic></article-title><source>J Appl Microbiol</source><year>1997</year><volume>83</volume><fpage>36</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9246769</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b123"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Masson</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tyramine production by a strain of <italic>Carnobacterium divergens</italic> inoculated in meat &#x02013; fat mixture</article-title><source>Meat Sci</source><year>1999</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>69</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b124"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mauguin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of lactic acid bacteria isolated from seafood</article-title><source>J Appl Bacteriol</source><year>1994</year><volume>76</volume><fpage>616</fpage><lpage>625</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b125"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCabe</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dietary tyramine and other pressor amines in MAOI regimes: a review</article-title><source>J Am Diet Assoc</source><year>1986</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>1059</fpage><lpage>1064</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3525654</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b126"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McMeekin</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Information systems in food safety management</article-title><source>Int J Food Microbiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>112</volume><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>194</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16934895</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b127"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McMullen</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microbial ecology of fresh pork stored under modified atmosphere at &#x02212;1&#x000b0;C, 4.4&#x000b0;C and 10&#x000b0;C</article-title><source>Int J Food Microbiol</source><year>1993</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8466808</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b128"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meisel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Heme-dependent cytochrome formation in <italic>Lactobacillus maltaromicus</italic></article-title><source>Syst Appl Microbiol</source><year>1994</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>20</fpage><lpage>23</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b129"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mejlholm</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Shelf life and safety aspects of chilled cooked and peeled shrimps (<italic>Pandalus borealis</italic>) in modified atmosphere packaging</article-title><source>J Appl Microbiol</source><year>2005</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>66</fpage><lpage>76</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15960666</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b130"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>M&#x000e9;tivier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Divercin V41, a new bacteriocin with two disulphide bonds produced by <italic>Carnobacterium divergens</italic> V41: primary structure and genomic organization</article-title><source>Microbiology</source><year>1998</year><volume>144</volume><fpage>2837</fpage><lpage>2844</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9802025</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b131"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Michel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biochemical identification of <italic>Lactobacillus piscicola</italic> strains from France and Belgium</article-title><source>Dis Aquat Org</source><year>1986</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>30</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b132"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Michel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diversity of lactic acid bacteria associated with fish and the fish farm environment, established by amplified rDNA gene restriction analysis</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2007</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>2947</fpage><lpage>2955</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17337536</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b133"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>A</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Lactobacillus maltaromicus</italic>, a new species producing a malty aroma</article-title><source>Int J System Bacteriol</source><year>1974</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>346</fpage><lpage>354</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b134"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Milli&#x000e8;re</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Carnobacterium piscicola</italic>, a common species of French soft cheeses from cow's raw milk</article-title><source>Neth Milk Dairy J</source><year>1994</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>30</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b135"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Milli&#x000e8;re</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Presence of <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> spp. in French surface mould-ripened soft-cheese</article-title><source>J Appl Bacteriol</source><year>1994</year><volume>76</volume><fpage>264</fpage><lpage>269</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b136"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mora</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reclassification of <italic>Lactobacillus maltaromicus</italic> (Miller <italic>et al.</italic>, 1974) DSM 20342<sup>T</sup> and DSM 20344 and <italic>Carnobacterium piscicola</italic> (Collins <italic>et al.</italic>, 1987) DSM 20730<sup>T</sup> and DSM 20722 as <italic>Carnobacterium maltaromaticum</italic> comb. nov</article-title><source>Int J System Evol Microbiol</source><year>2003</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>675</fpage><lpage>678</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12807185</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b137"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morea</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular and physiological characterization of dominant bacterial populations in traditional Mozzarella cheese processing</article-title><source>J Appl Microbiol</source><year>1999</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>574</fpage><lpage>582</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10583686</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b138"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morzel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fermentation of salmon fillets with a variety of lactic acid bacteria</article-title><source>Food Res Int</source><year>1997</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>777</fpage><lpage>785</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b139"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Naghmouchi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiple characterizations of <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic> sensitive and insensitive variants to divergicin M35, a new pediocin-like bacteriocin</article-title><source>J Appl Microbiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>29</fpage><lpage>39</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16405682</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b140"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Naser</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phylogeny and identification of enterococci by <italic>atpA</italic> gene sequence analysis</article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol</source><year>2005</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>2224</fpage><lpage>2230</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15872246</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b141"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Naser</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Lactobacillus cypricasei</italic> Lawson <italic>et al.</italic> 2001 is a later heterotypic synonym of <italic>Lactobacillus acidipiscis</italic> Tanasupawat <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</article-title><source>Int J System Evol Microbiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>1681</fpage><lpage>1683</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16825650</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b142"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Whole genome comparisons of serotype 4b and 1/2a strains of the food-borne pathogen <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic> reveal new insights into the core genome components of this species</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>2386</fpage><lpage>2395</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15115801</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b143"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Newberry</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diversity of prokaryotes and methanogenesis in deep subsurface sediments from the Nankai Trough, Ocean Drilling Program Leg 190</article-title><source>Environ Microbiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>274</fpage><lpage>287</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14871211</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b144"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Growth control of <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic> on cold-smoked salmon using a competitive lactic acid bacteria flora</article-title><source>J Food Prot</source><year>1999</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>336</fpage><lpage>342</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10419205</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b145"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of acetate in production of an autoinducible class IIa bacteriocin in <italic>Carnobacterium piscicola</italic> A9b</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2002</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>2251</fpage><lpage>2260</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11976095</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b146"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The contribution of bacteriocin to inhibition of <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic> by <italic>Carnobacterium piscicola</italic> strains in cold-smoked salmon systems</article-title><source>J Appl Microbiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>143</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14678166</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b147"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Growth inhibition of <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic> by a nonbacteriocinogenic <italic>Carnobacterium piscicola</italic></article-title><source>J Appl Microbiol</source><year>2005</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>172</fpage><lpage>183</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15610430</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b148"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ntougias</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bacterial diversity in spent mushroom compost assessed by amplified rDNA restriction analysis and sequencing of cultivated isolates</article-title><source>Syst Appl Microbiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>746</fpage><lpage>754</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15612633</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b149"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microbiological quality of raw ground chicken processed at high isostatic pressure</article-title><source>J Food Prot</source><year>1996</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>146</fpage><lpage>150</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b150"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paarup</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sensory, chemical and bacteriological changes in vacuum-packed pressurised squid mantle (<italic>Todaropsis eblanae</italic>) stored at 4&#x000b0;C</article-title><source>Int J Food Microbiol</source><year>2002</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11929163</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b151"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paludan-M&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of the role of <italic>Carnobacterium piscicola</italic> in spoilage of vacuum- and modified-atmosphere-packed cold-smoked salmon stored at 5&#x000b0;C</article-title><source>Int J Food Microbiol</source><year>1998</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>155</fpage><lpage>166</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9553794</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b152"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Papon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Factors affecting growth and lipase production by meat lactobacilli strains and <italic>Brochothrix thermosphacta</italic></article-title><source>J Appl Bacteriol</source><year>1988</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>107</fpage><lpage>115</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3372396</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b153"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peirson</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aerococci and carnobacteria cause discoloration in cooked cured bologna</article-title><source>Food Microbiol</source><year>2003</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>158</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b154"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pikuta</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Carnobacterium pleistocenium</italic> sp. nov., a novel psychrotolerant, facultative anerobe isolated from permafrost of the Fox tunnel in Alaska</article-title><source>Int J System Evol Microbiol</source><year>2005</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>473</fpage><lpage>478</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15653921</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b155"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pilet</surname><given-names>M-F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence for two bacteriocins produced by <italic>Carnobacterium piscicola</italic> and <italic>Carnobacterium divergens</italic> isolated from fish and active against <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic></article-title><source>J Food Prot</source><year>1995</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>256</fpage><lpage>262</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b156"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pond</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of conventional and molecular techniques to investigate the intestinal microflora of rainbow trout (<italic>Oncorhynchus mykiss</italic>)</article-title><source>Aquaculture</source><year>2006</year><volume>261</volume><fpage>194</fpage><lpage>203</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b157"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quadri</surname><given-names>LEN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical and genetic characterization of bacteriocins produced by <italic>Carnobacterium piscicola</italic> LV17B</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1994</year><volume>269</volume><fpage>12204</fpage><lpage>12211</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8163526</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b158"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quadri</surname><given-names>LEN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of the protein conferring immunity to the antimicrobial peptide carnobacteriocin B2 and expression of carnobacteriocins B2 and BM1</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>1995</year><volume>177</volume><fpage>1144</fpage><lpage>1151</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7868585</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b159"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quadri</surname><given-names>LEN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of amino acid substitutions on the activity of carnobacteriocin B2</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1997a</year><volume>272</volume><fpage>3384</fpage><lpage>3388</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9013580</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b160"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quadri</surname><given-names>LEN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of a locus from <italic>Carnobacterium piscicola</italic> LV17B involved in bacteriocin production and immunity: evidence for global inducer-mediated transcriptional regulation</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>1997b</year><volume>179</volume><fpage>6163</fpage><lpage>6171</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9324267</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b161"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rachman</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> species by restriction fragment length polymorphism of the 16S&#x02013;23S rRNA gene intergenic spacer region and species-specific PCR</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>4468</fpage><lpage>4477</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15294774</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b162"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Richard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence on inhibition of <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic> by divercin V41 action</article-title><source>Lett Appl Microbiol</source><year>2003</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>288</fpage><lpage>292</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12680940</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b163"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ring&#x000f8;</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of diet on aerobic bacterial flora associated with intestine of Arctic charr (<italic>Salvelinus alpinus</italic> L.)</article-title><source>J Appl Microbiol</source><year>1999</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>22</fpage><lpage>28</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10030010</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b164"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ring&#x000f8;</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification and characterization of carnobacteria associated with the gills of Atlantic salmon (<italic>Salmo salar</italic> L.)</article-title><source>Syst Appl Microbiol</source><year>2000</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>523</fpage><lpage>527</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11249022</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b165"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ring&#x000f8;</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of dietary fatty acids on lactic acid bacteria associated with the epithelial mucosa and from faecalia of Arctic charr, <italic>Salvelinus alpinus</italic> (L.)</article-title><source>J Appl Microbiol</source><year>1998</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>855</fpage><lpage>864</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9830121</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b166"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ring&#x000f8;</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lactic acid bacteria associated with the digestive tract of Atlantic salmon (<italic>Salmo salar</italic> L.)</article-title><source>J Appl Microbiol</source><year>2000</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>317</fpage><lpage>322</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10971765</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b167"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ring&#x000f8;</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification and characterization of carnobacteria isolated from fish intestine</article-title><source>Syst Appl Microbiol</source><year>2001</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>183</fpage><lpage>191</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11518321</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b168"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ring&#x000f8;</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of <italic>Carnobacterium divergens</italic> strain 6251 isolated from intestine of Arctic charr (<italic>Salvelinus alpinus</italic> L.)</article-title><source>Syst Appl Microbiol</source><year>2002a</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>120</fpage><lpage>129</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b169"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ring&#x000f8;</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of soybean, linseed and marine oils on aerobic gut microflora of Arctic charr (<italic>Salvelinus alpinus</italic> L.) before and after challenge with <italic>Aeromonas salmonicida</italic> spp. <italic>salmonicida</italic></article-title><source>Aquaculture Res</source><year>2002b</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>591</fpage><lpage>606</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b170"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ring&#x000f8;</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Holzapfel</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial activity of lactic acid bacteria isolated from aquatic animals and the use of lactic acid bacteria in aquaculture</article-title><source>Microbial Ecology in Growing Animals</source><year>2005</year><publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name><fpage>418</fpage><lpage>453</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b171"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ring&#x000f8;</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterisation of the microbiota associated with intestine of Atlantic cod (<italic>Gadus morhua</italic> L.). The effect of fish meal, standard soybean meal and a bioprocessed soybean meal</article-title><source>Aquaculture</source><year>2006</year><volume>261</volume><fpage>829</fpage><lpage>841</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b172"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ring&#x000f8;</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Histological changes in intestine of Atlantic salmon (<italic>Salmo salar</italic> L.) following <italic>in vitro</italic> exposure to pathogenic and probiotic bacterial strains</article-title><source>Cell Tissue Res</source><year>2007</year><volume>328</volume><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>116</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17120052</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b173"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>PAW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> sp. as a probiotic for Atlantic salmon (<italic>Salmo salar</italic> L.) and rainbow trout (<italic>Oncorhynchus mykiss</italic>, Walbaum)</article-title><source>Aquaculture</source><year>2000</year><volume>185</volume><fpage>235</fpage><lpage>243</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b174"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rohde</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional characterization of a three-component regulatory system involved in quorum sensing-based regulation of peptide antibiotic production in <italic>Carnobacterium maltaromaticum</italic></article-title><source>BMC Microbiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>93</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17054797</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b175"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roller</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Novel combinations of chitosan, carnocin and sulphite for the preservation of chilled pork sausages</article-title><source>Meat Sci</source><year>2002</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>165</fpage><lpage>177</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b176"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rudi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Explorative multivariate analyses of 16S rDNA gene data from microbial communities in modified-atmosphere-packed salmon and coalfish</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>5010</fpage><lpage>5018</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15294842</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b177"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sakala</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Change in the composition of the microflora on vacuum-packaged beef during chiller storage</article-title><source>Int J Food Microbiol</source><year>2002</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>87</fpage><lpage>99</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11929174</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b178"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Samelis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Blackburn</surname><given-names>C de W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Managing microbial spoilage in the meat industry</article-title><source>Food Spoilage Microorganisms</source><year>2006</year><publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Woodhead Publishing Limited</publisher-name><fpage>213</fpage><lpage>286</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b179"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Samelis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of the extent and type of bacterial contamination at different stages of processing of cooked ham</article-title><source>J Appl Microbiol</source><year>1998</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>649</fpage><lpage>660</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9633662</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b180"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Samelis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The spoilage microflora of cured, cooked turkey breasts prepared commercially with or without smoking</article-title><source>Int J Food Microbiol</source><year>2000</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>143</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10857539</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b181"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saucier</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Induction of bacteriocin in <italic>Carnobacterium piscicola</italic> LV17</article-title><source>J Appl Bacteriol</source><year>1995</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>684</fpage><lpage>690</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b182"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schillinger</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of lactobacilli from meat and meat products</article-title><source>Food Microbiol</source><year>1987</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>199</fpage><lpage>208</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b183"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schillinger</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>BJB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The genus <italic>Carnobacterium</italic></article-title><source>The Genera of Lactic Acid Bacteria</source><year>1995</year><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Blackie Academic &#x00026; Professional</publisher-name><fpage>307</fpage><lpage>326</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b184"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bacterial diversity in permanently cold and alkaline ikaite columns from Greenland</article-title><source>Extremophiles</source><year>2006</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>551</fpage><lpage>562</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16770690</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b185"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sch&#x000f6;bitz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A bacteriocin from <italic>Carnobacterium piscicola</italic> for the control of <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic> in vacuum-packaged meat</article-title><source>Food Microbiol</source><year>1999</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>249</fpage><lpage>255</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b186"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seppola</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Random amplification of polymorphic DNA (RAPD) typing of carnobacteria isolated from hindgut chamber and large intestine of Atlantic cod (<italic>Gadus morhua</italic> l)</article-title><source>Syst Appl Microbiol</source><year>2005</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>137</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16464694</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b187"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shannon</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of lactic acid bacteria in the larval midgut of the keratinophagous lepidopteran <italic>Hofmannophila pseudospretella</italic></article-title><source>Lett Appl Microbiol</source><year>2001</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>36</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11169039</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b188"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A numerical taxonomic study of lactic acid bacteria from vacuum-packed beef, pork, lamb and bacon</article-title><source>J Appl Bacteriol</source><year>1984</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6706886</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b189"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Signoretto</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Persistence of <italic>Enterococcus faecalis</italic> in aquatic environments via surface interactions with copepods</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2005</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>2756</fpage><lpage>2761</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15870369</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b190"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bacteriocin production by spray-dried lactic acid bacteria</article-title><source>Lett Appl Microbiol</source><year>2002</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11849498</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b191"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment of equine fecal contamination: the search for alternative bacterial source-tracking targets</article-title><source>FEMS Microbiol Ecol</source><year>2004</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>75</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b192"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sip</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enhancement of bacteriocin production by <italic>Carnobacterium divergens</italic> AS7 in the presence of a bacteriocin-sensitive strain <italic>Carnobacterium piscicola</italic></article-title><source>Int J Food Microbiol</source><year>1998</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>63</fpage><lpage>69</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9706799</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b193"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smit</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Flavour formation by lactic acid bacteria and biochemical flavour profiling of cheese products</article-title><source>FEMS Microbiol Rev</source><year>2005</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>591</fpage><lpage>610</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15935512</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b194"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spanggaard</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The probiotic potential against vibriosis of the indigenous microflora of rainbow trout</article-title><source>Environ Microbiol</source><year>2001</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>755</fpage><lpage>765</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11846769</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b195"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sprules</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>NMR solution structure of the precursor for carnobacteriocin B2, an antimicrobial peptide from <italic>Carnobacterium piscicola</italic>. Implications of the &#x003b1;-helical leader section for export and inhibition of type IIa bacteriocin activity</article-title><source>Eur J Biochem</source><year>2004a</year><volume>271</volume><fpage>1748</fpage><lpage>1756</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15096213</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b196"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sprules</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>NMR solution structure of imB2, a protein conferring immunity to antimicrobial activity of the type IIa bacteriocin, carnobacteriocin B2</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>2004b</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>11740</fpage><lpage>11749</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15362858</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b197"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Starliper</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation of <italic>Carnobacterium piscicola</italic> and an unidentified Gram-positive bacillus from sexually mature and post-spawning rainbow trout <italic>Oncorhynchus mykiss</italic></article-title><source>Dis Aquat Org</source><year>1992</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>187</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b198"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stoffels</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation and properties of a bacteriocin-producing <italic>Carnobacterium piscicola</italic> isolated from fish</article-title><source>J Appl Bacteriol</source><year>1992a</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>309</fpage><lpage>316</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1429307</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b199"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stoffels</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Purification and characterization of a new bacteriocin isolated from a <italic>Carnobacterium</italic> sp</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>1992b</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>1417</fpage><lpage>1422</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1622206</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b200"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stohr</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spoilage potential and sensory profile associated with bacteria isolated from cold-smoked salmon</article-title><source>Food Res Int</source><year>2001</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>797</fpage><lpage>806</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b201"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Susiluoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Leuconostoc gasicomitatum</italic> is the dominating lactic acid bacterium in retail modified-atmosphere-packaged marinated broiler meat strips on sell-by-day</article-title><source>Int J Food Microbiol</source><year>2003</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>97</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12430775</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b202"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mode of action of piscicocin CS526 produced by <italic>Carnobacterium piscicola</italic> CS526</article-title><source>J Appl Microbiol</source><year>2005</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>1146</fpage><lpage>1151</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15836484</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b203"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tahiri</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Purification, characterization and amino acid sequencing of divergicin M35: a novel class IIa bacteriocin produced by <italic>Carnobacterium divergens</italic> M35</article-title><source>Int J Food Microbiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>136</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15541799</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b204"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Talon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Growth and effect of staphylococci and lactic acid bacteria on unsaturated free fatty acids</article-title><source>Meat Sci</source><year>2000</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>47</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b205"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thornley</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Observations on the microflora of minced chicken meat irradiated with 4 MeV cathode rays</article-title><source>J Appl Bacteriol</source><year>1957</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>286</fpage><lpage>298</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b206"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thornley</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Micro-organisms from chicken meat related to both lactobacilli and aerobic sporeformers</article-title><source>J Appl Bacteriol</source><year>1959</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>368</fpage><lpage>376</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b207"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Toffin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular monitoring of culturable bacteria from deep-sea sediment of the Nankai Trough, Leg 190 Ocean Drilling Program</article-title><source>FEMS Microbiol Ecol</source><year>2004</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>357</fpage><lpage>367</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b208"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Toranzo</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An epizootic in farmed, market-size rainbow trout in Spain caused by a strain of <italic>Carnobacterium piscicola</italic> of unusual virulence</article-title><source>Dis Aquat Org</source><year>1993a</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>87</fpage><lpage>99</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b209"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Toranzo</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Histopathology of rainbow trout, <italic>Oncorhynchus mykiss</italic> (Walbaum), and striped bass, <italic>Morone saxatilis</italic> (Walbaum), experimentally infected with <italic>Carnobacterium piscicola</italic></article-title><source>J Fish Dis</source><year>1993b</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>261</fpage><lpage>267</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b210"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Truelstrup Hansen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of the microflora isolated from spoiled cold-smoked salmon from three smokehouses</article-title><source>Food Res Int</source><year>1998</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>703</fpage><lpage>711</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b211"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Belkum</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of the theta-type plasmid pCD3.4 from <italic>Carnobacterium divergens</italic>, and modulation of its host range by repA mutation</article-title><source>Microbiology</source><year>2006</year><volume>152</volume><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>178</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16385127</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b212"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vermeiren</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The interaction of the non-bacteriocinogenic <italic>Lactobacillus sakei</italic> 10A and lactocin S producing <italic>Lactobacillus sakei</italic> 148 towards <italic>Listeia monocytogenes</italic> on a model cooked ham</article-title><source>Food Microbiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>511</fpage><lpage>518</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16943045</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b213"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vihavainen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of broiler carcasses and processing plant air in contamination of modified-atmosphere-packaged broiler products with psychrotrophic lactic acid bacteria</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2007</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>1136</fpage><lpage>1145</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17142357</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b214"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Freeze &#x02013; thaw tolerance and clues to the winter survival of a soil community</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>1784</fpage><lpage>1792</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16517623</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b215"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibition of <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic> by piscicolin 126 in milk and Camembert cheese manufactured with a thermophilic starter</article-title><source>J Appl Microbiol</source><year>1997</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>273</fpage><lpage>280</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12455889</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b216"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Solution structure of carnobacteriocin B2 and implications for structure&#x02013;activity relationships among type IIa bacteriocins from lactic acid bacteria</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>1999</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>15438</fpage><lpage>15447</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10569926</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b217"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Worobo</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characteristics and genetic determinant of a hydrophobic peptide bacteriocin, carnobacteriocin A, produced by <italic>Carnobacterium piscicola</italic> LV17A</article-title><source>Microbiology</source><year>1994</year><volume>140</volume><fpage>517</fpage><lpage>526</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8012574</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b218"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Worobo</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A signal peptide secretion-dependent bacteriocin from <italic>Carnobacterium divergens</italic></article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>1995</year><volume>177</volume><fpage>3143</fpage><lpage>3149</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7768812</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b219"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Etiological study for a case of multi-bacterial synergistic gangrene</article-title><source>Chinese Sci Bull</source><year>1997</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>511</fpage><lpage>517</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b220"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamazaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibition of <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic> in cold-smoked salmon by <italic>Carnobacterium piscicola</italic> CS526 isolated from frozen surimi</article-title><source>J Food Prot</source><year>2003</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>1420</fpage><lpage>1425</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12929829</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b221"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamazaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Purification and characterization of a novel class IIa bacteriocin, piscicocin CS526, from surimi-associated <italic>Carnobacterium piscicola</italic> CS526</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2005</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>554</fpage><lpage>557</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15640235</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b222"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yousif</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> evidence for the antibacterial role of lysozyme in salmonid eggs</article-title><source>Dis Aquat Org</source><year>1994</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>19</lpage></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>





