<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Microbiol.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Microbiology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-302X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27486455</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4949237</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2016.01135</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Microbiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Exploring the Diversity and Antimicrobial Potential of Marine Actinobacteria from the Comau Fjord in Northern Patagonia, Chile</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Undabarrena</surname><given-names>Agustina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/360171/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Beltrametti</surname><given-names>Fabrizio</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Claver&#x000ed;as</surname><given-names>Fernanda P.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/255744/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez</surname><given-names>Myriam</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>Edward R. B.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/25731/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Seeger</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>C&#x000e1;mara</surname><given-names>Beatriz</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/187474/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Laboratorio de Microbiolog&#x000ed;a Molecular y Biotecnolog&#x000ed;a Ambiental, Departamento de Qu&#x000ed;mica &#x00026; Centro de Biotecnolog&#x000ed;a Daniel Alkalay Lowitt, Universidad T&#x000e9;cnica Federico Santa Mar&#x000ed;a</institution><country>Valpara&#x000ed;so, Chile</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Actygea S.r.l.</institution><country>Gerenzano, Italy</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Culture Collection University of Gothenburg (CCUG), Sahlgrenska Academy, University of Gothenburg</institution><country>Gothenburg, Sweden</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup><institution>Department of Infectious Diseases, Sahlgrenska Academy, University of Gothenburg</institution><country>Gothenburg, Sweden</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Learn-Han Lee, Monash University Malaysia Campus, Malaysia</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Atte Von Wright, University of Eastern Finland, Finland; Polpass Arul Jose, Central Salt and Marine Chemicals Research Institute, India</p></fn><corresp id="fn001">*Correspondence: Beatriz C&#x000e1;mara <email xlink:type="simple">beatriz.camara@usm.cl</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn002"><p>This article was submitted to Antimicrobials, Resistance and Chemotherapy, a section of the journal Frontiers in Microbiology</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>7</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>1135</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>5</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>07</day><month>7</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2016 Undabarrena, Beltrametti, Claver&#x000ed;as, Gonz&#x000e1;lez, Moore, Seeger and C&#x000e1;mara.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Undabarrena, Beltrametti, Claver&#x000ed;as, Gonz&#x000e1;lez, Moore, Seeger and C&#x000e1;mara</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) or licensor are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Bioprospecting natural products in marine bacteria from fjord environments are attractive due to their unique geographical features. Although, <italic>Actinobacteria</italic> are well known for producing a myriad of bioactive compounds, investigations regarding fjord-derived marine <italic>Actinobacteria</italic> are scarce. In this study, the diversity and biotechnological potential of <italic>Actinobacteria</italic> isolated from marine sediments within the Comau fjord, in Northern Chilean Patagonia, were assessed by culture-based approaches. The 16S rRNA gene sequences revealed that members phylogenetically related to the <italic>Micrococcaceae, Dermabacteraceae, Brevibacteriaceae, Corynebacteriaceae, Microbacteriaceae, Dietziaceae, Nocardiaceae</italic>, and <italic>Streptomycetaceae</italic> families were present at the Comau fjord. A high diversity of cultivable <italic>Actinobacteria</italic> (10 genera) was retrieved by using only five different isolation media. Four isolates belonging to <italic>Arthrobacter, Brevibacterium, Corynebacterium</italic> and <italic>Kocuria</italic> genera showed 16S rRNA gene identity &#x0003c;98.7% suggesting that they are novel species. Physiological features such as salt tolerance, artificial sea water requirement, growth temperature, pigmentation and antimicrobial activity were evaluated. <italic>Arthrobacter, Brachybacterium, Curtobacterium, Rhodococcus</italic>, and <italic>Streptomyces</italic> isolates showed strong inhibition against both Gram-negative <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa, Escherichia coli</italic> and <italic>Salmonella enterica</italic> and Gram-positive <italic>Staphylococcus aureus, Listeria monocytogenes</italic>. Antimicrobial activities in <italic>Brachybacterium, Curtobacterium</italic>, and <italic>Rhodococcus</italic> have been scarcely reported, suggesting that non-mycelial strains are a suitable source of bioactive compounds. In addition, all strains bear at least one of the biosynthetic genes coding for NRPS (91%), PKS I (18%), and PKS II (73%). Our results indicate that the Comau fjord is a promising source of novel <italic>Actinobacteria</italic> with biotechnological potential for producing biologically active compounds.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>cultivable actinobacteria</kwd><kwd>antimicrobial activity</kwd><kwd>Comau fjord</kwd><kwd>marine sediments</kwd><kwd>Northern Patagonia</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn001">Fondo Nacional de Desarrollo Cient&#x000ed;fico y Tecnol&#x000f3;gico<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/501100002850</named-content></funding-source><award-id rid="cn001">11121571 (BC)</award-id><award-id rid="cn001">PhD fellowship (AU), Gastos Operacionales 21120621 (AU)</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn002">Vetenskapsr&#x000e5;det<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/501100004359</named-content></funding-source><award-id rid="cn002">2013-6713</award-id></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="6"/><table-count count="4"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="104"/><page-count count="16"/><word-count count="10351"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>The increased prevalence of multi-drug resistance pathogens along with the rapid development of cross resistances with new antibiotics is the driving force in the identification and production of novel therapeutic agents (Livermore, <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). All classes of antibiotics have seen emergence of resistance compromising their use; hence there is an urgent need for new bioactive compounds (Genilloud, <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). The traditional approach consisting of isolation and cultivation of new microorganisms of underexplored habitats is still rewarding (Axenov-Gribanov et al., <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>), and has brought to the identification, production and commercialization of most of the antibiotics (Newman and Cragg, <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). Despite the chemically synthetic efforts, natural environments are still the main source for the discovery of novel antibiotics (Fenical and Jensen, <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Bull and Stach, <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). Although, the diversity of life in terrestrial environments is well reported, the highest biodiversity is in the world's oceans (Donia and Hamann, <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>). Oceans are strongly complex habitats in terms of pressure, salinity and temperature variations (Fenical, <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">1993</xref>), therefore marine microorganisms have to develop physiological traits including chemically complex biosynthesized metabolites to ensure their survival in this highly dynamic habitat. Research has taken advantage from these unique molecules to discover novel bioactive compounds with antibacterial, antifungal and/or antitumor properties, and apply them in current clinical challenges (Gulder and Moore, <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>).</p><p>In this scenario, bacteria from the <italic>phylum Actinobacteria</italic> are a prominent source of biologically active natural compounds, since they are well known for their capacity to biosynthesize versatile secondary metabolites (Katz and Baltz, <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). Actinobacteria are one of the major phyla of the domain <italic>Bacteria</italic> (Goodfellow and Fiedler, <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). It encompasses high GC-content Gram-positive bacteria that includes 17 orders (Gao and Gupta, <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Sen et al., <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Surprisingly, the class <italic>Actinobacteria</italic> contains both the most deadly bacterial pathogen (i.e., <italic>Mycobacterium</italic> genus) and the microorganisms that are the most important for antibiotic production (i.e., <italic>Streptomyces</italic> genus) (Doroghazi and Metcalf, <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). <italic>Streptomyces</italic> are responsible for two-thirds of all known antibiotics. In addition, several other important biologically-active compounds have been found, including antitumoral, antifungal, herbicidal, and antiparasitic compounds (B&#x000e9;rdy, <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>). Due to the extensive sampling of soil <italic>Streptomyces</italic>, the rate of discovery of novel metabolites is decreasing (Fenical, <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">1993</xref>), which is the reason why bioprospecting efforts are currently being developed in marine underexplored ecosystems.</p><p>Marine environments are an established ecological niche for actinobacteria (Das et al., <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Ward and Bora, <xref rid="B97" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). Cultivable actinobacteria from marine habitats have been characterized from mangrove forests (Hong et al., <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Baskaran et al., <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Lee et al., <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">2014a</xref>,<xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">b</xref>; Ser et al., <xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>, <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>), marine sponges (Kim et al., <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Montalvo et al., <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Zhang et al., <xref rid="B101" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Jiang et al., <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Sun et al., <xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>), corals (Hodges et al., <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Kuang et al., <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Mahmoud and Kalendar, <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Pham et al., <xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>), sea cucumbers (Kurahashi et al., <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>), pufferfishes (Wu et al., <xref rid="B99" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>), and seaweed (Lee et al., <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). Notably, actinobacteria are predominant in marine sediments (Mincer et al., <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>; Magarvey et al., <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>; Jensen et al., <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Bredholdt et al., <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Gontang et al., <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Le&#x000f3;n et al., <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Maldonado et al., <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Duncan et al., <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Yuan et al., <xref rid="B100" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>) and also in deep sea sediments (Colquhoun et al., <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">1998</xref>; Pathom-Aree et al., <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). Marine actinobacteria have been described as an emerging source for novel bioactive molecules (Lam, <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Joint et al., <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Subramani and Aalbersberg, <xref rid="B91" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Zotchev, <xref rid="B103" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). The majority of these secondary metabolites are produced by polyketide synthases (PKS) and non-ribosomal peptide synthetases (NRPS) metabolic pathways (Salomon et al., <xref rid="B82" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>). Notably, it is reported that actinobacteria have a higher number of these biosynthetic genes (Donadio et al., <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>).</p><p>The extensive coast of Chile is a promising biome to explore marine actinobacterial communities, and in this context, the bioprospecting of sediments of a marine protected area, the Comau fjord, in the Chilean Northern Patagonia was proposed. The Comau fjord is a pristine area unique by its geological nature. It is comparatively smaller than other fjords in Chile, and also one of the deepest (Ugalde et al., <xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>); characterized by steep slopes, with surrounding mountains that have a height of up to 2000 m with a dense extratropical rainforest covering from the sea to the top (Lagger et al., <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). The aim of this study was to isolate marine actinobacteria from this unique ecosystem. The cultivable diversity of actinobacterial strains along with their environmental adaptation traits was investigated, and their ability to produce antibacterial activity against model strains was assessed.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials and methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec><title>Environmental samples</title><p>Sampling was performed in the Marine Protected Area of Huinay in January 2013, located in the Commune of Hualaihu&#x000e9;, in the Los Lagos Region, Chile. Samples were collected from marine sediments within the Comau Fjord in the Northern Patagonia. Four different coastal locations were sampled in front of Lilihuapi Island (42&#x000b0;20, 634&#x02032;S; 72&#x000b0;27, 429&#x02032;W), Tambor Waterfall (42&#x000b0;24, 161&#x02032;S; 72&#x000b0;25, 235&#x02032;W), Punta Llonco (42&#x000b0;22, 32&#x02032;S; 72&#x000b0;25, 4&#x02032;W), and in front of Lloncochaigua River mouth (42&#x000b0;22, 37&#x02032;S; 72&#x000b0;27, 25&#x02032;W) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). Underwater samples were collected by Huinay Scientific Field Station scuba divers, dispensing samples directly from marine sediments into sterile 50 mL tubes. Marine sediments were taken from subtidal zones at different depths, ranging from 0.25 to 26.2 m. Salinity was measured at each sampling site, and ranged from 5 &#x003bc;g L<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> in the coast in front of Lloncochaigua River mouth, where there is a meaningful input of fresh water, to 31 &#x003bc;g L<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> in the coast of Lilihuapi Island, located further away from continental land. Samples were maintained on ice until transported to the laboratory, where they were stored at 4&#x000b0;C.</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Geography of sampling sites for actinobacteria isolation from the Comau fjord in Northern Patagonia, Chile</bold>. Map of sampling locations within the Comau fjord (Los Lagos Region). Numbers indicate the sites where marine sediments were collected at the coast close to: Lilihuapi Island (1), Punta Llonco (2), Lloncochaigua River mouth (3), and Tambor Waterfall (4). Black dot indicates location of the Huinay Scientific Field Station.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-07-01135-g0001"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Isolation of actinobacteria</title><p>Samples were both plated directly or serially diluted (10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup> and 10<sup>&#x02212;6</sup>) before plating on selective media for the isolation of actinobacteria. Five selective media were used as previously reported (Claver&#x000ed;as et al., <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>): M1 Agar (Mincer et al., <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>), ISP2 and NaST21Cx Agar (Magarvey et al., <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>), R2A Agar (Difco), and Marine Agar (MA) 2216 (Difco). All media were amended with nalidixic acid (25 &#x003bc;g mL<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), as an inhibitor of primarily fast-growing Gram-negative bacteria, and cycloheximide (100 &#x003bc;g mL<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) for fungi inhibition [28]. All media with the exception of Marine Agar, were prepared with artificial sea water (ASW) (Kester et al., <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">1967</xref>). The agar media cultures were incubated at 30&#x000b0;C until visible colonies were observed, up to 1&#x02013;2 months. For isolation purposes, colonies were individually streaked out onto Tryptic Soy Agar medium (TSA) prepared with ASW (TSA-ASW) and eventually transferred on new plates until pure cultures were obtained. Isolated bacteria were stored at &#x02212;20 and &#x02212;80&#x000b0;C, in 20% glycerol, TSB medium and ASW for maintenance.</p></sec><sec><title>Detection and identification of actinobacteria</title><p>A PCR-assay was conducted as a screening method for detecting actinobacterial strains among the isolates with primers targeting the V3&#x02013;V5 regions of the 16S rRNA gene of actinobacteria (S-C-Act-0235-a-S-20 and S-C-Act-0878-A-19) (Stach et al., <xref rid="B89" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>). DNA extractions were performed, using a lysis method by culture boiling suspensions of bacterial cells (Moore et al., <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>). Each PCR reaction contained 1 &#x003bc;L of genomic DNA, 12.5 &#x003bc;L of GoTaq Green Master Mix (Promega) and 0.6 &#x003bc;M of each primer in a final reaction volume of 25 &#x003bc;L. The reaction started with an initial denaturation, at 95&#x000b0;C for 5 min, followed by 35 cycles of DNA denaturation, at 95&#x000b0;C for 1 min, primer-annealing, at 70&#x000b0;C for 1 min and extension cycle, at 72&#x000b0;C for 1.5 min, with a final extension at 72&#x000b0;C for 10 min (Claver&#x000ed;as et al., <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). PCR-amplicons were visualized in 2% agarose gel electrophoresis and subsequently revealed with SYBR Green staining (E-gel, Invitrogen).</p><p>Positive isolates were selected for 16S rRNA gene amplification, using universal primers 27F and 1492R (Lane, <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">1991</xref>). The reaction mix (50 &#x003bc;L) contained 1 &#x003bc;L of genomic DNA, 25 &#x003bc;L of GoTaq Green Master Mix (Promega) and 0.2 &#x003bc;M of each primer. The reaction started with an initial DNA denaturation at 95&#x000b0;C for 5 min, followed by 30 cycles of denaturation at 95&#x000b0;C for 1 min, primer-annealing at 55&#x000b0;C for 1 min and primer-extension at 72&#x000b0;C for 1.5 min, with a final extension at 72&#x000b0;C for 10 min. PCR products were sent to Macrogen Inc. (Seoul, Korea) for purification and sequencing using the conserved universal primer 800R. Retrieved sequences were manually edited and BLAST nucleotide analyses were performed with the National Center for Biotechnology Information server (NCBI) and actinobacteria were initially identified up to the genus level.</p></sec><sec><title>Antimicrobial activity tests</title><p>Bioprospecting for antimicrobial activity was initially performed using the cross-streak method as described (Haber and Ilan, <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>), with slight modifications (Claver&#x000ed;as et al., <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). Fresh cultures of the isolated actinobacterial strains were inoculated as a line in the middle of an agar medium plate and incubated at 30&#x000b0;C until notable growth was observed (7 days for mycelial strains and 5 days for non-mycelial strains). Strains were grown on TSA-ASW and ISP2-ASW media. Five reference bacteria were the target of inhibition tests: <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> NBRC 100910<sup>T</sup> (STAU); <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic> 07PF0776 (LIMO); <italic>Salmonella enterica</italic> subsp enterica LT2<sup>T</sup> (SAEN); <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> FAP1 (ESCO) and <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> DSM50071<sup>T</sup> (PSAU). Cultures were incubated at 37&#x000b0;C overnight and inhibition zones were ranked qualitatively as: &#x02212;, no inhibition; +/&#x02212;, attenuated growth of test strain in the area closest to the actinobacterial line; +, &#x0003c;50% growth inhibition (less than half of the bacterial line was inhibited); ++, 50% growth inhibition (half of the bacterial line was inhibited); +++, &#x0003e;50% growth inhibition (more than half of the bacterial line was inhibited). All experiments were performed in duplicate, using an internal control with one of the reference strains.</p><p>Further antimicrobial tests were performed with selected isolates <italic>Streptomyces</italic> sp. H-KF8, <italic>Arthrobacter</italic> sp. H-JH3, <italic>Brevibacterium</italic> sp. H-BE7, <italic>Kocuria</italic> sp. H-KB5 and <italic>Rhodococcus</italic> sp. H-CA8f. Strains were grown in a 50 mL liquid culture in ISP2-ASW medium for 10 days for non-mycelial strains and 15 days for the mycelial strain, with continuous shaking at 30&#x000b0;C. Crude extracts were obtained after solvent extraction using hexane, methanol and ethyl acetate in a 1:1 ratio (v/v) for two times. Evaporation of solvent was performed with speed vacuum, and extract was dissolved in 10% dimethyl sulphoxide (DMSO) until a final concentration of 5 mg mL<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. Antimicrobial assays were evaluated using 10 &#x003bc;L of each extract, over LB agar plates spread with the bacterial test strains STAU, PSAU, SAEN, and ESCO. Plates were incubated overnight at 37&#x000b0;C and inhibitions zones were checked. ISP2 medium and 10% DMSO were used as negative controls.</p></sec><sec><title>Detection of PKS and NRPS biosynthetic genes</title><p>Amplification of biosynthetic genes was carried out by PCR, using degenerate primers targeting the ketosynthase domain in PKS type I with primers KS-F (5&#x02032;CCSCAGSAGCGCSTS YTSCTSGA3&#x02032;) and KS-R (5&#x02032;GTSCCSGTSCCGTGSGYS TCSA3&#x02032;) (Gontang et al., <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>); and PKS type II with primers KS&#x003b1; (5&#x02032;TSGRCTACRTCA ACGGSCACGG3&#x02032;) and KS&#x003b2; (5&#x02032;TACSAGTCS WTC GCCTGGTTC3&#x02032;) (Ayuso et al., <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>). The adenylation domain in NRPS systems was detected with primers A3F (5&#x02032;GCSTACSYSATSTAC ACSTCSGG3&#x02032;) and A7R (5&#x02032;SASGTCVCCSGTS CGGTAS3&#x02032;) (Ayuso-Sacido and Genilloud, <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>). PCR programs were performed as previously described (Ayuso et al., <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Ayuso-Sacido and Genilloud, <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Gontang et al., <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). Products were visualized in 1% agarose gels electrophoresis, and stained with GelRed (Biotium). <italic>Streptomyces violeaceoruber</italic> DSM 40783 was used as a control for all PCR reactions. Detection was determined as +, if the amplicon was located at the expected size (700 bp for PKS type I; 800&#x02013;900 bp for PKS type II and 700&#x02013;800 bp for NRPS); and &#x02212;, if amplicon was absent or it was present at any other size.</p></sec><sec><title>Phylogenetic analysis</title><p>Representative strains for each genus identified from partial 16S rRNA gene sequence analyses were selected for the nearly-complete sequencing of this gene, as previously described (Claver&#x000ed;as et al., <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). PCR products were quantified and sent to Macrogen Inc. (Seoul, Korea) for purification and sequencing, using primers 27F, 518F, 800R, and 1492R. Manual sequence edition, alignment, and contig assembling were performed using Vector NTI v10 software package (Invitrogen). Sequence contigs were analyzed performing BLAST with NCBI to determine the closest type strain match using the 16S ribosomal RNA sequence of Bacteria and Archaea database. The Neighbor-Joining algorithm (Saitou and Nei, <xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr">1987</xref>) using MEGA software version 6.0 (Tamura et al., <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>) with bootstrap values based on 1000 replications (Felsenstein, <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">1985</xref>) was used to construct a phylogenetic tree based on the V1-V9 region of the 16S rRNA gene sequences. The 16S rRNA gene sequences were deposited in GenBank under the following accession numbers: <italic>Arthrobacter</italic> sp. H-JH3 (<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KT799841">KT799841</ext-link>); <italic>Brachybacterium</italic> sp. H-CG1 (<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KT799842">KT799842</ext-link>); <italic>Brevibacterium</italic> sp. H-BE7 (<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KT799843">KT799843</ext-link>); <italic>Corynebacterium</italic> sp. H-EH3 (<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KT799844">KT799844</ext-link>); <italic>Curtobacterium</italic> sp. H-ED12 (<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KT799845">KT799845</ext-link>); <italic>Kocuria</italic> sp. H-KB5 (<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KT799846">KT799846</ext-link>); <italic>Dietzia</italic> sp. H-KA4 (<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KT799847">KT799847</ext-link>); <italic>Micrococcus</italic> sp. H-CD9b (<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KT799848">KT799848</ext-link>); <italic>Rhodococcus</italic> sp. H-CA8f (<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KT799849">KT799849</ext-link>); <italic>Streptomyces</italic> sp. H-KF8 (<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KT799850">KT799850</ext-link>) and <italic>Streptomyces</italic> sp. H-CB3 (<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KT799851">KT799851</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec><title>Phenotypic characterization of actinobacterial strains</title><p>For the morphological and physiological characterization of the representative strains, colony pigmentation, spore formation, growth temperatures, ASW requirement and NaCl tolerance were evaluated. Optimal colony pigmentation was observed on TSA-ASW after a 3-month incubation at 4&#x000b0;C. To establish the effects of temperature on growth, 10 &#x003bc;L of actinobacterial cultures were streaked onto TSA-ASW plates, and incubated at 4, 20, 30, 37, and 45&#x000b0;C. For NaCl tolerance, LB agar with 0, 1, 3.5, 5.0, 7.0, 10, and 20% (w/v) NaCl was prepared. As described previously, 10 &#x003bc;L of the actinobacterial cultures were streaked onto LB agar plates and incubated at 30&#x000b0;C. To detect the requirement of seawater on growth, ISP2 was prepared as follows: medium with Milli-Q H<sub>2</sub>O; medium with ASW; and medium with Milli-Q H<sub>2</sub>O supplemented with 3.5% (w/v) NaCl (equivalent to ASW NaCl concentration). Incubation times were from 10 days (for non-mycelial strains) to 14 days (for mycelial stains) at 30&#x000b0;C. The reference time for growth was that on which growth was observed on control plates. Results were interpreted as: +, if the strain tested was able to grow on medium-ASW but did not grow on medium/Milli-Q H<sub>2</sub>O and on medium/Milli-Q H<sub>2</sub>O supplemented with 3.5% NaCl; and &#x02212;, if the strain tested was able to grow on all three media.</p></sec><sec><title>Resistance to model antibiotics</title><p>Representative strains of each genus were grown to exponential phase (turbidity at 600 nm of 0.3) and plated on Mueller-Hinton agar plates for antibiotic susceptibility testing. Antibiotic discs for Gram-positive bacteria (Valtek) were placed above and inhibition grown zones as diameters were measured and compared with values obtained from the Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute (CLSI) from year 2016 to determine susceptibility (S), or resistance (R) of each antibiotic tested.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Isolation and identification of actinobacteria</title><p>Eleven marine sediment samples were collected from four different sites in Comau fjord, Northern Patagonia, Chile (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). Altogether 25 marine actinobacteria were isolated. Their distribution according to the sampling site was: 40% from Lilihuapi island coast, 28% from Punta Llonco, and 16% from Loncohaigua river mouth and Tambor waterfall, each. The majority (80%) of the isolates were from sediments situated approximately 10 m deep. Only occasional isolates were obtained from deeper sediments or from the shallow locations. The <italic>Actinobacteria</italic> isolated belong to three suborders: <italic>Streptomycineae, Micrococcineae</italic>, and <italic>Corynebcaterineae</italic>; comprising eight different families. Relative abundances of the strains according to the genera isolated (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A</xref>) indicated that most abundant genera were <italic>Kocuria</italic> and <italic>Brachybacterium</italic>. The selective media had a major influence on the number of isolates obtained (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B</xref>). M1-ASW medium was the most effective regarding the number and diversity of isolates recovered. Interestingly, strains of <italic>Brachybacterium, Brevibacterium, Micrococcus</italic>, and <italic>Rhodococcus</italic> genera were isolated exclusively with this medium (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B</xref>).</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Biodiversity of actinobacteria from the Comau fjord in Northern Patagonia. (A)</bold> Distribution of the relative abundance of the actinobacterial genera isolated. <bold>(B)</bold> Number of actinobacteria of various genera isolated using different culture media.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-07-01135-g0002"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Antimicrobial activity assays</title><p>Our first approach was to screen all actinobacterial strains for antimicrobial activity, using the cross-streak method, against five reference strains: STAU, LIMO, PSAU, SAEN, and ESCO (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref>). Actinobacterial strains showed antimicrobial activity, presenting a broad spectrum of inhibition although with different inhibition patterns (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). Inhibition of reference strains largely depended on the media where actinobacterial strains were cultivated, proving TSA-ASW to be generally better for antimicrobial activity than ISP2-ASW medium. <italic>Arthrobacter, Brachybacterium, Curtobacterium</italic>, and <italic>Rhodococcus</italic> isolates showed potent antimicrobial bioactivity to more than one target (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). Regarding the Gram-negative bacteria tested, TSA-ASW-grown actinobacterial strains were able to inhibit ESCO (84%) and PSAU (24%); whereas ISP2-ASW-grown isolates inhibited up to 76 and 48%, respectively. Concerning the Gram-positive reference strains, 64% of the TSA-ASW-grown actinobacterial strains inhibited both LIMO and STAU; whereas ISP2-ASW-grown strains, 56% showed inhibition for LIMO and 36% for STAU (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref>).</p><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>Antimicrobial activity of actinobacterial strains from the Comau fjord in Northern Patagonia. (A)</bold> Cross-streak method of <italic>Rhodococcus</italic> sp. H-CA8f showing different patterns of inhibition zones with several model bacteria. <bold>(B)</bold> Antimicrobial activity of actinobacterial strains using the cross-streak method. STAU, <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>; LIMO, <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic>; PSAU, <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>; SAEN, <italic>Salmonella enterica</italic>; ESCO, <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>. I, ISP2-ASW media; T, TSA-ASW media.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-07-01135-g0003"/></fig><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><bold>Antimicrobial activity of actinobacterial strains against model pathogens using the cross-streak method</bold>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Strain</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Genus</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><bold>STAU</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><bold>LIMO</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><bold>PSAU</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><bold>SAEN</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><bold>ESCO</bold></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>ISP2</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>TSA</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>ISP2</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>TSA</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>ISP2</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>TSA</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>ISP2</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>TSA</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>ISP2</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>TSA</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H-CA8b</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Arthrobacter</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+++</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+++</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+++</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+++</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">++</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">++</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H-JH1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Arthrobacter</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">++</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H-JH3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Arthrobacter</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">++</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H-CA4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Brachybacterium</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+++</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">++</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+++</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H-CD1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Brachybacterium</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+++</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H-CE9</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Brachybacterium</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">++</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">++</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H-CF1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Brachybacterium</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">++</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">++</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">++</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H-CG1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Brachybacterium</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+++</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H-BE7</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Brevibacterium</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">++</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H-EH3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Corynebacterium</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+++</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H-KF5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Corynebacterium</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H-BE10</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Curtobacterium</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+++</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+++</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+++</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">++</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+++</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">++</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H-CD9a</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Curtobacterium</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H-ED12</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Curtobacterium</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">++</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">++</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">++</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H-KA4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Dietzia</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H-KA9</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Kocuria</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H-KA10</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Kocuria</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+++</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H-KB1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Kocuria</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H-KB5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Kocuria</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H-KB6</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Kocuria</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+++</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H-JH7</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Kocuria</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H-CD9b</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Microccocus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+++</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H-CA8f</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Rhodococcus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">++</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">++</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+++</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+++</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+++</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+++</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+++</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+++</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+++</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H-CB3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Streptomyces</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+++</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+++</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">++</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H-KF8</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Streptomyces</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+++</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+++</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>&#x02212;, no inhibition; +/&#x02212;, attenuated growth; +, &#x0003c;50% growth inhibition; ++, 50% growth inhibition; +++, &#x0003e;50% growth inhibition. Both media were prepared with ASW.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Notably, 67% of the antimicrobial activities observed with the cross-streak method were retrieved with various solvent extractions from actinobacterial liquid cultures (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). Ethyl acetate was more effective in extracting active compounds, as crude extracts from <italic>Rhodococcus</italic> sp. H-CA8f, <italic>Kocuria</italic> sp. H-KB5 and <italic>Brevibacterium</italic> sp. H-BE7 presented antimicrobial activity. On the other hand, antimicrobial activity from <italic>Arthrobacter</italic> sp. H-JH3 was effectively extracted from the cell pellet using methanol. Crude extracts from <italic>Rhodococcus</italic> sp. H-CA8f showed an antimicrobial effect against all bacteria tested, confirming results obtained from the cross-streak method.</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><bold>Antimicrobial activities of crude extracts using various solvents for selected actinobacterial isolates grown in ISP2-ASW medium</bold>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Strain</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Solvent</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="4" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><bold>Bacterial Test Strain</bold></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>STAU</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PSAU</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>SAEN</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>ESCO</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H-KF8</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hexane</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethyl acetate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Methanol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H-CA8f</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hexane</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethyl acetate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Methanol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H-KB5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hexane</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethyl acetate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Methanol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H-JH3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hexane</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethyl acetate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Methanol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H-BE7</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hexane</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethyl acetate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Methanol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Detection of PKS and NRPS biosynthetic genes</title><p>The presence of biosynthetic PKS (type I and II) and NRPS genes were detected by PCR in representative actinobacterial isolates (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>). Interestingly, most isolates bear at least one biosynthetic gene of PKS or NRPS. Among them, NRPS was the predominant gene observed (91%), followed by PKS type II (73%). Only 18% of actinobacterial isolates showed the presence of PKS type I gene.</p><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><bold>Biogeographic and physiological characteristics of representative actinobacterial strains</bold>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Strain</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Closest Type Strain (Accession N&#x000b0;) (% Identity)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="4" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><bold>Biogeographic Characteristics</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="4" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><bold>Physiological Characteristics</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="3" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><bold>Biosynthetic genes</bold></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sampling Site</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Depth (m)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Salinity (ppt)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sediment characteristics</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Temperature (&#x000b0;C)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Salinity (%NaCl)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>ASW Requirement</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Pigmentation</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PKS I</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PKS II</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>NRPS</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H-JH3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Arthrobacter oxydans</italic> DSM 20119<sup>T</sup> (X83408) (98,26)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lilihuapi Island</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shells and sponges</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4&#x02013;37</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bright cream</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H-CG1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Brachybacterium paraconglomeratum</italic> JCM 17781<sup>T</sup> (AB645761) (99.16)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tambor Waterfall</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hard sediment</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4&#x02013;37</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bright yellow</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H-BE7</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Brevibacterium oceani</italic> BBH7<sup>T</sup> (AM158906) (97.94)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Punta Llonco</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good water visibility</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4&#x02013;37</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bright orange</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H-EH3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Corynebacterium pilbarense</italic> IMMIB WACC-658<sup>T</sup> (FN295567) (98.10)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Loncochaigua River</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low tide</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20&#x02013;37</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bright cream</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H-ED12</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Curtobacterium oceanosedimentum</italic> ATCC 31317<sup>T</sup> (GU269547) (99.02)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Punta Llonco</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good water visibility</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20&#x02013;45</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pale cream</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H-KB5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Kocuria polaris</italic> CMS 76or<sup>T</sup> (NR028924)(96.97)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Loncochaigua River</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low tide</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4&#x02013;37</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bright pink</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H-KA4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Dietzia natronolimnaea</italic> DSM 444860<sup>T</sup> (FJ468329) (99.06)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tambor Waterfall</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sand, mussels and sea urchins</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4&#x02013;37</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intense orange</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H-jCD9b</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Micrococcus luteus</italic> NCTC 2665<sup>T</sup> (CP001628) (99.15)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Punta Llonco</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shells, poor water visibility</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20&#x02013;37</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Light yellow</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H-CA8f</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Rhodococcus jianlingiae</italic> djl-6-2<sup>T</sup> (DQ185597) (98.84)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lilihuapi Island</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.9</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shells and old nets</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4&#x02013;30</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Light pink</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H-KF8</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Streptomyces prasinus</italic> NRRL B-2712<sup>T</sup> (DQ026658) (99.92)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Punta Llonco</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shells, poor water visibility</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4&#x02013;37</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">White mycelium</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H-CB3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Streptomyces prasinus</italic> NRRL B-2712<sup>T</sup> (DQ026658) (99.86)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tambor Waterfall</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sand, mussels and sea urchins</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4&#x02013;37</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">White mycelium</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Phylogenetic analysis</title><p>For phylogenetic analysis, the 16S rRNA gene was sequenced for selected actinobacterial isolates, representatives of each genus retrieved in sediment samples from Comau fjord. A dendogram of the estimated phylogenetic relationships is presented in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref> and the sequence similarities of selected actinobacterial strains to type strains of related species are given in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>. Four of the actinobacterial isolates are below the 98.7% sequence identity threshold and therefore may be potential candidates of new taxons. These isolates belong to <italic>Arthrobacter</italic> and <italic>Kocuria</italic> genera (<italic>Micrococcaceae</italic> family), <italic>Brevibacterium</italic> genus (<italic>Brevibacteriaceae</italic> family), and <italic>Corynebacterium</italic> genus (<italic>Corynebacteriaceae</italic> family) (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>). Interestingly, the psychrotolerant isolate <italic>Kocuria</italic> sp. H-KB5 has a 96.97% sequence identity with the type strain <italic>K. polaris</italic> CMS 76 or<sup>T</sup>, a strain isolated from an Antarctic cyanobacterial mat sample (Reddy et al., <xref rid="B78" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>). Moreover, strain H-KB5 forms a separate branch within the <italic>Kocuria</italic> group in the phylogenetic tree (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). This isolate will be further characterized in a polyphasic approach to determine its taxonomic position.</p><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><bold>Phylogenetic tree of representative actinobacterial strains isolated from the Comau fjord in Northern Patagonia, Chile</bold>. Neighbour-joining tree of 16S rRNA gene showing the three suborders within the <italic>phylum Actinobacteria</italic>. Node numbers represent the percentage of bootstrap replicates (1000 resampling) which supported the proposed branching order shown at consistent nodes (values below 50% were not shown). Gene sequence positions 55&#x02013;1410 were considered, according to the <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> K12 (AP012306) 16S rRNA gene sequence numbering. Arrow points to the outgroup <italic>E. coli</italic> K12. GenBank accession numbers of 16S rRNA sequences are given in parentheses. Scale bar corresponds to 0.01 substitutions per nucleotide positions.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-07-01135-g0004"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Phenotypic characterization of isolated actinobacterial strains</title><p>The Comau fjord is characterized by defined zoning patterns of strong vertical and horizontal salinity gradients. The first 15 m underwater are influenced by waters of low salinity (~1.0%). Below this depth, a halocline is found that produces a constant water salinity of 3.2% (Castillo et al., <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). In order to analyze how the salinity affects the growth of the actinobacterial isolates, NaCl tolerance was determined for each strain (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>). 82% of the representative isolates were able to grow in the presence of 1.0, 3.5, 5.0, and 7.0% (w/v) NaCl (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>). 45% of the strains, belonging to <italic>Arthrobacter, Brachybacterium, Brevibacterium, Curtobacterium</italic>, and <italic>Kocuria</italic> genera, were able to grow in presence of 10% (w/v) NaCl (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>). None of the isolated actinobacteria was able to grow with 20% w/v NaCl.</p><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><bold>NaCl effect on actinobacterial growth</bold>. Upper panel: <bold>(A)</bold> Distribution of actinobacterial isolates and their ability to grow in LB medium with various percentages of NaCl. Bottom panel: As an example, the halophilic <italic>Brevibacterium</italic> sp. H-BE7 grown in LB medium containing: <bold>(B)</bold> 3.5%; <bold>(C)</bold> 5%; and <bold>(D)</bold> 10% NaCl concentrations.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-07-01135-g0005"/></fig><p>To study adaptation to marine environments, actinobacterial strains were tested for ASW requirement. Most strains (73%), belonging to <italic>Arthrobacter, Brachybacterium, Corynebacterium, Dietzia, Kocuria, Rhodococcus</italic>, and <italic>Streptomyces</italic> genera were positively influenced by sea water as they required ASW for growth, suggesting marine adaptation. Interestingly, strain <italic>Brevibacterium</italic> sp. H-BE7, showed improved growth with both ASW and 3.5% NaCl, rather than with Milli-Q H<sub>2</sub>O and 0% NaCl, suggesting a specific salt requirement confirmed by its growth in 10% (w/v) NaCl (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B&#x02013;D</xref>).</p><p>As the Comau fjord deep-waters reach temperatures below 10&#x000b0;C, actinobacterial strains were tested for growth at different temperatures. Notably, 73% of strains belonging to <italic>Arthrobacter, Brachybacterium, Brevibacterium, Kocuria, Dietzia</italic>, and <italic>Rhodococcus</italic>, and to a lesser extent, <italic>Streptomyces</italic>, were able to grow at 4&#x000b0;C (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>). Moreover, pigmentation of the colonies was more intense after growth at 4&#x000b0;C, in comparison to 30&#x000b0;C (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6B&#x02013;D</xref>). Colony pigmentation of all representative actinobacteria was visualized macroscopically and detailed in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>.</p><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><bold>Temperature effect on actinobacterial growth</bold>. Upper panel: <bold>(A)</bold> Distribution of actinobacterial isolates and their ability to grow in different temperatures. Bottom panel: As an example, actinobacterial strains grown in TSA-ASW medium at either 30&#x000b0;C (left) or 4&#x000b0;C (right), showing differences in pigmentations. <bold>(B)</bold>
<italic>Dietzia</italic> sp. H-KA4; <bold>(C)</bold>
<italic>Kocuria</italic> sp. H-KB5; <bold>(D)</bold>
<italic>Brachybacterium</italic> sp. H-CG1.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-07-01135-g0006"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Resistance to model antibiotics</title><p>Antibiogram experiments demonstrated that all isolated actinobacterial strains are resistant to at least one of the antibiotics tested. Furthermore, these isolates showed resistance to several antibiotics of different classes. Interestingly, strains H-JH3, H-BE7, H-KA4, H-CD9, H-CG1, H-ED12, and H-CA8f showed resistances to &#x02265;6 antibiotics, wherein resistance to tetracycline, ciprofloxacin and oxacyllin were observed for all the actinobacterial strains. Strain H-KA4 and H- ED12 showed resistance to all antibiotics tested, whereas strain H-BE7 was susceptible only for sulfonamides (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T4" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p><bold>Antibiotic resistance of selected actinobacterial strains</bold>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Antibiotic</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Class</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="11" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><bold>Huinay Isolates</bold></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>H-JH3</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>H-CG1</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>H-BE7</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>H-EH3</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>H-ED12</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>H-KB5</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>H-KA4</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>H-CD9</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>H-CA8f</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>H-KF8</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>H-CB3</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Penicillin (10 UOF)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b2;-Lactam</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NG</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloramphenicol (30 &#x003bc;g)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tetracycline (30 &#x003bc;g)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poliketide</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oxacyllin (1 &#x003bc;g)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b2;-Lactam</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Erythromycin (15 &#x003bc;g)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Macrolide</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clindamycin (2 &#x003bc;g)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lincosamides</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sulfa-Trimethroprim (25 &#x003bc;g)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sulfonamide</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ciprofloxacin (5 &#x003bc;g)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fluoro-quinolone</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cefazolin (30 &#x003bc;g)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cephalosporin (1st)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gentamicin (10 &#x003bc;g)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aminoglycoside</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>NG, No growth; R, Resistant; S, Susceptible.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>Marine actinomycetes isolated from the National Marine Protected Area of Huinay at the Comau fjord in Northern Patagonia were studied, along with their physiological and taxonomic properties, and their potential to produce antimicrobial compounds. Patagonian fjords are largely unexplored, and may provide a rich source of microorganisms producing novel anti-infective compounds. This is the first bioprospection report of cultivable actinobacteria in this unique ecosystem, where 25 actinobacteria were isolated and characterized. Two studies report the isolation of marine actinobacteria from sediments of Chile's vast coast; one from Chilo&#x000e9; Island (Hong et al., <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>) and a recent study performed in Valpara&#x000ed;so Central Bay (Claver&#x000ed;as et al., <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). Only a metagenomic study has been carried out with a microbial mat located in the Comau fjord, revealing that 1% of community reads was represented by the <italic>phylum Actinobacteria</italic> (Ugalde et al., <xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>).</p><p>In this study, a lower abundance of actinobacteria associated to marine sediments was observed compared to Valpara&#x000ed;so Bay where actinobacterial strains belonging to 18 genera were isolated, using the same cultivating conditions (Claver&#x000ed;as et al., <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). Although, members of the <italic>Rhodococcus</italic> and <italic>Dietzia</italic> genera were successfully isolated from the Comau fjord, they were less represented (8%) than in Valparaiso Bay (33%). The lower actinobacterial abundance in Comau fjord could be due to the lower content of organic matter in this microhabitat that can range between 0.5 and 3.4% of organic carbon content for Northern Chilean Patagonian fjords (Sep&#x000fa;lveda et al., <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). Gram-positive bacteria are more commonly observed in organic rich habitats (Fenical, <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">1993</xref>). Water samples from Valpara&#x000ed;so Bay are influenced by contamination with polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons as well as with heavy metals (Campos et al., <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">1987</xref>; Palma-Fleming et al., <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Fuentes et al., <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). It can also be influenced by hydrographic features such as seasonal upwelling which can supply nutrients to shallow waters (Capone and Hutchins, <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). In contrast, the Comau fjord has a high precipitation rate that provides a fresh water input (Silva, <xref rid="B87" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>) which can affect microorganisms in marine sediments. The four sites from Comau fjord have minimal anthropogenic intervention, thereof changes in microbial communities are given almost exclusively by natural processes.</p><p>Despite the fact that a relatively low number of actinobacterial strains were retrieved from Comau fjord, a rather high cultivable biodiversity (10 genera) was observed using 5 isolation media. In comparison, the actinobacteria isolated using 11 selective media from the Trondheim fjord (Norway) belonged to 12 genera (Bredholdt et al., <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). Also, in a culture-dependent study using sediments collected near Chilo&#x000e9; Island, Chile, five genera were retrieved using 7 media, being dominant the <italic>Micromonospora</italic> genus (Hong et al., <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). Although, no <italic>Micromonospora</italic> members have been isolated in this work, this could be due to the different isolation media used. In this report, 24% of isolates were obtained from NaST21Cx medium, which is derived from ST21Cx medium by elimination of yeast extract and replacement of artificial sea water (Magarvey et al., <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>). It has been reported that media composed of relatively simple nutrients yielded more cultured actinobacteria in diverse environments (Zhang et al., <xref rid="B101" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Gontang et al., <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Qin et al., <xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). This is consistent with the negligible amount of nutrients that are actually available for marine actinobacteria within hostile ocean ecosystems (Das et al., <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). This is the case for our study since more isolates were obtained with media containing low nutrients or complex carbon sources rather than common media constituents such as peptone and simple sugars, which are proposed to be unrealistic marine nutrients (Kurtb&#x000f6;ke et al., <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). In this study, the major abundance of actinobacteria was found in deeper samples, which is in accordance with that observed in the Trondheim fjord (Hakv&#x000e5;g et al., <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). Moreover, an elevated number (73%) of isolates showed an ASW requirement for growth. Evidence of isolation of seawater-dependent actinobacteria from marine sediments has been reported (Mincer et al., <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>; Maldonado et al., <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>). The fact that growth of some isolates is positively influenced by sea water can be an indicator that suggests they might be well adapted to the marine environments (Bredholdt et al., <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Penn and Jensen, <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Yuan et al., <xref rid="B100" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Nevertheless, since isolates obtained from Comau fjord can also grow without NaCl, they represent novel moderate halotolerant features in actinobacteria from this pristine sampling zone. This is consistent with the fact that these isolates have to overcome the dynamics of strong salinity gradients observed within the Comau fjord.</p><p>Reports of marine actinomycetes as a source of novel secondary bioactive metabolites have been extensively recognized (Haefner, <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>; Knight et al., <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>; Fiedler et al., <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Fenical and Jensen, <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Zhang et al., <xref rid="B101" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Gulder and Moore, <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Kurtb&#x000f6;ke et al., <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). Two screenings for antimicrobial activities were pursued in this report, and notably, inhibition of the growth of at least one of the model bacteria was observed. It is noteworthy to highlight that antimicrobial activities from non-mycelial strain (e.g., <italic>Rhodococcus</italic> sp. H-CA8f) outcompete the activities of mycelial-type strains. To our knowledge, this is the first report of strong antibacterial activities associated to a <italic>Rhodococcus</italic> isolated from marine sediments. The <italic>Rhodococcus</italic> strain isolated in this study has a strong activity (&#x0003e;50% growth inhibition) against <italic>E. coli, S. enterica, P. aeruginosa</italic>, and <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic>; whereas a <italic>Rhodococcus</italic> strain isolated from Valpara&#x000ed;so Bay sediments (Claver&#x000ed;as et al., <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>) had only a modest activity against <italic>E. coli</italic>. Antimicrobial activity from marine-derived isolates, but not necessarily from sediments, includes a <italic>Rhodococcus</italic> isolated from South China Sea corals that presented activity against <italic>B. subtilis, B. thuringiensis</italic>, and <italic>E. coli</italic> (Zhang et al., <xref rid="B102" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>), whereas <italic>Rhodococcus</italic> strains isolated from corals of the Arabian Gulf showed activity against <italic>S. aureus</italic> (Mahmoud and Kalendar, <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). In this study, antimicrobial activity of <italic>Arthrobacter</italic> sp. H-JH3 against <italic>S. enterica</italic> and <italic>E. coli</italic> is highlighted by its novelty. In this line, there are reports about antarctic <italic>Arthrobacter</italic> strains isolated from sponges that were able to inhibit the growth of <italic>Burkholderia cepacia</italic> complex by the production of volatile organic compounds (Fondi et al., <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Orlandini et al., <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Also, antimicrobial activity against <italic>Vibrio anguillarum</italic> and <italic>S. aureus</italic> was detected from samples collected from the Arctic Ocean (Wietz et al., <xref rid="B98" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). Interestingly, this is the first report indicating growth inhibition of Gram-negative strains by a <italic>Brevibacterium</italic> isolate. Only a bacteriocin able to inhibit <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic>, but inactive against Gram-negative was reported for this genus (Motta and Brandelli, <xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>). In contrast, antimicrobial activity against <italic>S. enterica</italic> was observed in crude extracts, suggesting a different mode of action.</p><p>It has been reported that most natural products with interesting biological activities are synthesized by PKS (type I or type II), NRPS, and even PKS-NRPS hybrid pathways (Fischbach and Walsh, <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). Some pharmacologically commercial examples include the polyketide antibiotic erythromycin (Staunton and Wilkinson, <xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">1997</xref>) and the non-ribosomal peptide antibiotic of the cephalosporin family (Aharonowitz and Cohen, <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1992</xref>). In this report, a PCR-based screening was pursued for the detection of these biosynthetic genes in actinobacterial isolates, in order to explore the potential to produce secondary metabolites with biotechnological applications. Notably, 91% of the isolates tested showed the presence of at least one of the three biosynthetic genes, which confirms that these metabolic pathways are widely distributed among this <italic>phylum</italic> (Donadio et al., <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). As molecular methods for analyzing these genes are useful for screening of isolates for prediction of potential bioactive molecule production (Hodges et al., <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>), future efforts will be focused in sequencing these biosynthetic genes, to gain knowledge of the novelty of the bioproducts in which they are involved in.</p><p>The marine habitat sampled in the Northern Patagonia of Chile was a promising scenario to search for novel actinobacterial strains. In this study, four putative new species are proposed: <italic>Arthrobacter</italic> sp. H-JH3, <italic>Brevibacterium</italic> sp. H-BE7, <italic>Corynebacterium</italic> sp. H-EH3 and <italic>Kocuria</italic> sp. H-KB5, based on numerical thresholds related to 16S rRNA gene sequences (Rossell&#x000f3;-M&#x000f3;ra and Amann, <xref rid="B80" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). In addition, representatives of <italic>Micrococcineae, Corynebacterineae</italic>, and <italic>Streptomycineae</italic> suborders were isolated. Interestingly, actinobacterial isolates showed sequence similarity with strains reported from colder habitats. 73% of the isolates belonging to <italic>Arthrobacter, Brachybacterium, Brevibacterium, Kocuria, Dietzia, Rhodococcus</italic>, and <italic>Streptomyces</italic> genera were able to grow at 4&#x000b0;C, suggesting a psychrotolerant adaptation which is in accordance with the water body temperature range of the Comau fjord (Lagger et al., <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Sobarzo, <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>), sustaining a thermohaline circulation (Bustamante, <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). A difference in colony pigmentation was observed at low temperatures. Pigments can be enhanced under specific conditions such as climate stress, since they are part of the non-enzymatic antioxidant mechanisms in cell defense to prevent oxidative damage (Correa-Llant&#x000e9;n et al., <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). Another role of pigments in response to cold is to decrease the membrane fluidity to counterbalance the effects of fatty acids in Antarctic bacteria (Chattopadhyay, <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). Pigments can also contribute to antibacterial activity, positioning them as interesting biotechnological candidates for food, cosmetic and textile industries (Rashid et al., <xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Leiva et al., <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>).</p><p>Comparison with 16S ribosomal RNA sequences Bacteria and Archaea NCBI database, reveals only two closest type strains of marine origin: <italic>Brevibacterium oceani</italic> BBH7<sup>T</sup> isolated from deep sea sediment of the Indian Ocean (Bhadra et al., <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>) and <italic>Curtobacterium oceanosedimentum</italic> ATCC 31317<sup>T</sup> isolated from Irish sea marine sediments (Kim et al., <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). In contrast, when sequences are compared with NCBI nucleotide collection database, actinobacterial isolates showed more similarity with polar marine isolates. This is the case for the psychrotolerant <italic>Arthrobacter</italic> sp. H-JH3, which showed a 98.82% identity with <italic>A. scleromae</italic> Asd M4-11 (Vardhan Reddy et al., <xref rid="B95" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>), a bacterium isolated from a melt water stream of an Arctic glacier. The psychrotolerant <italic>Brachybacterium</italic> sp. H-CG1 showed a high similarity (99.16%) with <italic>B. articum</italic> Lact 5.2 (Acc. Number: AF434185, unpublished), a bacterium isolated from a sea-ice sample from the permanently cold fjord of Wijde fjord, Spitzbergen, in the Arctic Ocean. Another interesting relation is given for strain H-CD9b from the genus <italic>Micrococcus</italic>, which has a 99.15% of sequence identity with the type strain <italic>M. luteus</italic> NCTC 2665<sup><italic>T</italic></sup> (Rokem et al., <xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>) that is a soil metal resistant bacterium, and a slightly more sequence identity (99.43%) with <italic>Micrococcus</italic> sp. strain MOLA4 (Acc. Number: CP001628, unpublished) a bacterium isolated from sea water of North Western Mediterranean Sea. Also, strain H-CA8f, showed a higher sequence similarity (98.91%) to <italic>Rhodococcus</italic> sp. TMT4-41 isolated from a glacier in China (Acc. Number: JX949806, unpublished) than to its closest type strain <italic>R. jialingiae</italic> djl-6-2<sup>T</sup> (Wang et al., <xref rid="B96" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>).</p><p>Antibiogram experiments demonstrated that, in general, actinobacterial strains showed resistance. Interestingly, <italic>Curtobacterium</italic> sp. H-ED12, <italic>Dietzia</italic> sp. H-KA4 and <italic>Brevibacterium</italic> sp. H-BE7 showed resistance to almost all antibiotics tested, possibly due to the presence of multiple biosynthetic clusters, involving different classes of antibiotic compounds. Strains H-BE7 and H-ED12 inhibited both Gram-positive and Gram-negative model bacteria, suggesting different modes of action of the antibacterial molecules produced by this strain. Thus, it seems plausible that biosynthetic pathways involving metabolites of similar nature could be present in these isolates. A typical cluster of secondary metabolism includes genes for multi-domains enzymes that carry out the synthesis of different bioactive metabolites and when this metabolite has an antimicrobial activity, it is coupled to its corresponding resistance gene (Zotchev, <xref rid="B104" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>).</p><p>To our knowledge, this is the first report of the isolation and ecophysiological characterization of actinobacteria from sediments of a Patagonian fjord. This single survey uncovered a broad cultivable diversity which provides the basis for the bioprospection of bioactive compounds. The isolation of novel actinobacterial species and the evidence that most of our isolates produced antibiotic activities supports our approach.</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Author contributions</title><p>AU conceived and designed the experiments, performed the experiments, analyzed the data, prepared the manuscript. FB designed the experiments. FC performed the experiments. MG performed the sampling and experiments. EM performed the sampling and edited the manuscript. MS performed the sampling, prepared and edited the manuscript. BC performed the sampling, conceived and designed the experiments, analyzed the data, prepared and edited the manuscript.</p><sec><title>Conflict of interest statement</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors thank the scuba divers and staff from Huinay Scientific Field Station. This work was supported by the Comisi&#x000f3;n Nacional de Investigaci&#x000f3;n Cient&#x000ed;fica y Tecnol&#x000f3;gica (FONDECYT 11121571 to BC) and Swedish Research Council N&#x000b0; 2013-6713 (to BC and EM) with additional funding from the Universidad T&#x000e9;cnica Federico Santa Mar&#x000ed;a (USM 131342, 131562 to MS). AU, FC acknowledges Conicyt PhD fellowship (AU), Conicyt Gastos Operacionales 21120621 (AU), and PIEA&#x0003e; UTFSM (AU, FC).</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aharonowitz</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Penicillin and Cephalosporin biosynthetic genes: structure, organization, regulation, and evolution</article-title>. <source>Annu. Rev. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>46</volume>, <fpage>461</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>495</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.mi.46.100192.002333</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1444264</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Axenov-Gribanov</surname><given-names>D. V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Voytsekhovskaya</surname><given-names>I. V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tokovenko</surname><given-names>B. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Protasov</surname><given-names>E. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gamaiunov</surname><given-names>S. V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rebets</surname><given-names>Y. V.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Actinobacteria isolated from an underground lake and moonmilk speleothem from the biggest conglomeratic karstic cave in Siberia as sources of novel biologically active compounds</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>e0152957</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0152957</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27028778</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ayuso</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salazar</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Genilloud</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>A novel actinomycete strain de-replication approach based on the diversity of polyketide synthase and nonribosomal peptide synthetase biosynthetic pathways</article-title>. <source>Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol.</source>
<volume>67</volume>, <fpage>795</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>806</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00253-004-1828-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15647936</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ayuso-Sacido</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Genilloud</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>New PCR primers for the screening of NRPS and PKS-I systems in actinomycetes: detection and distribution of these biosynthetic gene sequences in major taxonomic groups</article-title>. <source>Microb. Ecol.</source>
<volume>49</volume>, <fpage>10</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>24</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00248-004-0249-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15614464</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baskaran</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vijayakumar</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohan</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Enrichment method for the isolation of bioactive actinomycetes from mangrove sediments of Andaman Islands India</article-title>. <source>Malays. J. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>26</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>32</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>B&#x000e9;rdy</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Bioactive microbial metabolites</article-title>. <source>J. Antibiot.</source>
<volume>58</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>26</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ja.2005.1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15813176</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhadra</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Raghukumar</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pindi</surname><given-names>P. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shivaji</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Brevibacterium oceani sp. nov., isolated from deep-sea sediment of the Chagos Trench, Indian Ocean</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Syst. Evol. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>58</volume>, <fpage>57</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>60</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/ijs.0.64869-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18175683</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bredholdt</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Galatenko</surname><given-names>O. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Engelhardt</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fjaervik</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Terekhova</surname><given-names>L. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zotchev</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Rare actinomycete bacteria from the shallow water sediments of the Trondheim fjord, Norway: isolation, diversity and biological activity</article-title>. <source>Environ. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>2756</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2764</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1462-2920.2007.01387.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17922759</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bull</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stach</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Marine actinobacteria: new opportunities for natural product search and discovery</article-title>. <source>Trends Microbiol.</source>
<volume>15</volume>, <fpage>491</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>499</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tim.2007.10.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17997312</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bustamante</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>The southern Chilean fjord region: oceanographic aspects</article-title>, in <source>Marine Benthic Fauna of Chilean Patagonia</source>, eds <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>H&#x000e4;ussermann</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>F&#x000f6;rsterra</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>Santiago</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Nature in Focus</publisher-name>), <fpage>53</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>60</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Campos</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinochet</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Gregori</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lund Plantat</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zahr</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Delgado</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>1987</year>). <article-title>Estudios sobre contaminaci&#x000f3;n del agua en la Bah&#x000ed;a de Valpara&#x000ed;so</article-title>. <source>Bolet&#x000ed;n del Inst. Salud P&#x000fa;blica</source>
<volume>27</volume>, <fpage>72</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>83</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Capone</surname><given-names>D. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hutchins</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Microbial biogeochemistry of coastal upwelling regimes in a changing ocean</article-title>. <source>Nat. Geosci.</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>711</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>717</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ngeo1916</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Castillo</surname><given-names>M. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pizarro</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cifuentes</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramirez</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Djurfeldt</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Subtidal dynamics in a deep fjord of southern Chile</article-title>. <source>Cont. Shelf Res.</source>
<volume>49</volume>, <fpage>73</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>89</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.csr.2012.09.007</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chattopadhyay</surname><given-names>M. K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Mechanism of bacterial adaptation to low temperature</article-title>. <source>J. Biosci.</source>
<volume>31</volume>, <fpage>157</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>165</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02705244</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16595884</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Claver&#x000ed;as</surname><given-names>F. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Undabarrena</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seeger</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>C&#x000e1;mara</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Culturable diversity and antimicrobial activity of Actinobacteria from marine sediments in Valpara&#x000ed;so bay, Chile</article-title>. <source>Front. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>737</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2015.00737</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26284034</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Colquhoun</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heald</surname><given-names>S. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamaoka</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Horikoshi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Taxonomy and biotransformation activities of some deep-sea actinomycetes</article-title>. <source>Extremophiles</source>
<volume>2</volume>, <fpage>269</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>277</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s007920050069</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9783174</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Correa-Llant&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>D. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Amen&#x000e1;bar</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blamey</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Antioxidant capacity of novel pigments from an Antarctic bacterium</article-title>. <source>J. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>50</volume>, <fpage>374</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>379</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12275-012-2029-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22752899</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyla</surname><given-names>P. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Marine microbial diversity and ecology: importance and future perspectives</article-title>. <source>Curr. Sci.</source>
<volume>90</volume>, <fpage>1325</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1335</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Donadio</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Monciardini</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sosio</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Polyketide synthases and nonribosomal peptide synthetases: the emerging view from bacterial genomics</article-title>. <source>Nat. Prod. Rep.</source>
<volume>24</volume>, <fpage>1073</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1109</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/b514050c</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17898898</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Donia</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamann</surname><given-names>M. T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Marine natural products and their potential applications as anti-infective agents</article-title>. <source>Lancet Infect. Dis.</source>
<volume>3</volume>, <fpage>338</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>348</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(03)00655-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12781505</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doroghazi</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Metcalf</surname><given-names>W. W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Comparative genomics of actinomycetes with a focus on natural product biosynthetic genes</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source>
<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>611</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-14-611</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24020438</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haltli</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerr</surname><given-names>R. G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Bioprospecting from marine sediments of New Brunswick, Canada: exploring the relationship between total bacterial diversity and actinobacteria diversity</article-title>. <source>Mar. Drugs</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>899</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>925</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/md12020899</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24531187</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Felsenstein</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1985</year>). <article-title>Confidence limits on phylogenies: an approach using the bootstrap</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source>
<volume>39</volume>, <fpage>783</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>791</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/2408678</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fenical</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Chemical studies of marine bacteria: developing a new resource</article-title>. <source>Chem. Rev.</source>
<volume>93</volume>, <fpage>1673</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1683</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/cr00021a001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fenical</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>P. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Developing a new resource for drug discovery: marine actinomycete bacteria</article-title>. <source>Nat. Chem. Biol.</source>
<volume>2</volume>, <fpage>666</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>673</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nchembio841</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17108984</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fiedler</surname><given-names>H.-P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruntner</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bull</surname><given-names>A. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodfellow</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Potterat</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Marine actinomycetes as a source of novel secondary metabolites</article-title>. <source>Antonie Van Leeuwenhoek</source>
<volume>87</volume>, <fpage>37</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>42</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10482-004-6538-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15726289</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fischbach</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>C. T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Assembly-line enzymology for polyketide and nonribosomal peptide antibiotics: logic, machinery, and mechanisms</article-title>. <source>Chem. Inform.</source>
<volume>37</volume>, <fpage>3468</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3496</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/chin.200644265</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fondi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Orlandini</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maida</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Perrin</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Papaleo</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Emiliani</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Draft genome sequence of the volatile organic compound-producing Antarctic bacterium <italic>Arthrobacter</italic> sp. strain TB23, able to inhibit cystic fibrosis pathogens belonging to the <italic>Burkholderia cepacia</italic> complex</article-title>. <source>J. Bacteriol.</source>
<volume>194</volume>, <fpage>6334</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6335</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.01432-12</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23105071</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fuentes</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>G.-C.</given-names></name><name><surname>C&#x000e1;rdenas</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smalla</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seeger</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Assessing environmental drivers of microbial communities in estuarine soils of the Aconcagua River in Central Chile</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol. Ecol.</source>
<volume>91</volume>:<issue>fiv110</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/femsec/fiv110</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26362923</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>R. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Conserved indels in protein sequences that are characteristic of the phylum <italic>Actinobacteria</italic></article-title>. <source>Int. J. Syst. Evol. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>55</volume>, <fpage>2401</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2412</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/ijs.0.63785-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16280504</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Genilloud</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>The re-emerging role of microbial natural products in antibiotic discovery</article-title>. <source>Antonie Van Leeuwenhoek</source>
<volume>106</volume>, <fpage>173</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>188</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10482-014-0204-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24923558</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gontang</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fenical</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Phylogenetic diversity of gram-positive bacteria cultured from marine sediments</article-title>. <source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>73</volume>, <fpage>3272</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3282</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.02811-06</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17400789</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gontang</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaud&#x000ea;ncio</surname><given-names>S. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fenical</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>P. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Sequence-based analysis of secondary-metabolite biosynthesis in marine actinobacteria</article-title>. <source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>76</volume>, <fpage>2487</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2499</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.02852-09</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20154113</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goodfellow</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fiedler</surname><given-names>H.-P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>A guide to successful bioprospecting: informed by actinobacterial systematics</article-title>. <source>Antonie Van Leeuwenhoek</source>
<volume>98</volume>, <fpage>119</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>142</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10482-010-9460-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20582471</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gulder</surname><given-names>T. A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>B. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Chasing the treasures of the sea &#x02013; bacterial marine natural products</article-title>. <source>Curr. Opin. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>252</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>260</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mib.2009.05.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19481972</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haber</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ilan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Diversity and antibacterial activity of bacteria cultured from Mediterranean <italic>Axinella</italic> spp</article-title>. <source>sponges. J. Appl. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>116</volume>, <fpage>519</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>532</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jam.12401</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24268066</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haefner</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Drugs from the deep : marine natural products as drug candidates</article-title>. <source>Res. Focus</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>536</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>544</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s1359-6446(03)02713-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12821301</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hakv&#x000e5;g</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fjaervik</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Josefsen</surname><given-names>K. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ian</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellingsen</surname><given-names>T. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zotchev</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Characterization of <italic>Streptomyces</italic> spp. isolated from the sea surface microlayer in the Trondheim Fjord, Norway</article-title>. <source>Mar. Drugs</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>620</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>635</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/md6040620</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19172199</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hodges</surname><given-names>T. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Slattery</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Unique actinomycetes from marine caves and coral reef sediments provide novel PKS and NRPS biosynthetic gene clusters</article-title>. <source>Mar. Biotechnol.</source>
<volume>14</volume>, <fpage>270</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>280</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10126-011-9410-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22002467</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ru</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lujie</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ilei</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yunyang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Actinobacterial diversity of marine sediments samples from Chile</article-title>. <source>Acta Microbiol. Sin.</source>
<volume>50</volume>, <fpage>862</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>869</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>A.-H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Q.-Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>H. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>H.-P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Actinomycetes for marine drug discovery isolated from mangrove soils and plants in China</article-title>. <source>Mar. Drugs</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>24</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>44</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/md7010024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19370169</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>P. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gontang</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mafnas</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mincer</surname><given-names>T. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fenical</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Culturable marine actinomycete diversity from tropical Pacific Ocean sediments</article-title>. <source>Environ. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>1039</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1048</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1462-2920.2005.00785.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15946301</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Diversity of culturable actinobacteria isolated from marine sponge <italic>Haliclona</italic> sp</article-title>. <source>Antonie Van Leeuwenhoek</source>
<volume>92</volume>, <fpage>405</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>416</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10482-007-9169-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17566868</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Joint</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000fc;hling</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Querellou</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Culturing marine bacteria - an essential prerequisite for biodiscovery</article-title>. <source>Microb. Biotechnol.</source>
<volume>3</volume>, <fpage>564</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>575</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1751-7915.2010.00188.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21255353</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baltz</surname><given-names>R. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Natural product discovery: past, present, and future</article-title>. <source>J. Ind. Microbiol. Biotechnol.</source>
<volume>43</volume>, <fpage>155</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>176</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10295-015-1723-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26739136</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kester</surname><given-names>D. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Duedall</surname><given-names>I. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Connors</surname><given-names>D. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pytkowicz</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1967</year>). <article-title>Preparation of artificial seawater</article-title>. <source>Limnol. Oceanogr.</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>176</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>179</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4319/lo.1967.12.1.0176</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>B. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>O.-S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>E. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chun</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Proposal to transfer <italic>Flavobacterium oceanosedimentum</italic> Carty and Litchfield 1978 to the genus <italic>Curtobacterium</italic> as <italic>Curtobacterium oceanosedimentum</italic> comb. nov</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol. Lett.</source>
<volume>296</volume>, <fpage>137</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>141</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-6968.2009.01628.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19459968</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>T. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Garson</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuerst</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Marine actinomycetes related to the &#x0201c;<italic>Salinospora</italic>&#x0201d; group from the Great Barrier Reef sponge <italic>Pseudoceratina clavata</italic></article-title>. <source>Environ. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>509</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>518</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1462-2920.2005.00716.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15816928</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanglier</surname><given-names>J.-J.</given-names></name><name><surname>DiTullio</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Braccili</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonner</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Waters</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Diversifying microbial natural products for drug discovery</article-title>. <source>Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol.</source>
<volume>62</volume>, <fpage>446</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>458</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00253-003-1381-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12838377</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Diversity and distribution of Actinobacteria associated with reef coral <italic>Porites lutea</italic></article-title>. <source>Front. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>6</volume>:<issue>1094</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2015.01094</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26539166</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kurahashi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukunaga</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakiyama</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Harayama</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yokota</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Euzebya tangerina gen. nov., sp. nov., a deeply branching marine actinobacterium isolated from the sea cucumber Holothuria edulis, and proposal of Euzebyaceae fam. nov., <italic>Euzebyales</italic> ord. nov. and <italic>Nitriliruptoridae</italic> subclassis nov</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Syst. Evol. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>60</volume>, <fpage>2314</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2319</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/ijs.0.016543-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19915105</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kurtb&#x000f6;ke</surname><given-names>D. &#x00130;.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grkovic</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Quinn</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Marine Actinomycetes in biodiscovery</article-title>, in <source>Marine Microbiology and Biotechnology</source>, ed <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>Berlin; Heidelberg</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>), <fpage>663</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>676</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lagger</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>H&#x000e4;ussermann</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>F&#x000f6;rsterra</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tati&#x000e1;n</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Ascidians from the southern Chilean Comau Fjord</article-title>. <source>Spixiana</source>
<volume>32</volume>, <fpage>173</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>186</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>K. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Discovery of novel metabolites from marine actinomycetes</article-title>. <source>Curr. Opin. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>245</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>251</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mib.2006.03.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16675289</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>16S/23S rRNA Sequencing.pdf</article-title>, in <source>Nucleic Acid Techniques in Bacterial Systematicsid</source>, eds <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Stackebrandt</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodfellow</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>John Wiley and Sons</publisher-name>), <fpage>115</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>175</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schumann</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title><italic>Phycicola gilvus</italic> gen. nov., sp. nov., an actinobacterium isolated from living seaweed</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Syst. Evol. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>58</volume>, <fpage>1318</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1323</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/ijs.0.65283-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18523172</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zainal</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Azman</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eng</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ab Mutalib</surname><given-names>N. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>W. F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2014b</year>). <article-title>Streptomyces pluripotens sp. nov., a bacteriocin-producing streptomycete that inhibits meticillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title>. <source>Int. J. Syst. Evol. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>64</volume>, <fpage>3297</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3306</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/ijs.0.065045-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24994773</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zainal</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Azman</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eng</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bog</surname><given-names>B. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>W. F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014a</year>). <article-title>Diversity and antimicrobial activities of actinobacterial isolated from tropical mangrove sediments in Malaysia</article-title>. <source>Sci. World J.</source>
<volume>2014</volume>:<fpage>698178</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2014/698178</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leiva</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alvarado</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Garrido</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Diversity of pigmented Gram-positive bacteria associated with marine macroalgae from Antarctica</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol. Lett.</source>
<volume>362</volume>:<issue>fnv206</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/femsle/fnv206</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26507390</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Le&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liza</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Soto</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cuadra</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pati&#x000f1;o</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Actinomycetes bioactivos de sedimento marino de la costa central del Per&#x000fa;</article-title>. <source>Rev. Peru. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>14</volume>, <fpage>259</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>270</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15381/rpb.v14i2.1796</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Livermore</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Has the era of untreatable infections arrived?</article-title>
<source>J. Antimicrob. Chemother.</source>
<volume>64</volume>, <fpage>i29</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>i36</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jac/dkp255</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19675016</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Magarvey</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernan</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dworkin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>D. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Isolation and characterization of novel marine-derived actinomycete taxa rich in bioactive metabolites</article-title>. <source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>70</volume>, <fpage>7520</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7529</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.70.12.7520-7529.2004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15574955</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B63"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mahmoud</surname><given-names>H. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalendar</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Coral-associated actinobacteria: diversity, abundance, and biotechnological potentials</article-title>. <source>Front. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>7</volume>:<issue>204</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2016.00204</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26973601</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B64"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maldonado</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fenical</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kauffman</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mincer</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title><italic>Salinispora arenicola</italic> gen. nov., sp. nov. and <italic>Salinispora tropica</italic> sp. nov., obligate marine actinomycetes belonging to the family <italic>Micromonosporaceae</italic></article-title>. <source>Int. J. Syst. Evol. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>55</volume>, <fpage>1759</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1766</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/ijs.0.63625-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16166663</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B65"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maldonado</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stach</surname><given-names>J. E. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bull</surname><given-names>A. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodfellow</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Characterisation of micromonosporae from aquatic environments using molecular taxonomic methods</article-title>. <source>Antonie Van Leeuwenhoek</source>
<volume>94</volume>, <fpage>289</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>298</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10482-008-9244-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18465200</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B66"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mincer</surname><given-names>T. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>P. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kauffman</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fenical</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Widespread and persistent populations of a major new marine actinomycete taxon in ocean sediments</article-title>. <source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>68</volume>, <fpage>5005</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5011</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.68.10.5005-5011.2002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12324350</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B67"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Montalvo</surname><given-names>N. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohamed</surname><given-names>N. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Enticknap</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>R. T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Novel actinobacteria from marine sponges</article-title>. <source>Antonie Van Leeuwenhoek</source>
<volume>87</volume>, <fpage>29</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>36</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10482-004-6536-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15726288</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B68"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arnscheidt</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kr&#x000fc;ger</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Str&#x000f6;mpl</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mau</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Simplified protocols for the preparation of genomic DNA from bacterial cultures</article-title>. <source>Molecular Microbial Ecology Manual, vol. 1</source> (<publisher-loc>Dodrecht</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Kluwer Academic Publishers</publisher-name>), <fpage>3</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>18</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B69"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Motta</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brandelli</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Characterization of an antibacterial peptide produced by <italic>Brevibacterium linens</italic></article-title>. <source>J. Appl. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>92</volume>, <fpage>63</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>70</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2672.2002.01490.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11849329</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B70"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cragg</surname><given-names>G. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Natural products as sources of new drugs over the 30 years from 1981 to 2010</article-title>. <source>J. Nat. Prod.</source>
<volume>75</volume>, <fpage>311</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>335</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/np200906s</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22316239</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B71"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Orlandini</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maida</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fondi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Perrin</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Papaleo</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bosi</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Genomic analysis of three sponge-associated <italic>Arthrobacter</italic> Antarctic strains, inhibiting the growth of <italic>Burkholderia cepacia</italic> complex bacteria by synthesizing volatile organic compounds</article-title>. <source>Microbiol. Res.</source>
<volume>169</volume>, <fpage>593</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>601</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.micres.2013.09.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24231161</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B72"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Palma-Fleming</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cornejo</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>P&#x000e9;rez</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gutierrez</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sericano</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons and polychorinated biphenyls in coastal environments of Valdivia and Valparaiso, Chile</article-title>. <source>J. Chil. Chem. Soc.</source>
<volume>53</volume>, <fpage>1533</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1538</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4067/S0717-97072008000200020</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B73"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pathom-Aree</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stach</surname><given-names>J. E. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Horikoshi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bull</surname><given-names>A. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodfellow</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Diversity of actinomycetes isolated from Challenger Deep sediment (10,898 m) from the Mariana Trench</article-title>. <source>Extremophiles</source>
<volume>10</volume>, <fpage>181</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>189</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00792-005-0482-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16538400</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B74"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Penn</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>P. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Comparative genomics reveals evidence of marine adaptation in <italic>Salinispora</italic> species</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source>
<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>86</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-13-86</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22401625</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B75"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pham</surname><given-names>T. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiese</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wenzel-Storjohann</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Imhoff</surname><given-names>J. F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Diversity and antimicrobial potential of bacterial isolates associated with the soft coral <italic>Alcyonium digitatum</italic> from the Baltic Sea</article-title>. <source>Antonie van Leeuwenhoek</source>
<volume>109</volume>, <fpage>105</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>119</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10482-015-0613-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26558794</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B76"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H.-H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>G.-Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>W.-Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>L.-H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Abundant and diverse endophytic actinobacteria associated with medicinal plant <italic>Maytenus austroyunnanensis</italic> in Xishuangbanna tropical rainforest revealed by culture-dependent and culture-independent methods</article-title>. <source>Environ. Microbiol. Rep.</source>
<volume>4</volume>, <fpage>522</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>531</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1758-2229.2012.00357.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23760897</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B77"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rashid</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fakruddin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazumdar</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaniz</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chowdhury</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Anti-bacterial activity of pigments isolated from pigment-forming soil bacteria</article-title>. <source>Br. J. Pharm. Res.</source>
<volume>4</volume>, <fpage>880</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>894</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.9734/BJPR/2014/5148</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B78"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>G. S. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prakash</surname><given-names>J. S. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prabahar</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>G. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stackebrandt</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shivaji</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Kocuria polaris sp. nov., an orange-pigmented psychrophilic bacterium isolated from an Antarctic cyanobacterial mat sample</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Syst. Evol. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>53</volume>, <fpage>183</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>187</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/ijs.0.02336-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12656171</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B79"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rokem</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vongsangnak</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Comparative metabolic capabilities for <italic>Micrococcus luteus</italic> NCTC 2665, the &#x0201c;Fleming&#x0201d; strain, and actinobacteria</article-title>. <source>Biotechnol. Bioeng.</source>
<volume>108</volume>, <fpage>2770</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2775</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bit.23212</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21618466</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B80"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rossell&#x000f3;-M&#x000f3;ra</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Amann</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Past and future species definitions for Bacteria and Archaea</article-title>. <source>Syst. Appl. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>38</volume>, <fpage>209</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>216</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.syapm.2015.02.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25747618</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B81"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saitou</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nei</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1987</year>). <article-title>The neighbor-joining method: a new method for reconstructing phylogenetic trees</article-title>. <source>Mol. Biol. Evol.</source>
<volume>4</volume>, <fpage>406</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>425</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3447015</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B82"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salomon</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Magarvey</surname><given-names>N. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>D. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Merging the potential of microbial genetics with biological and chemical diversity: an even brighter future for marine natural product drug discovery</article-title>. <source>Nat. Prod. Rep.</source>
<volume>21</volume>, <fpage>105</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>121</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/b301384g</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15039838</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B83"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sen</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Daubin</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abrouk</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gifford</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Normand</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Phylogeny of the class <italic>Actinobacteria</italic> revisited in the light of complete genomes. The orders &#x0201c;<italic>Frankiales</italic>&#x0201d; and <italic>Micrococcales</italic> should be split into coherent entities: proposal of <italic>Frankiales</italic> ord. nov., <italic>Geodermatophilales</italic> ord. nov., <italic>Acidothermales</italic> ord. nov. an</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Syst. Evol. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>64</volume>, <fpage>3821</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3832</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/ijs.0.063966-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25168610</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B84"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sep&#x000fa;lveda</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pantoja</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hughen</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Sources and distribution of organic matter in northern Patagonia fjords, Chile (~44&#x02013;47&#x000b0;S): a multi-tracer approach for carbon cycling assessment</article-title>. <source>Cont. Shelf Res.</source>
<volume>31</volume>, <fpage>315</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>329</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.csr.2010.05.013</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B85"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ser</surname><given-names>H. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Palanisamy</surname><given-names>U. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>W. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abd Malek</surname><given-names>S. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>K. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goh</surname><given-names>B. H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Presence of antioxidative agent, Pyrrolo[1,2-a]pyrazine-1,4-dione, hexahydro- in newly isolated <italic>Streptomyces mangrovisoli</italic> sp. nov</article-title>. <source>Front. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>6</volume>:<issue>854</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2015.00854</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26347733</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B86"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ser</surname><given-names>H. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>L. T. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Palanisamy</surname><given-names>U. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abd Malek</surname><given-names>S. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>W. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>K. G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2016</year>). <article-title><italic>Streptomyces antioxidans</italic> sp. nov., a novel mangrove soil actinobacterium with antioxidative and neuroprotective potentials</article-title>. <source>Front. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>7</volume>:<issue>899</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2016.00899</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27379040</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B87"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Ox&#x000ed;geno disuelto, pH y nutrientes en canales y fiordos australes</article-title>, in <source>Avances en el Conocimiento Oceanogr&#x000e1;fico de las Aguas Interiores Chilenas</source>, eds <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Palma</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>Valpara&#x000ed;so</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Comit&#x000e9; Oceanogr&#x000e1;fico Nacional</publisher-name>). <fpage>37</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>43</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B88"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sobarzo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>La Regi&#x000f3;n de los fiordos de la zona sur de Chile</article-title>, in <source>Aspectos Oceanogr&#x000e1;ficos</source>, eds <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>H&#x000e4;ussermann</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>F&#x000f6;rsterra</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>Santiago</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Nature in Focus</publisher-name>), <fpage>6</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B89"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stach</surname><given-names>J. E. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maldonado</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodfellow</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bull</surname><given-names>A. T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>New primers for the class <italic>Actinobacteria</italic>: application to marine and terrestrial environments</article-title>. <source>Environ. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>5</volume>, <fpage>828</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>841</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1462-2920.2003.00483.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14510836</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B90"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Staunton</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Biosynthesis of Erythromycin and Rapamycin</article-title>. <source>Chem. Rev.</source>
<volume>97</volume>, <fpage>2611</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2630</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/cr9600316</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11851474</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B91"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Subramani</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aalbersberg</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Marine actinomycetes: an ongoing source of novel bioactive metabolites</article-title>. <source>Microbiol. Res.</source>
<volume>167</volume>, <fpage>571</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>580</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.micres.2012.06.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22796410</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B92"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Karthik</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Actinomycetes from the South China Sea sponges: isolation, diversity, and potential for aromatic polyketides discovery</article-title>. <source>Front. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>6</volume>:<issue>148</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2015.01048</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26483773</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B93"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stecher</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Filipski</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>MEGA6: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis version 6.0</article-title>. <source>Mol. Biol. Evol.</source>
<volume>30</volume>, <fpage>2725</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2729</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/mst197</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24132122</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B94"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ugalde</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallardo</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Belmar</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mu&#x000f1;oz</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruiz-Tagle</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferrada-Fuentes</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Microbial life in a fjord: metagenomic analysis of a microbial mat in Chilean patagonia</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>e71952</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0071952</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24015199</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B95"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vardhan Reddy</surname><given-names>P. V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shiva Nageswara Rao</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pratibha</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sailaja</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kavya</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Manorama</surname><given-names>R. R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Bacterial diversity and bioprospecting for cold-active enzymes from culturable bacteria associated with sediment from a melt water stream of Midtre Lovenbreen glacier, an Arctic glacier</article-title>. <source>Res. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>160</volume>, <fpage>538</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>546</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.resmic.2009.08.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19732827</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B96"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2010</year>). <article-title><italic>Rhodococcus jialingiae</italic> sp. nov., an actinobacterium isolated from sludge of a carbendazim wastewater treatment facility</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Syst. Evol. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>60</volume>, <fpage>378</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>381</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/ijs.0.013219-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19651732</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B97"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bora</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Diversity and biogeography of marine actinobacteria</article-title>. <source>Curr. Opin. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>279</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>286</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mib.2006.04.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16675292</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B98"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wietz</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000e5;nsson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blom</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gram</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Wide distribution of closely related, antibiotic-producing <italic>Arthrobacter</italic> strains throughout the Arctic Ocean</article-title>. <source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>78</volume>, <fpage>2039</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2042</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.07096-11</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22247128</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B99"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nie</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>A new tetrodotoxin-producing actinomycete, <italic>Nocardiopsis dassonvillei</italic>, isolated from the ovaries of puffer fish <italic>Fugu rubripes</italic></article-title>. <source>Toxicon</source>
<volume>45</volume>, <fpage>851</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>859</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.toxicon.2005.02.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15904680</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B100"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H.-R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.-H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Phylogenetic diversity and biological activity of actinobacteria isolated from the Chukchi Shelf marine sediments in the Arctic Ocean</article-title>. <source>Mar. Drugs</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>1281</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1297</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/md12031281</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24663116</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B101"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H. K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Culturable actinobacteria from the marine sponge <italic>Hymeniacidon perleve</italic>: isolation and phylogenetic diversity by 16S rRNA gene-RFLP analysis</article-title>. <source>Antonie Van Leeuwenhoek</source>
<volume>90</volume>, <fpage>159</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>169</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10482-006-9070-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16871424</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B102"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.-Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G.-H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X.-Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>S.-H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Diversity and antibacterial activity of culturable actinobacteria isolated from five species of the South China Sea gorgonian corals</article-title>. <source>World J. Microbiol. Biotechnol.</source>
<volume>29</volume>, <fpage>1107</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1116</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11274-013-1279-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23386321</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B103"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zotchev</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Marine actinomycetes as an emerging resource for the drug development pipelines</article-title>. <source>J. Biotechnol.</source>
<volume>158</volume>, <fpage>168</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>175</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jbiotec.2011.06.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21683100</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B104"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zotchev</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Genomics-based insights into the evolution of secondary metabolite biosynthesis in actinomycete bacteria</article-title>, in <source>Evolutionary Biology: Genome Evolution, Speciation, Coevolution and Origin of Life</source>, ed <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Pontarotti</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>Cham</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer International Publishing</publisher-name>), <fpage>35</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>46</lpage>. </mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>