<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Gastroenterology Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Gastroenterology Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Elmer Press</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Gastroenterology Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1918-2805</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1918-2813</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elmer Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27942327</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5139818</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4021/gr303w</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Multifocal Carcinoid Tumor of Small Intestine: A Rare Cause of Chronic Obscure Gastrointestinal Bleeding, Suspected on Capsule Endoscopy and Diagnosed on Double Balloon Enteroscopy</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="short">Diagnosis of Small Bowel Carcinoid Tumor</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hernandez</surname><given-names>Jose C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aa">a</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CORb">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rojas</surname><given-names>Juan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aa">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gurudu</surname><given-names>Suryakanth R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aa">a</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="Aa"><label>a</label>Division of Gastroenterology and Hepatology, Mayo Clinic-AZ, 13400 East Shea Boulevard, Scottsdale, Arizona, USA</aff><author-notes><corresp id="CORb"><label>b</label>Corresponding author: Jose C Hernandez, Division of Gastroenterology and Hepatology, Mayo Clinic-AZ, 13400 East Shea Boulevard, Scottsdale, AZ 85259. USA. Email: <email>hernandez.jose1@mayo.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>6</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>5</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><volume>4</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>125</fpage><lpage>126</lpage><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>4</month><year>2011</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright 2011, Hernandez et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><license license-type="open access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>We reported a case of multifocal carcinoid tumor of small intestine causing chronic obscure gastrointestinal bleeding, suspected on capsule endoscopy and diagnosed on double balloon enteroscopy.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Carcinoid tumor</kwd><kwd>Video capsule endoscopy</kwd><kwd>Double-balloon enteroscopy</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Case Report</title><p>A 64-year-old man with bouts of obscure, overt gastrointestinal bleeding (OGIB) in the past was transferred to our medical center for persistent melena. Over the past five years, he had undergone extensive inpatient evaluations at several hospitals for OGIB without a cause identified. On this occasion, the patient was found to have a hemoglobin of 5.7. He underwent a push enteroscopy which showed no obvious bleeding source and colonoscopy which showed evidence of old hemorrhage. A repeat video capsule endoscopy (VCE; Pill Cam SB, GIVEN, Yokneam, Israel) was performed which showed several polyploid lesions in the mid small bowel and continuing through the terminal ileum with fresh blood noted (see video).</p><p>Following transfusion with 8 units of packed red blood cells, he was transferred to our facility for retrograde double-balloon enteroscopy (DBE). His study was significant for two large, friable, ulcerated sessile polypoid lesions in the mid ileum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>) and multiple small polypoid lesions in the distal ileum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). Biopsies taken from these polyps showed low-grade neuroendocrine pathology consistent with carcinoid tumor (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). Further investigations performed at our medical center included a CT enterography and octreotide scan which confirmed localization of the tumor to the distal small bowel. He later underwent successful laparoscopic partial small bowel resection.</p><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Double-balloon enteroscopy. Friable, ulcerated sessile polypoid lesion in the mid ileum.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr-04-125-g001"/></fig><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Double-balloon enteroscopy. Multiple small polypoid lesions in the distal ileum.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr-04-125-g002"/></fig><fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Histopathology. Biopsies from distal ileum polyps showed low-grade neuroendocrine pathology consistent with carcinoid tumor (hematoxylin and eosin stain; magnification x 400).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr-04-125-g003"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Discussion</title><p>Carcinoid tumors are a form of neuroendocrine tumors and can present a dilemma for clinicians because the disease can encompass a wide range of clinical behaviors. Midgut carcinoids are the most common form of carcinoid tumor and originate most frequently in the terminal ileum. Due to the indolent behavior of small bowel carcinoid tumors, patients usually have symptoms for a mean of 5 years before the diagnosis is made [<xref rid="R01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Carcinoid syndrome occurs in only approximately 20% of patients with small bowel carcinoid.</p><p>Recent literature suggests that the diagnostic yield of DBE for suspected primary small bowel neuroendocrine tumor is low [<xref rid="R02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. As illustrated by a recently published database, the most common indication for DBE that ultimately led to the diagnosis of small bowel carcinoid included suspected small bowel malignancy, obstructive symptoms, and OGIB [<xref rid="R03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. As described in our case and in other published studies, DBE commonly detects small bowel mass lesions responsible for OGIB that are commonly missed or not readily identified by VCE [<xref rid="R04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Multiple submucosal masses presenting as chronic melena and ultimately diagnosed as multifocal carcinoid tumor in the proximal ileum have been described. To our knowledge, this is the first reported case that utilized both VCE and DBE in rapid succession to attain tissue diagnosis of small bowel carcinoid tumor in a non-invasive fashion. Our case illustrates that further studies combining the two methods during the evaluation of OGIB may serve to increase the diagnostic yield.</p></sec></body><back><sec id="s2a1"><title>Disclosure</title><p>All authors disclosed no financial relationships relevant to this publication.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R01"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pasieka</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><article-title>Carcinoid tumors</article-title><source>Surg Clin North Am</source><year>2009</year><volume>89</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1123</fpage><lpage>1137</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.suc.2009.06.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19836488</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R02"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bellutti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fry</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmitt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Seemann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Klose</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Malfertheiner</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Monkemuller</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><article-title>Detection of neuroendocrine tumors of the small bowel by double balloon enteroscopy</article-title><source>Dig Dis Sci</source><year>2009</year><volume>54</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1050</fpage><lpage>1058</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10620-008-0456-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18770038</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R03"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mitsui</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehara</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal><article-title>Role of double-balloon endoscopy in the diagnosis of small-bowel tumors: the first Japanese multicenter study</article-title><source>Gastrointest Endosc</source><year>2009</year><volume>70</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>498</fpage><lpage>504</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gie.2008.12.242</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19555947</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R04"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mehdizadeh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tokar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Leighton</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schembre</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal><article-title>Double balloon enteroscopy detects small bowel mass lesions missed by capsule endoscopy</article-title><source>Dig Dis Sci</source><year>2008</year><volume>53</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>2140</fpage><lpage>2143</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10620-007-0110-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18270840</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>