<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="brief-report"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Genom Data</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Genom Data</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Genomics Data</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2213-5960</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26484142</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4535614</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S2213-5960(14)00113-5</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gdata.2014.10.024</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Data in Brief</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Mapping of genomic double-strand breaks by ligation of biotinylated oligonucleotides to forum domains: Analysis of the data obtained for human rDNA units</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tchurikov</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></name><email>tchurikov@eimb.ru</email><xref rid="cr0005" ref-type="corresp">&#x0204e;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kretova</surname><given-names>O.V.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fedoseeva</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chechetkin</surname><given-names>V.R.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gorbacheva</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Karnaukhov</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kravatskaya</surname><given-names>G.I.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kravatsky</surname><given-names>Y.V.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af0005">Engelhardt Institute of Molecular Biology, Moscow, Russia</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cr0005"><label>&#x0204e;</label>Corresponding author at: Engelhardt Institute of Molecular Biology, Vavilov str. 32, Moscow, 119334, Russia. Tel.:&#x000a0;+7 499 135 97 53; fax:&#x000a0;+7 499 135 14 05. <email>tchurikov@eimb.ru</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>12</day><month>11</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>3</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>11</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>3</volume><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>10</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>10</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2014 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><license license-type="CC BY-NC-ND" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>DNA double-strand breaks (DSBs) are associated with different physiological and pathological processes in different organisms. To understand the role of DSBs in multiple cellular mechanisms, a robust method for genome-wide mapping of chromosomal breaks at one-nucleotide resolution is required. Many years ago, we detected large DNA fragments migrating from DNA-agarose plugs in pulsed-field gels, which we named &#x02018;forum domains&#x02019; [<xref rid="bb0005" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,2]. Recently, we developed a method for genome-wide mapping of DSBs that produces these 50&#x02013;150&#x000a0;kb DNA domains using microarrays or 454 sequencing (Tchurikov et al., 2011; 2013). Now we have used Illumina sequencing to map DSBs in repetitive rDNA units in human HEK293T cells. Here we describe in detail the experimental design and bioinformatics analysis of the data deposited in the Gene Expression Omnibus with accession number GSE49302 and associated with the study published in the Journal of Molecular Cell Biology (Tchurikov et al., 2014).</p></abstract><kwd-group><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Forum domains</kwd><kwd>Double-strand breaks</kwd><kwd>Fragile sites</kwd><kwd>rDNA</kwd><kwd>Bioinformatics</kwd><kwd>HEK293T</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s0010"><title>Specifications</title><p><table-wrap id="t0010" position="float"><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td align="left">Organism/cell line/tissue</td><td align="left">Homo sapiens/HEK 293T cells</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Sex</td><td align="left">Female</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Sequencer or array type</td><td align="left">Illumina Genome Analyzer IIx</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Data format</td><td align="left">Raw and processed.<break/>Raw data: FASTQ reads.<break/>Processed data: BED, WIG, and text table files.<break/>Metadata in SOFT and MINiML formats are supplied by GEO for automated processing.</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Experimental factors</td><td align="left">HEK293T cells were seeded in 10&#x000a0;cm culture plates 1&#x02013;2&#x000a0;days before experiments in DMEM containing 10% FBS, and were used at approximately 60&#x02013;80% confluency.</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Experimental features</td><td align="left">DNA domains, migrating in 0.8% agarose mini-gels from the DNA-agarose plugs, were electroeluted. Biotinylated oligonucleotides were ligated to DNA sequences at DSB sites.</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Consent</td><td align="left"><italic>Level of consent allowed for reuse if applicable (typically for human samples).</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Sample source location</td><td align="left">Moscow 119334, Russia</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="s0015"><title>Direct link to deposited data</title><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE49302" id="ir0030">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE49302</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec id="s0020"><title>Experimental design, materials and methods</title><sec id="s0025"><title>Sample preparation</title><p>DNA-agarose plugs were prepared as described previously <xref rid="bb0010" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, <xref rid="bb0015" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, <xref rid="bb0020" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="bb0025" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, <xref rid="bb0030" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. The major steps are illustrated in <xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>. About 6 million HEK 293T cells in 2&#x000a0;mL of culture medium were pelleted by centrifugation at 2000&#x000a0;rpm in a MiniSpin centrifuge (Eppendorf), resuspended in 0.3&#x000a0;mL of the same medium, gently mixed at 42&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C with an equal volume of a solution of 1% low-melt agarose L (LKB) in PBS, and distributed on a mold containing 100-&#x003bc;L wells. The mold was covered with parafilm and placed on ice for 2&#x02013;5&#x000a0;min. The agarose plugs were then placed in Petri dishes with 5&#x000a0;mL of solution containing 0.5&#x000a0;M EDTA (pH&#x000a0;9.5), 1% sodium lauroylsarcosine, and 1&#x02013;2&#x000a0;mg of proteinase K solution per mL for 40&#x02013;48&#x000a0;h at 50&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C, and stored at 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C in the same solution. Each DNA-agarose plug usually contained about 15&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g of DNA, corresponding to about 1 million cells.</p><p>To test the quality of isolated DNA, fractionation in pulsed-field gels was performed as described previously <xref rid="bb0010" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, <xref rid="bb0035" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. Portions of the original agarose-DNA plugs (5&#x02013;50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L) containing 1&#x02013;10&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g of DNA were used for electrophoresis without any restriction enzyme digestion. The DNA samples were run in 0.8% agarose gels on a Pulsaphor system (LKB) using a hexagonal electrode and switching times of 25 or 450&#x000a0;s.</p><p>For elution of DNA preparations, fractionation in a 0.8% agarose conventional mini-gel was performed. One-half of the DNA-agarose plug was washed in 1&#x000a0;&#x000d7; TE three times (for 15&#x000a0;min each), followed by washing (three times) in the same solution containing 17.4&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL phenylmethylsulfonyl fluoride (PMSF) in ethanol. After fractionation in the mini-gel, the ethidium bromide-stained DNA band was excised and electroeluted inside the dialysis cellulose-membrane bag. After overnight dialysis without stirring against 1&#x000a0;L of 0.01&#x000a0;&#x000d7; TE at 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C, the DNA was concentrated with PEG at 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C.</p></sec><sec id="s0030"><title>Rapid amplification of forum domains termini (RAFT) procedure</title><p>The steps of the procedure are shown schematically in <xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>A. About 1.5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g of isolated DNA (see above) was ligated with 70&#x000a0;ng of double-stranded oligonucleotide (25-bp long 5&#x02032;-phosphorylated 5&#x02032; pCCCCTGCAGTATAAGGAGAATTCGGG 3&#x02032; oligonucleotide annealed to a 26-bp long 5&#x02032; biotinylated 5&#x02032; bio-CCGAATTCTCCTTATACTGCAGGGG 3&#x02032; oligonucleotide) in 150&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L of solution containing 0.1&#x000a0;M NaCl, 50&#x000a0;mM Tris&#x02013;HCl (pH&#x000a0;7.4), 8&#x000a0;mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 9&#x000a0;mM 2-mercaptoethanol, 7&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M ATP, 7.5% PEG, and 40&#x000a0;units of T4 DNA ligase at 20&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 16&#x000a0;h. After heating at 65&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 10&#x000a0;min, the DNA preparation was digested with Sau3A enzyme to shorten the forum domain to the positions of the termini attached to the ligated oligonucleotide. The selection of such termini was performed in 0.5-mL Eppendorf tubes using 300&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L of a suspension containing Streptavidin Magnesphere Paramagnetic Particles, (SA-PMP; Promega) according to the manufacturer's recommendations. After extensive washing with 0.5&#x000a0;&#x000d7; SSC to remove DNA fragments corresponding to the internal parts of forum domains, the forum termini (FT) DNA preparation was eluted from the SA-PMP using digestion with EcoRI enzyme in a final volume of 50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L (double-stranded FT). The FT was then ligated with 100&#x000a0;&#x000d7; molar excess of double-stranded Sau3A adaptor (5&#x02032;-phosphorylated 5&#x02032; pGATCGTTTGCGGCCGCTTAAGCTTGGG 3&#x02032; oligonucleotide annealed to 5&#x02032; CCCAAGCTTAAGCGGCCGCAAAC 3&#x02032; oligonucleotide). In some experiments, the DNA preparation was eluted from the SA-PMP using heating by incubation at 100&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 3&#x000a0;min in 50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L of 0.01&#x000a0;&#x000d7; TE (single-stranded FT). Before heating, the FT preparation was ligated with 100&#x000a0;&#x000d7; molar excess of double-stranded Sau3A adaptor in suspension with SA-PMP (see above). Both final DNA samples (double-stranded FT or single-stranded FT) were used for PCR amplifications. PCR amplification (15&#x02013;20&#x000a0;cycles) in 30&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L of a solution containing 67&#x000a0;mM Tris&#x02013;HCl (pH&#x000a0;8.4); 6&#x000a0;mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>; 10&#x000a0;mM 2-mercaptoethanol; 16.6&#x000a0;mM ammonium sulfate; 6.7&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M EDTA; 5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL BSA; 1&#x000a0;mM dNTPs; 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g of primer corresponding to Sau3A adaptor (5&#x02032; CCCAAGCTTAAGCGGCCGCAAAC 3&#x02032;); 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g of primer corresponding to biotinylated oligonucleotide (5&#x02032; CCGAATTCTCCTTATACTGCAGGGG 3&#x02032;); and 1 U of Taq polymerase was performed using an Mastercycler Personal thermal cycler (Eppendorf). Amplification conditions were 90&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for melting, 65&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for annealing, and 72&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for extension, for 1&#x000a0;min each.</p></sec><sec id="s0035"><title>Library preparation</title><p>Libraries were prepared according to Illumina's instructions accompanying the DNA Sample Kit (Part# 0801-0303). Briefly, DNA was end-repaired using a combination of T4 DNA polymerase, <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> DNA Pol I large fragment (Klenow polymerase), and T4 polynucleotide kinase. The blunt, phosphorylated ends were treated with Klenow fragment and dATP to yield a protruding 3&#x02032;- A base for ligation of Illumina's adapters, which have a single T-base overhang at the 3&#x02032; end. After adapter ligation, DNA was PCR amplified with Illumina primers for 15&#x000a0;cycles, and library fragments of ~&#x000a0;200&#x02013;400&#x000a0;bp (insert plus adaptor and PCR primer sequences) were band isolated from an agarose gel. The purified DNA was captured on an Illumina flow cell for cluster generation. Libraries were sequenced on the Genome Analyzer IIx following the manufacturer's protocols.</p></sec><sec id="s0040"><title>Data processing</title><p><xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>B shows the bioinformatics pipeline used. Illumina Casava 1.8 software was used for basecalling. All reads were merged in the one file. Next, reads were trimmed for RAFT primer sequences by cutadapt v. 1.2.1 using the following options: --minimum-length&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;30 --trimmed-only --quality-base&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;33 --quality-cutoff&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3 -n 2 -g CCCAAGCTTAAGCGGCCGCAAAC -g CCGAATTCTCCTTATACTGCAGGGG. Option &#x0201c;--trimmed-only&#x0201d; was used to remove all sequences that do not have RAFT primers. Trimmed reads were mapped to rDNA (GenBank Accession number <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="ncbi-n:U13369" id="ir0035">U13369</ext-link>) and to hg19/GRCh37p10 by bwa <xref rid="bb0040" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref> 0.7.5a using mem algorithm and SAMtools 0.1.12a-r862 <xref rid="bb0045" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>. Variant calling was also performed by SAMtools. Final mappings were converted for further analysis into tables and formats, including BED and WIG, by <italic>ad hoc</italic> Perl scripts. The further genometric analysis was performed using GenometriCorr software package <xref rid="bb0050" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>.</p><p>Profile-like curves were obtained in the following way. First, the density coverage for the each alignment file was obtained by BEDTools <xref rid="bb0055" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>: bamToBed -ed. Second, the data were converted by density.bed to the profile data with F-seq <xref rid="bb0065" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>: fseq -f 200 density.bed. The resulting WIG files were converted to the common ASCII coordinate format files by our own <italic>ad hoc</italic> Perl script.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0005"><title>Discussion</title><p>The RAFT procedure includes several steps of manipulations with very long DNA molecules in solution (<xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>A)&#x02014;from elution of DNA domains to ligation of biotinylated oligonucleotide (steps 2&#x02013;5 in <xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>A). Although only a gentle mixing of solution after addition of ligase was performed, a random fragmentation of forum domains cannot be excluded during these steps. Nevertheless, our data demonstrate that the level of this random hydrodynamic fragmentation of DNA molecules in the conditions used is much lower than the non-random fragmentation detected at hot spots of DSBs (<xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>). The outline of mapped reads inside rDNA within one hot spot is shown in <xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>A. Nine major hot spots of DSBs, which we denote as Pleiades, were detected (<xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>B). We are aware that these data correspond to repeated rDNA units. There are about 300 copies of rDNA genes in the human genome <xref rid="bb0070" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>. It follows that to map the hot spot of DSBs with the same robustness as within unique genomic regions, one needs a higher number of original Illumina reads corresponding to the entire genome. Currently, we perform such analyses using HiSeq 2000 reads.</p><p>The validation of the approach was performed by comparison of the data obtained in different experiments using both the independent RAFT preparations and the deep-sequencing platforms. In these experiments, the same profiles of DSB hot spots were detected inside human rDNA units (<xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>B). The data regarding the correlation between the mapping data using GenometriCorr software package <xref rid="bb0050" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref> are shown in <xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;1</xref>.</p><p>The data on hot spots of DSBs inside rDNA units strongly suggest that the <italic>in vivo</italic> chromosomal breakage is associated with active transcription in these units, producing up to 80% of total cellular RNA in human cells <xref rid="bb0070" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>. Our data indicate that the hot spots of DSBs correspond to sites that are important for both regulation of expression and for inter- and intra-chromosomal interactions with specific regions of chromosomes also possessing hot spots of DSBs <xref rid="bb0025" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, <xref rid="bb0075" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. These data, taken together with the data on coordinated expression of genes located in forum domains that are delimited by hot spots of DSBs and binding sites of PARP1 and HRNPA2B1 <xref rid="bb0020" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, suggest that forum domains share some properties in common with so-called topological or interacting domains <xref rid="bb0080" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>. The data on mapping of hot spots of DSBs are important in cancer genomics and for the study of chromosomal translocations, including Robertsonian translocations involving five human chromosomes bearing rDNA clusters.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bb0005"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0005"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tchurikov</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ponomarenko</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Airich</surname><given-names>L.G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation of forum DNA&#x02014;a specific fraction in human DNA</article-title><source>Dokl. Akad. Nauk USSR</source><volume>303</volume><year>1988</year><fpage>491</fpage><lpage>497</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0010"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0010"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tchurikov</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ponomarenko</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detection of DNA domains in <italic>Drosophila</italic>, human and plant chromosomes possessing mainly 50- to 150-kilobase stretches of DNA</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.</source><volume>89</volume><year>1992</year><fpage>6751</fpage><lpage>6755</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1495963</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0015"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0015"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tchurikov</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kretova</surname><given-names>O.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sosin</surname><given-names>D.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zykov</surname><given-names>I.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhimulev</surname><given-names>I.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kravatsky</surname><given-names>Y.V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide profiling of forum domains in <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic></article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>39</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>3667</fpage><lpage>3685</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21247882</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0020"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0065"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tchurikov</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kretova</surname><given-names>O.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fedoseeva</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sosin</surname><given-names>D.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grachev</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Serebraykova</surname><given-names>M.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Romanenko</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vorobieva</surname><given-names>N.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kravatsky</surname><given-names>Y.V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DNA double-strand breaks coupled with PARP1 and HNRNPA2B1 binding sites flank coordinately expressed domains in human chromosomes</article-title><source>PLoS Genet.</source><volume>9</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>e1003429</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23593027</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0025"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0070"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tchurikov</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fedoseeva</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sosin</surname><given-names>D.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Snezhkina</surname><given-names>A.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Melnikova</surname><given-names>N.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kudryavtseva</surname><given-names>A.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kravatsky</surname><given-names>Y.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kretova</surname><given-names>O.V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hot spots of DNA double-strand breaks and genomic contacts of human rDNA units are involved in epigenetic regulation</article-title><source>J. Mol. Cell Biol.</source><volume>0</volume><issue>0</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>17</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0030"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0025"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tchurikov</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Krasnov</surname><given-names>A.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ponomarenko</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Golova</surname><given-names>Y.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chernov</surname><given-names>B.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Forum domain in <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> cut locus possesses looped domains inside</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>26</volume><year>1998</year><fpage>3221</fpage><lpage>3227</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9628922</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0035"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0030"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tchurikov</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kretova</surname><given-names>O.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chernov</surname><given-names>B.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Golova</surname><given-names>Y.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhimulev</surname><given-names>I.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zykov</surname><given-names>I.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SuUR protein binds to the boundary regions separating forum domains in <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic></article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><volume>279</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>11705</fpage><lpage>11710</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14702350</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0040"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0035"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Durbin</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fast and accurate long-read alignment with Burrows&#x02013;Wheeler Transform</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>26</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>589</fpage><lpage>595</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20080505</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0045"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0075"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Handsaker</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wysoker</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fennell</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Homer</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marth</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abecasis</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Durbin</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>1000 Genome Project Data Processing Subgroup</surname></name></person-group><article-title>The Sequence alignment/map (SAM) format and SAMtools</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>25</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>2078</fpage><lpage>2209</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19505943</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0050"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0080"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Favorov</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mularoni</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cope</surname><given-names>L.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Medvedeva</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mironov</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Makeev</surname><given-names>V.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wheelan</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exploring massive, genome scale datasets with the GenometriCorr Package</article-title><source>PLoS Comput. Biol.</source><volume>8</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>e1002529</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22693437</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0055"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0085"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quinlan</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>I.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>BEDTools: a flexible suite of utilities for comparing genomic features</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>26</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>841</fpage><lpage>842</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20110278</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0065"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0045"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boyle</surname><given-names>A.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guinney</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>G.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Furey</surname><given-names>T.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>F-Seq: a feature density estimator for high-throughput sequence tags</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>24</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>2537</fpage><lpage>2538</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18784119</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0070"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0050"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stults</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Killen</surname><given-names>M.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>E.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hourigan</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vargas</surname><given-names>H.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moscow</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pierce</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Human rRNA gene clusters are recombinational hotspots in cancer</article-title><source>Cancer Res.</source><volume>69</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>9096</fpage><lpage>9104</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19920195</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0075"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0055"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sosin</surname><given-names>D.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kretova</surname><given-names>O.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kravatsky</surname><given-names>Y.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tchurikov</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of genome-wide contacts of forum terminus in <italic>Drosophila</italic> S2 cells</article-title><source>Dokl. Biochem. Biophys.</source><volume>452</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>259</fpage><lpage>263</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24150587</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0080"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0060"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Selvaraj</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yue</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Topological domains in mammalian genomes identified by analysis of chromatin interactions</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>11</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>376</fpage><lpage>380</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22495300</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><ack id="ac0005"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>This work was supported by a grant from the Molecular and Cellular Biology Program of the <funding-source id="gts0010">Russian Academy of Sciences</funding-source> (#130220122525) and by grants from the <funding-source id="gts0005">Russian Foundation for Basic Research</funding-source> (#12-04-01416-a, #12-04-01311-&#x00430;, #14-04-01638-a, and #15-04-00299-a).</p></ack></back><floats-group><fig id="f0005"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Schematic representation of the procedure used for isolation of DNA samples inside 0.5% low-melt agarose.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig><fig id="f0010"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Experimental and bioinformatics pipelines. (A) The major steps of the RAFT procedure. (B) Bioinformatics analysis pipeline.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig><fig id="f0015"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Analysis of Illumina reads mapped inside rDNA units. (A) The mapping results of Illumina reads inside rDNA units using UGENE software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ugene.unipro.ru/" id="ir0025">http://ugene.unipro.ru/</ext-link>). The reads (1197 rows) that mapped the region of rDNA between 21.2 and 21.5&#x000a0;kb coordinates inside the 43-kb rDNA sequence (accession number U13369) are shown schematically. The region is indicated in panel B as R2. There are regions possessing many more mapped Illumina reads (R4&#x02013;R9 on the panel B). The bracket at the top shows the region of about 100&#x000a0;bp in length where DSBs are scattered. The arrow indicates the position of the Sau3A site that delimits the Illumina reads. (B). Comparison of profiles of DSBs determined in independent RAFT experiments using 454 or Illumina platforms. Hot spots of DSBs are indicated as R1&#x02013;R9 (Pleiades).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr3"/></fig><table-wrap id="t0005" position="float"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Correlation of the data on mapping of DSBs in a rDNA unit obtained by 454 or Illumina sequencing.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Tracks</th><th align="left">Relative distances by Kolmogorov&#x02013;Smirnov test</th><th align="left">Projection test</th><th align="left">Jaccard test</th><th align="left">Scaled absolute minimum distances test</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Illumina&#x02013;454</td><td align="left">Passed, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.0047</td><td align="left">Passed, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0</td><td align="left">Passed, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.001</td><td align="left">Passed, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.017</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>The Illumina's track was used as the reference, and the Roche 454 track was used as the query. GenometriCorr can process only segmented tracks (not profiles) in formats like BED, and so we used this type of data for the calculation of correlations. Results that are presented in the table are consistent with the visual analysis, and support the consistency of DSB mapping using different platforms and independent RAFT experiments.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></floats-group></article>