<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="abstract" xml:lang="en"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Head Face Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Head Face Med</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Head &#x00026; Face Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1746-160X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4304415</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1746-160X-10-S1-O3</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-160X-10-S1-O3</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Meeting Abstract</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Surgery first - prediction of surgical movements based on untreated cases</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A1"><name><surname>Stamm</surname><given-names>Thomas</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A2"><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>Susanne</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A3"><name><surname>Prigge</surname><given-names>Gudrun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A4"><name><surname>Kleinheinz</surname><given-names>Johannes</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Orthodontics, University Clinic M&#x000fc;nster, M&#x000fc;nster, Germany</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Department of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery, University Clinic M&#x000fc;nster, M&#x000fc;nster, Germany</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>12</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue>Suppl 1</issue><supplement><named-content content-type="supplement-title">IBRA Conference on Surgery of the Head, 6th International Orthognathic Surgery Forum: Meeting Abstracts</named-content></supplement><fpage>O3</fpage><lpage>O3</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2014 Stamm et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Stamm et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.head-face-med.com/content/10/S1/O3"/><conference><conf-date>14-15 February 2014</conf-date><conf-name>IBRA Conference on Surgery of the Head, 6th International Orthognathic Surgery Forum</conf-name><conf-loc>Interlaken, Switzerland</conf-loc></conference></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Aim</title><p>The aim of the study was to test the following hypothesis: There is no difference in orthognathic surgery protocols planned on pre-treatment patient records (Surgery First protocols) compared to surgery protocols planned on patient records after orthodontic preparation (Surgery Late protocols).</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Material and methods</title><p>Study type: Prospective, randomised, semi blinded trial. One hundred fifteen traditional treated orthognathic surgery cases were included based on inclusion and exclusion criteria. Pre-treatment records of the 115 cases were presented to a surgery team (surgeons, orthodontists) to generate a Surgery First protocol. The Surgery First protocols were then compared with the true (Surgery Late) protocols of the treated cases. The statistical power was 95%.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p>Surgery First and Surgery Late protocols of the same cases differ significantly. Impaction of the maxilla is the most predictable surgical movement with a mean error radius of 2.4 mm &#x000b1; 1.9 mm for each measurement landmark. Maxillary advancement showed an error radius of 3.2 mm &#x000b1; 2.9 mm. The highest errors were found in mandibular advancement / set back with 6.3 mm &#x000b1; 4.3 mm on each side. Overall the errors add up to 14.8 mm &#x000b1; 6.8 mm. Angle classes do not differ significantly concerning the planning errors.</p></sec><sec><title>Discussion and conclusion</title><p>The hypothesis that there is no difference between Surgery First and Surgery Late protocols must be rejected. Planning errors with the Surgery First concept are not predictable. The post-operative malocclusion generated with Surgery First could lead to situations which are not manageable with orthodontics. There is a high risk of unfavourable occlusion and further corrective surgery at the end of treatment. The initial Angle class is not a valid predictor of low or high planning errors.</p></sec></body></article>