<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Hum Genet</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Hum. Genet</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Human Genetics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0340-6717</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1432-1203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer Berlin Heidelberg</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Berlin/Heidelberg</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24509779</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4053598</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1427</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00439-014-1427-3</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Investigation</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Characterization of the DYX2 locus on chromosome 6p22 with reading disability, language impairment, and IQ</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Eicher</surname><given-names>John D.</given-names></name><address><email>john.eicher@yale.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Powers</surname><given-names>Natalie R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>Laura L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>Kathryn L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mascheretti</surname><given-names>Sara</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Marino</surname><given-names>Cecilia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff7"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff8"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Willcutt</surname><given-names>Erik G.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff9"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff10"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>DeFries</surname><given-names>John C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff9"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff10"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>Richard K.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff9"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff10"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>Shelley D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff11"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pennington</surname><given-names>Bruce F.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff12"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tomblin</surname><given-names>J. Bruce</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ring</surname><given-names>Susan M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gruen</surname><given-names>Jeffrey R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff13"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label/>Department of Genetics, Yale University School of Medicine, New Haven, CT USA </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label/>Department of Pediatrics, Yale University School of Medicine, New Haven, CT USA </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label/>MRC Integrative Epidemiology Unit, School of Social and Community Medicine, University of Bristol, Bristol, UK </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label/>Hearing, Language and Literacy, Murdoch Childrens Institute, Melbourne, Australia </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label/>Department of Communication Sciences and Disorders, The University of Iowa, Iowa City, IA USA </aff><aff id="Aff6"><label/>Child Psychopathology Unit, Scientific Institute, IRCCS Eugenio Medea, Bosisio Parini, Lecco Italy </aff><aff id="Aff7"><label/>Centre de Recherche de l&#x02019;Institut Universitaire en Sant&#x000e9; Mentale de Qu&#x000e9;bec, Qu&#x000e9;bec, Canada </aff><aff id="Aff8"><label/>Department of Psychiatry and Neuroscience, Universit&#x000e9; Laval, Qu&#x000e9;bec, Canada </aff><aff id="Aff9"><label/>Institute for Behavioral Genetics, University of Colorado, Boulder, CO USA </aff><aff id="Aff10"><label/>Department of Psychology and Neuroscience, University of Colorado, Boulder, CO USA </aff><aff id="Aff11"><label/>Departments of Pediatrics and Developmental Neuroscience, University of Nebraska Medical Center, Omaha, NE USA </aff><aff id="Aff12"><label/>Department of Psychology, University of Denver, Denver, CO USA </aff><aff id="Aff13"><label/>Investigative Medicine Program, Yale Child Health Research Center, Yale University School of Medicine, New Haven, CT USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>9</day><month>2</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>9</day><month>2</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>133</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>869</fpage><lpage>881</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>10</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>1</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2014</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License which permits any use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author(s) and the source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p>Reading disability (RD) and language impairment (LI) are common neurodevelopmental disorders with moderately strong genetic components and lifelong implications. RD and LI are marked by unexpected difficulty acquiring and processing written and verbal language, respectively, despite adequate opportunity and instruction. RD and LI&#x02014;and their associated deficits&#x02014;are complex, multifactorial, and often comorbid. Genetic studies have repeatedly implicated the DYX2 locus, specifically the genes <italic>DCDC2</italic> and <italic>KIAA0319</italic>, in RD, with recent studies suggesting they also influence LI, verbal language, and cognition. Here, we characterize the relationship of the DYX2 locus with RD, LI, and IQ. To accomplish this, we developed a marker panel densely covering the 1.4&#x000a0;Mb DYX2 locus and assessed association with reading, language, and IQ measures in subjects from the Avon Longitudinal Study of Parents and Children. We then replicated associations in three independent, disorder-selected cohorts. As expected, there were associations with known RD risk genes <italic>KIAA0319</italic> and <italic>DCDC2</italic>. In addition, we implicated markers in or near other DYX2 genes, including <italic>TDP2</italic>, <italic>ACOT13</italic>, <italic>C6orf62</italic>, <italic>FAM65B</italic>, and <italic>CMAHP</italic>. However, the LD structure of the locus suggests that associations within <italic>TDP2</italic>, <italic>ACOT13</italic>, and <italic>C6orf62</italic> are capturing a previously reported risk variant in <italic>KIAA0319</italic>. Our results further substantiate the candidacy of <italic>KIAA0319</italic> and <italic>DCDC2</italic> as major effector genes in DYX2, while proposing <italic>FAM65B</italic> and <italic>CMAHP</italic> as new DYX2 candidate genes. Association of DYX2 with multiple neurobehavioral traits suggests risk variants have functional consequences affecting multiple neurological processes. Future studies should dissect these functional, possibly interactive relationships of DYX2 candidate genes.</p><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>The online version of this article (doi:10.1007/s00439-014-1427-3) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></sec></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Springer-Verlag Berlin Heidelberg 2014</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p>Communication disorders and learning disabilities are common, and can have long-lasting, adverse effects on affected individuals&#x02019; academic performance, self-esteem, and socioeconomic outcomes. Specifically, reading disability (RD or dyslexia) and language impairment (LI) affect 5&#x02013;17 and 5&#x02013;8&#x000a0;% of schoolchildren, respectively (Newbury et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2010</xref>; Pennington and Bishop <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">2009</xref>). RD and LI are characterized by unexpected difficulties with reading and verbal language, respectively, despite adequate educational and socioeconomic opportunity and instruction, as well as otherwise normal development (Pennington and Bishop <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">2009</xref>; Newbury et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2010</xref>). Written and verbal language are closely related and share several neurocognitive processes, including phonological processing and short-term memory (Catts et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2005</xref>; Gathercole and Baddeley <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">1993</xref>; Newbury et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2010</xref>; Pennington <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">2006</xref>; Pennington and Bishop <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">2009</xref>; Wise et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">2007</xref>). In fact, children with LI are more likely to develop RD than their non-impaired peers (Pennington and Bishop <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">2009</xref>).</p><p>RD and LI are complex disorders with substantial genetic and environmental components (Bishop and Hayiou-Thomas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2008</xref>; Viding et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">2004</xref>). For instance, the DYX2 locus on chromosome 6p22 has been consistently implicated in RD (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) (Cardon et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">1994</xref>; Deffenbacher et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2004</xref>; Gay&#x000e1;n et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">1999</xref>; Kaplan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2002</xref>). Two DYX2 genes, <italic>DCDC2</italic> and <italic>KIAA0319</italic>, have been identified as RD risk genes, with considerable genetic and functional molecular evidence supporting the involvement of each (Couto et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2010</xref>; Cope et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2005</xref>; Elbert et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2011</xref>; Francks et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2004</xref>; Harold et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2006</xref>; Lind et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2010</xref>; Luciano et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2007</xref>; Marino et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2012</xref>; Meng et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2005</xref>; Newbury et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2011</xref>; Paracchini et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2008</xref>; Powers et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">2013</xref>; Scerri et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">2011</xref>; Schumacher et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">2006</xref>; Wilcke et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">2009</xref>; Zhong et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">2013</xref>; Zou et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">2012</xref>). Both <italic>DCDC2</italic> and <italic>KIAA0319</italic> function in neuronal migration during brain development, as demonstrated by in utero RNAi knockdown studies in rat (Meng et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2005</xref>; Paracchini et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2006</xref>). In both genes, putative functional variants appear to be regulatory in nature, as opposed to coding mutations. We previously identified a compound tandem repeat located within the breakpoints of a microdeletion in intron 2 of <italic>DCDC2</italic> as a risk variant (Marino et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2012</xref>; Meng et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2011</xref>; Powers et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">2013</xref>). This repeat, known as regulatory element associated with dyslexia 1 (READ1), specifically binds the transcription factor ETV6 and appears capable of modulating expression from the <italic>DCDC2</italic> promoter (Meng et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2011</xref>; Powers et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">2013</xref>). Within <italic>KIAA0319</italic>, the most strongly associated variant with RD is a 3-marker risk haplotype that spans approximately the 5&#x02032; half of the gene and some of its upstream sequence and neighboring gene <italic>TDP2</italic> (Cope et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2005</xref>; Francks et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2004</xref>; Paracchini et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2006</xref>). Both the risk haplotype itself and a putative functional SNP (rs9461045) in linkage disequilibrium with it have been shown to correlate with lower expression of the <italic>KIAA0319</italic> gene (Dennis et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2009</xref>; Elbert et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2011</xref>). Interestingly, there is evidence that READ1 and the <italic>KIAA0319</italic> risk haplotype interact in a non-additive fashion, suggesting that transcriptional co-regulation and interaction may play a key role in the relationship between the DYX2 locus and written/verbal language (Ludwig et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2008</xref>; Powers et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">2013</xref>).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Schematic of the genes within the DYX2 locus on chromosome 6p22. Genes in <italic>blue</italic>, <italic>DCDC2</italic> and <italic>KIAA0319</italic>, have replicated associations with written and verbal language phenotypes, namely RD and LI. Regions in <italic>red mark</italic> two functional variants, READ1 in <italic>DCDC2</italic> and a risk haplotype containing markers in <italic>KIAA0319</italic> and <italic>TDP2</italic>, which have been functionally associated with RD and LI using animal models and molecular techniques</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="439_2014_1427_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><p>Although the literature suggests that variants in <italic>DCDC2</italic> and <italic>KIAA0319</italic> are predominantly responsible for the linkage and association signals from DYX2, other genes and elements may also contribute. The <italic>KIAA0319</italic> risk haplotype spans part of the neighboring gene <italic>TDP2</italic> (previously known as <italic>TTRAP</italic>), raising the question of whether the risk haplotype also tags risk variants in <italic>TDP2</italic> (Cope et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2005</xref>; Francks et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2004</xref>; Paracchini et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2006</xref>). <italic>ACOT13</italic> (previously known as <italic>THEM2</italic>), a gene adjacent to <italic>TDP2</italic>, was associated with asymmetry in functional activation of the superior temporal sulcus during reading tasks (Pinel et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">2012</xref>). Genetic linkage analysis showed a linkage peak for full-scale and verbal IQ within <italic>ALDH5A1</italic>, located between <italic>KIAA0319</italic> and <italic>DCDC2</italic> (Plomin et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">2004</xref>). Verbal IQ is correlated with reading and language skills, so this linkage result may reflect verbal skills measured during IQ testing. <italic>ALDH5A1</italic> encodes succinic semialdehyde dehydrogenase (SSADH), which influences the neuromodulator &#x003b3;-hydroxybutyrate and the metabolism of &#x003b3;-amino-butyric acid (GABA). Recent investigations have associated other neurotransmitter factors, including <italic>DRD2</italic>, <italic>DRD4</italic>, and <italic>COMT</italic>, with verbal language and LI, suggesting that neural signaling influences linguistic and cognitive traits (Beaver et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2010</xref>; Eicher et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2013a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">b</xref>; Landi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2013</xref>; Wong et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">2013</xref>). Limited studies of other genes in the DYX2 locus suggest that they may also contribute to reading and language processes and their disorders.</p><p>The degree of relatedness of RD and LI indicates that they may share genetic and environmental risk factors. There are reports suggesting that some genes previously associated with RD also associate with LI, and vice versa. Within the DYX2 locus, <italic>KIAA0319</italic> has been associated with verbal language as well as reading (Newbury et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2011</xref>). The most widely studied gene in relation to language, <italic>FOXP2</italic>, was first implicated in verbal language disorders including dyspraxia of speech and LI, but various studies have expanded these associations with RD, as well as to endophenotypes identified using brain imaging methods (Fisher et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">1998</xref>,; Kaminen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2003</xref>; Lai et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2001</xref>; Peter et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">2011</xref>; Pinel et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">2012</xref>; Wilcke et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">2011</xref>). Similarly, <italic>CMIP</italic> was first implicated in LI and later associated with reading-related traits (Newbury et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2011</xref>; Scerri et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">2011</xref>). Recently, we performed a genome-wide association study (GWAS) on individuals with comorbid RD and LI, which identified <italic>ZNF385D</italic> as a contributor to processes underlying both disorders (Eicher et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2013b</xref>). There is strong evidence that RD and LI share genetic components; however, the specific genes and variants contributing to this shared genetic etiology remain largely unknown, as studies have typically been limited in overall number, number of genes examined, and statistical power. In particular, studies of the DYX2 locus have generally not covered the entire DYX2 locus or have tagged it incompletely, and have likely been underpowered to detect single-variant effects.</p><p>Therefore, the overall goal of this study was to characterize the associations of the DYX2 locus with RD, LI, and cognition as measured by IQ scores. To accomplish this task, we developed a single-nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) marker panel designed to capture the known common variation of the entire DYX2 locus. We genotyped this DYX2 marker panel in the Avon Longitudinal Study of Parents and Children (ALSPAC) and performed association analysis using reading, language, and cognitive measures collected between the ages of 7 and 9&#x000a0;years. We then replicated our associations in three cohorts selected for either RD or LI. We hypothesized that we would confirm the associations of <italic>DCDC2</italic> and <italic>KIAA0319</italic> with RD and LI and refine the locations of and possibly identify the variants responsible for these associations. Our results implicating a six-marker haplotype block in linkage disequilibrium with the READ1 element in <italic>DCDC2</italic> with Severe RD, and its non-additive genetic interaction with <italic>KIAA0319</italic> on reading, verbal language, and IQ performance are presented elsewhere (Powers et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">2013</xref>). Here, we report the additional results of the DYX2 association scan of RD, LI, and IQ.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Subjects</title><p>Our discovery cohort in this investigation was the Avon Longitudinal Study of Parents and Children (ALSPAC). The ALSPAC is a population-based birth cohort based in Avon, United Kingdom. Subjects were recruited before birth&#x02014;a total of 15,458 fetuses were recruited, of whom 14,701 were alive at 1&#x000a0;year of age. Recruitment, participants, and study methodologies are described in detail elsewhere (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bristol.ac.uk/alspac">http://www.bristol.ac.uk/alspac</ext-link>) (Boyd et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2012</xref>; Golding et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2001</xref>). The study website contains details of all the data that are available through a fully searchable data dictionary (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bris.ac.uk/alspac/researchers/data-access/data-dictionary">http://www.bris.ac.uk/alspac/researchers/data-access/data-dictionary</ext-link>). DNA samples for genetic analysis were available for 10,259 subjects. Reading, language, and IQ were assessed at ages 7, 8, and 9&#x000a0;years using standardized measures. We excluded subjects with IQ <underline>&#x0003c;</underline>75 on the Wechsler Intelligence Scale for Children (WISC-III) full scale IQ to prevent confounding effects of intellectual disability (Eicher et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2013a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">b</xref>; Powers et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">2013</xref>; Wechsler et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">1992</xref>). To prevent population stratification in genetic analyses, we excluded subjects of non-European descent. Samples with overall genotype call rates &#x0003c;0.85 were also excluded from analyses. This resulted in a final sample of 5,579 individuals for language-related analyses and 5,525 individuals for reading-related analyses. Ethical approval was obtained from the ALSPAC Ethics and Law Committee, Local UK Research Ethics Committees, and the Yale Human Investigation Committee.</p><p>Following discovery analyses in the ALSPAC, we replicated associated markers in three cohorts specifically recruited for either RD or LI (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The Iowa LI cohort is composed of 219 LI cases and 209 sex- and age-matched, unrelated controls collected at the University of Iowa. Subjects within the Iowa LI cohort completed a battery of language measures, which were used to derive a composite language score. This composite score was then dichotomized into case&#x02013;control status at &#x02212;1.14 standard deviations (Eicher et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2013a</xref>; Tomblin et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">1996</xref>; Weismer et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">2000</xref>). The Colorado Learning Disabilities Research Center (CLDRC) or Colorado RD cohort consists of 1,188 individuals within 292 families of twin pairs and their siblings. Families were recruited to the study if at least one member of each twin pair had a history of reading problems (Meng et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2005</xref>). Within the Colorado RD cohort, RD cases were defined as individuals with a discriminant score below the mean of an age- and sex-matched sample of twins with no school history for RD. The discriminant score is a weighted composite of the reading recognition, comprehension, and spelling subtests of the Peabody Individual Achievement test (PIAT) (Gay&#x000e1;n et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">1999</xref>). In the case of monozygotic twins, only one member of each twin pair was used for this study. The Italian cohort consists of 878 individuals in 304 nuclear families; these families were recruited via a proband with clinically diagnosed RD (Marino et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2012</xref>). Probands were diagnosed with RD if they scored two or more standard deviations below expected grade level on speed or accuracy on text, word, or nonword reading, had a full-scale IQ of at least 85, and did not have any sensory or neurological disorder (Marino et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2012</xref>). Ethical approval for recruitment and study methodologies were obtained from the Yale Human Investigation Committee, Institutional Review Boards at the University of Iowa, the University of Denver, University of Colorado-Boulder, University of Nebraska Medical Center, and the Scientific Review Board and the Ethical Committee of the Eugenio Medea Scientific Institute.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Replication cohorts</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left">Iowa LI</th><th align="left">Colorado RD</th><th align="left">Italy RD</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Cohort-type</td><td align="left">Case&#x02013;control</td><td align="left">Family-based</td><td align="left">Family-based</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Number of subjects</td><td align="left">428</td><td align="left">1,188</td><td align="left">878</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Number of families</td><td align="left">N/A</td><td align="left">292</td><td align="left">304</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Disorder</td><td align="left">LI</td><td align="left">RD</td><td align="left">RD</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Analysis</td><td align="left">SVS</td><td align="left">TDT (PLINK)</td><td align="left">TDT (PLINK)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Association conditioned on:</td><td align="left">Case&#x02013;control status</td><td align="left">Case&#x02013;control status, discriminant score</td><td align="left">Case&#x02013;control status</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Case status determined by:</td><td align="left">Composite score on language measures</td><td align="left">Composite discriminant score on reading tasks</td><td align="left">Text-, single-word, or non-word reading tasks</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>ALSPAC reading, language, and IQ measures</title><p>In ALSPAC, reading measures used in this investigation included a phoneme deletion task at age 7&#x000a0;years, single-word reading tasks at ages 7 and 9&#x000a0;years, and a single non-word reading task at age 9&#x000a0;years (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). The phoneme deletion task, also known as the Auditory Analysis test, measures phoneme awareness, a core deficit in RD (Rosner and Simon <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">1971</xref>). For this task, the child listens to a word spoken aloud and is then asked to remove a specific phoneme from that word to make a new word. Single-word reading was assessed at age 7&#x000a0;years using the reading subtest of the Wechsler objective reading dimensions (WORD) (Rust et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">1993</xref>). At age 9&#x000a0;years, single-word reading was again assessed by asking the child to read ten real words and ten non-words aloud (Nunes et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2003</xref>). To examine severe cases (Severe RD), we defined cases as having a score 2 or more standard deviations below the mean on the phoneme deletion task (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). We also defined cases with Moderate RD as scoring at least 1 standard deviation below the mean on single-word reading at age 7&#x000a0;years, single-word reading at age 9&#x000a0;years, and single non-word reading at age 9&#x000a0;years (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). We chose a threshold of 1 standard deviation as we included three different measures to isolate individuals with persistently poor decoding skills. We examined different severity levels because past studies in the DYX2 locus have shown differences in genetic association patterns depending on case severity, particularly with <italic>KIAA0319</italic> associating with more moderate RD case definitions and <italic>DCDC2</italic> with more severe definitions (Paracchini et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2008</xref>; Powers et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">2013</xref>; Scerri et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">2011</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>ALSPAC phenotype measures</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Measure</th><th align="left">Domain</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Phoneme deletion (PD) age 7&#x000a0;years</td><td align="left">Reading</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Single-word reading (SWR7) age 7&#x000a0;years</td><td align="left">Reading</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Single non-word reading (SNR) age 7&#x000a0;years</td><td align="left">Reading</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Single-word reading (SWR9) age 9&#x000a0;years</td><td align="left">Reading</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Wechsler objective language dimensions (WOLD) verbal comprehension age 8 years</td><td align="left">Language</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Nonword repetition task (NWR) age 8&#x000a0;years</td><td align="left">Language</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Wechsler Intelligence Scale for Children (WISC) full scale IQ (FSIQ) age 8 Years</td><td align="left">IQ</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Wechsler Intelligence Scale for Children (WISC) verbal IQ (VIQ) age 8 Years</td><td align="left">IQ</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Wechsler Intelligence Scale for Children (WISC) performance IQ (PIQ) age 8 Years</td><td align="left">IQ</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Phenotype definitions for ALSPAC analyses</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left">Phenotype definition</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">Reading (RD)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Severe RD</td><td align="left">2 Standard deviations below sample mean on the phoneme deletion task</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Moderate RD</td><td align="left">1 Standard deviation below sample mean on SWR7, SNR, and SWR tasks</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">Language (LI)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Severe LI</td><td align="left">2 Standard deviations below sample mean on either WOLD and/or NWR tasks</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Moderate WOLD</td><td align="left">1.5 Standard deviations below sample mean on the WOLD task</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Moderate NWR</td><td align="left">1.5 Standard deviations below sample mean on the NWR task</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">Cognition (IQ)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Total IQ</td><td align="left">Quantitative performance on WISC Total IQ task</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Verbal IQ</td><td align="left">Quantitative performance on WISC Verbal IQ task</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Performance IQ</td><td align="left">Quantitative performance on WISC Performance IQ task</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p>Language measures were collected at age 8&#x000a0;years (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). An adaptation of the nonword repetition task (NWR), in which subjects repeated recordings of nonwords, was used to assess short-term phonological memory and processing abilities (Gathercole and Baddeley <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">1996</xref>). Children also completed the Wechsler objective language dimensions (WOLD) verbal comprehension task at age 8&#x000a0;years (Wechsler <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">1996</xref>), where they answered questions about a paragraph read aloud by an examiner describing a presented picture. We chose these measures because individuals with LI are known to perform consistently poorly on NWR and WOLD tasks (Bishop et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">1996</xref>; Newbury et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2009</xref>). As with RD, we were interested in the association of the DYX2 locus in relation to severity of LI. Here, we defined severe LI cases by scores of 2 or more standard deviations below the sample mean on either language task (severe LI) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). In contrast, we defined two classes of moderate cases as scoring at least 1.5 standard deviations below the sample mean on either the NWR or WOLD task each task (moderate NWR and moderate WOLD) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Verbal IQ, performance IQ, and full scale IQ were assessed at age 8&#x000a0;years, using the Wechsler Intelligence Scale for Children (WISC-III) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). IQ measures were examined as quantitative traits (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Genotyping and genetic analyses</title><p>We developed a SNP marker panel in an attempt to capture the common variation in the DYX2 locus. TagSNPs in the locus were selected using the association study design server of Han et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2008</xref>). The final DYX2 panel contained 195 SNPs with an estimated average power of 83 and 68&#x000a0;% to capture known common and rare variants, respectively, in the DYX2 locus spanning approximately 1.4&#x000a0;Mb. Markers were genotyped on the Sequenom MassARRAY platform (San Diego, CA) following manufacturer&#x02019;s guidelines at the Yale Center for Genome Analysis (West Haven, CT). Briefly, markers were genotyped in nine multiplex reactions of 30&#x02013;36 markers each, totaling 300 markers (Supplemental Table&#x000a0;1). A subset of markers was not in the DYX2 locus and was not included in the subsequent characterization of the DYX2 locus. In addition to quality control via call rate and Hardy&#x02013;Weinberg, the histogram plot for each marker was manually evaluated, and a total of 15 markers showing aberrant patterns were excluded. To control for errors in labeling and manipulation of plates, the samples were also genotyped for four sex-determining SNPs in the genes <italic>AMELXY</italic> and <italic>ZNFXY</italic> in the pseudoautosomal regions of the X and Y chromosomes. These SNPs correctly determined sex for 99.5&#x000a0;% of samples; the remaining samples were excluded.</p><p>Markers that deviated substantially from Hardy&#x02013;Weinberg equilibrium (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.0001), or that had an overall call rate &#x0003c;85&#x000a0;%, were not used for genetic analyses. In the discovery ALSPAC cohort, single marker SNP analyses of case&#x02013;control status and quantitative traits were completed using SNP and variation suite (SVS) v7.6.4 (Bozeman, MT). Linkage disequilibrium was assessed and haplotype blocks were constructed using the four-gamete rule option in HaploView v4.2. Haplotype-based association tests were performed with haplotypes that had frequencies &#x02265;1&#x000a0;% using PLINK v1.07 (Barrett et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2005</xref>; Purcell et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">2007</xref>). To correct for multiple testing, we used a Bonferroni threshold of 0.000256 (0.05 divided by 195 markers) for discovery association tests in the ALSPAC cohort. However, associations with <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001 are also reported for the ALSPAC discovery cohort to indicate suggestive results.</p><p>We tested SNPs that had single marker or within-haplotype associations with <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001 in the ALSPAC for replication in the Iowa LI, Italian RD, and Colorado RD cohorts. Iowa LI was analyzed using SVS v7.6.4 (Bozeman, MT), while the family-based Italian RD and Colorado RD cohorts were examined using PLINK v1.07 (Purcell et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">2007</xref>). We moved suggestive ALSPAC results forward to our replication analyses to emphasize replication of associations over statistical corrections for multiple testing. Replications with<italic> p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05 in the Iowa LI, Italian RD, and Colorado RD cohorts are reported.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec6" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p>We performed association with DYX2 markers in three separate domains: (1) RD, (2) LI, and (3) IQ. For the sake of clarity, we present our association findings domain-by-domain, with an emphasis on replication as opposed to correction for multiple testing.</p><sec id="Sec7"><title>RD</title><p>We performed associations with RD using two different severity definitions: (1) Severe RD and (2) Moderate RD (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). For Severe RD, we observed single marker associations with <italic>KIAA0319</italic> and <italic>TDP2</italic> (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). There was an association of a six-marker haplotype within <italic>DCDC2</italic> that is linked to the risk element READ1 and Severe RD that is explored fully in Powers et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">2013</xref>). <italic>TDP2</italic> marker rs2294691 did not replicate its association in any of the three replication cohorts (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref>). However, <italic>KIAA0319</italic> marker rs10456309 did replicate in Iowa LI and Colorado RD cohorts (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref>). With Moderate RD, there was an association between rs1562422 near the gene <italic>FAM65B</italic> and the pseudogene <italic>CMAHP</italic>, which was replicated in the Colorado RD cohort (Tables&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>, <xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>Single marker genetic associations with various RD and LI case&#x02013;control definitions</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Phenotype</th><th align="left">Marker</th><th align="left">Gene</th><th align="left">BP location</th><th align="left">Model</th><th align="left">OR (95&#x000a0;% CI)</th><th align="left">
<italic>p</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Severe RD</td><td align="left">rs2294691</td><td align="left">
<italic>TDP2</italic>
</td><td align="left">24,652,843</td><td align="left">Allelic</td><td char="(" align="char">2.0 (1.3&#x02013;2.9)</td><td align="left">0.00050</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Severe RD</td><td align="left">rs2294691</td><td align="left">
<italic>TDP2</italic>
</td><td align="left">24,652,843</td><td align="left">Additive</td><td char="(" align="char">1.9 (1.3&#x02013;2.8)</td><td align="left">0.00053</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Severe RD</td><td align="left">rs2294691</td><td align="left">
<italic>TDP2</italic>
</td><td align="left">24,652,843</td><td align="left">Dominant</td><td char="(" align="char">2.3 (1.5&#x02013;3.7)</td><td align="left">0.00018*</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Severe RD</td><td align="left">rs10456309</td><td align="left">
<italic>KIAA0319</italic>
</td><td align="left">24,589,562</td><td align="left">Recessive</td><td char="(" align="char">10.5 (2.2&#x02013;49.5)</td><td align="left">0.00020*</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Moderate RD</td><td align="left">rs1562422</td><td align="left">
<italic>CMAHP</italic>
</td><td align="left">25,044,577</td><td align="left">Dominant</td><td char="(" align="char">1.7 (1.2&#x02013;2.2)</td><td align="left">0.00081</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Severe LI</td><td align="left">rs807694</td><td align="left">
<italic>DCDC2</italic>
</td><td align="left">24,303,383</td><td align="left">Additive</td><td char="(" align="char">1.8 (1.3&#x02013;2.5)</td><td align="left">0.00057</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Severe LI</td><td align="left">rs807694</td><td align="left">
<italic>DCDC2</italic>
</td><td align="left">24,303,383</td><td align="left">Allelic</td><td char="(" align="char">1.8 (1.3&#x02013;2.5)</td><td align="left">0.00050</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Severe LI</td><td align="left">rs807694</td><td align="left">
<italic>DCDC2</italic>
</td><td align="left">24,303,383</td><td align="left">Dominant</td><td char="(" align="char">1.9 (1.3&#x02013;2.7)</td><td align="left">0.00062</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Moderate WOLD</td><td align="left">rs3756814</td><td align="left">
<italic>C6orf62</italic>
</td><td align="left">24,705,835</td><td align="left">Additive</td><td char="(" align="char">0.7 (0.6&#x02013;0.9)</td><td align="left">0.00039</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Moderate WOLD</td><td align="left">rs3756814</td><td align="left">
<italic>C6orf62</italic>
</td><td align="left">24,705,835</td><td align="left">Allelic</td><td char="(" align="char">0.7 (0.6&#x02013;0.9)</td><td align="left">0.00047</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Moderate WOLD</td><td align="left">rs3777663</td><td align="left">
<italic>ACOT13</italic>
</td><td align="left">24,700,235</td><td align="left">Additive</td><td char="(" align="char">0.6 (0.5&#x02013;0.8)</td><td align="left">0.00039</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Moderate WOLD</td><td align="left">rs3777663</td><td align="left">
<italic>ACOT13</italic>
</td><td align="left">24,700,235</td><td align="left">Allelic</td><td char="(" align="char">0.7 (0.5&#x02013;0.8)</td><td align="left">0.00041</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>* Genetic association survives correction for multiple testing</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>LI</title><p>Association tests were performed on three LI phenotypes: (1) severe LI, (2) moderate NWR, and (3) moderate WOLD (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). As with severe RD, there were associations between <italic>DCDC2</italic> and Severe LI. The <italic>DCDC2</italic> haplotype that associated with severe LI is discussed in Powers et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">2013</xref>). A marker within this <italic>DCDC2</italic> haplotype, rs807694, showed association with Severe LI and was replicated in the Iowa LI cohort (Tables&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>, <xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref>). With a more moderate case definition, we observed associations with <italic>ACOT13</italic> and <italic>C6orf62</italic> (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>), genes neighboring <italic>KIAA0319</italic> and <italic>TDP2</italic>. Both rs3777663 in <italic>ACOT13</italic> and rs3756814 in <italic>C6orf62</italic> showed associations in the Italian RD and Iowa LI cohorts (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>IQ</title><p>We also performed association tests between DYX2 markers and verbal IQ, performance IQ, and full scale IQ (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Verbal IQ associations included single markers and haplotypes covering the 5&#x02032; half of <italic>KIAA0319</italic>, rs9348646 in <italic>FAM65B</italic>, and a haplotype spanning <italic>ACOT13</italic> and <italic>C6orf62</italic>, with evidence of replication (Tables&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>a, b, <xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref>). There was substantial overlap of DYX2 associations with verbal IQ and associations with RD and LI. This finding may be a result of the high correlations among these traits (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab7" ref-type="table">7</xref>). The associations of DYX2 with performance IQ and full scale IQ were weaker; there were no associations with performance IQ and a single, non-replicated association of full scale IQ with rs2328791, which is located in a large intergenic region telomeric to <italic>NRSN1</italic> and <italic>DCDC2</italic> (Tables&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>a, b, <xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab5"><label>Table&#x000a0;5</label><caption><p>Single marker (a) and haplotype-based (b) genetic associations with quantitative measure of cognition</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="7">(a) Single marker genetic associations with cognition</th></tr><tr><th align="left">Phenotype</th><th align="left">Marker</th><th align="left">Gene</th><th align="left">BP location</th><th align="left">Model</th><th align="left">Slope</th><th align="left">
<italic>p</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Verbal IQ</td><td align="left">rs9295626</td><td align="left">
<italic>KIAA0319</italic>
</td><td align="left">24,587,339</td><td align="left">Allelic</td><td char="." align="char">1.40</td><td align="left">0.00041</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Verbal IQ</td><td align="left">rs9295626</td><td align="left">
<italic>KIAA0319</italic>
</td><td align="left">24,587,339</td><td align="left">Additive</td><td char="." align="char">1.39</td><td align="left">0.00043</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Verbal IQ</td><td align="left">rs7763790</td><td align="left">
<italic>KIAA0319</italic>
</td><td align="left">24,615,063</td><td align="left">Allelic</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;1.40</td><td align="left">0.00045</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Verbal IQ</td><td align="left">rs7763790</td><td align="left">
<italic>KIAA0319</italic>
</td><td align="left">24,615,063</td><td align="left">Additive</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;1.38</td><td align="left">0.00048</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Verbal IQ</td><td align="left">rs6935076</td><td align="left">
<italic>KIAA0319</italic>
</td><td align="left">24,644,322</td><td align="left">Allelic</td><td char="." align="char">1.16</td><td align="left">0.00049</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Verbal IQ</td><td align="left">rs6935076</td><td align="left">
<italic>KIAA0319</italic>
</td><td align="left">24,644,322</td><td align="left">Additive</td><td char="." align="char">1.15</td><td align="left">0.00052</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Verbal IQ</td><td align="left">rs9348646</td><td align="left">
<italic>FAM65B</italic>
</td><td align="left">24,052,526</td><td align="left">Allelic</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;1.14</td><td align="left">0.00066</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Verbal IQ</td><td align="left">rs9348646</td><td align="left">
<italic>FAM65B</italic>
</td><td align="left">24,052,526</td><td align="left">Additive</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;1.14</td><td align="left">0.00066</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Full scale IQ</td><td align="left">rs2328791</td><td align="left">N/A</td><td align="left">23,736,848</td><td align="left">Allelic</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;1.21</td><td align="left">0.00066</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Full scale IQ</td><td align="left">rs2328791</td><td align="left">N/A</td><td align="left">23,736,848</td><td align="left">Additive</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;1.18</td><td align="left">0.00075</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Full scale IQ</td><td align="left">rs2328791</td><td align="left">N/A</td><td align="left">23,736,848</td><td align="left">Recessive</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;3.36</td><td align="left">0.00042</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="6">(b) Haplotype-based genetic associations with cognition</th></tr><tr><th align="left">Markers</th><th align="left">Haplotype</th><th align="left">Gene</th><th align="left">BP location</th><th align="left">Slope</th><th align="left">
<italic>p</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">rs2817201, rs9295626</td><td align="left">AT</td><td align="left">
<italic>KIAA0319</italic>
</td><td align="left">24,585,214, 24,587,339</td><td char="." align="char">1.42</td><td align="left">0.000378</td></tr><tr><td align="left">rs10456309, rs4576240, rs17307478, rs9356939, rs7763790, rs6456621</td><td align="left">GGTCAC</td><td align="left">
<italic>KIAA0319</italic>
</td><td align="left">24,589,562, 24,596,478, 24,605,024 24,613,354, 24,615,063, 24,618,511</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;1.40</td><td align="left">0.000569</td></tr><tr><td align="left">rs6456624, rs6935076, rs2038137, rs3756821, rs1883593, rs3212236</td><td align="left">AGATA</td><td align="left">
<italic>KIAA0319</italic>
</td><td align="left">24,639,223, 24,644,322, 24,645,943, 24,646,821, 24,647,191, 24,648,455</td><td char="." align="char">1.81</td><td align="left">0.0000145*</td></tr><tr><td align="left">rs3777663, rs3756814, rs6931809, rs6916186, rs6933328, rs17491647</td><td align="left">TGTGGA</td><td align="left">
<italic>ACOT13/C6orf62</italic>
</td><td align="left">24,700,235, 24,705,835, 24,706,770, 24,708,523, 24,710,920, 24,713,723</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;1.56</td><td align="left">0.000742</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>* Genetic association survives correction for multiple testing</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab6"><label>Table&#x000a0;6</label><caption><p>Replication of genetic associations in the Iowa, Italian, and Colorado cohorts</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Marker</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">Gene</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Iowa case control</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Italy case control</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Colorado case control</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Colorado discriminant score</th></tr><tr><th align="left">OR</th><th align="left">
<italic>p</italic>
</th><th align="left">OR</th><th align="left">
<italic>p</italic>
</th><th align="left">OR</th><th align="left">
<italic>p</italic>
</th><th align="left">Slope</th><th align="left">
<italic>p</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">rs2328791</td><td align="left">N/A</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">0.813</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">1.000</td><td align="left">0.9</td><td align="left">0.646</td><td char="." align="char">0.087</td><td align="left">0.447</td></tr><tr><td align="left">rs33914824<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>DCDC2</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<bold>2.2</bold>
</td><td align="left">
<bold>0.034</bold>
</td><td align="left">0.9</td><td align="left">0.768</td><td align="left">1.1</td><td align="left">0.847</td><td char="." align="char">0.023</td><td align="left">0.934</td></tr><tr><td align="left">rs807694<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>DCDC2</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<bold>1.9</bold>
</td><td align="left">
<bold>0.028</bold>
</td><td align="left">0.9</td><td align="left">0.786</td><td align="left">0.9</td><td align="left">0.853</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;0.025</td><td align="left">0.919</td></tr><tr><td align="left">rs707864<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>DCDC2</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<bold>1.6</bold>
</td><td align="left">
<bold>0.017</bold>
</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">0.840</td><td align="left">1.2</td><td align="left">0.446</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;0.246</td><td align="left">0.101</td></tr><tr><td align="left">rs10456301<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>DCDC2</italic>
</td><td align="left">0.9</td><td align="left">0.553</td><td align="left">1.1</td><td align="left">0.811</td><td align="left">1.5</td><td align="left">0.289</td><td char="." align="char">0.221</td><td align="left">0.162</td></tr><tr><td align="left">rs16889066<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>DCDC2</italic>
</td><td align="left">1.2</td><td align="left">0.517</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">0.884</td><td align="left">1.2</td><td align="left">0.622</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;0.304</td><td align="left">0.150</td></tr><tr><td align="left">rs9379651<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>DCDC2</italic>
</td><td align="left">1.1</td><td align="left">0.602</td><td align="left">1.3</td><td align="left">0.225</td><td align="left">0.6</td><td align="left">0.059</td><td char="." align="char">0.205</td><td align="left">0.141</td></tr><tr><td align="left">rs2817201</td><td align="left">
<italic>KIAA0319</italic>
</td><td align="left">1.1</td><td align="left">0.733</td><td align="left">1.2</td><td align="left">0.129</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">1.000</td><td char="." align="char">0.034</td><td align="left">0.787</td></tr><tr><td align="left">rs9295626</td><td align="left">
<italic>KIAA0319</italic>
</td><td align="left">1.1</td><td align="left">0.579</td><td align="left">
<bold>0.6</bold>
</td><td align="left">
<bold>0.0055</bold>
</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">0.823</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;0.158</td><td align="left">0.169</td></tr><tr><td align="left">rs10456309</td><td align="left">
<italic>KIAA0319</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<bold>0.5</bold>
</td><td align="left">
<bold>0.073</bold>
</td><td align="left">0.7</td><td align="left">0.189</td><td align="left">0.4</td><td align="left">0.206</td><td char="." align="char">
<bold>0.628</bold>
</td><td align="left">
<bold>0.0133</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">rs4576240</td><td align="left">
<italic>KIAA0319</italic>
</td><td align="left">1.1</td><td align="left">0.825</td><td align="left">
<bold>1.9</bold>
</td><td align="left">
<bold>0.0027</bold>
</td><td align="left">1.1</td><td align="left">0.862</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;0.052</td><td align="left">0.754</td></tr><tr><td align="left">rs17307478</td><td align="left">
<italic>KIAA0319</italic>
</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">0.996</td><td align="left">1.3</td><td align="left">0.292</td><td align="left">0.8</td><td align="left">0.555</td><td char="." align="char">0.039</td><td align="left">0.803</td></tr><tr><td align="left">rs9356939</td><td align="left">
<italic>KIAA0319</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<bold>4.0</bold>
</td><td align="left">
<bold>0.018</bold>
</td><td align="left">0.8</td><td align="left">0.069</td><td align="left">1.3</td><td align="left">0.151</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;0.116</td><td align="left">0.254</td></tr><tr><td align="left">rs7763790</td><td align="left">
<italic>KIAA0319</italic>
</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">0.831</td><td align="left">1.1</td><td align="left">0.627</td><td align="left">1.4</td><td align="left">0.163</td><td char="." align="char">0.014</td><td align="left">0.910</td></tr><tr><td align="left">rs6456621</td><td align="left">
<italic>KIAA0319</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<bold>2.2</bold>
</td><td align="left">
<bold>0.019</bold>
</td><td align="left">1.6</td><td align="left">0.405</td><td align="left">1.8</td><td align="left">0.366</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;0.458</td><td align="left">0.104</td></tr><tr><td align="left">rs3756821</td><td align="left">
<italic>KIAA0319</italic>
</td><td align="left">1.2</td><td align="left">0.278</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">0.842</td><td align="left">1.2</td><td align="left">0.327</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;0.033</td><td align="left">0.734</td></tr><tr><td align="left">rs1883593</td><td align="left">
<italic>KIAA0319</italic>
</td><td align="left">1.3</td><td align="left">0.169</td><td align="left">
<bold>1.6</bold>
</td><td align="left">
<bold>0.0052</bold>
</td><td align="left">1.3</td><td align="left">0.239</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;0.108</td><td align="left">0.395</td></tr><tr><td align="left">rs3212236</td><td align="left">
<italic>KIAA0319</italic>
</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">0.883</td><td align="left">1.1</td><td align="left">0.496</td><td align="left">0.9</td><td align="left">0.745</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;0.124</td><td align="left">0.319</td></tr><tr><td align="left">rs2294691</td><td align="left">
<italic>TDP2</italic>
</td><td align="left">1.1</td><td align="left">0.779</td><td align="left">1.9</td><td align="left">0.0578</td><td align="left">1.4</td><td align="left">0.491</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;0.290</td><td align="left">0.247</td></tr><tr><td align="left">rs3777663</td><td align="left">
<italic>ACOT13</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<bold>0.7</bold>
</td><td align="left">
<bold>0.016</bold>
</td><td align="left">
<bold>0.6</bold>
</td><td align="left">
<bold>0.0052</bold>
</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">0.908</td><td char="." align="char">0.101</td><td align="left">0.345</td></tr><tr><td align="left">rs3756814</td><td align="left">
<italic>C6orf62</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<bold>0.7</bold>
</td><td align="left">
<bold>0.005</bold>
</td><td align="left">
<bold>0.7</bold>
</td><td align="left">
<bold>0.023</bold>
</td><td align="left">0.9</td><td align="left">0.600</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;0.003</td><td align="left">0.980</td></tr><tr><td align="left">rs6931809</td><td align="left">
<italic>C6orf62</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<bold>1.4</bold>
</td><td align="left">
<bold>0.023</bold>
</td><td align="left">
<bold>1.4</bold>
</td><td align="left">
<bold>0.017</bold>
</td><td align="left">1.2</td><td align="left">0.491</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;0.096</td><td align="left">0.382</td></tr><tr><td align="left">rs6916186</td><td align="left">
<italic>C6orf62</italic>
</td><td align="left">0.9</td><td align="left">0.757</td><td align="left">1.2</td><td align="left">0.413</td><td align="left">1.2</td><td align="left">0.547</td><td char="." align="char">0.112</td><td align="left">0.490</td></tr><tr><td align="left">rs6933328</td><td align="left">
<italic>C6orf62</italic>
</td><td align="left">0.9</td><td align="left">0.612</td><td align="left">0.9</td><td align="left">0.613</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">0.827</td><td char="." align="char">
<bold>0.215</bold>
</td><td align="left">
<bold>0.0515</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">rs17491647</td><td align="left">
<italic>C6orf62</italic>
</td><td align="left">0.8</td><td align="left">0.155</td><td align="left">0.7</td><td align="left">0.104</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">0.901</td><td char="." align="char">0.042</td><td align="left">0.709</td></tr><tr><td align="left">rs9348646</td><td align="left">
<italic>FAM65B</italic>
</td><td align="left">0.9</td><td align="left">0.358</td><td align="left">1.1</td><td align="left">0.535</td><td align="left">1.4</td><td align="left">0.144</td><td char="." align="char">
<bold>&#x02212;0.415</bold>
</td><td align="left">
<bold>0.00051</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">rs1562422</td><td align="left">
<italic>CMAHP</italic>
</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">0.793</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">0.796</td><td align="left">
<bold>0.6</bold>
</td><td align="left">
<bold>0.093</bold>
</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;0.030</td><td align="left">0.840</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>
<sup>a</sup>These markers are part of the six-marker risk haplotype in <italic>DCDC2</italic> fully discussed in Powers et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">2013</xref>)</p><p>Bold denotes nominally associated markers</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab7"><label>Table&#x000a0;7</label><caption><p>Phenotype correlations in the ALSPAC cohort</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left">NWR</th><th align="left">WOLD</th><th align="left">SWR7</th><th align="left">SWR9</th><th align="left">SNR</th><th align="left">PD</th><th align="left">FSIQ</th><th align="left">VIQ</th><th align="left">PIQ</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">NWR</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">WOLD</td><td align="left">0.214</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">SWR7</td><td align="left">0.403</td><td align="left">0.259</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">SWR9</td><td align="left">0.351</td><td align="left">0.202</td><td align="left">0.722</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">SNR</td><td align="left">0.306</td><td align="left">0.149</td><td align="left">0.660</td><td align="left">0.708</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">PD</td><td align="left">0.362</td><td align="left">0.165</td><td align="left">0.688</td><td align="left">0.550</td><td align="left">0.538</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">FSIQ</td><td align="left">0.324</td><td align="left">0.386</td><td align="left">0.500</td><td align="left">0.387</td><td align="left">0.343</td><td align="left">0.406</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">VIQ</td><td align="left">0.346</td><td align="left">0.424</td><td align="left">0.536</td><td align="left">0.421</td><td align="left">0.421</td><td align="left">0.426</td><td align="left">0.871</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">PIQ</td><td align="left">0.192</td><td align="left">0.216</td><td align="left">0.292</td><td align="left">0.218</td><td align="left">0.218</td><td align="left">0.246</td><td align="left">0.819</td><td align="left">0.435</td><td align="left">1</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>All correlations <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05</p><p>
<italic>NWR</italic> nonword repetition age 8&#x000a0;years, <italic>WOLD</italic> Wechsler objective language dimensions verbal comprehension age 8&#x000a0;years, <italic>SWR7</italic> single word reading age 7&#x000a0;years, <italic>SWR9</italic> single word reading age 9&#x000a0;years, <italic>SNR</italic> single nonword reading age 9&#x000a0;years, <italic>PD</italic> phoneme deletion age 7&#x000a0;years, <italic>FSIQ</italic> full scale IQ age 8&#x000a0;years, <italic>VIQ</italic> verbal IQ age 8&#x000a0;years, <italic>PIQ</italic> performance IQ age 8&#x000a0;years</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Linkage disequilibrium within DYX2</title><p>In our analyses, we observed replicated associations in the following genes: <italic>DCDC2</italic>, <italic>KIAA0319</italic>, <italic>TDP2</italic>, <italic>ACOT13</italic>, <italic>C6orf62</italic>, <italic>FAM65B</italic>, and the pseudogene <italic>CMAHP</italic>. However, as these SNPs are in close proximity to each other, we next assessed linkage disequilibrium (LD) among our marker panel to determine whether the associated SNPs were tagging the same variation in the locus. Our previous work showed that <italic>DCDC2</italic> associations tagged READ1 alleles (Powers et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">2013</xref>). Within <italic>KIAA0319</italic>, there appears to be two clear LD blocks separating the gene into a 5&#x02032; half and a 3&#x02032; half (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). The 5&#x02032; half of <italic>KIAA0319</italic> is in strong LD with <italic>TDP2</italic>, <italic>ACOT13</italic>, and <italic>C6orf62</italic>, indicating that associations within these genes may be capturing that same variation (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Associations in <italic>FAM65B</italic> and <italic>CMAHP</italic> appear to be tagging independent associations (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). Although rs1562422 is located intergenic to <italic>FAM65B</italic> and <italic>CMAHP</italic>, this marker is in strong LD with other markers within the <italic>CMAHP</italic> pseudogene. Integration of our association analyses and LD structure indicate four independent association signals centered on (1) <italic>DCDC2</italic>, (2) the 5&#x02032; half of <italic>KIAA0319</italic>, (3) <italic>FAM65B</italic>, and (4) <italic>CMAHP</italic>.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Linkage disequilibrium between associated markers and haplotypes in <italic>KIAA0319</italic>, <italic>TDP2</italic>, <italic>ACOT13</italic>, and <italic>C6Orf62</italic> for RD, LI, and/or verbal IQ. <italic>Asterisks</italic> represent single-marker associations, while <italic>black bars</italic> represent associations with haplotypes. <italic>Numbered boxes</italic> show LD (as measured by D&#x02019;) between markers. Genes are not drawn to scale; the size of a gene in the diagram depends on the number of markers in our panel that localize to that gene</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="439_2014_1427_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig><fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Linkage disequilibrium between associated markers and haplotypes in <italic>FAM65B</italic> and <italic>CMAHP</italic> for RD or verbal IQ. <italic>Asterisks</italic> represent single-marker associations. <italic>Numbered boxes</italic> show LD (as measured by D&#x02032;) between markers. Genes are not drawn to scale; the size of a gene in the diagram depends on the number of markers in our panel that localize to that gene</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="439_2014_1427_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec11" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>In this investigation, we characterized the relationship of the DYX2 locus with RD, LI, and IQ (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). Our results confirm the associations of RD risk genes <italic>KIAA0319</italic> and <italic>DCDC2</italic> with LI. Additionally, we identify <italic>FAM65B</italic> and <italic>CMAHP</italic> as candidate genes for linguistic traits. Markers within the DYX2 locus showed association with multiple aspects of communication, including RD, LI, and verbal IQ. However, there was a marked absence of DYX2 associations with full scale IQ and performance IQ, suggesting that the DYX2 locus influences language-related processes to a greater extent than general cognition.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>An updated schematic of genes in our study with markers that show replicated associations with RD, LI, and/or IQ. The list of these genes (shown in <italic>blue</italic>) has expanded to seven (<italic>DCDC2</italic>, <italic>KIAA0319</italic>, <italic>TDP2</italic>, <italic>ACOT13</italic>, <italic>C6orf62</italic>, <italic>FAM65B</italic>, and <italic>CMAHP</italic>), although linkage disequilibrium may account for multiple associations (particularly for <italic>KIAA0319</italic>, <italic>TDP2</italic>, <italic>ACOT13</italic>, and <italic>C6orf62</italic>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="439_2014_1427_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p><p>The genetic association of DYX2 with RD, LI, and verbal IQ is the latest example of various neurocognitive and communication processes sharing genetic associations. Our group and others have shown that these neurobehavioral traits have common genetic contributors, including variants in <italic>FOXP2</italic>, <italic>KIAA0319</italic>, <italic>CMIP</italic>, <italic>ZNF385D</italic>, <italic>CNTNAP2</italic>, and <italic>DCDC2</italic> (Eicher et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2013b</xref>; Newbury et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2011</xref>, Pennington and Bishop <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">2009</xref>, Peter et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">2011</xref>; Pinel et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">2012</xref>; Powers et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">2013</xref>; Scerri et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">2011</xref>; Wilcke et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">2011</xref>). The expansion of DYX2&#x02019;s association from reading to include other language-related processes suggests that the causative variants may affect reading and verbal language in a pleiotropic manner, as opposed to one or the other exclusively. Our findings provide additional evidence for a &#x02018;generalist genes hypothesis,&#x02019; which is also supported by a recent genome-wide complex trait analysis (GTCA) of cognitive and learning abilities (Trzaskowski et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">2013</xref>). The strong correlations and relatedness among these neurocognitive measures (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab7" ref-type="table">7</xref>) suggest that these DYX2 genes affect neurocognitive processes central to language learning, which in turn manifest themselves phenotypically in various ways, including reading, language, and cognition.</p><p>That multiple DYX2 genes showed association with the phenotypes in this study is interesting, and at first glance somewhat unexpected. One possibility is that one or two genes are not solely responsible for the consistent implication of this locus in reading, language, and cognitive phenotypes. <italic>KIAA0319</italic> and <italic>DCDC2</italic> are currently considered as the two major risk genes in the DYX2 locus. Both genes have been implicated in both RD and sub-clinical variation in reading performance, using both classical neurobehavioral measures, and more recently, neuroimaging techniques (Eicher and Gruen <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2013</xref>; Graham and Fisher <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2013</xref>). Other genes in DYX2 have been associated with RD, although not nearly as often as <italic>DCDC2</italic> and <italic>KIAA0319</italic>. In this study, with a dense SNP panel, we were able to observe associations with other DYX2 elements, including <italic>FAM65</italic>B and <italic>CMAHP</italic>. It would appear possible that instead of a single gene&#x02014;or in this case two genes (<italic>DCDC2</italic> and <italic>KIAA0319</italic>)&#x02014;multiple elements, possibly regulatory in nature, within DYX2, influence language processes. However, DYX2 has repeatedly shown strong linkage to RD, a pattern generally indicative of one or two variants of large effect, and not of multiple independent variants with more modest effect sizes.</p><p>Another possible explanation for the number of DYX2 genes associating in this study is LD within the DYX2 locus. In fact, LD likely explains the cluster of associations around <italic>KIAA0319</italic>, <italic>TDP2</italic>, <italic>ACOT13</italic>, and <italic>C6orf62</italic>. As shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, two major LD blocks span <italic>KIAA0319</italic>&#x02014;one spans the 3&#x02032; half of the gene, while the other spans the 5&#x02032; region of <italic>KIAA0319</italic> as well as <italic>ACOT13</italic>, <italic>TDP2</italic>, and part of <italic>C6orf62</italic>. Nearly all of the associations in this study localize to this 5&#x02032; LD block, which also contains the previously reported <italic>KIAA0319</italic> RD risk haplotype (Cope et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2005</xref>; Francks et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2004</xref>; Paracchini et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2006</xref>). Because of this LD structure, it is impossible to determine whether the associations in this region are independent or are capturing the same functional variant. We consider the latter possibility the most likely and believe that the associations in this region are likely tagging the same causative variant captured by the <italic>KIAA0319</italic> RD risk haplotype. Functional study of this region&#x02014;particularly of the less studied genes <italic>TDP2</italic>, <italic>ACOT13</italic>, and <italic>C6orf62</italic>&#x02014;will almost certainly be necessary to determine whether these associations are independent or not.</p><p>By contrast, the markers within or near <italic>FAM65B</italic> and <italic>CMAHP</italic> appear to be capturing distinct association signals from two different LD blocks (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). The SNP rs9348646, which showed association with verbal IQ, is located within an intron of <italic>FAM65B</italic> in one LD block, while rs1562422, which showed association with moderate RD, localized to a separate LD block. While rs1562422 is an intergenic marker located physically between <italic>FAM65B</italic> and <italic>CMAHP</italic>, it shows strong LD with markers in <italic>CMAHP</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). The LD patterns within the DYX2 locus suggest that associations in <italic>KIAA0319</italic>, <italic>TDP2</italic>, <italic>ACOT13</italic>, and <italic>C6orf62</italic> are tagging the same causative variant, while rs9348646 in <italic>FAM65B</italic> and rs1562422 near <italic>CMAHP</italic> are independent.</p><p>The other DYX2 genes, including <italic>FAM65B</italic> and <italic>CMAHP</italic>, have been less studied than the established risk genes <italic>DCDC2</italic> and <italic>KIAA0319</italic>. Little is known about <italic>FAM65B</italic> in terms of biological function; however, there is evidence that <italic>FAM65B</italic> may influence migration in T lymphocytes (Rougerie et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">2013</xref>). Animal models of <italic>DCDC2</italic> and <italic>KIAA0319</italic> have implicated these genes in migratory processes, albeit in a neural context. <italic>CMAHP</italic>, which encodes a key enzyme in the synthesis of the sialic acids Neu5Ac and Neu5Gc in other mammals, was rendered a pseudogene in humans by an inactivating microdeletion and subsequent fixation of the inactive allele in early human populations (Chou et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">1998</xref>). Although <italic>ACOT13</italic> appears to be tagging variation within <italic>KIAA0319</italic>, the preliminary functional studies of <italic>ACOT13</italic> are intriguing. <italic>ACOT13</italic> was recently associated with lower asymmetric activation of the posterior superior temporal sulcus during reading and phonology tasks (Pinel et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">2012</xref>). The protein product encoded by <italic>ACOT13</italic> has been co-localized with beta-tubulin on microtubules; microtubule binding is postulated to be important to RD, as <italic>DCDC2</italic> contains two doublecortin domains that are thought to bind microtubules (Cheng et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2006</xref>).</p><p>Genes and regulatory elements within the DYX2 locus may contribute interactively to reading and language domains, as seen with the apparent non-additive relationship between putative regulatory variants in <italic>DCDC2</italic> and <italic>KIAA0319</italic> (Powers et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">2013</xref>, Ludwig et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2008</xref>). These risk variants have been shown to influence gene expression and to interact with each other to substantially influence performance on reading- and language-related tasks. It is likely that a complex network, where regulatory elements interact and co-regulate other DYX2 genes and elements, contributes to reading, language, and cognitive phenotypes. If so, it is likely that the READ1 element in <italic>DCDC2</italic> and the causative variant tagged by the <italic>KIAA0319</italic> risk haplotype have the strongest effects on gene expression and the ultimate neurocognitive phenotype. Supporting this idea is the fact that so many of the association hits in the study&#x02014;both single-marker and haplotype-based, and with all three phenotypes&#x02014;localize to the same LD block as the <italic>KIAA0319</italic> risk haplotype. This result, together with the <italic>KIAA0319</italic> risk haplotype&#x02019;s association with reduced <italic>KIAA0319</italic> expression and its synergistic interaction with a regulatory element in an intron of <italic>DCDC2</italic>, strongly suggests the presence of at least one regulatory variant in this region that influences <italic>KIAA0319</italic> expression. The locations of the only other independent hits in the locus (aside from READ1 in <italic>DCDC2</italic>)&#x02014;an intron of <italic>FAM65B</italic> and downstream of a pseudogene&#x02014;may suggest additional regulatory regions that influence gene expression. Thus, any roles <italic>FAM65B</italic> and <italic>CMAHP</italic> play in RD and LI may be of small effect and modulatory in nature. Though much further work is needed, we postulate, based on these and previous results, that <italic>DCDC2</italic> and <italic>KIAA0319</italic> are the major effector genes responsible for DYX2&#x02019;s influence on RD and LI risk and that alteration of gene expression levels or patterns is the mechanism by which this effect is exerted.</p><p>In our study design, we emphasized replication of genetic associations in independent cohorts, as opposed to reliance on statistical corrections for multiple testing, for validation of associations in the ALSPAC discovery cohort. The replications of genetic association with our neurocognitive traits of interest, particularly in the varied cohorts in this investigation, provide strong evidence that the results of this study are not due to type I error. However, we also report uncorrected <italic>p</italic> values and a statistical threshold correcting for 195 genetic markers (threshold of 0.000256) to present the reader with the context of our findings in terms of multiple testing. Nonetheless, our three replication cohorts were not identical and had inherent differences to each other and relative to the discovery cohort that may have prevented replication. These differences included (1) the disorder each cohort was selected for (RD vs. LI vs. unselected), (2) severity of case definition and recruitment, and (3) country of recruitment (UK vs. US vs. Italy), and language spoken (English vs. Italian). Iowa LI and Colorado RD had moderate case definitions, which may be more comparable to Moderate RD, Moderate NWR, and Moderate WOLD case definitions in ALSPAC. On the other hand, Italy RD used a more severe case cutoff of 2 standard deviations, which may be more comparable to severe RD and severe LI case definitions in ALSPAC. Regardless, our observation of multiple replicated associations throughout the DYX2 locus increases confidence in these results.</p><p>In summary, our analyses indicate four association signals for RD, LI, and Verbal IQ in the DYX2 locus: <italic>DCDC2</italic>, <italic>KIAA0319</italic>, <italic>FAM65B</italic>, and the pseudogene <italic>CMAHP</italic>. Our association results within the <italic>DCDC2</italic> and <italic>KIAA0319</italic> (including <italic>TDP2</italic>, <italic>ACOT13</italic>, and <italic>C6orf62</italic>) areas are in LD with two previously reported risk variants: the READ1 regulatory element in <italic>DCDC2</italic> and the <italic>KIAA0319</italic> risk haplotype in <italic>KIAA0319</italic> and <italic>TDP2</italic>. These results point strongly, albeit circumstantially, to variation in gene expression as a mediator of DYX2&#x02019;s effect on reading and language phenotypes. As these variants appear to demonstrate pleiotropy, the role of DYX2 in other neurobehavioral disorders, including attention deficit-hyperactivity disorder, autism spectrum disorders, and speech-sound disorder, awaits full characterization to determine the potentially wide range of effects the DYX2 locus has upon the brain and behavior.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><sec id="Sec12"><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="439_2014_1427_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><caption><p>Supplementary material 1 (DOCX 15&#x000a0;kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p>J. D. Eicher and N. R. Powers contributed to this work equally.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><p>We thank all the families and participants who took part in these studies. We also wish to acknowledge the midwives for their help in recruiting them, and the whole ALSPAC team, which includes interviewers, computer and laboratory technicians, clerical workers, research scientists, volunteers, managers, receptionists and nurses. The UK medical research council and the Wellcome Trust (Grant ref: 092731) and the University of Bristol provide core support for the ALSPAC. This research was specifically funded by the National Institutes of Health (Grant ref: R01 NS043530 [NRP, JRG], P50 HD027802 [EGW, JCD, RKO, SDS, BFP, JRG] and F31 DC012270 [JDE]), the Italian Ministry of Health (SM, CM), the National Health and Medical Research Council (APP1023493) (KLM), the Victorian Government Operational Infrastructure Support Program (KLM), the Manton Family Foundation (JDE, NRP, JRG). The collaboration between JRG and CM rose during a multidisciplinary summer symposium held in Como, Italy, 2004 convened by The Dyslexia Foundation to which we are grateful. We are also grateful to the Yale Center for Genome Analysis, specifically Irina Tikhonova and Anna Rogers, for genotyping services.</p></ack><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Fry</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Maller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Daly</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Haploview: analysis and visualization of LD and haplotype maps</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2005</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>263</fpage><lpage>265</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bth457</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15297300</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beaver</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Delisi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaughn</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association between the A1 allele of the DRD2 gene and reduced verbal abilities in adolescence and early adulthood</article-title><source>J Neural Transm</source><year>2010</year><volume>117</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>827</fpage><lpage>830</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00702-010-0421-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20532925</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayiou-Thomas</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Heritability of specific language impairment depends on diagnostic criteria</article-title><source>Genes Brain Behav</source><year>2008</year><volume>7</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>365</fpage><lpage>372</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1601-183X.2007.00360.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17919296</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name><name><surname>North</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Donlan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nonword repetition as a behavioural marker for inherited language impairment: evidence from a twin study</article-title><source>J Child Physiol Psychiatry</source><year>1996</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>391</fpage><lpage>403</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-7610.1996.tb01420.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Golding</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Macleod</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawlor</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Molloy</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ness</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ring</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Davey</surname><given-names>Smith G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cohort profile: the &#x02018;children of the 90&#x000a0;s&#x02019;&#x02014;the index offspring of the Avon Longitudinal Study of Parents and Children</article-title><source>Int J Epidemiol</source><year>2012</year><volume>42</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>127</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ije/dys064</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22507743</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cardon</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Fulker</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimberling</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pennington</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name><name><surname>DeFries</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantitative trait locus for reading disability on chromosome 6</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1994</year><volume>266</volume><issue>5183</issue><fpage>276</fpage><lpage>279</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.7939663</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7939663</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Catts</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name><surname>Adlof</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hogan</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name><surname>Weismer</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Are specific language impairment and dyslexia distinct disorders?</article-title><source>J Speech Lang Hear Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>48</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1378</fpage><lpage>1396</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1044/1092-4388(2005/096)</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16478378</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Human thioesterase superfamily 2 (hTHEM2) is co-localized with beta-tubulin onto the microtubule</article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><year>2006</year><volume>350</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>850</fpage><lpage>853</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbrc.2006.09.105</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17045243</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name><surname>Takematsu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Diaz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Iber</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Knickerson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Muchmore</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name><surname>Varki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A mutation in human CMP-sialic acid hydroxylase occurred after the Homo-Pan divergence</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>1998</year><volume>95</volume><issue>20</issue><fpage>11751</fpage><lpage>11756</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.95.20.11751</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9751737</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cope</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Harold</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Moskvina</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevenson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmans</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Owen</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Donovan</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Strong evidence that KIAA0319 on chromosome 6p is a susceptibility gene for developmental dyslexia</article-title><source>Am J Hum Genet</source><year>2005</year><volume>76</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>581</fpage><lpage>591</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/429131</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15717286</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Couto</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Livne-Bar</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Cate-Carter</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wigg</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Humphries</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tannock</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerr</surname><given-names>EN</given-names></name><name><surname>Lovett</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Bremner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Barr</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association of reading disabilities with regions marked by acetylated H3 histones in KIAA0319</article-title><source>Am J Med Genet B Neuropsychatr Genet</source><year>2010</year><volume>153B</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>447</fpage><lpage>462</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deffenbacher</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Kenyon</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoover</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Pennington</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name><name><surname>DeFries</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Refinement of the 6p21.3 quantitative trait locus influencing dyslexia: linkage and association analyses</article-title><source>Hum Genet</source><year>2004</year><volume>115</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>128</fpage><lpage>138</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00439-004-1126-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15138886</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dennis</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name><surname>Paracchini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Scerri</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Prokunina-Olsson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wade-Martins</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Coggill</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><name><surname>Monaco</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A common variant associated with dyslexia reduces expression of the KIAA0319 gene</article-title><source>PLoS Genet</source><year>2009</year><volume>5</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>e1000436</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1000436</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19325871</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eicher</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Gruen</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Imaging-genetics in dyslexia: connecting risk genetic variants to brain neuroimaging and ultimately to reading impairments</article-title><source>Mol Genet Metab</source><year>2013</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23916419</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eicher</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Powers</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ring</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomblin</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Gruen</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Associations of prenatal nicotine exposure and the dopamine related genes ANKK1 and DRD2 to verbal language</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>e63762</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0063762</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23691092</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Eicher JD, Powers NR, Miller LL, Akshoomoff N, Amaral DG, Bloss CS, Libiger O, Schork NJ, Darst BF, Casey BJ, Chang L, Ernst T, Frazier J, Kaufmann WE, Keating B, Kenet T, Kennedy D, Mostofsky S, Murray SS, Sowell ER, Bartsch H, Kuperman JM, Brown TT, Hagler DJ Jr, Dale AM, Jernigan TL, St. Pourcain B, Davey Smith G, Ring SM, Gruen JR, Pediatric Imaging, Neurocognition, and Genetics Study (2013b) Genome-wide association study of shared components of reading disability and language impairment. Genes Brain Behav 12(8):792&#x02013;801</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elbert</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lovett</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Cate-Carter</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Pitch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerr</surname><given-names>EN</given-names></name><name><surname>Barr</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic variation in the KIAA0319 5&#x02032; region as a possible contributor to dyslexia</article-title><source>Behav Genet</source><year>2011</year><volume>41</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>89</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10519-010-9434-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21207242</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Vargha-Khadem</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Watkins</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Monaco</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Pembrey</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Localisation of a gene implicated in a severe speech and language disorder</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>1998</year><volume>18</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>168</fpage><lpage>170</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng0298-168</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9462748</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Francks</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Paracchini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Scerri</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Cardon</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name><surname>Marlow</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>MacPhie</surname><given-names>IL</given-names></name><name><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pennington</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>DeFries</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Monaco</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A 77-kilobase region of chromosome 6p22.2 is associated with dyslexia in families from the United Kingdom and from the United States</article-title><source>Am J Hum Genet</source><year>2004</year><volume>75</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1046</fpage><lpage>1058</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/426404</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15514892</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gathercole</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Baddeley</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phonological memory deficits in language disordered children: is there a causal connection?</article-title><source>J Mem Lang</source><year>1990</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>336</fpage><lpage>360</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0749-596X(90)90004-J</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gathercole</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Baddeley</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group><source>Working memory and language</source><year>1993</year><publisher-loc>Mahwah</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gathercole</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Baddeley</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group><source>The children&#x02019;s test of nonword repetition</source><year>1996</year><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>The Psychological Corportation</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gay&#x000e1;n</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Cherny</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Cardon</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name><surname>Fulker</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Brower</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Pennington</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name><name><surname>DeFries</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantitative-trait locus for specific language and reading deficits on chromosome 6p</article-title><source>Am J Hum Genet</source><year>1999</year><volume>64</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>157</fpage><lpage>164</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/302191</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9915954</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Golding J, Pembrey M, Jones R, ALSPAC Study Team</collab></person-group><article-title>ALSPAC&#x02014;the Avon Longitudinal Study of Parents and Children. I. Study methodology</article-title><source>Paediatr Perinat Epidemiol</source><year>2001</year><volume>15</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>74</fpage><lpage>87</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-3016.2001.00325.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11237119</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Decoding the genetics of speech and language</article-title><source>Curr Opin Neurobiol</source><year>2013</year><volume>23</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.conb.2012.11.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23228431</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaitlen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Eskin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efficient association study design via power-optimized tag SNP selection</article-title><source>Ann Hum Genet</source><year>2008</year><volume>72</volume><issue>Pt 6</issue><fpage>834</fpage><lpage>847</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-1809.2008.00469.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18702637</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harold</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Paracchini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Scerri</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Dennis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cope</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Moskvina</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Owen</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Donovan</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Monaco</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Further evidence that the KIAA0319 gene confers susceptibility to developmental dyslexia</article-title><source>Mol Psychiatry</source><year>2006</year><volume>11</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1085</fpage><lpage>1091</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.mp.4001904</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17033633</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaminen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hannula-Jouppi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kestil&#x000e4;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lahermo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaaranen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Myllyluoma</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Voutilainen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyytinen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nopola-Hemmi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kere</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A genome scan for developmental dyslexia confirms linkage to chromosome 2p11 and suggests a new locus on 7q32</article-title><source>J Med Genet</source><year>2003</year><volume>40</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>340</fpage><lpage>345</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/jmg.40.5.340</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12746395</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Gay&#x000e1;n</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Won</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name><surname>Pauls</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>DeFries</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Pennington</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name><name><surname>Page</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Gruen</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence for linkage and association with reading disability on 6p21.3-22</article-title><source>Am J Hum Genet</source><year>2002</year><volume>70</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1287</fpage><lpage>1298</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/340449</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11951179</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hurst</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Vargha-Khadem</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Monaco</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A forkhead-domain gene is mutated in a severe speech and language disorder</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2001</year><volume>413</volume><issue>6855</issue><fpage>519</fpage><lpage>523</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35097076</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11586359</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Landi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Frost</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mencl</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><name><surname>Preston</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yrigollen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pugh</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Grigorenko</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The COMT Val/Met polymorphism is associated with reading-related skills and consistent patterns of functional neural activation</article-title><source>Dev Sci</source><year>2013</year><volume>16</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1467-7687.2012.01180.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23278923</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lind</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Luciano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Montgomery</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name><name><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dyslexia and DCDC2: normal variation in reading and spelling is associated with DCDC2 polymorphisms in an Australian population sample</article-title><source>Eur J Hum Genet</source><year>2010</year><volume>18</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>668</fpage><lpage>673</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ejhg.2009.237</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20068590</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luciano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lind</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Duffy</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Castles</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Montgomery</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name><name><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A haplotype spanning KIAA0319 and TTRAP is associated with normal variation in reading and spelling ability</article-title><source>Biol Psychiatry</source><year>2007</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>811</fpage><lpage>817</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsych.2007.03.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17597587</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ludwig</surname><given-names>KU</given-names></name><name><surname>Roeske</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Schumacher</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulte-Korne</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Konig</surname><given-names>IR</given-names></name><name><surname>Warnke</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Plume</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ziegler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Remschmidt</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Muller-Myhsok</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Nothen</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Investigation of interaction between DCDC2 and KIAA0319 in a large German dyslexia sample</article-title><source>J Neural Transm</source><year>2008</year><volume>115</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1587</fpage><lpage>1589</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00702-008-0124-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18810304</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marino</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Mascheretti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rusconi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cope</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Giorda</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Molteni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gruen</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DCDC2 genetic variants and susceptibility to developmental dyslexia</article-title><source>Psychiatr Genet</source><year>2012</year><volume>22</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/YPG.0b013e32834acdb2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21881542</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Hager</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Held</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Pennington</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name><name><surname>DeFries</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Gelernter</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Reilly-Pol</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Somlo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Skudlarski</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaywitz</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaywitx</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Marchione</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Paramasiyam</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>LoTurco</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Page</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Gruen</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DCDC2 is associated with reading disability and modulates neuronal development in the brain</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2005</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>17053</fpage><lpage>17058</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0508591102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16278297</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Powers</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Cope</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>PX</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuleihan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Page</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Gruen</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A dyslexia-associated variant in DCDC2 changes gene expression</article-title><source>Behav Genet</source><year>2011</year><volume>41</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>58</fpage><lpage>66</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10519-010-9408-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21042874</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Newbury</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Winchester</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Addis</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Paracchini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Buckingham</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Cowie</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Dworzynski</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Everitt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodyer</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hennessy</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kindley</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Nasir</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Hare</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Simkin</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Simonoff</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Slonims</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ragoussis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Seckl</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Helms</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bolton</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name><surname>Pickles</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Conti-Ramsden</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Baird</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name><name><surname>Monaco</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CMIP and ATP2C2 modulate phonological short-term memory in language impairment</article-title><source>Am J Hum Genet</source><year>2009</year><volume>85</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>264</fpage><lpage>272</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajhg.2009.07.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19646677</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Newbury</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Monaco</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recent advances in the genetics of language impairment</article-title><source>Genome Med</source><year>2010</year><volume>2</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>6</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gm127</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20193051</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Newbury</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Paracchini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Scerri</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Winchester</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Addis</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Talcott</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Monaco</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Investigation of dyslexia and SLI risk variants in reading- and language-impaired subjects</article-title><source>Behav Genet</source><year>2011</year><volume>41</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>90</fpage><lpage>104</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10519-010-9424-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21165691</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nunes</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Bryant</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Olssen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Learning morphological and phonological spelling rules: an intervention study</article-title><source>Sci Stud Read</source><year>2003</year><volume>7</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>289</fpage><lpage>307</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1207/S1532799XSSR0703_6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paracchini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Castro</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Paramasivam</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Keating</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hacking</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Scerri</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Francks</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wade-Martins</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Copp</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Loturco</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Monaco</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The chromosome 6p22 haplotype associated with dyslexia reduces the expression of KIAA0319, a novel gene involved in neuronal migration</article-title><source>Hum Mol Genet</source><year>2006</year><volume>15</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1659</fpage><lpage>1666</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/hmg/ddl089</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16600991</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paracchini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Steer</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Buckingham</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Ring</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Scerri</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pembrey</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Ragoussis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Golding</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Monaco</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association of the KIAA0319 dyslexia susceptibility gene with reading skills in the general population</article-title><source>Am J Psychiatry</source><year>2008</year><volume>165</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1576</fpage><lpage>1584</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/appi.ajp.2008.07121872</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18829873</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pennington</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>From single to multiple deficit models of developmental disorders</article-title><source>Cognition</source><year>2006</year><volume>101</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>385</fpage><lpage>413</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cognition.2006.04.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16844106</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pennington</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name><name><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relations among speech, language, and reading disorders</article-title><source>Annu Rev Psychol</source><year>2009</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>283</fpage><lpage>306</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.psych.60.110707.163548</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18652545</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peter</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Raskind</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsushita</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lisowski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Berninger</surname><given-names>VW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wijsman</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Brkanac</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Replication of CNTNAP2 association with nonword repetition and support for FOXP2 association with timed reading and motor activities in a dyslexia family sample</article-title><source>J Neurodev Disord</source><year>2011</year><volume>3</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>39</fpage><lpage>49</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11689-010-9065-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21484596</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pinel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Fauchereau</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbot</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lathrop</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zelenika</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Bihan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Poline</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Bourgeron</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Dehaene</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetics variants of <italic>FOXP2</italic> and <italic>KIAA0319</italic>/<italic>TTRAP</italic>/<italic>THEM2</italic> locus are associated with altered brain activation in distinct language-related regions</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2012</year><volume>32</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>817</fpage><lpage>825</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.5996-10.2012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22262880</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Plomin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Turic</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Turic</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Stephens</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Owen</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Donovan</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A functional polymorphism in the succinate-semialdehyde dehydrogenase (aldehyde dehydrogenase 5 family, member A1) gene is associated with cognitive ability</article-title><source>Mol Psychiatry</source><year>2004</year><volume>9</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>582</fpage><lpage>586</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.mp.4001441</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14981524</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Powers</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name><surname>Eicher</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Butter</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ring</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gruen</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alleles of a polymorphic ETV6 binding site in DCDC2 confer risk of reading and language impairment</article-title><source>Am J Hum Genet</source><year>2013</year><volume>93</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>28</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajhg.2013.05.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23746548</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Purcell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Neale</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Todd-Brown</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bender</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Maller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sklar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>de Bakker</surname><given-names>PI</given-names></name><name><surname>Daly</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sham</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PLINK: a tool set for whole-genome association and population-based linkage analyses</article-title><source>Am J Hum Genet</source><year>2007</year><volume>81</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>559</fpage><lpage>575</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/519795</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17701901</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The auditory analysis test: an initial report</article-title><source>J Learn Disabil</source><year>1971</year><volume>4</volume><issue>384</issue><fpage>40</fpage><lpage>48</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rougerie</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Largeteau</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Megrelis</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Carrette</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lejeune</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Toffali</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeghouf</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cherfils</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>COnstantin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Laudanna</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bismuth</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Mangeney</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Delon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Famb65b is a new transcriptional target of FOXO1 that regulates RhoA signaling for T lymphocyte migration</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>2013</year><volume>190</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>748</fpage><lpage>755</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.1201174</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23241886</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rust</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Golombok</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Trickey</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><source>WORD: Wechsler objective reading dimensions manual</source><year>1993</year><publisher-loc>Sidcup</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Psychological Corporation</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scerri</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Buckingham</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Newbury</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Monaco</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name><name><surname>Paracchini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DCDC2, KIAA0319 and CMIP are associated with reading-related traits</article-title><source>Biol Psychiatry</source><year>2011</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>237</fpage><lpage>245</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsych.2011.02.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21457949</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schumacher</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Anthoni</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Dahdouh</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#x000f6;nig</surname><given-names>IR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hillmer</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kluck</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Manthey</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Plume</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Warnke</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Remschmidt</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>H&#x000fc;lsmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cichon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindgren</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Propping</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Zucchelli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ziegler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Peyrard-Janvid</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulte-K&#x000f6;rne</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>N&#x000f6;then</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kere</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Strong genetic evidence of DCDC2 as a susceptibility gene for dyslexia</article-title><source>Am J Hum Genet</source><year>2006</year><volume>78</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>52</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/498992</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16385449</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tomblin</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Records</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A system for the diagnosis of specific language impairment in kindergarten children</article-title><source>J Speech Hear Res</source><year>1996</year><volume>39</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1284</fpage><lpage>1294</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8959613</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trzaskowski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>OS</given-names></name><name><surname>DeFries</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Visscher</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Plomin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DNA evidence for strong genome-wide pleiotropy of cognitive and learning abilities</article-title><source>Behav Genet</source><year>2013</year><volume>43</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>267</fpage><lpage>273</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10519-013-9594-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23609157</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Viding</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Spinath</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name><name><surname>Dale</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Plomin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic and environmental influence on language impairment in 4-year-old same-sex and opposite-sex twins</article-title><source>J Child Psychol Psychiatry</source><year>2004</year><volume>45</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>315</fpage><lpage>325</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-7610.2004.00223.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14982245</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wechsler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><source>Wechsler objective language dimensions (WOLD)</source><year>1996</year><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Psychological Corporation</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wechsler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Golombok</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rust</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><source>WISC-III UK: Wechsler Intelligence Scale for Children</source><year>1992</year><publisher-loc>Sidcup</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Psychological Corporation</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weismer</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomblin</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Buckwalter</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Chynoweth</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nonword repetition performance in school-age children with and without language impairment</article-title><source>J Speech Lang Hear Res</source><year>2000</year><volume>43</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>865</fpage><lpage>878</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11386474</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilcke</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Weissfuss</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirsten</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolfram</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Boltze</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahnert</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of gene DCDC2 in German dyslexics</article-title><source>Ann Dyslexia</source><year>2009</year><volume>59</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11881-008-0020-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19238550</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilcke</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ligges</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Burkhardt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Quente</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahnert</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Muller-Myhsok</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Cichon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Boltze</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirsten</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Imaging genetics of FOXP2 in dyslexia</article-title><source>Eur J Hum Genet</source><year>2011</year><volume>20</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>224</fpage><lpage>229</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ejhg.2011.160</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21897444</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wise</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Sevcik</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Lovett</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The relationship among reception and expressive vocabulary, listening comprehension, pre-reading skills, word identification skills, and reading comprehension by children with reading disabilities</article-title><source>J Speech Lang Hear Res</source><year>2007</year><volume>50</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1093</fpage><lpage>1099</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1044/1092-4388(2007/076)</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17675607</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ettlinger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Linguistic grammar learning and DRD2-TAQ-1A polymorphism</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>e64983</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0064983</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23741438</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>LQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Miao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Meta-analysis of the association between DCDC2 polymorphisms and risk of dyslexia</article-title><source>Mol Neurobiol</source><year>2013</year><volume>47</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>435</fpage><lpage>442</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12035-012-8381-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23229871</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Miao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic variant in KIAA0319, but not in DYX1C1, is associated with risk of dyslexia: an integrated meta-analysis</article-title><source>Am J Med Genet B Neuropsychiatr Genet</source><year>2012</year><volume>159B</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>970</fpage><lpage>976</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ajmg.b.32102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23065966</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>