<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="letter"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Indian Dermatol Online J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Indian Dermatol Online J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IDOJ</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Indian Dermatology Online Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2229-5178</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2249-5673</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Medknow Publications &#x00026; Media Pvt Ltd</publisher-name><publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24860773</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4030366</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">IDOJ-5-226</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/2229-5178.131144</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Letters to the Editor</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Art of publication: The title, abstract, and cover letter</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>Kieran</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">BMJ Learning, BMJ, BMA House, London, UK</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold>Address for correspondence:</bold> Dr. Kieran Walsh, BMJ Learning, BMA House, Tavistock Square, London WC1H 9JR, UK. E-mail: <email xlink:href="kmwalsh@bmj.com">kmwalsh@bmj.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>Apr-Jun</season><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>226</fpage><lpage>226</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; Indian Dermatology Online Journal</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions></article-meta></front><body><p>Sir,</p><p>Singh <italic>et al</italic>. offer excellent advice on how best to select a journal for a paper and how to format the paper and hence that it is most likely to be accepted.[<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]</p><p>However, the paper misses a number of important points when putting together a paper. First, putative authors should give adequate time to writing their abstract. The abstract is generally short in the context of the entire article and yet it is the part that is most likely to be read. Certainly, it is most likely to be read first by the editor who will be deciding whether or not to publish the article. In fact, some editors screen papers by reading the abstract and don&#x02019;t actually read the paper if they are not sufficiently impressed by the abstract. However, authors typically leave writing their abstract to the last minute when they are often exhausted and short of time. This practice should be turned on its head. Authors should spend a significant amount of time writing the abstract and ensuring that it is of high quality and in the correct format for the journal.</p><p>Second, there is the issue of the cover letter. Most journals give authors the opportunity to write a cover letter explaining why their article is important and/or topical and/or significant. The cover letter should not just reproduce the abstract-rather it should address the editor directly and explain why the article is right for the journal and its readership. Authors should beware exaggerating the importance of their paper; however, some authors leave the cover letter section blank, and this is to miss out on a great opportunity.</p><p>Third and finally, there is the issue of the title. Singh <italic>et al</italic>. are correct to suggest that titles should be both attractive and accurate. However, authors should also give some consideration as to the format of titles that the journal typically publishes. Authors should ask themselves whether titles are in the form of a question, or are descriptive, or are more journalistic in style. Authors should then format their title in the way that the journal typically publishes. In publishing as in life, first impressions count and the best way to make a good first impression in medical publishing is to pay adequate attention to the title, abstract and cover letter.</p></body><back><ref-list><title>REFERENCE</title><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mercy</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Art of publication and selection of journal</article-title><source>Indian Dermatol Online J</source><year>2014</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>4</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24616846</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>