<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Mol Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Int. J. Mol. Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IJMM</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>International Journal of Molecular Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1107-3756</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1791-244X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>D.A. Spandidos</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22012631</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3307794</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3892/ijmm.2011.814</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ijmm-29-01-0102</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Sensitizing human multiple myeloma cells to the proteasome inhibitor bortezomib by novel curcumin analogs</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>MUJTABA</surname><given-names>TASKEEN</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ijmm-29-01-0102">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>KANWAR</surname><given-names>JYOTI</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ijmm-29-01-0102">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>WAN</surname><given-names>SHENG BIAO</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-ijmm-29-01-0102">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>CHAN</surname><given-names>TAK HANG</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-ijmm-29-01-0102">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3-ijmm-29-01-0102">3</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1-ijmm-29-01-0102"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>DOU</surname><given-names>Q. PING</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ijmm-29-01-0102">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1-ijmm-29-01-0102"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af1-ijmm-29-01-0102"><label>1</label>The Developmental Therapeutics Program, Barbara Ann Karmanos Cancer Institute, and Departments of Oncology, Pharmacology and Pathology, School of Medicine, Wayne State University, Detroit, MI, USA</aff><aff id="af2-ijmm-29-01-0102"><label>2</label>Department of Applied Biology and Chemistry, The Polytechnic University of Hong Kong, Hung Hum, Hong Kong SAR, P.R. China</aff><aff id="af3-ijmm-29-01-0102"><label>3</label>Department of Chemistry, McGill University, Montreal, Quebec H3A 2K6, Canada</aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1-ijmm-29-01-0102">Correspondence to: Dr Q.P. Dou, The Developmental Therapeutics Program, Barbara Ann Karmanos Cancer Institute, School of Medicine, Wayne State University, 540.1 HWCRC, 4100 John R Road, Detroit, MI 48201-2013, USA, E-mail: <email>doup@karmanos.org</email>. Dr T.H. Chan, Department of Chemistry, McGill University, Montreal, Quebec H3A 2K6, Canada, E-mail: <email>tak-hang.chan@mcgill.ca</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>1</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>13</day><month>10</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>13</day><month>10</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>29</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>102</fpage><lpage>106</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>09</day><month>8</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>08</day><month>9</month><year>2011</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2012, Spandidos Publications</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0"><license-p>This is an open-access article licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License. The article may be redistributed, reproduced, and reused for non-commercial purposes, provided the original source is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>The proteasome plays a vital role in the degradation of proteins involved in several pathways including the cell cycle, cellular proliferation and apoptosis and is a validated target in cancer treatment. Bortezomib (Velcade<sup>&#x000ae;</sup>, PS-341) is the first US FDA approved proteasome inhibitor anticancer drug used in the treatment of refractory multiple myeloma. In spite of its improved efficacy compared to alternative therapies, about 60% of patients do not respond to bortezomib due to the emergence of resistance. We hypothesized that novel small molecules could enhance the proteasome-inhibitory and anticancer activities of bortezomib in resistant multiple myeloma cells <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic>. The dietary polyphenol curcumin has been shown to exert anti-cancer activity in several cancer cell lines, but the effects of curcumin in solid tumors have been modest primarily due to poor water solubility and poor bioavailability in tissues remote from the gastrointestinal tract. Here we show that the water-soluble analog of curcumin #12, but not curcumin, in combination with bortezomib could enhance the proteasome-inhibitory effect in multiple myeloma cells. Furthermore, the sensitivity of the myeloma cells to cytotoxic killing in the presence of otherwise sublethal concentrations of bortezomib was enhanced by incubation with the curcumin analog #12. These findings justify further investigation into those combinations that may yield potential therapeutic benefit.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>multiple myeloma</kwd><kwd>bortezomib</kwd><kwd>curcumin</kwd><kwd>curcumin analogs</kwd><kwd>drug resistance</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Multiple myeloma (MM) is a neoplasm of mature clonal B cells and is the second most common hematological malignancy after non-Hodgkin&#x02019;s lymphoma. It accounts for approximately 15% of all lymphohematopoietic cancers. Incidence of MM increases with age and its rate of occurrence is higher in men. Despite the availability of new drugs MM still remains an incurable disease. Current cancer therapies are intended to selectively target specific biomarkers that are altered in the malignant phenotype to dampen tumor progression, which is limited by many factors. Alternatively, targeting the proteasome, which regulates multiple cellular events, represents one of the most successful anticancer strategies.</p><p>Bortezomib (Velcade<sup>&#x000ae;</sup>, PS-341) is the first US food and drug administration (FDA) approved proteasome inhibitor. It has shown remarkable success in the treatment of hematological malignancies, however about 60% of patients do not respond to bortezomib due to the emergence of resistance. Some of the molecular mechanisms for resistance have been found to be the overexpression of the &#x003b2;5 subunit of the proteasome (<xref rid="b1-ijmm-29-01-0102" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>) overexpression of the anti-apoptosis protein Bcl-2 (<xref rid="b2-ijmm-29-01-0102" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>), and high secretion of GRP-78, a chaperone protein of the unfolded protein response (<xref rid="b3-ijmm-29-01-0102" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). In B-cell lymphomas overexpression of heat shock protein (HSP)27, HSP70, HSP90 and T-cell factor 4 is associated with bortezomib resistance (<xref rid="b4-ijmm-29-01-0102" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). In solid tumor cell lines (lung, cervical and colon) bortezomib treatment had minimal effects as it induced the formation of stress granules (<xref rid="b5-ijmm-29-01-0102" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Proteasome inhibitor-resistant constitutive activation of NF-&#x003ba;B has also been reported (<xref rid="b6-ijmm-29-01-0102" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Targeting these resistance mechanisms could therefore increase the efficacy of proteasome inhibition by bortezomib. Another potential limitation of bortezomib therapy is its interaction with several natural products including polyphenols containing vicinal diols that block its activity (<xref rid="b7-ijmm-29-01-0102" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Overcoming these challenges requires identification of mechanisms that confer sensitivity to proteasome inhibition and identification of a novel class of agents, which can be safely used in combination with bortezomib.</p><p>A potential prospect is to use natural compounds that do not interact with bortezomib to sensitize tumors to bortezomib therapy. Several naturally occurring products have great potential as chemopreventive agents. Curcumin is one such compound that has attracted much interest due to its proven pharmacological safety and its many favorable biological activities such as anti-inflammation, anti-oxidation, chemopreventive and chemotherapeutic activities (<xref rid="b8-ijmm-29-01-0102" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). Recently, the tumor cellular proteasome has been reported as an important target of curcumin (<xref rid="b9-ijmm-29-01-0102" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>).</p><p>The anticancer effects of curcumin, both alone and in combination with chemotherapeutics are widely supported by several studies (<xref rid="b10-ijmm-29-01-0102" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="b12-ijmm-29-01-0102" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). Curcumin in combination with bortezomib has been reported to synergistically induce apoptosis in human multiple myeloma U266 cells (<xref rid="b13-ijmm-29-01-0102" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). Curcumin was reported to potentiate the effect of bortezomib against human multiple myeloma in a nude mice model (<xref rid="b14-ijmm-29-01-0102" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). These observations therefore suggest that a superior therapeutic index may be achieved with curcumin when used in combination and could be advantageous in the treatment of refractory tumors.</p><p>Unfortunately, the <italic>in vivo</italic> biological activities of curcumin were found to be greatly reduced due to its low solubility and bioavailability in tissues remote from the gastrointestinal tract (<xref rid="b10-ijmm-29-01-0102" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="b12-ijmm-29-01-0102" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). In an effort to enhance the bioavailability of curcumin, we synthesized several novel analogs of curcumin, and we recently reported that water soluble amino acid conjugates of curcumin are potent proteasome inhibitors and showed a potent antiproliferative effect in several human cancer cell lines (<xref rid="b15-ijmm-29-01-0102" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). Docking studies of these conjugates suggested that they may serve as the water soluble analogs of curcumin (<xref rid="b15-ijmm-29-01-0102" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). In the present study, we examined the ability of the curcumin analogs 6&#x02013;13 (<xref rid="f1-ijmm-29-01-0102" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>) (<xref rid="b15-ijmm-29-01-0102" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>) to sensitize multiple myeloma cells to otherwise sublethal concentrations of bortezomib and enhance its proteasome-inhibitory anticancer activities.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec><title>Cell culture</title><p>Human multiple myeloma Arp cell line, kindly provided by Dr Ramesh Batchu (Wayne State University), were grown in RPMI-1640 medium supplemented with 10% FBS, 100 U/ml of penicillin, and 100 &#x003bc;g/ml of streptomycin. Cells were maintained at 37&#x000b0;C in 5% CO<sub>2</sub>.</p></sec><sec><title>Chemicals</title><p>Amino acid conjugates 6&#x02013;13 of curcumin were prepared as previously reported (<xref rid="b15-ijmm-29-01-0102" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Inhibition of purified 20S and cellular 26S proteasome activity by curcumin and its analogs</title><p>Arp multiple myeloma cells were treated with curcumin or amino acid conjugated water soluble curcumin analogs either alone or in combination with bortezomib for 48 h at 37&#x000b0;C. Cell extracts from these cells were then used to measure the proteasomal chymotryptic (CT) activity, trypsin like activity, PGPH activity and caspase-3 activity. All activities in both the purified proteasome and the cellular proteasome were measured following a previously described protocol (<xref rid="b16-ijmm-29-01-0102" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Cell proliferation and viability</title><p>Myeloma cells were grown in 96-well plates. Cells were treated with the indicated concentrations of curcumin or the curcumin analogs alone or in combination with bortezomib for 24&#x02013;48 h followed by an MTT assay to measure cell proliferation and cell viability (<xref rid="b17-ijmm-29-01-0102" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Immunoblotting</title><p>Multiple myeloma cells were treated with either curcumin or its analogs both alone and in combination with bortezomib at 5 nM concentration for 48 h. Cells were then harvested for the preparation of lysates. Equal amounts of protein (40 &#x003bc;g/lane) were electrophoresed on SDS-PAGE gels, transferred to nitrocellulose, and probed with the indicated antibodies as previously described (<xref rid="b17-ijmm-29-01-0102" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Curcumin analogs enhance the inhibitory effect of bortezomib on the purified 20S proteasome</title><p>To determine if the curcumin analogs could add to or inhibit bortezomib&#x02019;s activity, the analogs alone or in combination with bortezomib were evaluated for their ability to inhibit the purified 20S proteasome CT activity. Curcumin analogs were examined at 2.5, 5 and 10 &#x003bc;M both alone and in combination with bortezomib (Vel) at 10 nM. Curcumin analogs 6, 7, 8 and 9 did not significantly inhibit CT-activity of purified 20S proteasome when compared with bortezomib. They did not add to or inhibit bortezomib activity in combination studies (data not shown). On the other hand, the water soluble analogs of curcumin 10, 11, 12 and 13 alone potently inhibited proteasomal CT activity (data not shown). When used in combination with 10 nM bortezomib the effect was additive and they further lowered the CT activity compared with bortezomib alone. The most pronounced effect was observed with analog #12 (<xref rid="f2-ijmm-29-01-0102" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). In particular, #12 at 10 &#x003bc;M in combination with bortezomib at 20 nM was appreciably more effective in suppressing CT-like activity than bortezomib at 20 nM alone. In comparison, curcumin at 10 &#x003bc;M in combination with bortezomib at 20 nM did not have a pronounced inhibitory effect under our experimental conditions.</p></sec><sec><title>Curcumin analogs enhance the proteasome-inhibitory effect of bortezomib in human myeloma cells</title><p>We next determined if the curcumin analogs could add to bortezomib&#x02019;s activity in intact myeloma cells. Arp cells were co-treated with curcumin analogs 10, 11, 12 and 13 at 10 &#x003bc;M for 48 h both alone and in combination with bortezomib at 10 nM, and cell extracts were then prepared and assayed for three proteasomal activities (CT-, PGPH- and trypsin-like). None of the analogs alone at 10 &#x003bc;M could inhibit the activities of the proteasome in these cells (data not shown). Analog #12, but not curcumin, enhanced the effects of bortezomib and the co-treatment showed potent inhibitory effects on CT-, PGPH- and trypsin-like activities of the proteasome (<xref rid="f3-ijmm-29-01-0102" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3A&#x02013;C</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Curcumin analogs enhance bortezomib-mediated proliferation inhibition and apoptosis induction in multiple myeloma cells</title><p>We then determined whether the observed enhancement of the proteasome-inhibitory effect of bortezomib by the water soluble curcumin analog #12 was associated with an increase in the growth inhibition and apoptosis induction in these cells. Water soluble curcumin analogs were tested for inhibition of cell proliferation in ARP multiple myeloma cells by the MTT assay at various concentrations, (2.5, 5, and 10 &#x003bc;M) both alone and in combination with bortezomib at 5 and 10 nM. DMSO and curcumin were used as controls. Curcumin analogs 10, 11, 13 and especially 12 showed inhibition of cell proliferation but further inhibition was observed when they were combined with bortezomib at 5 and 10 nM (<xref rid="f4-ijmm-29-01-0102" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> and data not shown). In the cells co-treated with analog #12 and bortezomib (<xref rid="f3-ijmm-29-01-0102" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>), caspase-3 activity was also enhanced (<xref rid="f3-ijmm-29-01-0102" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3D</xref>). The combination of curcumin and bortezomib had no such enhancing effect. These results show that the sensitivity of Arp myeloma cells to cytotoxic killing in the presence of otherwise sublethal concentrations of bortezomib was enhanced by incubation with curcumin analog #12.</p></sec><sec><title>Curcumin analog #12 increases cellular proteasome-inhibitory and apoptosis-inducing activity of bortezomib in a time-dependent manner</title><p>To understand the mechanism of sensitization by the curcumin analog #12, we performed a kinetic experiment using a combination of 10 &#x003bc;M of analog #12 and 5 nM bortezomib in Arp cells. Western blot analysis of the co-treatment revealed a time-dependent increase in the accumulation of ubiquitinylated proteins and the proteasome target protein p27 in co-treated cells compared with each treatment alone (<xref rid="f5-ijmm-29-01-0102" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>). Compared with bortezomib treatment alone, co-treatment with analog #12 also increased PARP and caspase 3 cleavages at early time points (<xref rid="f5-ijmm-29-01-0102" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>). These results suggest that analog #12 induced apoptosis in the presence of otherwise sublethal concentrations of bortezomib.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Cancer treatment requires simultaneous suppression of multiple signaling/survival pathways. Therefore, emphasis has been laid on combinational therapies that may be more effective than single agents. Previously, curcumin has been reported to synergize with bortezomib and potentiate the apoptotic effects in human multiple myeloma U266 cells via down regulating NF-&#x003ba;B and its regulated gene products (<xref rid="b13-ijmm-29-01-0102" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). We have previously reported that curcumin can potentially inhibit the proteasome activity which is required for the subsequent activation of the NF-&#x003ba;B pathway (<xref rid="b9-ijmm-29-01-0102" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). Although curcumin is very effective, it is poorly water soluble and less bioavailable in tissues remote from the gastrointestinal tract. In our efforts to enhance its bioavailability we synthesized amino acid-conjugated curcumin analogs and have previously reported them to be potent inhibitors of the proteasome and cell proliferation (<xref rid="b15-ijmm-29-01-0102" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). Based on our previous work with curcumin analogs we further investigated the efficacy of these analogs as chemosensitizers, in combination with bortezomib.</p><p>Consistent with our earlier observations in human colon cancer and prostate cancer cells, water soluble amino acid-conjugated curcumin analogs showed potent inhibition of the proteasome and cell proliferation in Arp multiple myeloma cells. Among the curcumin analogs, combination of analog #12 and bortezomib had a more additive effect on proteasome inhibition, proliferation inhibition, and apoptosis induction in these cells. To confirm that the additive effects of this analog were possibly through inhibition of the cellular proteasome activity in these cells we investigated the various proteasomal activities. Our results from the proteasomal activity assays indicate that analog #12 of curcumin when combined with bortezomib could extensively inhibit the CT-like, trypsin-like and PGPH-like activities of the cellular proteasome (<xref rid="f3-ijmm-29-01-0102" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>). Furthermore, the combination of analog #12 with bortezomib results in a considerable increase in caspase activity. An increase in caspase-3 cleavage at earlier time points in the combination treatments could trigger apoptosis in these cells (<xref rid="f5-ijmm-29-01-0102" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>).</p><p>In chemoresistant multiple myeloma cells from patients, the NF-&#x003ba;B pathway has been shown to be constitutively active compared with chemosensitive lines and has been associated with resistance to anticancer therapy (<xref rid="b6-ijmm-29-01-0102" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). However, the activation of NF-&#x003ba;B has been shown to be prevented by proteasome inhibitors (<xref rid="b18-ijmm-29-01-0102" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). Thus, in the ARP human MM cell line, our results suggest that analog #12 of curcumin could induce apoptosis in the presence of otherwise sublethal concentrations of bortezomib possibly through the down-regulation of the NF-&#x003ba;B pathway as a downstream effect of proteasome inhibition, which will be investigated in the near future. Therefore, it is possible that water soluble curcumin analog #12 with increased bioavailability may be useful as potential replacement of curcumin and could be used in combination to bortezomib. Validation of such possibility using animal models is warranted.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Dr Ramesh Batchu (Wayne State University) for providing human multiple myeloma Arp cell line. This work was partially supported by grants from Karmanos Cancer Institute 2009 Pilot project funding (to Q.P.D) and the National Cancer Institute (1R01CA120009, 3R01CA120009-04S1 and 5R01CA127258-05, to Q.P.D).</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="b1-ijmm-29-01-0102"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oerlemans</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Franke</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name><name><surname>Assaraf</surname><given-names>YG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular basis of bortezomib resistance: proteasome subunit beta5 (PSMB5) gene mutation and overexpression of PSMB5 protein</article-title><source>Blood</source><volume>112</volume><fpage>2489</fpage><lpage>2499</lpage><year>2008</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18565852</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b2-ijmm-29-01-0102"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Correia</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Noxa/Bcl-2 protein interactions contribute to bortezomib resistance in human lymphoid cells</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>286</volume><fpage>17682</fpage><lpage>17692</lpage><year>2011</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21454712</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b3-ijmm-29-01-0102"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kern</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Untergasser</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Zenzmaier</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>GRP-78 secreted by tumor cells blocks the antiangiogenic activity of bortezomib</article-title><source>Blood</source><volume>114</volume><fpage>3960</fpage><lpage>3967</lpage><year>2009</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19713465</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b4-ijmm-29-01-0102"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shringarpure</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Catley</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhole</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gene expression analysis of B-lymphoma cells resistant and sensitive to bortezomib</article-title><source>Br J Haematol</source><volume>134</volume><fpage>145</fpage><lpage>156</lpage><year>2006</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16846475</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b5-ijmm-29-01-0102"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fournier</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gareau</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazroui</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The chemotherapeutic agent bortezomib induces the formation of stress granules</article-title><source>Cancer Cell Int</source><volume>10</volume><fpage>12</fpage><year>2010</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20429927</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b6-ijmm-29-01-0102"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kahl</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Markovina</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyamoto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of bortezomib-resistant constitutive NF-kappaB activity in mantle cell lymphoma</article-title><source>Mol Cancer</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>40</fpage><year>2008</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18489772</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b7-ijmm-29-01-0102"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Golden</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>PY</given-names></name><name><surname>Kardosh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Green tea polyphenols block the anticancer effects of bortezomib and other boronic acid-based proteasome inhibitors</article-title><source>Blood</source><volume>113</volume><fpage>5927</fpage><lpage>5937</lpage><year>2009</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19190249</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b8-ijmm-29-01-0102"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hatcher</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Planalp</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Torti</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Torti</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Curcumin: from ancient medicine to current clinical trials</article-title><source>Cell Mol Life Sci</source><volume>65</volume><fpage>1631</fpage><lpage>1652</lpage><year>2008</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18324353</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b9-ijmm-29-01-0102"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Milacic</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Landis-Piwowar</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name><name><surname>Majumdar</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Dou</surname><given-names>QP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Curcumin inhibits the proteasome activity in human colon cancer cells in vitro and in vivo</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><volume>68</volume><fpage>7283</fpage><lpage>7292</lpage><year>2008</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18794115</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b10-ijmm-29-01-0102"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bava</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name><surname>Puliappadamba</surname><given-names>VT</given-names></name><name><surname>Deepti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nair</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Karunagaran</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Anto</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sensitization of taxol-induced apoptosis by curcumin involves down-regulation of nuclear factor-kappaB and the serine/threonine kinase Akt and is independent of tubulin polymerization</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>280</volume><fpage>6301</fpage><lpage>6308</lpage><year>2005</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15590651</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b11-ijmm-29-01-0102"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Notarbartolo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Poma</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Perri</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Dusonchet</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Cervello</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x02019;Alessandro</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antitumor effects of curcumin, alone or in combination with cisplatin or doxorubicin, on human hepatic cancer cells. Analysis of their possible relationship to changes in NF-&#x003ba;B activation levels and in IAP gene expression</article-title><source>Cancer Lett</source><volume>224</volume><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><year>2005</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15911101</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b12-ijmm-29-01-0102"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chirnomas</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Taniguchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>de la Vega</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Chemosensitization to cisplatin by inhibitors of the Fanconi anemia/BRCA pathway</article-title><source>Mol Cancer Ther</source><volume>5</volume><fpage>952</fpage><lpage>961</lpage><year>2006</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16648566</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b13-ijmm-29-01-0102"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayyappan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Curcumin in combination with bortezomib synergistically induced apoptosis in human multiple myeloma U266 cells</article-title><source>Mol Oncol</source><volume>2</volume><fpage>317</fpage><lpage>326</lpage><year>2008</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19383353</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b14-ijmm-29-01-0102"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunnumakkara</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Sethi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Anand</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Guha</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Aggarwal</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Curcumin circumvents chemoresistance in vitro and potentiates the effect of thalidomide and bortezomib against human multiple myeloma in nude mice model</article-title><source>Mol Cancer Ther</source><volume>8</volume><fpage>959</fpage><lpage>970</lpage><year>2009</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19372569</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b15-ijmm-29-01-0102"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of curcumin acetates and amino acid conjugates as proteasome inhibitors</article-title><source>Int J Mol Med</source><volume>26</volume><fpage>447</fpage><lpage>455</lpage><year>2010</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20818481</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b16-ijmm-29-01-0102"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kazi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Synthetic peracetate tea polyphenols as potent proteasome inhibitors and apoptosis inducers in human cancer cells</article-title><source>Front Biosci</source><volume>10</volume><fpage>1010</fpage><lpage>1023</lpage><year>2005</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15769601</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b17-ijmm-29-01-0102"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Frezza</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shakya</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Inhibition of the proteasome activity by gallium(III) complexes contributes to their anti prostate tumor effects</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><volume>67</volume><fpage>9258</fpage><lpage>9265</lpage><year>2007</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17909033</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b18-ijmm-29-01-0102"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The proteasome inhibitor PS-341 markedly enhances sensitivity of multiple myeloma tumor cells to chemotherapeutic agents</article-title><source>Clin Cancer Res</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>1136</fpage><lpage>1144</lpage><year>2003</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12631619</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="f1-ijmm-29-01-0102" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Structures of (A) curcumin and (B&#x02013;D) amino acid-conjugated curcumin analogs 6&#x02013;13.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="IJMM-29-01-0102-g00"/></fig><fig id="f2-ijmm-29-01-0102" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Curcumin analogs inhibit CT activity of the purified 20S proteasome. (A) Curcumin analog #12 was examined at 2.5 and 5 &#x003bc;M both alone and in combination with bortezomib (Vel) at 10 nM. DMSO and curcumin were used as controls. (B) The curcumin analog #12 was examined at 10 &#x003bc;M both alone and in combination with bortezomib (Vel) at 20 nM. Error bars indicate SD of the mean for all treatments in triplicate.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="IJMM-29-01-0102-g01"/></fig><fig id="f3-ijmm-29-01-0102" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Effect of curcumin analogs plus bortezomib on various proteasome activities and caspase-3 activity. Protein extracts from Arp myeloma cells after treatment with analog #12 and bortezomib at the indicated concentrations for 48 h were examined for all three proteasome activities and caspase-3 activity. Analog #12 when combined with 10 nM bortezomib significantly inhibited chymotryptic (CT)-, PGPH- and trypsin-like activities of the proteasome and also increased the caspase-3 activity in these cells. Error bars indicate SD of the mean of all treatment values in triplicate.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="IJMM-29-01-0102-g02"/></fig><fig id="f4-ijmm-29-01-0102" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Curcumin analogs inhibit cell proliferation. Arp multiple myeloma cells were treated with curcumin analog #12 at the indicated concentrations both alone and in combination with bortezomib (Vel) at 5 and 10 nM. Analog #12 showed potent inhibition of cell proliferation both alone and in combination with bortezomib (Vel).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="IJMM-29-01-0102-g03"/></fig><fig id="f5-ijmm-29-01-0102" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Immunoblot experiment with protein extracts from Arp multiple myeloma cells after treatment with analog #12 and bortezomib at the indicated concentrations for various time points. Increased accumulation of proteasome target protein p27 and ubiquitinylated (Ub) proteins and increased PARP and caspase 3 (Casp-3) cleavages at early time points was observed in combination treatments compared to bortezomib (Vel) alone.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="IJMM-29-01-0102-g04"/></fig></floats-group></article>