<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Appl Oral Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Appl Oral Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">J Appl Oral Sci</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Applied Oral Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1678-7757</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1678-7765</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Faculdade de Odontologia de Bauru da Universidade de S&#x000e3;o
Paulo</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25025554</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4072264</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/1678-775720130017</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Influence of time, toothpaste and saliva in the retention of
<italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic> and <italic>Streptococcus sanguinis</italic>
on different toothbrushes</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>SCHMIDT</surname><given-names>Julia Caroline</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff01">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn01">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>BUX</surname><given-names>Miriam</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff02">2</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn01">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>FILIPUZZI-JENNY</surname><given-names>Elisabeth</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff02">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>KULIK</surname><given-names>Eva Maria</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff02">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>WALTIMO</surname><given-names>Tuomas</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff02">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>WEIGER</surname><given-names>Roland</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff01">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>WALTER</surname><given-names>Clemens</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff01">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff01"><label>1</label> Department of Periodontology, Endodontology and Cariology, School of
Dental Medicine, University of Basel, Basel, Switzerland.</aff><aff id="aff02"><label>2</label> Clinic of Preventive Dentistry and Oral Microbiology, School of Dental
Medicine, University of Basel, Basel, Switzerland.</aff><author-notes><corresp id="c01"><bold>Corresponding address:</bold> Clemens Walter - Department of Periodontology,
Endodontology and Cariology, School of Dental Medicine - University of Basel -
Hebelstrasse 3 - 4056 Basel - Switzerland - Phone: +41 61 2672628 - Fax: +41 61
2672659 - e-mail: <email>clemens.walter@unibas.ch</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>May-Jun</season><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>22</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>152</fpage><lpage>158</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>08</day><month>1</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>06</day><month>2</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>03</day><month>3</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License which permits unrestricted
non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the
original work is properly cited. </license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Objectives</title><p>The intraoral transmission of cariogenic and periodontopathogenic species seems to
be facilitated by contaminated toothbrushes and other oral hygiene devices. The
aim of this investigation was to analyze the <italic>in vitro</italic> retention
and survival rate of <italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic> and
<italic>Streptococcus sanguinis</italic> on different toothbrushes. The impacts
of human saliva and antimicrobial toothpaste on these parameters were further
evaluated.</p></sec><sec><title>Material and Methods</title><p>Part I: Four toothbrushes (Colgate 360&#x000b0;, Curaprox CS5460 ultra soft, elmex InterX,
Trisa Flexible Head3) were contaminated by <italic>S. mutans</italic> DSM 20523 or
<italic>S. sanguinis</italic> DSM 20068 suspensions for three minutes. Bacteria
were removed from the toothbrushes after either three minutes (T<sub>0</sub>) or
24 hours (T<sub>24</sub>) of dry storage and grown on Columbia blood agar plates
for the quantification of colony-forming units (CFUs). Part II: The effects of
saliva from a caries-active or a caries-inactive person and of toothpaste
containing 0.12% chlorhexidine digluconate were also tested.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Part I: After three minutes of dry storage, approximately one percent of the
bacteria were still detectable on the toothbrushes. After 24 hours, <italic>S.
sanguinis</italic> exhibited a more pronounced decrease in viable cell numbers
compared with <italic>S. mutans</italic> but the differences were not significant
(Kruskal-Wallis test, p&#x0003e;0.05). Part II: The addition of human saliva from a
caries-active or caries-inactive person slightly increased the retention of both
streptococcal species at T<sub>0</sub>. The use of toothpaste had no influence on
the amount of viable streptococci at T<sub>0</sub>, but it reduced the microbial
load after 24 hours of storage. There were only slight nonsignificant differences
(p&#x0003e;0.05) between the four toothbrushes.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p><italic>In vitro</italic> bacterial retention and survival of <italic>S.
sanguinis</italic> and <italic>S. mutans</italic> on different toothbrushes
occurred. Within the limitations of this study, the use of human saliva or an
antimicrobial toothpaste did not lead to significant differences in the microbial
load on toothbrushes.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Toothbrushing</kwd><kwd>Bacterial adhesion</kwd><kwd><italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic></kwd><kwd><italic>Streptococcus sanguinis</italic></kwd><kwd>Saliva</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><sec><title>Therefore</title><p>Both periodontitis and dental caries are infectious diseases caused by microorganisms
in a pathogenic biofilm. A biofilm is a complex bacterial structure on a solid wet
surface that protects microorganisms from the host's immune defense and from
antimicrobial agents<sup><xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup>. therefore
an integral part of the prevention and treatment of periodontitis and dental
caries<sup><xref rid="r03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup>. Without proper
supragingival plaque control, the initiation and progression of oral infectious
diseases may occur<sup><xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup>. The
relationship between the amount of plaque accumulation and its pathogenic effect is
described by the unspecific plaque hypothesis<sup><xref rid="r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup>. In contrast, the specific plaque hypothesis refers to
specific pathogens in the etiology ofperiodontal diseases<sup><xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup>. This view is supported by the finding that certain
bacterial species are more virulent than others<sup><xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup>. The oral cavity
naturally harbors a large variety of different bacteria<sup><xref rid="r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup>. <italic>Streptococcus sanguinis</italic> is among
the pioneer bacteria in oral biofilm formation preceding the attachment of subsequent
colonizers and therefore of great importance in the development of periodontal
diseases<sup><xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup>.
<italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic> is not considered to be a characteristic
periodontal pathogen but the major causative microorganism associated with dental
caries initiation<sup><xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup>. However, a
dramatic increase of <italic>S. mutans</italic> may occur after non-surgical
periodontal therapy, possibly leading to an increased cariogenic activity<sup><xref rid="r06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup>. The treatment of periodontitis and
dental caries should prevent bacterial recolonization due to intraoral transmission
of pathogenic bacteria<sup><xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup>.
Transmission of cariogenic and periodontopathogenic species was demonstrated for
contaminated toothbrushes and other oral hygiene devices<sup><xref rid="r07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> . A large
variety of different toothbrush designs exist that may facilitate the retention,
survival and intraoral transmission of bacteria<sup><xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup>. To prevent periodontal and cariogenic infection and avoid
reinfection, an adequate disinfection of oral hygiene devices such as toothbrushes is
considered to be clinically relevant<sup><xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup>.</p><p>The first aim of the present study was to evaluate the adhesion and survival rate of
<italic>S. sanguinis</italic> and <italic>S. mutans</italic> on four different
toothbrushes (Part I). The second aim was to investigate the influence of saliva and
of an antimicrobial toothpaste on bacterial retention (Part II).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIAL AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Toothbrushes</title><p>Four toothbrushes were tested in this study: Colgate 360&#x000b0; (Colgate-Palmolive AG,
Thalwil, Switzerland), Curaprox CS5460 ultra soft (Curaden AG, Kriens, Switzerland),
Elmex InterX (GABA AG, Therwil, Switzerland), and Trisa Flexible Head3 (Trisa AG,
Triengen, Switzerland). The relevant characteristics of the toothbrushes are provided
in <xref ref-type="table" rid="t01">Figure 1</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="t01" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Characteristics of the toothbrushes used in the study</p></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr style="background-color:#dcdcde"><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of bristles</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dimension of head (mm)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hardness</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length of bristles (mm)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Additional characteristics</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Colgate 360&#x000b0;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1323</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26x11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">medium <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tfn01t01">*</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9-12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">soft rubber polishing cups, tongue and cheek cleaner</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#dcdcde"><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Curaprox CS5460</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5460 <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tfn01t01">*</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22x11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">medium <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tfn01t01">*</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elmex nterX</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">648-702 <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tfn01t01">*</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21x9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">soft <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tfn01t01">*</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10-12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">some bristles at a 60&#x000b0; angle to the rest of bristles</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#dcdcde"><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trisa Flexible Head</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1916</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26x9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">medium <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tfn01t01">*</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10-12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">flexible head</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn01t01"><label>*</label><p>as described by the respective manufacturer</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Part I</title><sec><title>Bacterial strains and growth conditions</title><p><italic>S. sanguinis</italic> DSM 20068 and <italic>S. mutans</italic> DSM 20523
were obtained from Deutsche Sammlung von Mikroorganismen und Zellkulturen
(Braunschweig, Germany) and preserved in 15% skim milk solution at -20&#x000b0;C. For the
experiments, 10&#x000b5;l inoculums of each of the streptococci were suspended in 5 ml of
Schaedler broth (BBL, Becton Dickinson, Basel, Switzerland) and grown aerobically
at 37&#x000b0;C for either five (<italic>S. mutans</italic>) or eight
(<italic>S.sanguinis</italic>) hours<sup><xref rid="r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup>. Then, 900 &#x000b5;l of these bacterial suspensions was
transferred to 45 ml of fresh Schaedler broth and aerobically incubated at 37&#x000b0;C
for 16 (<italic>S. mutans</italic>) or 20 (<italic>S. sanguinis</italic>) hours.
To determine consistent bacterial counts (CFU/ml) of the bacterial suspensions
used to contaminate the toothbrushes, cultures were ultrasonicated for 30 s with a
maximum power of 130 W (Sonics Vibra Cell VCX130, Huber, Meyrin/Satigny,
Switzerland), and appropriate dilutions (10<sup>-5</sup>, 10<sup>-6</sup>) were
plated onto Columbia blood agar plates (BBL; Becton Dickinson, Basel, Switzerland)
supplemented with 50 ml/l of human blood, 0.5 mg/l of menadione and 5 mg/l of
hemin at 37&#x000b0;C prior to each experiment<sup><xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup>. The plates were incubated anaerobically using
atmosphere generation system packs (AnaeroGenTM Compact, Oxoid, Pratteln,
Switzerland) at 37&#x000b0;C for one day, and the colonies were then counted.</p></sec><sec><title>Retention of streptococci on toothbrushes</title><p>For the retention experiments, two toothbrushes of each brand were aseptically
removed from the original wrappings. Each new toothbrush was used once. First, the
toothbrush heads were placed in 15 ml of bacterial suspensions of approximately
5x10<sup>8</sup> CFU/ml and left in place for three minutes, such that the head
of the toothbrush and approximately 1 cm of the handle were exposed to the
bacterial culture. The time of three minutes was chosen due to the average time
usually spent for an oral hygiene session<sup><xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup>. The toothbrushes
were then dipped three times in 15 ml of 0.9% NaCl and stored with the bristles
facing up in a dry environment at room temperature for either three minutes
(T<sub>0</sub>) or 24 hours (T<sub>24</sub>). For microbial analysis, the head
of each toothbrush was clipped off, placed in 15 ml of 0.9% NaCl, vortexed for one
minute, ultrasonicated for one minute with a maximum power of 100 W and again
vortexed for one minute. Appropriate dilutions (10<sup>-0</sup>, 10<sup>-1</sup>,
10<sup>-2</sup>, 10<sup>-3</sup>, 10<sup>-4</sup>) were then plated onto
Columbia blood agar plates. The plates were incubated anaerobically at 37&#x000b0;C for
one day, and the colonies were counted.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Part II</title><sec><title>Influence of saliva on the retention of streptococci on toothbrushes</title><p>The saliva of two subjects with different caries activity was used in this study.
Both subjects were informed regarding the purposes of the study, and informed
consent was obtained. The study was approved by the Research ethics Committee of
the University of Basel, Switzerland (eK: 295/08).</p><p>Subject 1 (caries-active, CA) was a 25-year-old male student. He had 24 teeth with
insufficiently restored carious lesions [decayed, missing and filled teeth (DMFT)
=16]. Subject 2 (caries-inactive, CI) was a 30-year-old female dental student. She
had 28 teeth with no carious lesions (DMFT=1; one filling due to aesthetic
reasons). Whole saliva from both volunteers was collected by paraffin stimulation
over a three-week period. Saliva was collected in the morning, and the volunteers
were advised not to drink or eat overnight. Approximately 35-50 ml of saliva was
collected <italic>per</italic> day in sterile, ice-chilled tubes and stored at
-20&#x000b0;C. After collecting a total of 350-400 ml of saliva, the samples from each
volunteer were gently thawed in cold water, pooled and filtered through a 70&#x000b5;m
filter (Cell Strainer, Becton Dickinson, Basel, Switzerland) into sterile,
ice-chilled tubes. The saliva was ultrasonicated for 30 s with a maximum power of
100 W and then centrifuged at 21,800 x g for one hour at 4&#x000b0;C. The supernatant was
filtered through 0.45- and 0.22mm filters (Millex-HV and Millex-GV, respectively;
Millipore AG, Zug, Switzerland) and frozen at -20&#x000b0;C in 15-ml aliquots. Before use,
the saliva was gently thawed by placing the tubes in cold water, and the pH value
was adjusted to 7 with phosphate buffer (1.5 ml of 491 mM
Na<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub> and 1.5 ml of 275.6 mM
KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>
<italic>per</italic> 15 ml of saliva) in order to standardize this parameter. For
experiments using bacteria suspended in human saliva, 15 ml of the respective
bacterial cultures were centrifuged at 6,200 x g for 5 minutes. The bacterial
pellets were then washed once with 0.9% NaCl, harvested again by centrifugation
and suspended in 15 ml of buffered saliva<sup><xref rid="r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup>. To determine the correct bacterial counts, appropriate
dilutions (10<sup>-0</sup>, 10<sup>-1</sup>, 10<sup>-2</sup>, 10<sup>-3</sup>,
10<sup>-4</sup>) were plated onto Columbia blood agar plates. The plates were
incubated anaerobically at 37&#x000b0;C for one day, and the colonies were counted.</p><p>The experimental setup of the retention experiments was identical to that
described in Part I, except that the bacteria were suspended in human saliva. The
time of dry storage after toothbrush contamination amounted three minutes
(T<sub>0</sub>).</p></sec><sec><title>Influence of toothpaste on the retention of streptococci on
toothbrushes</title><p>To examine the influence of antibacterial toothpaste on the retention of
streptococci on toothbrushes, the experiments were repeated using a toothpaste
containing 0.12% chlorhexidine digluconate (Curasept ADS 712, Curaden AG, Kriens,
Switzerland) at T<sub>0</sub> (without saliva, CA, CI) and T<sub>24 </sub>(without
saliva). The unaltered overthe-counter toothpaste was provided by the
manufacturer.</p><p>To mimic normal use, 0.5 g of the toothpaste was applied by repeatedly brushing
the agent into the respective toothbrush for 10 s. The toothbrush head was then
placed in 10 ml of sterile 0.9% NaCl and vortexed for one minute to cause foaming
of the toothpaste. Afterward, the retention test with either <italic>S.
sanguinis</italic> or <italic>S. mutans</italic> was performed as described
above.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Analysis</title><p>Two separate experiments were performed for each set of parameters. The retention of
the bacteria on each toothbrush was assessed by assessing the difference in bacterial
growth (i.e., the log<sub>10 </sub>number of bacteria CFUs) before and after
retention to the toothbrush. A descriptive analysis was also performed. The
reductions are shown as the mean-log<sub>10 </sub>factors and standard deviations,
and "&#x02265;" denotes reductions greater than the respective detection limit. A statistical
analysis was performed using SPSS<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> software (SPSS<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> Statistics
20.0.0; SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, USA). The nonparametric Kruskal-Wallis test was used
to assess the differences between the tested variables. A result was considered to be
statistically significant if p&#x0003c;0.05.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>Part I</title><sec><title>Retention of streptococci on toothbrushes</title><p>The bacterial counts (CFU/ml) used to artificially contaminate the toothbrushes
were between 9.8x10<sup>7</sup> and 7.6x10<sup>8</sup> for <italic>S.
mutans</italic> and between 1.1x10<sup>8</sup> and 7.5x10<sup>8</sup> for
<italic>S. sanguinis</italic>. Of these bacteria, approximately one percent,
corresponding to a mean log<sub>10</sub> reduction of approximately 2, was still
retained on the toothbrushes after rinsing and three minutes of storage
(T<sub>0</sub>) at room temperature (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t02">Table
1</xref>).</p><p>No significant differences in the retention of <italic>S. mutans</italic> and
<italic>S. sanguinis</italic> between the four toothbrushes could be detected.
After 24 hours of storage (T<sub>24</sub>), a decrease in bacterial retention on
the toothbrush heads, compared with the retention at three minutes
(T<sub>0</sub>), was found for all toothbrushes and both bacteria. For <italic>S.
sanguinis</italic>, the reductions in viable cell numbers after one day
(T<sub>24</sub>) on all toothbrushes were more pronounced compared with
<italic>S. mutans</italic>. The decrease in <italic>S. sanguinis</italic>
bacterial counts was higher than 6 log factors and thereby below the detection
limit, except for the Colgate 360&#x000b0; toothbrush. The differences were not
statistically significant (p&#x0003e;0.05).</p><table-wrap id="t02" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p> Influence of time, toothpaste and saliva on the reduction of streptococcal
retention on four different toothbrushes. Either no saliva or saliva
collected from a caries-inactive (CI) or a caries-active (CA) volunteer was
used, and the artificially contaminated toothbrushes were analyzed after
either three minutes (T<sub>0</sub>) or 24 hours (T<sub>24</sub>). The
reductions in bacterial counts are shown as the mean-log10 factors and
standard deviations. Two independent experiments (n=2) were performed for
each set of parameters. A higher number indicates a greater bacterial
reduction, and "&#x02265;" denotes reductions to levels below the respective
detection limits</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr style="background-color:#dcdcde"><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Toothbrush and bacteria</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Without toothpaste</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">With toothpaste</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">no saliva</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">CI</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">CA</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">no saliva</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">CI</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">CA</th></tr><tr style="background-color:#dcdcde"><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T<sub>0</sub></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T<sub>24</sub></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T<sub>0</sub></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T<sub>0</sub></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T<sub>0</sub></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T<sub>24</sub></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T<sub>0</sub></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T<sub>0</sub></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Colgate 360&#x000ba;</td><td colspan="8" rowspan="1">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#dcdcde"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>S. sanguinis</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.15&#x000b1;0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.84&#x000b1;0.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.04&#x000b1;0.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.96&#x000b1;0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.15&#x000b1;0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265; 6.35&#x000b1;0.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.91&#x000b1;0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.79&#x000b1;0.17</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>S. mutans</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.16&#x000b1;0.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.97&#x000b1;0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.76&#x000b1;0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.78&#x000b1;0.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.27&#x000b1;0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5&#x000b1;0.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.70&#x000b1;0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.94&#x000b1;0.05</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#dcdcde"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Curaprox CS5460</td><td colspan="8" rowspan="1">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>S. sanguinis</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.64&#x000b1;0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265; 6.76&#x000b1;0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.10&#x000b1;0.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.27&#x000b1;0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.35&#x000b1;0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265; 6.25&#x000b1;0.21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.95&#x000b1;0.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.04&#x000b1;0.01</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#dcdcde"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>S. mutans</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.40&#x000b1;0.16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.51&#x000b1;0.16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.01&#x000b1;0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.37&#x000b1;0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.13&#x000b1;0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.27&#x000b1;0.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.48&#x000b1;0.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.58&#x000b1;0.05</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elmex interX</td><td colspan="8" rowspan="1">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#dcdcde"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>S. sanguinis</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.58&#x000b1;0.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265; 6.59&#x000b1;0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.23&#x000b1;0.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.11&#x000b1;0.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.36&#x000b1;0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265; 6.25&#x000b1;0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.95&#x000b1;0.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.07&#x000b1;0.12</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>S. mutans</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.12&#x000b1;0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.04&#x000b1;0.42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.93&#x000b1;0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.86&#x000b1;0.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.53&#x000b1;0.21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.48&#x000b1;0.27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.96&#x000b1;0.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.96&#x000b1;0.29</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#dcdcde"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trisa Flexible Head</td><td colspan="8" rowspan="1">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>S. sanguinis</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.47&#x000b1;0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265; 6.64&#x000b1;0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.86&#x000b1;0.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.96&#x000b1;0.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.11&#x000b1;0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265; 6.42&#x000b1;0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.90&#x000b1;0.20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.05&#x000b1;0.13</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#dcdcde"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>S. mutans</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.96&#x000b1;0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.24&#x000b1;0.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.60&#x000b1;0.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.69&#x000b1;0.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.35&#x000b1;0.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.38&#x000b1;0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.54&#x000b1;0.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.78&#x000b1;0.17</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec><title>Part II</title><sec><title>Influence of saliva on the retention of streptococci on toothbrushes</title><p>The retention of the two streptococcal species was tested in the presence of
saliva isolated from the person with or without caries activity (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t02">Table 1</xref>).</p><p>When the two streptococcal species were compared with respect to the presence or
absence of either saliva, slightly more bacterial cells remained attached to the
toothbrushes at T<sub>0</sub> when saliva was added. There was no particular
preference regarding the retention of the two streptococcal species using the
saliva from the person with or without caries activity.</p></sec><sec><title>Influence of toothpaste on the retention of streptococci on
toothbrushes</title><p>The chlorhexidine-digluconate-containing toothpaste had no influence on the amount
of viable bacteria of either species at time point T<sub>0 </sub>either in the
presence or absence of saliva. For <italic>S. mutans</italic>, a reduction in cell
numbers over time (T<sub>24</sub>) was detectable for all toothbrushes. For
<italic>S. sanguinis</italic>, a reduction was only detected for the Colgate
360&#x000b0; toothbrush after 24 hours. The influence of the antibacterial toothpaste
could not be determined for the other three toothbrushes because the bacterial
numbers at T<sub>24</sub> compared with those in the settings without toothpaste
were already below the detection limit. There were no significant differences
between any tested variables (p&#x0003e;0.05).</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>This study demonstrated that the contamination of different toothbrushes with <italic>S.
sanguinis</italic> and <italic>S. mutans</italic> occurred. The microbial load
decreased after a period of dry storage and the additional use of toothpaste. However,
the differences were not significant for our experimental setting.</p><p>These observations are in agreement with previous studies examining the presence of
different microorganisms on toothbrushes<sup><xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="r08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="r09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup>.</p><p>The present study was conducted <italic>in vitro</italic>. This approach allows for the
control of several parameters that may influence the retention of bacteria on
toothbrushes, such as the bacterial species used to contaminate the toothbrushes. During
normal toothbrush use, the indigenous oral microflora will adhere to the toothbrush.
There is, however, high inter- and intraindividual variability in the bacterial load and
the composition of the oral microflora. Oral hygiene measures and the dental health
status of patients are closely related to the presence of commensal and potentially
pathogenic microorganisms<sup><xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup>. A
correlation between the dental status of patients and the microbial load of toothbrushes
was demonstrated<sup><xref rid="r08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup>. Therefore, the use
of specific bacterial strains, such as S. mutans and S. sanguinis, ensures a
reproducible and standardized contamination protocol. A previous study also examined the
retention and viability of <italic>S. mutans</italic> on toothbrushes using an in vitro
approach<sup><xref rid="r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup>. This study revealed
decreasing numbers of <italic>S. mutans</italic> with time. Viable bacterial cells were
detectable on the toothbrushes for up to four hours<sup><xref rid="r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup>.</p><p><italic>S. mutans</italic> was selected due to its significant role in the etiology of
dental caries<sup><xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup>. Its primary
ecological niche is the supragingival plaque. <italic>S. sanguinis</italic> was included
in the present study because of its relevance in supragingival and subgingival biofilm
formation<sup><xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup>. Streptococci belong
to the group of early oral plaque colonizers. They enable the subsequent attachment and
multiplication of so-called late colonizers, which may include potential pathogenic
bacteria<sup><xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup>. Bacteria classified
as late colonizers often require an anaerobic environment and prefer receptors on other
oral bacteria<sup><xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup>. Nevertheless,
toothbrushes infected with a wide spectrum of microorganisms also exhibited
gram-negative, strict anaerobic bacteria, such as <italic>Porphyromonas
gingivalis</italic><sup><xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup>. Specific
contamination with <italic>Aggregatibacter actinomycetemcomitans</italic> was further
evaluated in a clinical setting<sup><xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup>.</p><p>While no differences between <italic>S. mutans</italic> and <italic>S.
sanguinis</italic> retention were detectable after three minutes, S. sanguinis levels
were decreased to a greater extent after 24 hours, both with and without the use of
antimicrobial toothpaste. This result suggests that <italic>S. mutans</italic> is more
resistant against both adverse environmental conditions, such as starvation and
dehydration, and the antimicrobial effect of the chlorhexidine-digluconate-containing
toothpaste. Furthermore, the adhesion of <italic>S. mutans</italic> may be stronger than
that of <italic>S. sanguinis</italic>. This finding possibly reflects the greater
pathogenic potential of the cariogenic species <italic>S. mutans</italic>. This
microorganism is characterized by several virulence factors, such as acid production,
the synthesis of extracellular polysaccharides and the expression of adhesins on the
bacterial surface<sup><xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup>. These adhesins
allow the bacteria to attach to oral surfaces and other species. <italic>S.
sanguinis</italic> is also able to adhere to tooth and bacterial surfaces<sup><xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup>.</p><p>Using an <italic>in vitro</italic> mono-species approach, the potential synergisms and
antagonisms between oral bacteria cannot be taken into account<sup><xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup>. Phenotypes of bacteria from the oral cavity, especially
those derived from dental biofilms, may also differ from these <italic>in vitro</italic>
planktonic bacteria with regard to their adhesion characteristics<sup><xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> . Biofilms are complex three-dimensional
structures that consist of microbial colonies surrounded by an exopolymer
matrix<sup><xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup>. The diversity of the
oral microbiota, which is comprised of over 1,000 different bacterial species<sup><xref rid="r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup>, limits the possibility of reflecting
the intraoral environment in a multi-species biofilm laboratory model. In addition to
microbial aspects, the <italic>in vitro</italic> design of the present study assures
uniform toothbrush practice methods, rinsing and storage conditions, as well as
consistent toothbrush wear.</p><p>The present study demonstrated the influence of storage time, toothbrush type, human
saliva and toothpaste use on toothbrush contamination.</p><p>Bacterial counts decreased over time. A reduction in counts was detectable after a
storage period of 24 hours, although <italic>S. mutans</italic> still remained
detectable. This finding implies that the non-humid atmosphere and the absence of
nutrients during dry storage prevent the survival of most microorganisms. The observed
decrease in the number of microorganisms with storage time is in accordance with
previous observations. Most studies included an examination time of up to 24
hours<sup><xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="r08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup>. While some authors
reported a critical reduction in the proportion of vital microorganisms within twelve
hours, others described a gradual decrease over a period of 48 hours<sup><xref rid="r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup>.</p><p>The present investigation revealed some differences in bacterial counts using different
types of toothbrushes. The Colgate 360&#x000b0; toothbrush harbored more <italic>S.
sanguinis</italic> than the other toothbrushes after 24 hours. This finding indicates
that different toothbrush designs may influence the retention of microorganisms.
Different toothbrush components, such as the bristle number or length and the bristle
material, may affect colonization. As a result of their surface morphology, in terms of
roughness and microscopic defects, toothbrush bristles may further provide niches for
bacteria. The additional soft rubber polishing cups and textured tongue and cheek
scraper on the back of one toothbrush head may provide an additional surface for
bacterial adhesion.</p><p>A previous publication compared different toothbrushes with respect to bacterial
retention<sup><xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup>. The authors
concluded that bacteria retention increased with the exposed area of the toothbrush.
Whether bristles with anchoring part harbor more bacteria compared to bristles without
anchoring part was analyzed<sup><xref rid="r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup>. It was
demonstrated that the results for bristles with and without anchoring parts did not
differ<sup><xref rid="r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup>.</p><p>However, the impact of different types of anchoring parts on bacterial retention was
subsequently revealed<sup><xref rid="r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup>. In addition,
the degree of toothbrush bristle wear seems to have an impact on <italic>S.
mutans</italic> retention, with new toothbrushes harboring more bacterial
cells<sup><xref rid="r09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup>. In addition, hard
deposits between the toothbrush bristles were shown to be niches for bacterial
growth<sup><xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup>.</p><p>Several studies examined the value of coated tufts, including triclosan and
chlorhexidine<sup><xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup>. Inconsistent
results were obtained regarding a potential superior effect of these impregnated
bristles compared with non-coated bristles.</p><p>The use of toothpaste seems to affect the survival rate of bacteria, but it appears to
be insufficient to prevent bacterial contamination. In our study, there was a greater
reduction in microbial load after 24 hours of dry storage for both species and all
toothbrushes. Additive bactericidal effects of toothpastes have also been observed in
clinical and <italic>in vitro</italic> studies<sup><xref rid="r04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup>. It was noted
that toothpastes differ in their antibacterial activity depending on their
composition<sup><xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup>.</p><p>Dentifrices usually contain several therapeutic substances with antimicrobial
activity<sup><xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup>. The
toothpaste used in the present investigation contained 0.12% chlorhexidine digluconate
as a therapeutic agent. Chlorhexidine is considered to be the gold standard of oral
hygiene<sup><xref rid="r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup>. Its bactericidal
effect is based on its adsorption to bacterial cell surfaces, resulting in increased
cell membrane permeability or the precipitation of cytoplasm. Chlorhexidine that is
adherent to tooth surfaces exhibits prolonged bacteriostatic action<sup><xref rid="r01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup>. This characteristic could therefore
explain the observed influence of chlorhexidine on bacterial viability.</p><p>A greater amount of bacteria adhered to the toothbrushes when they were suspended in
saliva from a person with either high or low caries activity. Differences in saliva
composition due to different caries activity may therefore not influence the adhesion
process of <italic>S. mutans</italic> and <italic>S. sanguinis</italic> in this
<italic>in vitro</italic> approach. On tooth surfaces, salivary molecules, such as
proteins, glycoproteins and mucines, first adsorb and form an acquired pellicle, which
provides binding sites for bacterial receptors<sup><xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup>. Salivary constituents most likely also bind to the toothbrush
surfaces and thereby facilitate the colonization of bacteria, which may actively bind to
the saliva-coated toothbrushes or could be passively retained due to the high viscosity
and capillary action of saliva<sup><xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup>.
Regarding the known hydrophobic and electrostatic interactions between microorganisms
and solid surfaces, however, microbial attachment seems to be more conceivable<sup><xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup>.</p><p>Toothbrush contamination seems to be clinically relevant because subsequent intraoral
translocations of microorganisms or reinfections may occur<sup><xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup>. Several studies revealed the translocation of
cariogenic and periodontopathogenic species from a contaminated oral hygiene aid or a
dental instrument. The translocation of <italic>S. mutans</italic> strains was
demonstrated via dental floss. Bacteria were further transferred by means of dental
explorers<sup><xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>CONCLUSION</title><p>In conclusion, the present study showed that <italic>in vitro</italic> bacterial
adhesion and survival of <italic>S. sanguinis</italic> and <italic>S. mutans</italic> on
toothbrushes is possible with no remarkable differences among the toothbrushes. Within
the limitations of this study, the use of human saliva of a caries-active and a
caries-inactive proband or an antimicrobial toothpaste, containing chlorhexidine, did
not lead to significant differences in the microbial load on the toothbrushes
tested.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn id="fn01" fn-type="other"><label>*</label><p>both authors contributed equally to this work.</p></fn><fn fn-type="conflict"><p><bold>CONFLICT OF INTEREST</bold></p><p>The authors declare that there is no conflict of interest.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title><p>Parts of this research were conducted by M. Bux in partial fulfilment of the
requirements for an MD degree from the University of Basel, Switzerland. The authors
thank Colgate-Palmolive AG (Thalwil, Switzerland), Curaden AG (Kriens, Switzerland),
GABA AG (Therwil, Switzerland) and Trisa AG (Triengen, Switzerland) for provision of the
toothbrushes used in this study and the Curaden AG (Kriens, Switzerland) for providing
the toothpaste.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="r01"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Addy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chlorhexidine compared with other locally delivered antimicrobials. A
short review</article-title><source>J Clin Periodontol</source><year>1986</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>957</fpage><lpage>964</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3540026</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r02"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Al-Ahmad</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiedmann-Al-Ahmad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Deimling</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaser</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pelz</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wittmer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>An antimicrobial effect from silver-coated toothbrush
heads</article-title><source>Am J Dent</source><year>2010</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>251</fpage><lpage>254</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21207790</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r03"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Axelsson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Nystr&#x000f6;m</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindhe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The long-term effect of a plaque control program on tooth mortality,
caries and periodontal disease in adults. Results after 30 years of
maintenance</article-title><source>J Clin Periodontol</source><year>2004</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>749</fpage><lpage>757</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15312097</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r04"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bertolini</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name><surname>Biondi</surname><given-names>O</given-names><suffix>Filho</suffix></name><name><surname>Pomilio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinheiro</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial capacity of Aloe vera and propolis dentifrice against
Streptococcus mutans strains in toothbrushes: an in vitro study</article-title><source>J Appl Oral Sci</source><year>2012</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>32</fpage><lpage>37</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22437675</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r05"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bunetel</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Tricot-Doleux</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Agnani</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonnaure-Mallet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vitro evaluation of the retention of three species of pathogenic
microorganisms by three different types of toothbrush</article-title><source>Oral Microbiol Immunol</source><year>2000</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>313</fpage><lpage>316</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11154423</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r06"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Soete</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dekeyser</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pauwels</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Teughels</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>van Steenberghe</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Quirynen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Increase in cariogenic bacteria after initial periodontal
therapy</article-title><source>J Dent Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>48</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15615875</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r07"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edman</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Keene</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Shklair</surname><given-names>IL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoerman</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dental floss for implantation and sampling of Streptococcus mutans
from approximal surfaces of human teeth</article-title><source>Arch Oral Biol</source><year>1975</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>145</fpage><lpage>148</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1054583</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r08"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Glass</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name><surname>Lare</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Toothbrush contamination: a potential health risk?</article-title><source>Quintessence Int</source><year>1986</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>39</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3457393</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r09"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goldsmith</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Shey</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Houpt</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Fine</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Schreiner</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Toothbrush bristle wear and adherence of Streptococcus
mutans</article-title><source>Pediatr Dent</source><year>2007</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>243</fpage><lpage>247</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17688023</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karibasappa</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagesh</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sujatha</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment of microbial contamination of toothbrush head: an in vitro
study</article-title><source>Indian J Dent Res</source><year>2011</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>2</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21525668</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kolenbrander</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Periasamy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jakubovics</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oral multispecies biofilm development and the key role of cell-cell
distance</article-title><source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source><year>2010</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>471</fpage><lpage>480</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20514044</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Loesche</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemotherapy of dental plaque infections</article-title><source>Oral Sci Rev</source><year>1976</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>107</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1067529</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Loesche</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of Streptococcus mutans in human dental decay</article-title><source>Microbiol Rev</source><year>1986</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>353</fpage><lpage>380</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3540569</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Loesche</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Svanberg</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Pape</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intraoral transmission of Streptococcus mutans by a dental
explorer</article-title><source>J Dent Res</source><year>1979</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>1765</fpage><lpage>1770</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">288753</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Malmberg</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Birkhed</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Norvenius</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Nor&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Dahl&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microorganisms on toothbrushes at day-care centers</article-title><source>Acta Odontol Scand</source><year>1994</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>98</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8048328</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>M&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><name><surname>Lange</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Actinobacil lus actinomycetemcomitans contamination of toothbrushes
from patients harbouring the organism</article-title><source>J Clin Periodontol</source><year>1989</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>388</fpage><lpage>390</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2760252</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nascimento</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Scarabel</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name><name><surname>Miani</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Pedrazzi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vitro evaluation of the microbial contamination on new
toothbrushes: a preliminary study</article-title><source>Microsc Res Tech</source><year>2012</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>42</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21618654</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nelson-Filho</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Isper</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Assed</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Faria</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>IY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of triclosan dentifrice on toothbrush
contamination</article-title><source>Pediatr Dent</source><year>2004</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15080352</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quirynen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>De Soete</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dierickx</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>van Steenberghe</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The intra-oral translocation of periodontopathogens jeopardises the
outcome of periodontal therapy. A review of the literature</article-title><source>J Clin Periodontol</source><year>2001</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>499</fpage><lpage>507</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11350516</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quirynen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>De Soete</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pauwels</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gizani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Meerbeek</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>van Steenberghe</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Can toothpaste or a toothbrush with antibacterial tufts prevent
toothbrush contamination?</article-title><source>J Periodontol</source><year>2003</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>312</fpage><lpage>322</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12710750</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quirynen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>de Soete</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pauwels</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Goossens</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Teughels</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>van Eldere</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Bacterial survival rate on tooth- and interdental brushes in relation
to the use of toothpaste</article-title><source>J Clin Periodontol</source><year>2001</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>1106</fpage><lpage>1114</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11737507</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rohrer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Widmer</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Waltimo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kulik</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiger</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Filipuzzi-Jenny</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial efficacy of 3 oral antiseptics containing octenidine,
polyhexamethylene biguanide, or Citroxx: can chlorhexidine be
replaced?</article-title><source>Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol</source><year>2010</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>733</fpage><lpage>739</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20518635</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saravia</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson-Filho</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Faria</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>IY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Viability of Streptococcus mutans toothbrush bristles</article-title><source>J Dent Child (Chic)</source><year>2008</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>29</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18505645</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sbordone</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramaglia</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Gulletta</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Iacono</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recolonization of the subgingival microflora after scaling and root
planing in human periodontitis</article-title><source>J Periodontol</source><year>1990</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>579</fpage><lpage>584</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2213468</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaugg</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiger</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Brushing without brushing? - a review of the efficacy of powered
toothbrushes in noncontact biofilm removal</article-title><source>Clin Oral Investig</source><year>2013</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>687</fpage><lpage>709</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spolidorio</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Negrini</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>Spolidorio</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Viability of Streptococcus mutans on transparent and opaque
toothbrushes</article-title><source>J Dent Hyg</source><year>2003</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>114</fpage><lpage>117</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12861791</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Theilade</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The non-specific theory in microbial etiology of inflammatory
periodontal diseases</article-title><source>J Clin Periodontol</source><year>1986</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>905</fpage><lpage>911</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3540019</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wade</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The oral microbiome in health and disease</article-title><source>Pharmacol Res</source><year>2013</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>137</fpage><lpage>143</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23201354</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldschmidt</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Adler-Storthz</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Keene</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effects of toothpastes on the residual microbial contamination of
toothbrushes</article-title><source>J Am Dent Assoc</source><year>2001</year><volume>132</volume><fpage>1241</fpage><lpage>1245</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11665348</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wetzel</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaumburg</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ansari</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kroeger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sziegoleit</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microbial contamination of toothbrushes with different principles of
filament anchoring</article-title><source>J Am Dent Assoc</source><year>2005</year><volume>136</volume><fpage>758</fpage><lpage>765</lpage><comment>quiz 806</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16022040</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>