<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Cell Biol</journal-id><journal-title>The Journal of Cell Biology</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0021-9525</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1540-8140</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Rockefeller University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">9679140</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2133052</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Pex20p of the Yeast <italic>Yarrowia lipolytica</italic> Is Required for the Oligomerization of Thiolase in the Cytosol and for Its Targeting to the Peroxisome </article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Titorenko</surname><given-names>Vladimir I.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>Jennifer J.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Szilard</surname><given-names>Rachel K.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rachubinski</surname><given-names>Richard A.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="N0x2147b80N0x3e72758">Department of Cell Biology and Anatomy, University of Alberta, Edmonton, Alberta T6G 2H7, Canada</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>27</day><month>7</month><year>1998</year></pub-date><volume>142</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>403</fpage><lpage>420</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>8</day><month>4</month><year>1998</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>9</day><month>6</month><year>1998</year></date></history><copyright-year>1998</copyright-year><abstract><p><italic>Pex</italic> mutants are defective in peroxisome assembly. In the <italic>pex20-1</italic> mutant strain of the yeast <italic>Yarrowia lipolytica</italic>, the peroxisomal matrix protein thiolase is mislocalized exclusively to the cytosol, whereas  the import of other peroxisomal proteins is unaffected.  The <italic>PEX20</italic> gene was isolated by functional complementation of the <italic>pex20-1</italic> strain and encodes a protein,  Pex20p, of 424 amino acids (47,274 D). Despite its role  in the peroxisomal import of thiolase, which is targeted  by an amino-terminal peroxisomal targeting signal-2  (PTS2), Pex20p does not exhibit homology to Pex7p,  which acts as the PTS2 receptor. Pex20p is mostly cytosolic, whereas 4&#x02013;8% is associated with high-speed  (200,000 <italic>g</italic>) pelletable peroxisomes. In the wild-type  strain, all newly synthesized thiolase is associated with  Pex20p in a heterotetrameric complex composed of two  polypeptide chains of each protein. This association is  independent of PTS2. Pex20p is required for both the  oligomerization of thiolase in the cytosol and its targeting to the peroxisome. Our data suggest that monomeric Pex20p binds newly synthesized monomeric thiolase in the cytosol and promotes the formation of a  heterotetrameric complex of these two proteins, which  could further bind to the peroxisomal membrane.  Translocation of the thiolase homodimer into the peroxisomal matrix would release Pex20p monomers back  to the cytosol, thereby permitting a new cycle of binding-oligomerization-targeting-release for Pex20p and  thiolase.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>biogenesis</kwd><kwd>import</kwd><kwd>translocation</kwd><kwd>chaperone</kwd><kwd>cross-linking</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p>P<sc>roteins</sc> targeted to the ER, mitochondria, and chloroplasts are translocated across the organellar  membrane in an unfolded conformation, and folding and oligomerization of the proteins into active structures occurs within the organelle (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">McNew and Goodman,  1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">Schatz and Dobberstein, 1996</xref>). Maintenance of the  unfolded, import-competent conformation is served by cytosolic chaperones that guide newly synthesized proteins  from their site of synthesis at the ribosome to the target  membrane (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Hendrick and Hartl, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Bukau et al., 1996</xref>;  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Hartl, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">Schatz and Dobberstein, 1996</xref>). However, recent evidence has shown that protein unfolding and disassembly are not prerequisites for import into the peroxisome. Completely folded polypeptides, oligomeric proteins,  disulfide-bonded and chemically cross-linked proteins,  and even proteins conjugated to 9-nm gold particles can be  imported into the peroxisomal matrix (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Glover et al.,  1994</xref><italic>a</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">McNew and Goodman, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">Walton et al., 1995</xref>;  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Elgersma et al., 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">H&#x000e4;usler et al., 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Leiper et al., 1996</xref>;  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Lee et al., 1997</xref>). Whether the formation and maintenance  of the folded, oligomeric import-competent conformation  of peroxisomal proteins are assisted by a specialized set of  cytosolic chaperones, or whether they occur spontaneously, remains unclear. Moreover, although numerous examples of peroxisomal import of oligomeric proteins have  been reported (for reviews see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">Rachubinski and Subramani, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">McNew and Goodman, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">Subramani,  1998</xref>), this does not necessarily imply that all peroxisomal  multimeric proteins enter the organelle strictly as preassembled oligomeric complexes. For example, alcohol oxidase monomers are imported into the matrix before the  assembly of enzymatically active octamers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Bellion and  Goodman, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">Waterham et al., 1997</xref>), and alanine:glyoxylate aminotransferase 1 can be imported with equal efficiency as a dimer or monomer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Leiper et al., 1996</xref>).</p><p>Two well-characterized peroxisomal targeting signals  (PTS)<sup>1</sup> specify the sorting of matrix proteins to the organelle: a carboxyl-terminal tripeptide PTS1 and an  amino-terminal nonapeptide PTS2 (for reviews see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">Purdue and Lazarow, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">Rachubinski and Subramani,  1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">Subramani, 1998</xref>). Import receptors and docking  proteins for both PTS1- and PTS2-containing proteins  have been identified (for reviews see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">Rachubinski and  Subramani, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Erdmann et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">Kunau, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">Subramani, 1998</xref>). The subcellular location of PTS1 and PTS2  receptors is a matter of debate and has been reported to  be mainly cytosolic, partially peroxisomal, or even exclusively intraperoxisomal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">Rachubinski and Subramani,  1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Erdmann et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">Subramani, 1998</xref>). Accordingly, two models for PTS1 and PTS2 import receptor action have been proposed. One model proposes that peroxisomal import receptors are mobile, shuttling between the  cytosol and the peroxisome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">Marzioch et al., 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Dodt  and Gould, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Albertini et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Elgersma et al.,  1998</xref>), whereas the other proposes that the receptors act  from inside the peroxisome to pull proteins in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">Szilard et al.,  1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">Zhang and Lazarow, 1995</xref>). Whether the accessibility of folded and oligomeric peroxisomal proteins to import receptors and/or their docking proteins could be  served by specialized cytosolic proteins that stabilize the  folded and oligomeric import-competent conformation  and/or keep the PTS exposed for interaction with the import machineries is unknown. Here, we identify and characterize a cytosolic peroxin, Pex20p, of the yeast <italic>Yarrowia  lipolytica</italic> that is required for the oligomerization of PTS2-containing thiolase (THI) in the cytosol and for its targeting to the peroxisome.</p><sec id="MaterialsMethods" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Strains, Culture Conditions, and Microbial Techniques</title><p>The <italic>Y</italic>. <italic>lipolytica</italic> strains used in this study are listed in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="TI">I</xref>. The new  nomenclature for peroxisome assembly genes and proteins has been used  (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Distel et al., 1996</xref>). Media, growth conditions, and genetic techniques for  <italic>Y</italic>. <italic>lipolytica</italic> have been described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">Nuttley et al., 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">Szilard et al., 1995</xref>).  Media components were as follows: (<italic>a</italic>) YEPD, 1% yeast extract, 2% peptone, 2% glucose; (<italic>b</italic>) YPBO, 0.3% yeast extract, 0.5% peptone, 0.5%  K<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub>, 0.5% KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, 1% Brij 35, 1% (wt/vol) oleic acid; (<italic>c</italic>) YNAS,  0.67% yeast nitrogen base without amino acids, 0.1% yeast extract, 18.2%  sorbitol, 2% sodium acetate; (<italic>d</italic>) YND, 0.67% yeast nitrogen base without  amino acids, 2% glucose; and (<italic>e</italic>) YNO, 0.67% yeast nitrogen base without  amino acids, 0.05% (wt/vol) Tween 40, 0.1% (wt/vol) oleic acid. YNAS,  YND, and YNO media were supplemented with leucine, uracil, lysine,  and histidine, each at 50 &#x003bc;g/ml, as required. DNA manipulation and  growth of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> were performed as previously described  (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Ausubel et al., 1989</xref>). </p></sec><sec><title>Cloning, Sequencing, and Integrative Disruption of the  PEX20 Gene</title><p>The <italic>pex20-1</italic> mutant was initially isolated from randomly mutagenized <italic>Y</italic>.  <italic>lipolytica</italic> strain <italic>E122</italic> by screening for the inability to use oleic acid as a  sole carbon source (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">Nuttley et al., 1993</xref>). The <italic>PEX20</italic> gene was isolated by  functional complementation of the <italic>pex20-1</italic> strain using a <italic>Y</italic>. <italic>lipolytica</italic> genomic DNA library in the autonomously replicating <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic> shuttle vector  pINA445 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">Nuttley et al., 1993</xref>). Plasmid DNA was introduced into cells by  electroporation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">Nuttley et al., 1993</xref>). Leu<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> transformants recovered on  YNAS agar plates were replica plated onto selective YNO agar plates and  screened for restoration of their ability to use oleic acid as a sole carbon  source. Total DNA was isolated from colonies that recovered growth and  used to transform <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic> for plasmid recovery. Restriction fragments prepared from genomic inserts were subcloned and tested for their ability to  functionally complement the <italic>pex20-1</italic> strain. Various restriction endonuclease fragments of the <italic>PEX20</italic> gene were cloned into the vectors  pGEM5Zf (&#x0002b;) and pGEM7Zf (&#x0002b;) (<named-content content-type="company" xlink:href="promega">Promega Corp.</named-content>, Madison, WI) for  dideoxynucleotide sequencing of both strands. The deduced Pex20p  amino acid sequence was compared with other known protein sequences  using the GENEINFO (R) Blast Network Service (Blaster) of the National Center for Biotechnology Information (Bethesda, MD).</p><p>Targeted integrative disruption of the <italic>PEX20</italic> gene was performed with  the <italic>URA3</italic> gene of <italic>Y</italic>. <italic>lipolytica</italic>. A 1.65-kbp SalI fragment containing the  <italic>URA3</italic> gene was made blunt and ligated in reverse orientation into a plasmid containing the <italic>PEX20</italic> gene cut with NcoI and made blunt. In this  way, 1,092 bp of the coding region and 2 bp of the 5&#x02032; untranslated region  of the <italic>PEX20</italic> gene were replaced with the <italic>URA3</italic> gene flanked by 767 and  1,022 bp of the 5&#x02032; and 3&#x02032; regions, respectively, of the <italic>PEX20</italic> gene. This  construct was cleaved with HindIII/SphI to liberate the <italic>URA3</italic> gene  flanked by <italic>PEX20</italic> sequences. The resulting linear construct was used to  transform <italic>Y</italic>. <italic>lipolytica</italic> strains <italic>E122</italic> and <italic>22301-3</italic> to uracil prototrophy.  Ura<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> transformants that were unable to grow on YNO agar were further  characterized by Southern blotting. <italic>pex20::URA3</italic> integrants were mated  to each other, to wild-type strains, and to the <italic>pex20-1</italic> mutant strain, and  the resulting diploids were subjected to complementation and random  spore analyses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">Nuttley et al., 1993</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Immunofluorescence and Electron Microscopy</title><p>Double-labeling, indirect immunofluorescence microscopy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">Szilard et al.,  1995</xref>), and electron microscopy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Goodman et al., 1990</xref>) were performed as  described. For morphometric analysis of random electron microscopic  sections of cells, 12 &#x000d7; 14-cm prints and 8 &#x000d7; 10-cm negatives of 35&#x02013;40 cell  sections of each strain at 24,000&#x02013;29,000 magnification were scanned and  converted to digitized images with an Apple Color OneScanner (Apple  Computers Inc., Cupertino, CA) and Adobe Photoshop 3.0 software  (Adobe Systems Inc., San Jose, CA). Quantitation of digitized images was  performed using NIH Image 1.55 software (National Institutes of Health,  Bethesda, MD). Relative area of peroxisome section (%) was calculated  as &#x0201c;area of peroxisome section/area of cell section &#x000d7; 100&#x0201d;. Peroxisomes  were counted in electron micrographs, and data are expressed as the number of peroxisomes per &#x003bc;m<sup>3</sup> of cell section volume.</p></sec><sec><title>Organelle Fractionation and Isolation of Peroxisomes</title><p>The initial step in the subcellular fractionation of YPBO-grown cells was  performed as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">Szilard et al., 1995</xref>) and included the  differential centrifugation of lysed and homogenized spheroplasts at 1,000 <italic>g</italic>  for 8 min at 4&#x000b0;C in a rotor (model JS13.1; Beckman Instrs., Inc., Palo Alto,  CA) to yield a postnuclear supernatant (PNS) fraction. The PNS fraction  was further subjected to differential centrifugation at 20,000 <italic>g</italic> for 30 min  at 4&#x000b0;C in a rotor (model JS13.1; Beckman Instrs.) to yield pellet (20KgP)  and supernatant (20KgS) fractions. The 20KgS fraction was further subfractionated by differential centrifugation at 200,000 <italic>g</italic> for 1 h at 4&#x000b0;C in a  rotor (model TLA120.2; Beckman Instrs., Inc.) to yield pellet (200KgP)  and supernatant (200KgS) fractions. The 200 KgP was further fractionated  by flotation on a two-step sucrose gradient. Specifically, the 200 KgP was  resuspended in 400 &#x003bc;l of 60% (wt/wt) sucrose in buffer H (5 mM MES,  pH 5.5, 1 mM KCl, 0.5 mM EDTA, 0.1% [vol/vol] ethanol), overlaid with  2.3 ml of 50% (wt/wt) sucrose and 2.3 ml of 20% (wt/wt) sucrose (both in  buffer H), and subjected to centrifugation in a rotor (model SW50.1;  Beckman Instrs.) at 200,000 <italic>g</italic> for 18 h at 4&#x000b0;C. Gradients were fractionated  from the bottom, and 18 fractions of &#x0223c;270 &#x003bc;l each were collected. Protein  extraction and protease protection analysis of different subcellular fractions were performed as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">Szilard et al., 1995</xref>).</p><p>Highly purified peroxisomes were isolated essentially as described  (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">Titorenko et al., 1996</xref>). 4 vol of 0.5 M sucrose in buffer H were added to  the peak peroxisomal fraction 4 recovered after isopycnic centrifugation  on a discontinuous sucrose gradient. Peroxisomes were sedimented  through a 150-&#x003bc;l cushion of 2 M sucrose in buffer H by centrifugation at  200,000 <italic>g</italic> for 20 min at 4&#x000b0;C in a TLA120.2 rotor. The resultant pellet was  resuspended in buffer H containing 1 M sorbitol and was subjected to further centrifugation on a linear 20&#x02013;60% (wt/wt) sucrose gradient (in buffer  H) at 197,000 <italic>g</italic> for 18 h at 4&#x000b0;C in a rotor (model SW41Ti; Beckman Instrs.,  Inc.). Peak peroxisomal fraction 5 equilibrating at a density of 1.21 g/cm<sup>3</sup>  was recovered, and peroxisomes were pelleted at 200,000 <italic>g</italic> for 20 min at  4&#x000b0;C in a TLA120.2 rotor, as described above. Pelleted peroxisomes were  resuspended in 400 &#x003bc;l of 60% (wt/wt) sucrose in buffer H and subjected to  flotation on a two-step sucrose gradient as described above. Peak peroxisomal fraction 11 was recovered and used for biochemical analyses. Peroxisomes isolated by this multistep method were greater than 97% pure, as  judged by the presence of marker proteins of other organelles. </p></sec><sec><title>Radiolabeling, Subcellular Fractionation, Chemical  Cross-linking, and Immunoprecipitation</title><p>For pulse-chase experiments, YPBO-grown cells were pelleted at 10,000 <italic>g</italic>  for 8 min at room temperature, washed three times with water, incubated  in 50 mM potassium phosphate buffer, pH 7.5, containing 10 mM DTT for  10 min at 30&#x000b0;C, and repelleted at 10,000 <italic>g</italic> for 8 min at room temperature.   Cells were resuspended at a concentration of 0.25 g/ml in 25 mM potassium phosphate buffer, pH 7.5, containing 0.55 M MgSO<sub>4</sub>, and converted  to spheroplasts by digestion at 30&#x000b0;C with Zymolyase 100T (ICN Biochemicals, Inc., Mississauga, Ontario, Canada) at 1 mg/ml of cells.  Spheroplasts  were harvested at 10,000 <italic>g</italic> for 8 min at room temperature and resuspended at a concentration of 6 OD<sub>600</sub>/ml in YNO medium supplemented  with 1 M sucrose.  Spheroplasts were incubated for 90 min at 30&#x000b0;C, labeled  with <sc>l</sc>-[<sup>35</sup>S]methionine (ICN Biochemicals, Inc.) at 40 &#x003bc;Ci/OD<sub>600 </sub>for 1.5  min or 3 min at 30&#x000b0;C, and chased with an equal volume of 2&#x000d7; YPBO medium supplemented with 1 M sucrose and 10 mM unlabeled <sc>l</sc>-methionine.   Samples were taken at various times of chase, and spheroplasts were immediately pelleted in a rotor (model F241.5; Beckman Instrs., Inc.) at  20,000 <italic>g</italic> for 2 min at 4&#x000b0;C.  All subsequent steps were performed at 4&#x000b0;C,  and all solutions contained unlabeled <sc>l</sc>-methionine.  Spheroplasts were  resuspended in 150 &#x003bc;l of buffer H containing 1 M sorbitol and a mixture of  protease inhibitors, as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">Szilard et al., 1995</xref>).  In protease protection experiments, protease inhibitors were omitted.  Spheroplasts were osmotically lysed by addition of 300 &#x003bc;l of buffer H containing  0.1 M sorbitol and protease inhibitors.  Lysis was greater than 90%, as determined by microscopy and enzymatic assay of the cytosolic marker  G6PDH.  The original osmolarity was reestablished by addition of 300 &#x003bc;l  of buffer H containing 1.9 M sorbitol and protease inhibitors.  The lysate  was subjected to centrifugation at 1,000 <italic>g</italic> for 3 min at 4&#x000b0;C in a rotor  (model F241.5; Beckman Instrs., Inc.) to yield a PNS fraction.  The PNS  fraction was loaded onto a 150-&#x003bc;l cushion of 1.2 M sucrose in buffer H  containing protease inhibitors and subjected to centrifugation at 20,000 <italic>g</italic>  for 20 min at 4&#x000b0;C in a rotor (model TLA120.2; Beckman Instrs., Inc.) to  yield pellet (20KgP) and supernatant (20KgS) fractions.  The 20KgS fraction was further sedimented through a 150-&#x003bc;l cushion of 1.2 M sucrose in  buffer H containing protease inhibitors at 200,000 <italic>g</italic> for 20 min at 4&#x000b0;C in a  rotor (model TLA120.2; Beckman Instrs., Inc.) to yield pellet (200KgP)  and supernatant (200KgS) fractions.  Immunoprecipitation under native  conditions was performed by immunoaffinity chromatography with antibodies covalently coupled to protein A&#x02013;Sepharose (<named-content content-type="company" xlink:href="pharmacia">Pharmacia LKB Biotechnology</named-content>, Piscataway, NJ), as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">Szilard et al., 1995</xref>).   For immunoprecipitation under denaturing conditions, SDS was added to  2%, and samples were warmed at 65&#x000b0;C for 10 min.  Samples were allowed  to cool to room temperature, and 4 vol of 60 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.4, buffer  containing 1.25% (vol/vol) Triton X-100, 190 mM NaCl, and 6 mM EDTA  were added.  Samples were subsequently processed for immunoprecipitation, as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Franzusoff et al., 1991</xref>).</p><p>Chemical cross-linking of proteins was performed using dithiobis(succinimidylpropionate) (DSP) and disuccinimidyl suberate (DSS) (<named-content content-type="company" xlink:href="pierce">Pierce  Chemical Co.</named-content>, Rockford, IL), essentially as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">Sanders et al.,  1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">Marshall et al., 1996</xref>).  Highly purified peroxisomes or the 200 KgP  fraction were lysed in 20 mM sodium phosphate buffer, pH 7.5, containing  150 mM NaCl.  Lysates were clarified by centrifugation at 200,000 <italic>g</italic> for 20  min at 4&#x000b0;C in a rotor (model TLA120.2; Beckman Instrs., Inc.), and the resultant supernatants were used for chemical cross-linking.  Sodium phosphate buffer, pH 7.5, and NaCl were added to the supernatants to final  concentrations of 20 and 150 mM, respectively.  Cross-linking with DSP or  DSS was initiated by the addition of cross-linker (50 mM stock in DMSO)  and continued for 1 h at 4&#x000b0;C.  Cross-linking was quenched by addition of  0.1 vol of 1 M Tris-HCl, pH 7.5, and incubation for 30 min at 4&#x000b0;C.  SDS  was added to 1.25%, and samples were warmed at 65&#x000b0;C for 20 min and  then cooled to room temperature. 4 vol of 60 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.4, 1.25%  (vol/vol) Triton X-100, 190 mM NaCl, and 6 mM EDTA were added to  the cooled samples, which were then subjected to immunoprecipitation, as  described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Franzusoff et al., 1991</xref>).  All immunoprecipitated samples were  analyzed by SDS-PAGE under reducing or nonreducing conditions, i.e.,  with or without DTT in the sample buffer, respectively.  Gels were treated  with 22.2% 2,5-diphenyloxazole in either DMSO or glacial acetic acid  (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Coligan et al., 1995</xref>), dried, and then exposed to preflashed <named-content content-type="company" xlink:href="kodak">Kodak</named-content>  X-Omat AR X-ray film (<named-content content-type="company" xlink:href="kodak">Eastman-Kodak Co.</named-content>, Rochester, NY) at &#x02212;80&#x000b0;C  with intensifying screens.</p></sec><sec><title>Antibodies</title><p>Antibodies to Pex20p were raised in guinea pig and rabbit against a maltose-binding protein-Pex20p fusion, as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Eitzen et al.,  1995</xref>).  To produce antibodies to Pex20p, the entire open reading frame of  the <italic>PEX20</italic> gene was amplified by PCR and inserted into pMAL-c2 (New  England BioLabs, Beverly, MA) in-frame and downstream of the open  reading frame encoding the maltose-binding protein (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Eitzen et al., 1995</xref>).</p><p>Guinea pig polyclonal antibodies to <italic>Y</italic>. <italic>lipolytica</italic> isocitrate lyase (ICL),  thiolase (THI), Pex2p, Pex5p, and Pex16p and to <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> acyl-CoA oxidase (AOX); and rabbit polyclonal anti-SKL antibodies  have been described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">Szilard et al., 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Eitzen et al., 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">1997</xref>).  Rabbit  polyclonal antibodies to <italic>S</italic>. <italic>cerevisiae</italic> malate synthase (MLS) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Eitzen et al.,  1996</xref>) and to <italic>Y</italic>. <italic>lipolytica</italic> Sls1p (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Boisram&#x000e9; et al., 1996</xref>), Kar2p (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">Titorenko  et al., 1997</xref>) and Sec14p (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">Lopez et al., 1994</xref>) were described previously.   Anti-MLS antibodies were kindly provided by A. Hartig (Institute of Biochemistry and Molecular Cell Biology, Vienna, Austria).  Anti-Sls1p and  anti-Sec14p antibodies were generous gifts of C. Gaillardin (Institut National Agronomique Paris-Grignon, Thiveral-Grignon, France).  Rabbit  polyclonal antibody A-9521 specific for <italic>S</italic>. <italic>cerevisiae</italic> glucose-6-phosphate  dehydrogenase (G6PDH) was from <named-content content-type="company" xlink:href="sigma">Sigma Chemical Co.</named-content> (St. Louis, MO).</p></sec><sec><title>Other Methods</title><p>Whole cell lysates were prepared as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Goodman et al., 1990</xref>).   The progressive permeabilization of yeast membranes with digitonin was  performed as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B62">Zhang et al., 1993</xref>).  In vitro coupled transcription/translation of the <italic>PEX20</italic> gene was performed using the TNT T7  Quick-Coupled Transcription/Translation System (<named-content content-type="company" xlink:href="promega">Promega Corp.</named-content>).  Blot  overlay (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">Radu et al., 1995</xref>), including the denaturation/renaturation of  transferred proteins by treatment with guanidinium chloride, followed by  multistep dilution with water (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Dingwall et al., 1995</xref>) and elution of bound  proteins with urea (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">Radu et al., 1995</xref>), were performed according to established procedures.  Enzymatic activities of catalase and cytochrome <italic>c</italic> oxidase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">Szilard et al., 1995</xref>); NADPH:cytochrome <italic>c</italic> reductase, &#x003b1;-mannosidase, and vanadate-sensitive plasma membrane ATPase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">Roberts et al.,  1991</xref>); guanosine diphosphatase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Abeijon et al., 1989</xref>); fumarase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">Smith  et al., 1997</xref>); and alkaline phosphatase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">Thieringer et al., 1991</xref>); and thiolase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Glover et al., 1994<italic>b</italic></xref>) were determined by established methods.  Inorganic phosphate liberated in assays of the activities of guanosine diphosphatase and vanadate-sensitive plasma membrane ATPase was measured  as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">Lanzetta et al., 1979</xref>).  Southern blot analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Ausubel et al.,  1989</xref>), SDS-PAGE (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">Laemmli, 1970</xref>), and immunoblotting using a semi-dry electrophoretic transfer system (model ET-20; Tyler Research Instruments, Edmonton, Alberta, Canada) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">Kyhse-Andersen, 1984</xref>) were performed as described.  Antigen&#x02013;antibody complexes were detected by enhanced chemiluminescence (<named-content content-type="company" xlink:href="amersham">Amersham Life Sciences</named-content>, Oakville, Ontario,  Canada).  Quantitation of immunoblots was performed as described  (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">Szilard et al., 1995</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Isolation and Characterization of the PEX20 Gene</title><p>We have previously reported the isolation of <italic>Y</italic>. <italic>lipolytica</italic>  mutants that are unable to use oleic acid as a sole carbon  source (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">Nuttley et al., 1993</xref>).  This collection of ole<sup>&#x02212;</sup> mutants was screened by indirect immunofluorescence using  antibodies to PTS1, to the peroxisomal matrix protein  THI, which is targeted by PTS2, and to the peroxisomal  membrane protein Pex2p.  One mutant strain, <italic>pex20-1</italic>, exhibited a punctate pattern characteristic of peroxisomes  when stained with either anti-PTS1 or anti-Pex2p antibodies (see below).  However, unlike wild-type cells, a diffuse  pattern of staining was seen with anti-THI antibodies, indicating that the <italic>pex20-1</italic> mutant strain is impaired in the  import of THI into peroxisomes.</p><p>The <italic>PEX20</italic> gene was isolated by functional complementation of the <italic>pex20-1</italic> strain.  Of the 2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>4</sup> Leu<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>  transformants screened, five strains were found to have restored growth on oleic acid.  The complementing plasmids  were recovered after transformation of <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic>.  Restriction map analysis showed that all five complementing plasmids shared a 5.8-kbp region. Restriction fragments from  this region were subcloned and tested for their ability to  functionally complement the <italic>pex20-1</italic> strain.  The minimum complementing fragment was localized to a 2.9-kbp HindIII/BamHI restriction fragment.  Sequencing this  fragment revealed a 1,272-bp open reading frame encoding a 424-amino acid protein, Pex20p, with a predicted molecular weight of 47,274 (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>).  Pex20p shows 16.3 to  28.1% identity to Pex5p peroxins of yeast and mammals,  including <italic>Y</italic>. <italic>lipolytica</italic> Pex5p, but does not contain tetratricopeptide repeat motifs.  Pex5p peroxins function as PTS1  import receptors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Erdmann et al., 1997</xref>).  However, Pex20p  is not required for the import of PTS1 proteins (see below).  Despite its role in the peroxisomal import of PTS2-containing THI, Pex20p does not exhibit homology to yeast or human Pex7p peroxins, which act as import receptors for  PTS2-containing proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Erdmann et al., 1997</xref>). </p><p>The putative <italic>PEX20</italic> gene was disrupted by targeted integration of the <italic>Y</italic>. <italic>lipolytica URA3</italic> gene to create the  strains <italic>pex20KO-1A</italic> and <italic>pex20KO-2B</italic> in the <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic> mating types, respectively (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="TI">I</xref>). Strains containing a disrupted <italic>PEX20</italic> gene were unable to grow on oleic acid and  had the morphological and biochemical characteristics of  the original <italic>pex20-1</italic> strain (see below). The diploid strain  <italic>D1-20</italic> from the mating of wild-type strain <italic>E122</italic> to strain  <italic>pex20KO-2B</italic>, and the diploid strains <italic>D2-20</italic> and <italic>D3-20</italic>  from the mating of strains <italic>pex20KO-1A</italic> and <italic>pex20-1</italic>, respectively, to wild-type strain <italic>22301-3</italic> (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="TI">I</xref>), could  grow on oleic acid-containing medium, demonstrating  the recessive nature of the <italic>pex20-1</italic>, <italic>pex20KO-1A,</italic> and  <italic>pex20KO-2B</italic> mutations. The diploid strain <italic>D4-20</italic> from the  mating of the original <italic>pex20-1</italic> mutant strain to strain  <italic>pex20KO-2B</italic>, and the diploid strain <italic>D5-20</italic> from the mating of the <italic>pex20KO-1A</italic> strain to strain <italic>pex20KO-2B</italic> (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="TI">I</xref>), were unable to grow on oleic acid-containing medium. Random spore analysis of the diploid strains <italic>D1-20</italic>  and <italic>D2-20</italic> showed monogenic segregation for both Ura<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>  and ole<sup>&#x02212;</sup> phenotypes, whereas the <italic>URA3</italic> gene invariably  cosegregated with the ole<sup>&#x02212;</sup> phenotype. Random spore  analysis of the diploid strain <italic>D4-20</italic> and of the diploid  strain <italic>D5-20</italic> revealed no meiotic segregants with a recombinant ole<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> phenotype. Taken together, these data indicate that the authentic <italic>PEX20</italic> gene had been cloned.</p></sec><sec><title>Subcellular Localization and Intracellular Trafficking  of Pex20p</title><p>Antibodies to Pex20p specifically recognized an &#x0223c;60-kD  polypeptide in whole cell lysates prepared from the wild-type strain, but not from the <italic>pex20-1</italic> or <italic>pex20KO</italic> mutant  strains (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> <italic>A</italic>). The difference between the predicted  molecular weight of Pex20p (47,274 D) and its empirical  molecular weight (&#x0223c;60,000 D), as determined from SDS-PAGE, is an intrinsic feature of this protein. Indeed, in  vitro coupled transcription/translation of the <italic>PEX20</italic> gene  yielded a polypeptide that comigrated identically with in  vivo synthesized Pex20p on SDS-PAGE (data not shown).  Why Pex20p shows reduced electrophoretic mobility on  SDS-PAGE is unknown, but may be due to the large number of acidic amino acids (14.4%) present in Pex20p. </p><p>Synthesis of Pex20p is induced by growth of <italic>Y</italic>. <italic>lipolytica</italic>  on oleic acid (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> <italic>B</italic>). A small amount of Pex20p was  present in wild-type cells grown in glucose-containing medium. Shifting cells to oleic acid-containing medium  caused an increase in the level of Pex20p, which reached  levels &#x0223c;24 times that found in glucose-grown cells 8 h after  the shift (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> <italic>B</italic>).</p><p>In wild-type cells, most (98 &#x000b1; 8%) of Pex20p localized  to the cytosol, whereas 6 &#x000b1; 2% associated with a high-speed (200,000 <italic>g</italic>) pelletable organellar fraction (200KgP)  (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> <italic>C</italic>) enriched for high-speed pelletable (HSP) peroxisomes (see below). Cytosolic G6PDH was not detected in  the 200KgP isolated under these fractionation conditions  (data not shown). No Pex20p was detected in a low-speed  (20,000 <italic>g</italic>) organellar fraction (20KgP) (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> <italic>C</italic>) enriched  for low-speed pelletable (LSP) peroxisomes (see below).  The predominantly cytosolic location of Pex20p was confirmed by two additional approaches. Spheroplasts of oleic  acid-grown wild-type cells were permeabilized by incubation with increasing amounts of digitonin, and the subsequent leakage of Pex20p and marker proteins from the  cells was quantitated. Pex20p was released at low concentrations of digitonin, as was the cytosolic marker G6PDH.  50% release of both Pex20p and G6PDH was observed at  21 &#x003bc;g digitonin/ml (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> <italic>D</italic>). The peroxisomal matrix proteins CAT and THI, and the mitochondrial matrix protein  fumarase (<italic>FUM</italic>), were released at much higher concentrations of digitonin (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> <italic>D</italic>). Double-labeling, indirect immunofluorescence analysis of wild-type cells grown in  oleic acid-containing medium with anti-THI antibodies  yielded a punctate pattern of staining characteristic of peroxisomes (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> <italic>E</italic>). In contrast, a diffuse pattern of staining was observed with anti-Pex20p antibodies (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> <italic>E</italic>),  indicating that most Pex20p is localized to the cytosol in  wild-type cells.</p><p>Pex20p localized to the 200KgP is present in membrane-associated form and is not due to aggregation. Flotation of  the 200KgP from wild-type cells on a two-step sucrose gradient revealed that Pex20p, similar to the matrix proteins  AOX and THI, floated out of the most dense sucrose and  concentrated at the interface between 50 and 20% sucrose  (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> <italic>F</italic>). The distribution of Pex20p around peak fraction  11 coincided with the distributions of AOX and THI (Fig.  <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> <italic>F</italic>), suggesting that Pex20p is localized to HSP peroxisomes. Further fractionation of the 200KgP on additional  gradients showed that Pex20p cofractionated with the peroxisomal proteins AOX, THI, MLS, Pex2p, and Pex16p,  but not with markers of the ER, Golgi, vacuole, or plasma  membrane (data not shown). Together, these data indicate  that Pex20p is localized to HSP peroxisomes and is not associated with any other organelle. Extraction of the  200KgP-associated form of Pex20p with various solubilizing agents showed that Pex20p fractionated as a peripheral  membrane protein that was solubilized to a significant  extent by either 1 M NaCl or 1 M urea or completely by  0.1 M Na<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub>, pH 11 (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> <italic>G</italic>). Protease protection experiments revealed that the 200KgP-associated form of  Pex20p was sensitive to trypsin digestion even in the absence of Triton X-100, whereas the peroxisomal matrix  protein THI was degraded by trypsin only when the membranes of the 200KgP-associated organelles were disrupted by the detergent (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> <italic>H</italic>). Taken together, these  data indicate that in wild-type cells, the 200KgP-associated  form of Pex20p is a peripheral membrane protein associated with the cytosolic surface of HSP peroxisomes.</p><p>Intracellular trafficking of Pex20p was studied by immunoprecipitation of pulse-labeled and chased Pex20p from  the 20KgP, 200KgP, and 200KgS (cytosolic) fractions of  oleic acid-grown wild-type cells. At 0 min of chase, all  Pex20p was found in the cytosol (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref> <italic>A</italic>). By 3 min of  chase, a minor portion of Pex20p (10% of the total pool)  was chased to the 200KgP enriched for HSP peroxisomes.  By 10 min of chase, the 200KgP-associated Pex20p reached  its maximal level of 26% of the total pool of pulse-labeled  Pex20p (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref> <italic>A</italic>). After 10 min of chase, the level of  200KgP-associated Pex20p gradually decreased and, by 90  min of chase, reached 55% of its maximal level (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref> <italic>A</italic>).  No Pex20p was chased to the 20KgP (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref> <italic>A</italic>), enriched  for LSP peroxisomes. All pulse-labeled Pex20p chased to  the 200KgP was sensitive to trypsin digestion even in the  absence of Triton X-100 (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref> <italic>B</italic>) and, therefore, was associated with the cytosolic surface of HSP peroxisomes  present in the 200KgP. These data suggest that a minor  fraction (not more than 26%) of newly synthesized Pex20p  is targeted from the cytosol to the outer surface of HSP  peroxisomes with a half-time of 4 min. These results are  consistent with a model in which Pex20p shuttles between  the cytosol and the cytosolic surface of HSP peroxisomes;  however, we cannot rule out the possibility that the decrease in the levels of pulse-labeled Pex20p in the 200KgP  over time is due to its turnover in this fraction. </p></sec><sec><title>Ultrastructure of the Wild-Type and pex20 Mutant Strains</title><p>We assessed the effects of mutations in the <italic>PEX20</italic> gene  on the size and number of peroxisomes in oleic acid-grown  cells. EM and morphometric analysis showed that in wild-type cells, 36.2 &#x000b1; 0.8% of all peroxisomes had relative areas of peroxisome section from 1.01&#x02013;1.5%, whereas very  small peroxisomes with relative areas of peroxisome section from 0.05 to 0.2% were much less abundant (5.3 &#x000b1;  0.2% of all peroxisomes) (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>).  Neither the <italic>pex20-1</italic> nor  the <italic>pex20KO</italic> mutant showed a significant decrease in the  percentage of peroxisomes with relative areas of peroxisome section from 0.21 to 3.0%, but both mutants showed  3.5- to 4.9-fold increases in the percentage of very small  peroxisomes with relative areas of peroxisome section  from 0.05 to 0.2% (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>).  This increased percentage in  small peroxisomes in mutant cells was due to a large increase in their number per cell rather than to a reduction  in the number of large peroxisomes. Indeed, mutations in  the <italic>PEX20</italic> gene did not significantly decrease the number  of peroxisomes with relative areas of peroxisome section  greater than 0.2% (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). Rather, the <italic>pex20-1</italic> and  <italic>pex20KO</italic> mutations led to 3.5- to 4.5-fold increases in the  number of very small peroxisomes with relative areas of  peroxisome section less than 0.2% (7.6 &#x000b1; 0.8 and 9.9 &#x000b1; 1.0  peroxisomes per &#x003bc;m<sup>3</sup> of cell section volume, respectively)  vis-&#x000e0;-vis their number in wild-type cells (2.2 &#x000b1; 0.3 peroxisomes per &#x003bc;m<sup>3</sup> of cell section volume). Biochemical results  demonstrating the selective enrichment of MLS, CAT,  Pex2p, and Pex16p in HSP peroxisomes in <italic>pex20-1</italic> and  <italic>pex20KO</italic> cells (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>), combined with immunofluorescence data showing an accumulation of punctate structures decorated by anti-MLS or anti-Pex2p antibodies but  not anti-SKL antibodies in these cells (see Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref> <italic>A</italic>),  strengthened the interpretation of EM data showing a  large increase in the number of small peroxisomes in the  <italic>pex20-1</italic> and <italic>pex20KO</italic> mutants.   </p></sec><sec><title>Mutations in the PEX20 Gene Selectively Affect the  Import of Thiolase into Peroxisomes</title><p>Subcellular fractionation of wild-type cells grown in oleic  acid-containing medium showed that from 82 to 92% of  peroxisomal matrix (AOX, 62- and 64-kD anti-SKL reactive proteins, ICL, CAT, MLS, and THI) and membrane  (Pex2p and Pex16p) proteins was associated with a LSP  organellar fraction (20KgP), whereas from 10 to 23% was  localized to a HSP fraction (200KgP) (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>). Matrix proteins and the intraperoxisomal peripheral membrane protein Pex16p localized to the 20KgP and 200KgP of wild-type cells were resistant to exogenously added protease  (trypsin) in the absence of Triton X-100 and were therefore in membrane-enclosed structures (data not shown).  In contrast, in <italic>pex20-1</italic> and <italic>pex20KO</italic> cells, THI was found  exclusively in the 200KgS (cytosolic) fraction (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>) and  was accessible to external protease (data not shown). No  other peroxisomal matrix or membrane protein was mislocalized to the cytosol in <italic>pex20</italic> mutants (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>). However,  mutations in the <italic>PEX20</italic> gene altered the relative distributions of CAT, MLS, Pex2p, and Pex16p between the 20KgP  and 200KgP fractions. In wild-type cells, 82&#x02013;87% of these  four proteins was found in the 20KgP, whereas 8&#x02013;21% was  associated with 200KgP (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>). In <italic>pex20-1</italic> and <italic>pex20KO</italic>  cells, 44&#x02013;74% of CAT, MLS, Pex2p, and Pex16p was localized to the 200KgP, whereas 30&#x02013;45% was found in the  20KgP (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>). Neither the <italic>pex20-1</italic> nor the <italic>pex20KO</italic> mutation altered the relative distributions of AOX, 62-kD  SKL, 64-kD SKL and ICL between the 20KgP and  200KgP fractions (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>).</p><p>Pulse-chase labeling and immunoprecipitation of proteins from the 20KgP, 200KgP, and 200KgS (cytosolic)  fractions showed that in wild-type cells, peroxisomal matrix proteins moved from the cytosol to the 200KgP fraction and from there to the 20KgP fraction (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref> <italic>A</italic>, data  for AOX, MLS and THI; data for 62-kD SKL, 64 kD-SKL,  and ICL not shown). Furthermore, in wild-type cells, the  peroxisomal membrane proteins Pex2p and Pex16p were  initially targeted to the 20KgP, presumably to a subpopulation of ER-derived membranes that accumulates in this  fraction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">Titorenko and Rachubinski, 1998</xref>), and were subsequently chased to the 200KgP and from there to the  20KgP (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref> <italic>A</italic>, data for Pex2p; data for Pex16p not  shown). Mutations in the <italic>PEX20</italic> gene selectively abolished the targeting of THI from the cytosol to the 200KgP  (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref> <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic>, compare data for THI). All THI accumulating in the cytosol of the <italic>pex20-1</italic> and <italic>pex20KO</italic> mutant  strains was present as the 47-kD precursor form (data not  shown). In wild-type cells, maturation of the THI precursor to the 45-kD mature form occurred in the 200KgP (Fig.  <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref> <italic>C</italic>). </p><p>In contrast to the targeting defect for THI, the rates and  efficiencies of targeting from cytosol to the 200KgP of  other peroxisomal matrix and membrane proteins were  unaffected in <italic>pex20</italic> mutant strains (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref> <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B,</italic> compare half-times for the targeting of AOX, MLS, and Pex2p  from the 200KgS to the 200KgP; data for 62-kD SKL, 64-kD  SKL, and ICL not shown). The <italic>pex20-1</italic> and <italic>pex20KO</italic> mutations also did not affect the rates and efficiencies of transit of AOX, 62-kD SKL, 64-kD SKL and ICL from the  200KgP to the 20KgP (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref> <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic>, compare data for  AOX; data for 62-kD SKL, 64-kD SKL, and ICL not  shown). However, mutations in the <italic>PEX20</italic> gene significantly decreased the rates and efficiencies of transit of  MLS, Pex2p, and Pex16p from the 200KgP to the 20KgP  (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>, <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic>, compare data for MLS and Pex2p; data  for Pex16p not shown).</p><p>The accumulation of thiolase in the cytosol and the differential transit of two subsets of peroxisomal proteins  from the 200KgP to the 20KgP in <italic>pex20-1</italic> and <italic>pex20KO</italic>  mutants should lead to the accumulation in these mutants  of LSP peroxisomes that completely lack THI, are partially depleted of MLS, Pex2p, and Pex16p, but contain  wild-type amounts of AOX, 62-kD SKL, and 64-kD SKL  and ICL.  To test this prediction, the 20KgP fractions from  oleic-acid grown wild-type, <italic>pex20-1,</italic> and <italic>pex20KO</italic> cells  were separated by isopycnic centrifugation on a discontinuous sucrose gradient (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>). In the wild-type strain, all  peroxisomal proteins were primarily in fractions 1&#x02013;7,  peaking in fraction 4 at a density of 1.21 g/cm<sup>3</sup> (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>, <italic>left  panel</italic>). In the <italic>pex20-1</italic> and <italic>pex20KO</italic> mutants, all peroxisomal proteins, except THI, also peaked in fraction 4 at the  same density (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>, <italic>middle</italic> and <italic>right panels</italic>, respectively).  No THI was recovered in gradient fractions isolated from  <italic>pex20-1</italic> and <italic>pex20KO</italic> cells (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>, <italic>middle</italic> and <italic>right panels</italic>). Therefore, LSP peroxisomes accumulating in <italic>pex20</italic>  mutants have the same buoyant density as LSP peroxisomes present in wild-type cells, but they lack THI. AOX,  62-kD SKL, and 64-kD SKL, and ICL were present in LSP  peroxisomes of the <italic>pex20-1</italic> and <italic>pex20KO</italic> strains at levels  comparable to those found in LSP peroxisomes of the  wild-type strain. On the other hand, the levels of MLS,  CAT, Pex2p, and Pex16p in LSP peroxisomes of the  <italic>pex20-1</italic> and <italic>pex20KO</italic> strains were 37&#x02013;57% of their levels  in LSP peroxisomes of the wild-type strain. Again, no THI  was found in LSP peroxisomes of the <italic>pex20</italic> mutant strains. </p><p>In immunofluorescence analysis, oleic acid-grown wild-type cells showed a punctate pattern of staining characteristic of peroxisomes with anti-THI antibodies, whereas the  <italic>pex20-1</italic> and <italic>pex20KO</italic> strains showed a diffuse pattern of  staining characteristic of the cytosol (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref> <italic>A</italic>, <italic>leftmost  panels</italic>). Anti-MLS and anti-SKL antibodies (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref> <italic>A</italic>,  <italic>middle panels</italic>), or anti-Pex2p and anti-SKL antibodies  (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref> <italic>A</italic>, <italic>rightmost panels</italic>), revealed a punctate pattern of  staining in wild-type, <italic>pex20-1,</italic> and <italic>pex20KO</italic> cells. These  data support the conclusion that mutations in the <italic>PEX20</italic>  gene abolish THI import into peroxisomes but not the import of other peroxisomal matrix and membrane proteins.  It is interesting to note that most cells of the <italic>pex20-1</italic> and  <italic>pex20KO</italic> strains contained up to 20% of peroxisomes that  were decorated by anti-MLS or anti-Pex2p antibodies, but  not by anti-SKL antibodies (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref> <italic>B</italic>, <italic>arrows</italic>). Similarly  decorated punctate structures were rarely observed in  wild-type cells. Anti-MLS and anti-Pex2p antibodies always colocalized in punctate structures in wild-type,  <italic>pex20-1,</italic> and <italic>pex20KO</italic> cells (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref> <italic>B</italic>, <italic>rightmost panels</italic>,  data for <italic>pex20KO</italic> cells; data for wild-type and <italic>pex20-1</italic>  cells is not shown). Therefore, wild-type cells apparently  accumulate a few peroxisomes containing both MLS and  Pex2p but not anti-SKL&#x02013;reactive proteins, and mutations  in the <italic>PEX20</italic> gene significantly increase the number of  this type of peroxisome. These data, combined with EM  results presented above showing a large increase in very  small peroxisomes in <italic>pex20</italic> cells versus wild-type cells; the  selective enrichment in the 200KgP of MLS, CAT, Pex2p,  and Pex16p; and the decreased rate and efficiency of transit of MLS, Pex2p, and Pex16p from the 200KgP to the  20KgP, suggest that mutations in the <italic>PEX20</italic> gene lead to a  large increase in very small peroxisomes that are enriched  for MLS, CAT, Pex2p, and Pex16p. The role that Pex20p  might play in the accumulation of very small HSP peroxisomes enriched for these proteins is currently under investigation.</p></sec><sec><title>Association of Pex20p with Newly Synthesized Thiolase in the Cytosol Is Not Dependent on the PTS2 of Thiolase</title><p>Our data showing that (<italic>a</italic>) most Pex20p is localized to the  cytosol, (<italic>b</italic>) Pex20p apparently shuttles between the cytosol and the cytosolic surface of HSP peroxisomes, and (<italic>c</italic>)  Pex20p is essential for the import of THI from the cytosol  into HSP peroxisomes, led to a prediction that Pex20p and  THI form a complex in the cytosol. To test this prediction,  pulse-labeled Pex20p and THI were immunoprecipitated  from the 200KgS (cytosolic) fraction of the wild-type  strain under native conditions. Both anti-Pex20p and anti-THI antibodies immunoprecipitated two radiolabeled proteins with molecular weights of 59.8 and 47.0 kD, which  could be decorated with anti-Pex20p and anti-THI antibodies, respectively (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9</xref> <italic>A</italic>, <italic>panels 1</italic> and <italic>6</italic>). Therefore,  Pex20p and THI form a complex in the cytosol of wild-type cells. Proteins that did not bind to protein A&#x02013;Sepharose and were recovered in the flow-through following  native (first) immunoprecipitation with anti-Pex20p or  anti-THI antibodies were subjected to a second immunoprecipitation under denaturing conditions with anti-Pex20p or anti-THI antibodies. Neither Pex20p nor THI  was recovered in the flow-through when the native immunoprecipitation had been performed with anti-Pex20p antibodies (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9</xref> <italic>A</italic>, <italic>panels 2</italic> and <italic>3</italic>, respectively). Therefore,  all newly synthesized THI was associated with Pex20p in  the cytosol of wild-type cells. On the other hand, a significant portion of Pex20p, but no THI, was recovered in the  flow-through when the native immunoprecipitation had  been performed with anti-THI antibodies (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9</xref> <italic>A</italic>, <italic>panels  7</italic> and <italic>8</italic>, respectively). Therefore, in the cytosol of wild-type cells, Pex20p is present in two forms, namely associated or unassociated with newly synthesized THI. Newly  synthesized 62-kD SKL, 64-kD SKL, and MLS were not  associated with either Pex20p or THI in the cytosol of  wild-type cells, since none of these proteins was coimmunoprecipitated by anti-Pex20p (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9</xref> <italic>A</italic>, <italic>panels 1</italic>, <italic>4</italic>, and <italic>5</italic>)  or anti-THI (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9</xref> <italic>A</italic>, <italic>panels 6</italic>, <italic>9</italic>, and <italic>10</italic>) antibodies under  native conditions. Native immunoprecipitation using anti-SKL antibodies did not lead to coimmunoprecipitation of  Pex20p, THI, or MLS with 62-kD SKL and 64-kD SKL  proteins (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9</xref> <italic>A</italic>, <italic>panels 11&#x02013;15</italic>). </p><p>We tested whether the cleaved PTS2 of THI is essential  for Pex20p binding. Only the precursor form of THI  (pTHI) accumulates in peroxisomes of the <italic>pex5KO</italic> mutant deficient in the PTS1 import receptor (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9</xref> <italic>B</italic>)  (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">Szilard et al., 1995</xref>), whereas wild-type peroxisomes contain only the mature (mTHI) form of THI lacking its PTS2  (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9</xref> <italic>B</italic>). Radiolabeled pTHI and mTHI forms were purified from peroxisomes of <italic>pex5KO</italic> and wild-type cells, respectively, and used as probes in a blot overlay assay with  unlabeled proteins of either the cytosol of wild-type cells  containing Pex20p (refer to Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> <italic>A</italic>) or the cytosols of  <italic>pex20-1</italic> and <italic>pex20KO</italic> cells lacking Pex20p (refer to Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>  <italic>A</italic>). Both pTHI and mTHI bound with equal efficiency to a  59.8-kD protein present in the cytosol of wild-type cells  but absent in the cytosols of <italic>pex20-1</italic> or <italic>pex20KO</italic> cells  (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9</xref> <italic>C</italic>). Neither pTHI nor mTHI interacted with any  protein when the wild-type cytosol was depleted of Pex20p  by native immunoprecipitation with anti-Pex20p antibodies (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9</xref> <italic>C</italic>). Stripping of the proteins bound to the wild-type cytosol confirmed the binding of pTHI and mTHI  (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9</xref> <italic>D</italic>). These data indicate that the association of Pex20p  with newly synthesized THI in the cytosol of wild-type  cells is not dependent on the presence of a PTS2 in THI.</p></sec><sec><title>Peroxisomal Pex20p and Thiolase Do Not Form a Complex</title><p>We tested whether THI remains associated with Pex20p  after targeting of their complex from the cytosol to HSP  peroxisomes. Proteins pulse labeled and chased for 5 min  were immunoprecipitated from the 200KgP fraction of the  wild-type strain under native conditions with anti-Pex20p  or anti-THI antibodies. Proteins that did not bind to protein A&#x02013;Sepharose and were recovered in the flow-through  were subjected to a second immunoprecipitation under  denaturing conditions with anti-Pex20p or anti-THI antibodies. No coimmunoprecipitation of Pex20p and THI  was seen with either anti-Pex20p or anti-THI antibodies  (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10</xref>, <italic>panels 1&#x02013;3</italic> and <italic>6&#x02013;8</italic>). Therefore, Pex20p and THI  associated with HSP peroxisomes do not form a complex  with each other. This finding is in agreement with the results of protease protection experiments showing that  Pex20p associated with the 200KgP is a peripheral membrane protein bound to the cytosolic surface of HSP peroxisomes, whereas THI is located exclusively in the matrix  of HSP peroxisomes (refer to Figs. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> <italic>H</italic> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref> <italic>B</italic>). 62-kD  SKL, 64-kD SKL, and MLS associated with HSP peroxisomes also did not coimmunoprecipitate with either  Pex20p or THI (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10</xref>, <italic>panels 1</italic>, <italic>4&#x02013;6</italic>, <italic>9</italic>, and <italic>10</italic>). Therefore, none of the matrix proteins tested associated with  each other or with Pex20p in HSP peroxisomes. </p></sec><sec><title>pex20 Mutations Affect Thiolase Oligomerization in the  Cytosol and Prevent the Formation of a  Heterotetrameric Complex between Thiolase and Pex20p</title><p>As shown above, all newly synthesized THI is associated  with Pex20p in the cytosol of wild-type cells. We studied  the oligomeric state of THI and of the complex formed between THI and Pex20p in wild-type cytosol by chemical  cross-linking. The 200KgS (cytosolic) fraction of oleic acid-grown wild-type cells pulse-labeled with <sc>l</sc>-[<sup>35</sup>S]methionine  was subjected to increasing concentrations of the noncleavable, amine-reactive, homobifunctional cross-linker  DSS. Proteins were immunoprecipitated under denaturing  conditions with anti-THI antibodies, and proteins that did  not bind to protein A&#x02013;Sepharose and were recovered in  the flow-through were subjected to a second immunoprecipitation under denaturing conditions with anti-Pex20p  antibodies. SDS-PAGE analysis of cross-linked radiolabeled proteins immunoprecipitated with anti-THI antibodies revealed a 217-kD complex whose amount increased with increasing DSS, and a 47-kD (monomeric)  form of THI that concomitantly decreased and eventually  disappeared (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">11</xref> <italic>A</italic>). Immunoprecipitation of Pex20p  from the flow-through of the first immunoprecipitation  with anti-THI antibodies showed that as the concentration  of DSS increased, the level of unbound Pex20p decreased  (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">11</xref> <italic>B</italic>). Immunoprecipitation of cytosolic proteins  with anti-Pex20p antibodies revealed that as the DSS concentration increased, a prominent 217-kD complex appeared and increased (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">12</xref> <italic>B</italic>). The electrophoretic mobility of this complex was identical to that of the 217-kD  complex immunoprecipitated with anti-THI antibodies  when samples were separated on the same gel (data not  shown). Immunoprecipitation of THI from the protein  A&#x02013;Sepharose flow-through after immunoprecipitation with  anti-Pex20p antibodies showed that as the DSS concentration increased, unbound, monomeric THI decreased and  eventually disappeared (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">11</xref> <italic>D).</italic> Taken together, these  data indicate that in wild-type cytosol, all newly synthesized THI and a significant portion of Pex20p are components of a 217-kD complex. The fact that only THI and  Pex20p can be coimmunoprecipitated under native conditions with either anti-THI or anti-Pex20p antibodies (refer  to Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9</xref> <italic>A</italic>) suggests that they are the only protein components of the 217-kD complex. That this was the case was  confirmed by experiments using the thiol-cleavable,  homobifunctional cross-linker DSP. Treatment of cytosolic proteins with increasing concentrations of DSP, followed by immunoprecipitation with anti-THI antibodies  and evaluation of radiolabeled proteins by nonreducing  SDS-PAGE and fluorography, showed that even at low  concentrations of DSP, a 217-kD complex appeared,  whereas there was concomitant disappearance of 47-kD  monomeric THI (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">11</xref> <italic>E</italic>, <italic>left</italic>). When DSP was cleaved  with DTT, and the immunoprecipitated proteins were resolved by SDS-PAGE under reducing conditions, only two  proteins of 59.8 and 47.0 kD were detected in the samples  treated with DSP (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">11</xref> <italic>E</italic>, <italic>right</italic>). To quantitate the  stoichiometry of Pex20p and THI in the 217-kD complex,  the densities of the signals for Pex20p and THI in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">11</xref>  <italic>E</italic>, <italic>right</italic>, <italic>lane 1</italic>.<italic>0</italic> were divided by 17 and 8, respectively, the  number of methionine residues in Pex20p and THI, respectively. The ratio obtained was 1.1 &#x000b1; 0.1 (data from  four independent experiments), indicating that Pex20p  and THI are present in equimolar amounts in the complex.  Based on this observation and on a consideration of the  molecular weights of Pex20p, pTHI, and the complex  formed by these two proteins (59.8-, 47.0-, and 217-kD, respectively), we conclude that in the cytosol of wild-type  cells, all newly synthesized THI is associated with Pex20p  in a heterotetrameric complex composed of two polypeptide chains of each protein.  </p><p>We also tested the effects of the <italic>pex20-1</italic> and <italic>pex20KO</italic>  mutations on the oligomerization of THI in the cytosol. Interestingly, most THI in the cytosol of <italic>pex20</italic> mutants is  present as the monomeric form, even at the highest concentration of DSS (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">11</xref>, <italic>F</italic> and <italic>G</italic>). Therefore, mutations  in the <italic>PEX20</italic> gene affect oligomerization of newly synthesized THI in the cytosol and prevent the formation of the  heterotetrameric complex between Pex20p and THI.</p><p>We also evaluated the oligomeric state of mature THI in  LSP and HSP peroxisomes of oleic-acid grown wild-type  cells. Both forms of peroxisomes were treated with increasing concentrations of DSS or DSP and then subjected  to immunoprecipitation with anti-THI antibodies. Treatment of DSS cross-linked proteins under reducing conditions and DSP cross-linked proteins under nonreducing  conditions revealed a prominent 86-kD protein that increased with increasing concentration of cross-linker (Fig.  <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">11</xref>, <italic>H</italic> and <italic>J</italic>, and <italic>I</italic> and <italic>K</italic> [<italic>left panels</italic>]). No monomeric THI  was detected in either LSP or HSP peroxisomes in samples  treated with the highest concentration of cross-linker. On  the other hand, only monomeric THI was seen in DSP-treated samples cleaved with DTT and analyzed by SDS-PAGE under reducing conditions (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">11</xref>, <italic>I</italic> and <italic>K</italic>, <italic>right  panels</italic>). From these data, we conclude that the mature  form of THI is present exclusively as a homodimer in LSP  and HSP peroxisomes of the wild-type strain.</p></sec><sec><title>Mutations in the PEX20 Gene Do Not Affect the  Oligomerization of Isocitrate Lyase and Acyl-CoA  Oxidase in the Cytosol</title><p>Chemical cross-linking of pulse-labeled proteins, followed  by the immunoprecipitation with anti-ICL or anti-AOX  antibodies, was used to study the oligomeric state of ICL  and AOX in the cytosol and in peroxisomes of the wild-type and <italic>pex20</italic> mutant strains.   Treatment with increasing  concentrations of either DSS or DSP showed that ICL and  AOX were present primarily as complexes rather than as  monomers in the 200KgS (cytosolic) fraction (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">12</xref>, <italic>A</italic>, <italic>C</italic>,  <italic>G,</italic> and <italic>I</italic>), in LSP peroxisomes (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">12</xref>, <italic>B</italic>, <italic>E</italic>, <italic>H</italic>, and <italic>K</italic>) and  in HSP peroxisomes (data not shown) of the wild-type  strain.  The electrophoretic mobilities of ICL- and AOX-containing complexes from the cytosol were identical to  those from LSP and HSP peroxisomes when resolved by  SDS-PAGE on the same gel (data not shown). DTT treatment and reducing SDS-PAGE analysis of DSP cross-linked samples showed that only the monomeric forms of  ICL and AOX could be recovered from cytosol (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">12</xref>, <italic>D</italic>  and <italic>J</italic>), LSP peroxisomes (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">12</xref>, <italic>F</italic> and <italic>L</italic>) and HSP peroxisomes (data not shown) of the wild-type strain. The oligomerization of ICL or AOX was unaffected in both the  <italic>pex20-1</italic> and <italic>pex20K</italic>O mutants (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">12</xref>, data for the  <italic>pex20KO</italic> strain; data for the <italic>pex20-1</italic> strain not shown).  From these data, we conclude that newly synthesized ICL  and AOX rapidly oligomerize in the cytosol of wild-type  cells and are imported into peroxisomes as homooligomers.  Mutations in the <italic>PEX20</italic> gene do not affect the formation  of the homooligomers of ICL and AOX in the cytosol and  do not impair their subsequent import into peroxisomes.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Discussion"><title>Discussion</title><sec><title>Oligomerization of Thiolase in the Cytosol Is a  Prerequisite for Its Targeting to the Peroxisome</title><p>Our kinetic data show that the oligomerization of THI in  the cytosol precedes its import into the peroxisome. At the  end of a short pulse with radiolabeled methionine, all labeled THI was found exclusively in a cytosolic heterotetrameric complex of two THI and two Pex20p polypeptide  chains. Labeled THI was chased to peroxisomes and was  imported exclusively as a homodimer. Mutations in the  <italic>PEX20</italic> gene not only affected the oligomerization of THI  in the cytosol but also abolished import of THI into peroxisomes. Two interpretations for the observed effects of  <italic>pex20</italic> mutations on the oligomerization and peroxisomal  targeting of THI can be proposed. First, Pex20p could be  required only for the oligomerization and maintenance of  the import-competent oligomeric state of THI and, therefore, oligomerization of THI in the cytosol not only precedes but is also required for its targeting to the peroxisome. Second, Pex20p could not only act as a cytosolic  chaperone assisting oligomerization of THI in the cytosol,  but could also function as a cytosolic THI import receptor  that interacts with a specific docking site(s) on the peroxisomal membrane, thereby mediating docking of THI to  the peroxisome.</p><p>Our data also show that not only THI, which contains a  PTS2, but also ICL, which is targeted by PTS1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Barth and  Scheuber, 1993</xref>), and AOX, which lacks any conserved  variant of PTS1 or PTS2 (Nicaud et al., 1988), are imported into peroxisomes of <italic>Y</italic>. <italic>lipolytica</italic> as oligomers. Our  results extend recent observations that peroxisomes can  translocate folded, disulfide-bonded and oligomeric proteins, and even 9-nm colloidal gold particles, across their  membranes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Glover et al., 1994</xref><italic>a</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">McNew and Goodman,  1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">Walton et al., 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Elgersma et al., 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">H&#x000e4;usler et  al., 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Leiper et al., 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Lee et al., 1997</xref>). Although  polypeptide chains lacking a PTS can be translocated into  the peroxisomal matrix in a piggyback fashion on PTS1-  and PTS2-containing proteins (for review see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">Rachubinski  and Subramani, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">McNew and Goodman, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">Subramani, 1998</xref>), we did not see evidence of piggybacking of  THI, ICL, or AOX into the peroxisomal matrix in <italic>Y</italic>. <italic>lipolytica</italic>. According to our data, THI penetrates the peroxisome exclusively as a homodimer rather than as a component of a cytosolically formed heterotetrameric complex  of THI and Pex20p.  Our data also show that newly synthesized ICL and AOX rapidly homooligomerize in the  cytosol and are imported as homooligomers, which suggests that they are not piggybacked into peroxisomes.</p></sec><sec><title>Pex20p May Act As a Cytosolic Chaperone Assisting  Thiolase Oligomerization</title><p>Mutations in the <italic>PEX20</italic> gene abolish the assembly of  newly synthesized monomers of THI into a heterotetrameric complex of THI and Pex20p, suggesting that  Pex20p may act as a cytosolic chaperone that assists in the  oligomerization of THI in vivo. Molecular chaperones  were originally defined as temporary partners that assist in  the oligomeric assembly of unassembled subunits of oligomeric proteins (for review see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Hendrick and Hartl, 1993</xref>).  Our results indicate that two polypeptides of Pex20p bind  temporarily to two polypeptide chains of THI and that this  heterotetrameric complex dissociates upon binding to the  outer surface of the peroxisomal membrane, releasing  THI homodimer into the peroxisomal matrix. Moreover,  since oligomerization of THI in the cytosol (see above) is a  prerequisite for its targeting to the peroxisome, we propose that Pex20p acts as a putative cytosolic chaperone to  maintain the import-competent oligomeric state of THI.  Our data also show that the substrate specificity of Pex20p  as a putative cytosolic chaperone is limited to THI. Pex20p  does not bind the newly synthesized cytosolic form of any  peroxisomal protein other than THI, and it is not essential  for the targeting of any peroxisomal protein other than  THI from the cytosol to the peroxisome nor is it required  for the oligomeric assembly of ICL and AOX in the cytosol. Pex20p is also apparently not required for the folding  of newly synthesized monomers of THI in the cytosol, as  our results show that newly synthesized monomeric THI is  enzymatically active (data not shown), does not form insoluble aggregates and is not degraded in the cytosol of  the <italic>pex20</italic> mutant strains. This step of THI maturation in  the cytosol may be assisted by other cytosolic chaperone(s) such as TRiC (TCP1 ring complex), the eukaryotic  homologue of GroEL (for review see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Horwich and Willison, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Bukau et al., 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Hartl, 1996</xref>), or cytosolic  Hsp70. TriC has been shown to assist in the folding of the  peroxisomal matrix protein, firefly luciferase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Frydman et al.,  1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Frydman and Hartl, 1996</xref>), and to bind to the peroxisomal membrane protein, PMP22 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">Pause et al., 1997</xref>). Cytosolic Hsp70 also binds to firefly luciferase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Frydman et al.,  1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Frydman and Hartl, 1996</xref>) and has been shown to  play an essential role in peroxisomal protein import (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">Walton et al., 1994</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>A Model for Pex20p-mediated Oligomerization and  Peroxisomal Import of Thiolase</title><p>The results of this study can be summarized in the following model for Pex20p-assisted oligomerization and peroxisomal import of THI. Monomeric Pex20p binds newly synthesized monomeric THI in the cytosol and promotes the  formation of a heterotetrameric complex composed of two  polypeptide chains of each protein.  The association of  Pex20p with THI is independent of the PTS2 in THI. The  heterotetrameric complex binds to the peroxisomal membrane. Translocation of the THI homodimer into the peroxisomal matrix may release Pex20p monomers back to  the cytosol, thereby permitting a new cycle of binding- oligomerization-targeting-release for Pex20p and THI.  Binding of Pex20p to THI is PTS2 independent because,  as we have shown, Pex20p interacts with PTS2-containing  and PTS2-lacking forms of THI with equal efficiency. No  receptor that binds PTS2 directly and is required for import of PTS2-containing THI has yet been identified in <italic>Y</italic>.  <italic>lipolytica</italic>. However, PTS2 receptors of the Pex7p peroxin  family have been identified in <italic>S</italic>. <italic>cerevisiae</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">Marzioch et al.,  1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">Zhang and Lazarow, 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B64">1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">Rehling et al.,  1996</xref>), <italic>Kluyveromyces lactis</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Motley et al., 1997</xref>), <italic>Pichia  pastoris</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Elgersma et al., 1998</xref>), mouse (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Braverman et al.,  1997</xref>) and human (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Braverman et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Motley et al.,  1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">Purdue et al., 1997</xref>). The exact subcellular location  of the PTS2 receptor is a matter of debate and has been reported as mainly cytosolic and partially peroxisomal  (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">Marzioch et al., 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">Rehling et al., 1996</xref>) or exclusively  intraperoxisomal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">Zhang and Lazarow, 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B64">1996</xref>). Accordingly, two alternative models for PTS2 receptor action  have been proposed.  The first proposes that Pex7p is a  mobile receptor, shuttling between the cytosol and the  peroxisome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">Marzioch et al., 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">Rehling et al., 1996</xref>).  The second proposes that Pex7p acts from within the peroxisome to pull THI inside the organelle and predicts the  existence of another peroxin to interact with PTS2-containing THI, either in the cytosol or at the outer surface of  the peroxisomal membrane (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">Zhang and Lazarow, 1995</xref>,  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B64">1996</xref>). Both models could accommodate the existence of a  cytosolic peroxin such as Pex20p that not only maintains  the oligomeric (import-competent) state of THI but which  could also stabilize a conformation of THI that makes  PTS2 more accessible to Pex7p.  In the first model, cytosolic Pex20p could interact with a region of THI outside of  the PTS2, whereas cytosolic Pex7p would bind the PTS2  directly.  The cooperative action of Pex7p and Pex20p in the  cytosol would permit correct targeting of THI to the peroxisomal docking protein Pex14p (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Albertini et al., 1997</xref>), followed by translocation of THI into the matrix.  In the second model, cytosolic Pex20p would maintain the oligomeric  (import-competent) state of THI and could stabilize a conformation of THI that makes PTS2 more accessible to  Pex7p, thereby mediating targeting of THI to the peroxisomal membrane. Subsequent interaction of intraperoxisomal  Pex7p with an exposed PTS2 would initiate pulling of THI  inside the organelle. It should be noted that in the blot overlay assay, no cytosolic protein other than Pex20p was seen  to interact with pTHI or mTHI. The inability to detect a  cytosolic PTS2 receptor that interacts only with pTHI but  not with mTHI may be the result of Pex20p having a significantly higher affinity for pTHI than does any other cytosolic  protein. An alternative explanation might be that the <italic>Y</italic>.  <italic>lipolytica</italic> PTS2 receptor is exclusively intraperoxisomal. We  are currently developing genetic screens aimed at identifying Pex7p of <italic>Y</italic>. <italic>lipolytica</italic> so as to critically evaluate both  models in regards to a cooperative action of Pex7p and  Pex20p in the peroxisomal import of THI.</p><p>In conclusion, the results described herein provide evidence that the oligomerization of THI in the cytosol requires the peroxin Pex20p and is a prerequisite for THI  import into peroxisomes in <italic>Y</italic>. <italic>lipolytica</italic>. THI and Pex20p  interact in a PTS2-independent manner and form a heterotetrameric cytosolic complex composed of two polypeptide chains of each protein. After targeting of the complex to the peroxisomal membrane, the homodimer of  THI is translocated into the peroxisomal matrix, and  Pex20p monomers are envisaged to recycle to the cytosol  to permit a new cycle of binding-oligomerization-targeting-release between Pex20p and THI.</p></sec></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="display-objects"><title>Figures and Tables</title><table-wrap position="float" id="TI"><label>Table I</label><caption><p>Yarrowia lipolytica Strains Used in This Study </p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Strain</th><th/><th>Genotype</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><italic>E122<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFI-150">&#x0002a;</xref></italic></td><td align="left"/><td align="left"><italic>MATA, ura3-302, leu2-270, lys8-11</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>22301-3<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFI-150">&#x0002a;</xref></italic></td><td align="left"/><td align="left"><italic>MATB, ura3-302, leu2-270, his1</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>pex5KO</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFI-152">&#x02021;</xref></td><td align="left"/><td align="left"><italic>MATA, ura3-302, leu2-270, lys8-11, pex5::LEU2</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>pex20-1</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFI-153">&#x000a7;</xref></td><td align="left"/><td align="left"><italic>MATA, ura3-302, leu2-270, lys8-11, pex20-1</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>pex20KO-1A</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFI-153">&#x000a7;</xref></td><td align="left"/><td align="left"><italic>MATA, ura3-302, leu2-270, lys8-11, pex20::URA3</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>pex20KO-2B</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFI-153">&#x000a7;</xref></td><td align="left"/><td align="left"><italic>MATB, ura3-302, leu2-270, his1, pex20::URA3</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>D1-20</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFI-153">&#x000a7;</xref></td><td align="left"/><td align="left"><italic>MATA/MATB, ura3-302/ura3-302, leu2-270/leu2-270, &#x02003;lys8-11/</italic>&#x0002b;<italic>,</italic> &#x0002b;<italic>his1,</italic> &#x0002b;<italic>/pex20::URA3</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>D2-20</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFI-153">&#x000a7;</xref></td><td align="left"/><td align="left"><italic>MATB/MATA, ura3-302/ura3-302, leu2-270/leu2-270,</italic> &#x02003;&#x0002b;<italic>/lys8-11, his1/</italic>&#x0002b;<italic>,</italic> &#x0002b;<italic>/pex20::URA3</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>D3-20</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFI-153">&#x000a7;</xref></td><td align="left"/><td align="left"><italic>MATB/MATA, ura3-302/ura3-302, leu2-270/ leu2-270,</italic> &#x02003;&#x0002b;<italic>/lys8-11, his1/</italic>&#x0002b;<italic>,</italic> &#x0002b;<italic>/pex20-1</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>D4-20</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFI-153">&#x000a7;</xref></td><td align="left"/><td align="left"><italic>MATA/MATB, ura3-302/ura3-302, leu2-270/leu2-270, &#x02003;lys8-11/</italic>&#x0002b;<italic>,</italic> &#x0002b;<italic>/his1, pex20-1/pex20::URA3</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>D5-20</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFI-153">&#x000a7;</xref></td><td align="left"/><td align="left"><italic>MATA/MATB, ura3-302/ura3-302, leu2-270/leu2-270, &#x02003;lys8-11/</italic>&#x0002b;, &#x0002b;/his1, pex20::URA3/pex20::URA3</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TFI-150"><label>&#x0002a;</label><p>&#x02009;C. Gaillardin (Institut National Agronomique Paris-Grignon) Thiverval-Grignon, France.  &#x000a0;</p></fn><fn id="TFI-152"><label>&#x02021;</label><p>&#x02009;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">Szilard et al., 1995</xref>.  &#x000a0;</p></fn><fn id="TFI-153"><label>&#x000a7;</label><p>&#x02009;This study.  &#x000a0;</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Nucleotide sequence of the <italic>PEX20</italic> gene and deduced  amino acid sequence of Pex20p. These sequence data are available from EMBL/GeneBank/DDBJ under accession number  <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="AF054613">AF054613</ext-link>. </p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JCB9804034.f1"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Subcellular localization and regulation of synthesis of Pex20p. (<italic>A</italic>) Immunoblot analysis of whole cell  lysates (3 &#x000d7; 10<sup>8</sup> cells) of wild-type strain <italic>E122</italic> (<italic>WT</italic>), and  <italic>pex20-1</italic> and <italic>pex20KO</italic> mutant strains probed with anti-Pex20p antibodies. Strains  were grown in YPBO for 9 h.  (<italic>B</italic>) Wild-type strain <italic>E122</italic>  was grown in YEPD until the  cell titer was 6.0 &#x000d7; 10<sup>7</sup> cells/ ml.  Cells were transferred to  YPBO and incubated at  30&#x000b0;C. Equal aliquots of cells  were taken at the times indicated. The levels of Pex20p  in whole cell lysates were determined by immunoblotting.   Blots were probed with anti-Pex20p antibodies. (<italic>C</italic>) Equal  portions of the indicated  subcellular fractions from  YPBO-grown wild-type cells  were separated by SDS-PAGE and analyzed by  immunoblotting with anti-Pex20p antibodies. (<italic>D</italic>) Release of intracellular proteins  by progressive digitonin titration of YPBO-grown wild-type cells. Aliquots of  spheroplasts were incubated  with different concentrations of digitonin for 30 min  at 4&#x000b0;C and then subjected to  centrifugation at 20,000 <italic>g</italic> for  10 min at 4&#x000b0;C. Supernatants  were analyzed for the release of proteins. The activities of the peroxisomal enzyme catalase (<italic>CAT</italic>) and the mitochondrial enzyme fumarase (<italic>FUM</italic>) were determined. The cytosolic marker G6PDH, the peroxisomal matrix marker THI, and Pex20p were determined by immunoblotting. Immunoblots were scanned densitometrically, and protein levels were quantitated. The amount of each protein released  to the supernatant was normalized to the amount of that protein released to the supernatant at a concentration of 1,000 &#x003bc;g digitonin/ml.  (<italic>E</italic>) Double-labeling, indirect immunofluorescence analysis of YPBO-grown wild-type cells using rabbit anti-THI and guinea pig anti-Pex20p primary antibodies. Primary antibodies were detected with fluorescein-conjugated goat anti&#x02013;rabbit IgG and rhodamine-conjugated donkey anti&#x02013;guinea pig IgG secondary antibodies. (<italic>F</italic>) The 200KgP fraction of the wild-type strain <italic>E122</italic> grown in YPBO for 9 h  was subjected to flotation on a two-step sucrose gradient. Sucrose density (g/cm<sup>3</sup>) and percent recovery of loaded protein in gradient  fractions are presented.  Equal volumes of gradient fractions were analyzed by immunoblotting with anti-AOX, anti-THI, and anti-Pex20p antibodies. (<italic>G</italic>) Equal portions of the 200KgP fraction of the wild-type strain <italic>E122</italic> grown in YPBO for 9 h were treated with one  of Ti8 buffer (10 mM Tris-HCl, pH 8.0, 5 mM EDTA, 1 mM PMSF, 1 &#x003bc;g leupeptin/ml, 1 &#x003bc;g pepstatin/ml, 1 &#x003bc;g aprotinin/ml), 1 M NaCl,  1 M urea or 0.1 M Na<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub>. After incubation on ice for 45 min, samples were separated into supernatant (<italic>S</italic>) and pellet (<italic>P</italic>) fractions by  centrifugation at 200,000 <italic>g</italic> for 1 h at 4&#x000b0;C, and then subjected to immunoblot analysis with anti-Pex20p antibodies.  (<italic>H</italic>) Protease protection analysis. The 200KgP fraction (60 &#x003bc;g of protein) of the wild-type strain <italic>E122</italic> grown in YPBO for 9 h was incubated with 0, 4, 8, or  20 &#x003bc;g trypsin in the absence (&#x02212;) or presence (&#x0002b;) of 1.0% (vol/vol) Triton X-100 for 60 min on ice. Reactions were terminated by addition of TCA to 10%. Equal portions of the samples were subjected to immunoblot analysis with anti-Pex20p and anti-THI antibodies.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JCB9804034.f2a"/><graphic xlink:href="JCB9804034.f2bc"/><graphic xlink:href="JCB9804034.f2d"/><graphic xlink:href="JCB9804034.f2ef"/><graphic xlink:href="JCB9804034.f2gh"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Trafficking of  Pex20p. (<italic>A</italic>) Wild-type strain  <italic>E122</italic> grown in YPBO for 9 h  was pulse-labeled with  <sc>l</sc>-[<sup>35</sup>S]methionine and chased  with unlabeled <sc>l</sc>-methionine.  Samples were taken at the indicated times after chase.  Cells were subjected to subcellular fractionation to yield  20KgP, 200KgP, and 200KgS  (cytosolic) fractions.  Pex20p was immunoprecipitated from the  fractions. Immunoprecipitates were resolved by SDS-PAGE and  visualized by fluorography. (<italic>B</italic>) Equal portions of the 200KgP  fraction isolated from YPBO-grown wild-type cells pulse-labeled  with <sc>l</sc>-[<sup>35</sup>S]methionine and chased for 5 min with unlabeled  <sc>l</sc>-methionine, were incubated with 0, 4, 8, or 20 &#x003bc;g trypsin in the  absence (&#x02212;) or presence (&#x0002b;) of 1.0% (vol/vol) Triton X-100 for  60 min on ice. Reactions were terminated by addition of TCA to  10%. Samples were subjected to immunoprecipitation with anti-Pex20p or anti-THI antibodies, and immunoprecipitates were resolved by SDS-PAGE and then visualized by fluorography.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JCB9804034.f3"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Ultrastructure of  wild-type and <italic>pex20</italic> mutant  strains. Wild-type strain  <italic>E122</italic> (<italic>WT</italic>) and mutant  strains <italic>pex20-1</italic> and <italic>pex20KO</italic>  grown for 9 h in YPBO were  fixed in KMnO<sub>4</sub> and processed for EM. <italic>P</italic>, peroxisome; <italic>M</italic>, mitochondrion; <italic>N</italic>,  nucleus. <italic>Arrowheads</italic>, peroxisomes having a &#x0201c;relative area  of peroxisome section (%)&#x0201d;  of 0.05&#x02013;0.2%. Bar, 1 &#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JCB9804034.f4"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Subcellular localization of peroxisomal  matrix and membrane proteins in wild-type and  <italic>pex20</italic> mutant strains. The recoveries of the matrix proteins AOX, 62-kD SKL, 64-kD SKL,  ICL, CAT, MLS, and THI, and of the membrane  proteins Pex2p and Pex16p, in different subcellular fractions of the wild-type strain <italic>E122</italic> (<italic>WT</italic>)  and of the mutant strains <italic>pex20-1</italic> and <italic>pex20KO</italic>  are presented. Strains were grown for 9 h in  YPBO and subjected to subcellular fractionation. Equal portions of the PNS, 20KgP, 20KgS,  200KgP, and 200KgS were analyzed by immunoblotting with antibodies to the indicated proteins. The activity of CAT was assayed enzymatically. Values for CAT activity in the 20KgP,  20KgS, 200KgP, and 200KgS fractions are relative to CAT activity in the PNS fraction of the indicated strain. Values for enzymatic activities are  the means &#x000b1; SD from three independent experiments.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JCB9804034.f5a"/><graphic xlink:href="JCB9804034.f5b"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F8"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Double-labeling, indirect immunofluorescence analysis of wild-type and mutant strains.   Wild-type strain <italic>E122</italic> (<italic>WT</italic>) and mutant strains  <italic>pex20-1</italic> and <italic>pex20KO</italic> were grown in YPBO.  Cells were processed for immunofluorescence microscopy with guinea pig anti-THI and  rabbit anti-SKL; rabbit anti-MLS and guinea pig anti&#x02013;SKL; guinea pig anti-Pex2p and  rabbit anti-SKL; and rabbit anti-MLS and guinea pig anti-Pex2p primary antibodies.  Primary antibodies were detected with fluorescein-conjugated goat anti-rabbit IgG and  rhodamine-conjugated donkey anti-guinea pig IgG secondary antibodies. <italic>Arrows</italic> in <italic>B</italic> indicate punctate structures in <italic>pex20KO</italic> cells that are decorated with anti-MLS (<italic>leftmost  panels</italic>) or anti-Pex2p (<italic>middle panels</italic>) antibodies but not with anti-SKL antibodies.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JCB9804034.f8ab"/><graphic xlink:href="JCB9804034.f8c"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Trafficking of peroxisomal matrix and  membrane proteins in wild-type and <italic>pex20KO</italic>  cells. Wild-type strain <italic>E122</italic> (<italic>WT</italic>) (<italic>A</italic> and <italic>C</italic>) and  mutant strain <italic>pex20KO</italic> (<italic>B</italic>) grown in YPBO for 9 h  were pulse labeled with <sc>l</sc>-[<sup>35</sup>S]methionine and  chased with unlabeled <sc>l</sc>-methionine.  Samples were  taken at the indicated times after chase. Cells were  subjected to subcellular fractionation to yield 20KgP,  200KgP, and 200KgS (cytosolic) fractions. AOX,  MLS, Pex2p, and THI were immunoprecipitated  from the fractions. Immunoprecipitates were resolved by SDS-PAGE and visualized by fluorography. Fluorograms were quantitated by densitometry. The maximal level of a protein in a particular  fraction is set at 100%. Half-times for the exit  from, and for the import into, a particular fraction  by a protein in either wild-type or <italic>pex20KO</italic> cells  were calculated. (<italic>C</italic>) Conversion of the precursor  form of THI (<italic>pTHI</italic>) to the mature form of THI  (<italic>mTHI</italic>) occurs in the 200KgP fraction of wild-type  cells. 200KgP fractions were isolated from wild-type cells subjected to pulse labeling with <sc>l</sc>-[<sup>35</sup>S]methionine and chase with unlabeled <sc>l</sc>-methionine.  pTHI and mTHI were immunoprecipitated from  the 200KgP fractions isolated from cells harvested  at the indicated times after chase, resolved by  SDS-PAGE, and then visualized by fluorography.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JCB9804034.f6a"/><graphic xlink:href="JCB9804034.f6b"/><graphic xlink:href="JCB9804034.f6d"/><graphic xlink:href="JCB9804034.f6c"/><graphic xlink:href="JCB9804034.f6e"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F7"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Isolation of LSP peroxisomes from wild-type and mutant strains. Wild-type strain <italic>E122</italic> (<italic>WT</italic>) and mutant strains <italic>pex20-1</italic> and  <italic>pex20KO</italic> were grown in YPBO.  Peroxisomes were isolated from the 20KgP of each strain by isopycnic centrifugation on a discontinuous sucrose density gradient.  Equal amounts of protein were loaded onto each gradient.  Sucrose density (g/cm<sup>3</sup>) of gradient fractions,  and the percent recovery of loaded protein and of CAT (peroxisome) and cytochrome <italic>c</italic> oxidase (<italic>CCO</italic>) (mitochondria) marker enzyme  activities in gradient fractions are presented.  Equal volumes of gradient fractions were analyzed by immunoblotting with antibodies to  peroxisomal matrix (<italic>AOX</italic>, <italic>ICL</italic>, <italic>SKL</italic>, <italic>MLS</italic>, <italic>THI</italic>) and membrane (<italic>Pex2p</italic>) proteins.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JCB9804034.f7"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F9"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p>The association of Pex20p with newly synthesized THI in the cytosol is independent of the PTS2 of THI. (<italic>A</italic>) Wild-type <italic>E122</italic>  cells grown in YPBO for 9 h were pulse-labeled with <sc>l</sc>-[<sup>35</sup>S]methionine for 1.5 min and immediately subjected to subcellular fractionation to yield a 200KgS (cytosolic) fraction. The 200KgS fraction was divided into three equal aliquots, and Pex20p (<italic>1</italic>), THI (<italic>6</italic>), and  anti-SKL&#x02013;reactive proteins (<italic>11</italic>) were immunoprecipitated under native conditions.   Immunoprecipitated proteins were eluted from  protein A&#x02013;Sepharose with 100 mM glycine, pH 2.8, and eluates were each divided into equal aliquots that were resolved by SDS-PAGE.  One aliquot was subjected to fluorography, whereas the other four were analyzed by immunoblotting with anti-Pex20p, anti-THI, anti-SKL, or anti-MLS antibodies. Unbound proteins recovered in the flow-through after native immunoprecipitation with anti-Pex20p,  anti-THI, and anti-SKL antibodies were subjected to a second immunoprecipitation under denaturing conditions using anti-Pex20p (<italic>2</italic>,  <italic>7</italic>, <italic>12</italic>), anti-THI (<italic>3</italic>, <italic>8</italic>, <italic>13</italic>), anti-SKL (<italic>4</italic>, <italic>9</italic>, <italic>14</italic>) or anti-MLS (<italic>5</italic>, <italic>10</italic>, <italic>15</italic>) antibodies. Immunoprecipitates were divided into equal aliquots  that were resolved by SDS-PAGE. One aliquot was subjected to fluorography, whereas the other four were analyzed by immunoblotting using the antibodies indicated. (<italic>B</italic>) The wild-type strain <italic>E122</italic> and the mutant strain <italic>pex5KO</italic> grown in YPBO for 9 h were pulse labeled with <sc>l</sc>-[<sup>35</sup>S]methionine and chased for 30 min with unlabeled <sc>l</sc>-methionine. Cells were subjected to subcellular fractionation and  peroxisomes were purified from the 20KgP fraction. Pulse-labeled and chased peroxisomal matrix proteins were subjected to immunoaffinity chromatography with anti-THI antibodies linked to protein A&#x02013;Sepharose. Immunoprecipitated mature (<italic>mTHI</italic>) and precursor (<italic>pTHI</italic>) forms of THI were eluted with 100 mM glycine, pH 2.8, and the eluates were divided into equal aliquots. One aliquot of each  eluate was resolved by SDS-PAGE and subjected to fluorography (<italic>B</italic>), whereas the other aliquots were used as probes in a blot overlay  assay. (<italic>C</italic>) Unlabeled proteins from the 200KgS fraction of wild-type cells were divided into equal aliquots. One aliquot was subjected to  depletion of Pex20p by native immunoprecipitation with Pex20p antibodies (<italic>pre-IP: anti-Pex20p</italic>), whereas the second aliquot remained  untreated. Unbound cytosolic proteins recovered in the flow-through after native immunoprecipitation with anti-Pex20p, unlabeled  proteins from the untreated 200KgS fraction of wild-type cells, and unlabeled proteins from the 200KgS fractions of <italic>pex20-1</italic> and  <italic>pex20KO</italic> cells were divided into equal aliquots, resolved by SDS-PAGE, and transferred to nitrocellulose. After denaturation/renaturation of the transferred proteins, the blots were subjected to an overlay assay using mTHI (<italic>strips 1</italic>) or pTHI (<italic>strips 2</italic>) as probes. One set  of blots was subjected to fluorography (<italic>C</italic>), whereas a second set was used for stripping of bound mTHI and pTHI with urea (<italic>D</italic>). (<italic>D</italic>)  Radiolabeled mTHI and pTHI (lanes <italic>3</italic> and <italic>4</italic>, respectively) bound to proteins present only in the untreated 200KgS fraction of the wild-type strain and stripped with urea, were resolved by SDS-PAGE and subjected to fluorography.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JCB9804034.f9"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F10"><label>Figure 10</label><caption><p>Pex20p and THI in the 200KgP fraction do not form a  complex. Wild-type <italic>E122</italic> cells grown in YPBO for 9 h were pulse  labeled with <sc>l</sc>-[<sup>35</sup>S]methionine and chased for 5 min with unlabeled <sc>l</sc>-methionine. Cells were subjected to subcellular fractionation, and the 200KgP fraction was divided into equal aliquots  that were subjected to immunoprecipitation under native conditions with anti-Pex20p (<italic>1</italic>) or anti-THI (<italic>6</italic>) antibodies. Proteins  that did not bind to protein A&#x02013;Sepharose and were recovered in  the flow-through after native immunoprecipitation with either  anti-Pex20p or anti-THI antibodies were subjected to a second  immunoprecipitation under denaturing conditions using anti-Pex20p (<italic>2</italic>, <italic>7</italic>), anti-THI (<italic>3</italic>, <italic>8</italic>), anti-SKL (<italic>4</italic>, <italic>9</italic>) or anti-MLS (<italic>5</italic>, <italic>10</italic>)  antibodies. These immunoprecipitates were resolved by SDS-PAGE and were analyzed by fluorography and immunoblotting  with the indicated antibodies.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JCB9804034.f10"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F11"><label>Figure 11</label><caption><p>Mutations in the <italic>PEX20</italic> gene affect oligomerization of THI in the cytosol  and prevent the formation of a heterotetrameric complex between Pex20p and THI.  Wild-type strain <italic>E122</italic> and mutant strains <italic>pex20-1</italic> and <italic>pex20KO</italic> grown in YPBO for  9 h were pulse labeled with <sc>l</sc>-[<sup>35</sup>S]methionine for 1.5 min and chased with unlabeled  <sc>l</sc>-methionine. 200KgS (cytosolic) fractions were isolated from each strain at chase time  0. A 200KgP fraction (<italic>200KgP</italic>) enriched for HSP peroxisomes was isolated from wild-type cells chased for 7 min. LSP peroxisomes (<italic>Peroxisome</italic>) were isolated from the  20KgP of wild-type cells chased for 30 min. Cytosolic and peroxisomal proteins were  treated with increasing concentrations of the cross-linkers DSS (<italic>A&#x02013;D, F&#x02013;H, J</italic>) or DSP  (<italic>E, I, K</italic>) and subjected to immunoprecipitation with anti-THI (<italic>A, E, F&#x02013;K</italic>) or anti-Pex20p (<italic>C</italic>) antibodies under denaturing conditions. Immunoprecipitates were resolved by SDS-PAGE and subjected to fluorography. Proteins that did not bind to protein A&#x02013;Sepharose during immunoprecipitation of DSS-treated cytosolic proteins from  wild-type cells with anti-THI (<italic>A</italic>) or anti-Pex20p (<italic>C</italic>) antibodies, were further immunoprecipitated with anti-Pex20p (<italic>B</italic>) or anti-THI (<italic>D</italic>)  antibodies under denaturing conditions. Immunoprecipitates were resolved by SDS-PAGE and subjected to fluorography. Immunoprecipitated proteins treated with the noncleavable crosslinker DSS were analyzed by SDS-PAGE only under reducing conditions (<italic>A&#x02013;D,  F&#x02013;H, J</italic>), whereas immunoprecipitated proteins treated with the thiol-cleavable cross-linker DSP were analyzed by SDS-PAGE under  both nonreducing (<italic>E, I, K</italic>, <italic>left panels</italic>) and reducing (<italic>E, I, K, right panels</italic>) conditions. The positions of the monomeric and oligomeric  forms of THI, of the monomeric form of Pex20p, and of the complex between Pex20p and THI are indicated by arrowheads (<italic>right</italic>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JCB9804034.f11ab"/><graphic xlink:href="JCB9804034.f11cd"/><graphic xlink:href="JCB9804034.f11ef"/><graphic xlink:href="JCB9804034.f11g"/><graphic xlink:href="JCB9804034.f11h"/><graphic xlink:href="JCB9804034.f11ij"/><graphic xlink:href="JCB9804034.f11k"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F12"><label>Figure 12</label><caption><p>The oligomerization of  ICL and AOX is unaffected in the  <italic>pex20KO</italic> mutant. The wild-type  strain <italic>E122</italic> and the mutant strain  <italic>pex20KO</italic> grown in YPBO for 9 h  were pulse labeled with <sc>l</sc>-[<sup>35</sup>S]methionine and chased with unlabeled  <sc>l</sc>-methionine. One aliquot of cells  of each strain was taken at chase  time 0 and then subjected to subcellular fractionation to yield a 200KgS  (cytosolic) fraction. The second aliquots of the wild-type and <italic>pex20KO</italic> mutant cells were chased for 30 min, and LSP peroxisomes were isolated from the 20KgP fraction.  Cytosolic and peroxisomal proteins were treated with increasing concentrations of the crosslinkers DSS (<italic>A</italic>, <italic>B</italic>, <italic>G</italic>, and <italic>H</italic>) or DSP (<italic>C&#x02013;F</italic>,  <italic>I&#x02013;L</italic>) and subjected to immunoprecipitation with anti-ICL (<italic>A&#x02013;F</italic>) or anti-AOX (<italic>G&#x02013;L</italic>) antibodies under denaturing conditions. Immunoprecipitates were resolved by SDS-PAGE and subjected to fluorography. Immunoprecipitated proteins treated with the noncleavable  crosslinker DSS were analyzed by SDS-PAGE only under reducing conditions (<italic>A</italic>, <italic>B</italic>, <italic>G</italic>, and <italic>H</italic>). Immunoprecipitated proteins treated  with the thiol-cleavable cross-linker DSP were analyzed by SDS-PAGE under nonreducing (<italic>C</italic>, <italic>E</italic>, <italic>I</italic>, and <italic>K</italic>) and reducing (<italic>D</italic>, <italic>F</italic>, <italic>J</italic>, and  <italic>L</italic>) conditions. The positions of the monomeric and oligomeric forms of ICL and AOX are indicated by arrowheads (<italic>right</italic>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JCB9804034.f12ab"/><graphic xlink:href="JCB9804034.f12c"/><graphic xlink:href="JCB9804034.f12d"/><graphic xlink:href="JCB9804034.f12ef"/><graphic xlink:href="JCB9804034.f12gh"/><graphic xlink:href="JCB9804034.f12i"/><graphic xlink:href="JCB9804034.f12j"/><graphic xlink:href="JCB9804034.f12kl"/></fig></sec><ack><p>We thank H. Chan (University of Alberta, Edmonton, Alberta, Canada)  for help with electron microscopy.</p><p>This work was supported by grant MT-9208 from the Medical Research  Council (MRC) of Canada to R.A. Rachubinski. R.A. Rachubinski is an  MRC Senior Scientist and an International Research Scholar of the  Howard Hughes Medical Institute.</p></ack><glossary><title>Abbreviations used in this paper</title><def-list><def-item><term>AOX</term><def><p>acyl-CoA oxidase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CAT</term><def><p>catalase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DSP</term><def><p>dithiobis(succinimidylproprionate)</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DSS</term><def><p>disuccinimidyl suberate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FUM</term><def><p>fumarase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>G6PDH</term><def><p>glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HSP</term><def><p>high-speed (200,000 <italic>g</italic>) pelletable</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ICL</term><def><p>isocitrate lyase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LSP</term><def><p>low-speed  (20,000 <italic>g</italic>) pelletable</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>20KgP</term><def><p>20,000 <italic>g</italic> pellet</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>20KgS</term><def><p>20,000 <italic>g</italic> supernatant</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>200KgP</term><def><p>200,000 <italic>g</italic> pellet</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>200KgS</term><def><p>200,000 <italic>g</italic> supernatant (cytosol)</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MLS</term><def><p>malate synthase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PNS</term><def><p>postnuclear supernatant</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PTS</term><def><p>peroxisomal targeting signal</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>THI</term><def><p>thiolase</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abeijon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Orlean</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Robins</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirschberg</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Topography of glycosylation in yeast: characterization of GDP-mannose transport and lumenal guanosine diphosphatase activities in Golgi-like vesicles</article-title><source>Proc Natl  Acad Sci USA</source><year>1989</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>6935</fpage><lpage>6939</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2476806</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Albertini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rehling</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Erdmann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Girzalsky</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiel</surname><given-names>JAKW</given-names></name><name><surname>Veenhuis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunau</surname><given-names>W-H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pex14p, a peroxisomal membrane protein binding both receptors of the two PTS-dependent import pathways</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1997</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>83</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9094717</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="other">Ausubel, F.J., R. Brent, R.E. Kingston, D.D. Moore, J.G. Seidman, J.A. Smith,  and K. Struhl. 1989. <italic>In</italic> Current Protocols in Molecular Biology. Greene Publishing Associates, New York. 3.1&#x02013;3.17, 13.11&#x02013;13.12.</citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barth</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheuber</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cloning of the isocitrate lyase gene (ICL1)  from <italic>Yarrowia lipolytica</italic>and characterization of the deduced protein</article-title><source>Mol  Gen Genet</source><year>1993</year><volume>241</volume><fpage>422</fpage><lpage>430</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8246896</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bellion</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Proton ionophores prevent assembly of a peroxisomal protein</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1987</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>165</fpage><lpage>173</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3539364</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boisram&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Beckerich</surname><given-names>J-M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaillardin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sls1p, an endoplasmic  reticulum component, is involved in the protein translocation process in the  yeast <italic>Yarrowia lipolytica. </italic></article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1996</year><volume>271</volume><fpage>11668</fpage><lpage>11675</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8662639</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Braverman</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Steel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Obie</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Moser</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Moser</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Gould</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Valle</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Human <italic>PEX7</italic>encodes the peroxisomal PTS2 receptor and is responsible for rhizomelic chondrodysplasia punctata</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>1997</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>369</fpage><lpage>376</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9090381</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bukau</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hesterkamp</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Luirink</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Growing in a dangerous environment: a network of multiple targeting and folding pathways for nascent polypeptides in the cytosol</article-title><source>Trends Cell Biol</source><year>1996</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>480</fpage><lpage>486</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15157507</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="other">Coligan, J.E., B.M. Dunn, H.L. Ploegh, D.W. Speicher, and P.T Wingfield.  1995. <italic>In</italic> Current Protocols in Protein Science. Wiley Interscience, New  York. 10.11.1&#x02013;10.11.6.</citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dingwall</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kandels-Lewis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>S&#x000e9;raphin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A family of Ran binding proteins that includes nucleoporins</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>1995</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>7525</fpage><lpage>7529</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7638224</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Distel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Erdmann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gould</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Blobel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Crane</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name><name><surname>Cregg</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Dodt</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujiki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Just</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiel</surname><given-names>JAKW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunau</surname><given-names>W-H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lazarow</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name><surname>Mannaerts</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Moser</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Osumi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Rachubinski</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Roscher</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Subramani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tabak</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name><name><surname>Valle</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Klei</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>van Veldhoven</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><name><surname>Veenhuis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A unified nomenclature for peroxisome biogenesis</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>1996</year><volume>135</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>3</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8858157</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dodt</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Gould</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiple <italic>PEX</italic>genes are required for proper subcellular distribution and stability of Pex5p, the PTS1 receptor: evidence that PTS1 protein import is mediated by a cycling receptor</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>1996</year><volume>135</volume><fpage>1763</fpage><lpage>1774</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8991089</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eitzen</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Aitchison</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Szilard</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Veenhuis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nuttley</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rachubinski</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The <italic>Yarrowia lipolytica</italic> gene <italic>PAY2</italic>encodes a 42-kDa peroxisomal integral membrane protein essential for matrix protein import and peroxisome enlargement but not for peroxisome membrane proliferation</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1995</year><volume>270</volume><fpage>1429</fpage><lpage>1436</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7836411</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eitzen</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Titorenko</surname><given-names>VI</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Veenhuis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Szilard</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Rachubinski</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The <italic>Yarrowia lipolytica</italic> gene <italic>PAY5</italic>encodes a peroxisomal integral membrane protein homologous to the mammalian peroxisome assembly factor PAF-1</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1996</year><volume>271</volume><fpage>20300</fpage><lpage>20306</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8702763</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eitzen</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Szilard</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Rachubinski</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enlarged peroxisomes  are present in oleic acid-grown <italic>Yarrowia lipolytica</italic> overexpressing the  <italic>PEX16</italic>gene encoding an intraperoxisomal peripheral membrane peroxin</article-title><source>J  Cell Biol</source><year>1997</year><volume>137</volume><fpage>1265</fpage><lpage>1278</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9182661</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elgersma</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Vos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>van den Berg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>van Roermund</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Sluijs</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Distel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Tabak</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of the carboxyl-terminal peroxisomal targeting signal 1 in a homologous context in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae.  </italic></article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1996</year><volume>271</volume><fpage>26375</fpage><lpage>26382</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8824293</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Erdmann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Veenhuis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunau</surname><given-names>W-H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Peroxisomes: organelles at the crossroads</article-title><source>Trends Cell Biol</source><year>1997</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>400</fpage><lpage>407</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17708989</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elgersma</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Elgersma-Hooisma</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wenzel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>McCaffery</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Farquhar</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Subramani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A mobile PTS2 receptor for peroxisomal  protein import in <italic>Pichia pastoris. </italic></article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>1998</year><volume>140</volume><fpage>807</fpage><lpage>820</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9472033</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Franzusoff</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rothblatt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Schekman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of polypeptide transit through yeast secretory pathway</article-title><source>Methods Enzymol</source><year>1991</year><volume>194</volume><fpage>662</fpage><lpage>674</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2005814</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frydman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartl</surname><given-names>F-U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Principles of chaperone-assisted protein folding: differences between in vitro and in vivo mechanisms</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1996</year><volume>272</volume><fpage>1497</fpage><lpage>1502</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8633246</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frydman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nimmesgern</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohtsuka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartl</surname><given-names>F-U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Folding of nascent polypeptide chains in a high molecular mass assembly with molecular chaperones</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1994</year><volume>370</volume><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>117</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8022479</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Glover</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Rachubinski</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>a. Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>peroxisomal thiolase is imported as a dimer</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci  USA</source><year>1994</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>10541</fpage><lpage>10545</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7937990</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Glover</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Subramani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rachubinski</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mutagenesis of the amino targeting signal of <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>3-ketoacyl-CoA thiolase reveals conserved amino acids required for import into peroxisomes in vivo</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1994b</year><volume>269</volume><fpage>7558</fpage><lpage>7563</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8125978</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tramp</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Hang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Veenhuis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Peroxisomes induced in <italic>Candida Baden</italic>by methanol, oleic acid and D-alanine vary in metabolic function but share common integral membrane proteins</article-title><source>J Cell Sci</source><year>1990</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>193</fpage><lpage>204</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2258389</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hartl</surname><given-names>F-U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular chaperones in cellular protein folding</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1996</year><volume>381</volume><fpage>571</fpage><lpage>580</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8637592</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hendrick</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartl</surname><given-names>F-U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular chaperone functions of heat-shock proteins</article-title><source>Annu Rev Biochem</source><year>1993</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>349</fpage><lpage>384</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8102520</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>H&#x000e4;usler</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Stierhof</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wirtz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Clayton</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Import of DHFR hybrid protein into glycosomes in vivo is not inhibited by the folate-analogue aminopterin</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>1996</year><volume>132</volume><fpage>311</fpage><lpage>324</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8636210</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Horwich</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Willison</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protein folding in the cell: functions of two families of molecular chaperone, hsp60 and TF55-TCP1</article-title><source>Phil Trans R  Soc Lond</source><year>1993</year><volume>339</volume><fpage>313</fpage><lpage>326</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8098536</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B29"><citation citation-type="other">Kunau, W.-H. 1998. Peroxisome biogenesis: from yeast to man. <italic>Curr. Opin. Microbiol.</italic> In press.</citation></ref><ref id="B30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kyhse-Andersen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Electroblotting of multiple gels: a simple apparatus without buffer tank for rapid transfer of proteins from polyacrylamide to nitrocellulose</article-title><source>J Biochem Biophys Methods</source><year>1984</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>203</fpage><lpage>209</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6530509</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laemmli</surname><given-names>UK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cleavage of structural proteins during the assembly of the head of bacteriophage T4</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1970</year><volume>227</volume><fpage>680</fpage><lpage>685</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5432063</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lanzetta</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Reinach</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Candia</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An improved assay for nanomole amounts of inorganic phosphate</article-title><source>Anal Biochem</source><year>1979</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>97</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">161695</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Mullen</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name><surname>Trelease</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oilseed isocitrate lyases lacking their essential type I peroxisomal targeting signal are piggybacked to glyoxysomes</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>1997</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>185</fpage><lpage>197</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9061950</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leiper</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Oatey</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name><surname>Danpure</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibition of alanine:glyoxylate aminotransferase 1 dimerization is a prerequisite for its peroxisome-to-mitochondrion mistargeting in primary hyperoxaluria type 1</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>1996</year><volume>135</volume><fpage>939</fpage><lpage>951</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8922378</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicaud</surname><given-names>J-M</given-names></name><name><surname>Skinner</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><name><surname>Vergnolle</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kader</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bankaitis</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaillardin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A phosphatidylinositol/phosphatidylcholine  transfer protein is required for differentiation of the dimorphic yeast <italic>Yarrowia lipolytica</italic>from the yeast to the mycelial form</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>1994</year><volume>125</volume><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>127</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8138566</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dyer</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Quick</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Redox-sensitive homodimerization of Pex11p: a proposed mechanism to regulate peroxisomal division</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>1996</year><volume>135</volume><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>137</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8858168</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marzioch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Erdmann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Veenhuis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunau</surname><given-names>W-H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>PAS7</italic>encodes a novel yeast member of the WD-40 protein family essential for import of 3-oxoacyl-CoA thiolase, a PTS2-containing protein, into peroxisomes</article-title><source>EMBO (Eur Mol Biol Organ) J</source><year>1994</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>4908</fpage><lpage>4918</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7957058</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McNew</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An oligomeric protein is imported into peroxisomes in vivo</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>1994</year><volume>127</volume><fpage>1245</fpage><lpage>1257</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7962087</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McNew</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The targeting and assembly of peroxisomal proteins: some old rules do not apply</article-title><source>Trends Biochem Sci</source><year>1996</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>54</fpage><lpage>58</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8851661</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B40"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Motley</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hettema</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Hogenhout</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Brites</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>ten Asbroek</surname><given-names>ALMA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wijburg</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name><surname>Baas</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Heijmans</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tabak</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name><name><surname>Wanders</surname><given-names>RJA</given-names></name><name><surname>Distel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rhizomelic chondrodysplasia punctata is a peroxisomal targeting disease caused by a non-functional PTS2 receptor</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>1997</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>377</fpage><lpage>380</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9090382</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B41"><citation citation-type="other">Nicaud, J.-M., A. Le Clainche, M.-T. Le Dall, H. Wang, and C. Gaillardin. 1998.  <italic>Yarrowia lipolytica</italic>, a yeast model for the genetic studies of hydroxy fatty acids  biotransformation into lactones. <italic>J. Mol. Catal. B Enzymatic.</italic> 151: In press.</citation></ref><ref id="B42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nuttley</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Brade</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaillardin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Eitzen</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Glover</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Aitchison</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Rachubinski</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rapid identification and characterization of peroxisomal assembly mutants in <italic>Yarrowia lipolytica. </italic></article-title><source>Yeast</source><year>1993</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>507</fpage><lpage>517</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B43"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pause</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Diestelk&#x000f6;tter</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Heid</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Just</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cytosolic factors mediate protein insertion into the peroxisomal membrane</article-title><source>FEBS (Fed Eur  Biochem Soc) Lett</source><year>1997</year><volume>414</volume><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>98</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9305739</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B44"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Purdue</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Lazarow</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Peroxisomal biogenesis: multiple pathways of protein import</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1994</year><volume>269</volume><fpage>30065</fpage><lpage>30068</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7982905</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B45"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Purdue</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Skoneczny</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lazarow</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rhizomelic chondrodysplasia punctata is caused by deficiency of human Pex7p, a homologue of the yeast PTS2 receptor</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>1997</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>381</fpage><lpage>384</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9090383</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B46"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rachubinski</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Subramani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How proteins penetrate peroxisomes</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1995</year><volume>83</volume><fpage>525</fpage><lpage>528</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7585954</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B47"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Radu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Blobel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The peptide repeat domain of nucleoporin Nup98 as a docking site in transport across the nuclear pore complex</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1995</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>215</fpage><lpage>222</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7736573</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B48"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rehling</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Marzioch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Niesen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Wittke</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Veenhuis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunau</surname><given-names>W-H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The import receptor for the peroxisomal targeting signal 2  (PTS2) in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> is encoded by the <italic>PAS7</italic>gene</article-title><source>EMBO  (Eur Mol Biol Organ) J</source><year>1996</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>2901</fpage><lpage>2913</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8670791</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B49"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Raymond</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamashiro</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Methods for studying the yeast vacuole</article-title><source>Methods Enzymol</source><year>1991</year><volume>194</volume><fpage>644</fpage><lpage>661</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1706462</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B50"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sanders</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitfield</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Schekman</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sec61p and BiP directly facilitate polypeptide translocation into the ER</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1992</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>353</fpage><lpage>365</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1568250</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B51"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schatz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Dobberstein</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Common principles of protein translocation across membranes</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1996</year><volume>271</volume><fpage>1519</fpage><lpage>1526</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8599107</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B52"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Szilard</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Marelli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rachubinski</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The peroxin  Pex17p of the yeast <italic>Yarrowia lipolytica</italic>is associated peripherally with the peroxisomal membrane and is required for the import of a subset of matrix proteins</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>1997</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>2511</fpage><lpage>2520</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9111320</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B53"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Subramani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Components involved in peroxisome import, biogenesis, proliferation, turnover, and movement</article-title><source>Pharmacol Rev</source><year>1998</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>188</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B54"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Szilard</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Titorenko</surname><given-names>VI</given-names></name><name><surname>Veenhuis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rachubinski</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pay32p of the yeast <italic>Yarrowia lipolytica</italic>is an intraperoxisomal component of the matrix protein translocation machinery</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>1995</year><volume>131</volume><fpage>1453</fpage><lpage>1469</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8522603</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B55"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thieringer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Shio</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lazarow</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Peroxisomes in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>: immunofluorescence analysis and import of catalase A into isolated peroxisomes</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>1991</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>510</fpage><lpage>522</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1986244</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B56"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Titorenko</surname><given-names>VI</given-names></name><name><surname>Rachubinski</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mutants of the yeast <italic>Yarrowia lipolytica</italic>defective in protein exit from the endoplasmic reticulum are also defective in peroxisome biogenesis</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>1998</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>2789</fpage><lpage>2803</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9566898</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B57"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Titorenko</surname><given-names>VI</given-names></name><name><surname>Eitzen</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rachubinski</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mutations in the  <italic>PAY5</italic> gene of the yeast <italic>Yarrowia lipolytica</italic>cause the accumulation of multiple subpopulations of peroxisomes</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1996</year><volume>271</volume><fpage>20307</fpage><lpage>20314</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8702764</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B58"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Titorenko</surname><given-names>VI</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogrydziak</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rachubinski</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Four distinct  secretory pathways serve protein secretion, cell surface growth, and peroxisome biogenesis in the yeast <italic>Yarrowia lipolytica. </italic></article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>1997</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>5210</fpage><lpage>5226</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9271399</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B59"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walton</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wendland</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Subramani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rachubinski</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Welch</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Involvement of 70-kD heat-shock proteins in peroxisomal import</article-title><source>J  Cell Biol</source><year>1994</year><volume>125</volume><fpage>1037</fpage><lpage>1046</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8195287</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B60"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walton</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Subramani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Import of stably folded proteins into peroxisomes</article-title><source>Mol Biol Cell</source><year>1995</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>675</fpage><lpage>683</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7579687</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B61"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Waterham</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>de Vries</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Cregg</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Peroxisomal  targeting, import, and assembly of alcohol oxidase in <italic>Pichia pastoris. </italic></article-title><source>J Cell  Biol</source><year>1997</year><volume>139</volume><fpage>1419</fpage><lpage>1431</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9396748</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B62"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Luckey</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lazarow</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Three peroxisome protein packaging pathways suggested by selective permeabilization of yeast mutants defective in peroxisome biogenesis</article-title><source>Mol Biol Cell</source><year>1993</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1351</fpage><lpage>1359</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7909460</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B63"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lazarow</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>PEB1 (PAS7)</italic> in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>encodes a hydrophilic, intra-peroxisomal protein that is a member of the WD repeat family and is essential for the import of thiolase into peroxisomes</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>1995</year><volume>129</volume><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>80</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7535304</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B64"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lazarow</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Peb1p (Pas7p) is an intraperoxisomal receptor for the NH<sub>2</sub>-terminal, type 2, peroxisomal targeting signal of thiolase:  Peb1p itself is targeted to peroxisome by an NH<sub>2</sub>-terminal peptide</article-title><source>J Cell  Biol</source><year>1996</year><volume>132</volume><fpage>325</fpage><lpage>334</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8636211</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list><fn-group><fn><p>Address all correspondence to Richard A. Rachubinski, Department of  Cell Biology and Anatomy, University of Alberta, Medical Sciences  Building 5-14, Edmonton, Alberta T6G 2H7, Canada. Tel.: (403) 492-9868. Fax: (403) 492-9278. E-mail: <email>rick.rachubinski&#x00040;ualberta.ca</email></p></fn></fn-group></back></article>


