<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Cell Biol</journal-id><journal-title>The Journal of Cell Biology</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0021-9525</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1540-8140</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Rockefeller University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">10366589</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2133151</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Chs7p, a New Protein Involved in the Control of Protein Export from the  Endoplasmic Reticulum that Is Specifically Engaged in the Regulation of  Chitin Synthesis in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>  </article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Trilla</surname><given-names>Jose A.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dur&#x000e1;n</surname><given-names>Angel</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Roncero</surname><given-names>Cesar</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="N0x1d14fb0N0x3a63558">Instituto de Microbiolog&#x000ed;a Bioqu&#x000ed;mica, Consejo Superior de Investigaciones Cient&#x000ed;ficas/Universidad de Salamanca and  Departamento de Microbiolog&#x000ed;a y Gen&#x000e9;tica, Universidad de Salamanca 37007 Salamanca, Spain </aff><author-notes><fn><p>Address correspondence to Cesar Roncero, Departamento de Microbiolog&#x000ed;a y Gen&#x000e9;tica. CSIC/Universidad de Salamanca, Edificio Departamental, R-219, Avda Campo Charro s/n, 37007 Salamanca, Spain. Tel.:  34-923-294733. Fax: 34-923-224876. E-mail: <email>crm&#x00040;gugu.usal.es</email></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>14</day><month>6</month><year>1999</year></pub-date><volume>145</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1153</fpage><lpage>1163</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>12</month><year>1999</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>7</day><month>5</month><year>1999</year></date></history><copyright-year>1999</copyright-year><abstract><p>The <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae CHS7</italic> gene  encodes an integral membrane protein located in the  ER which is directly involved in chitin synthesis  through the regulation of chitin synthase III (CSIII) activity. In the absence of <italic>CHS7</italic> product, Chs3p, but  not other secreted proteins, is retained in the ER, leading to a severe defect in CSIII activity and consequently, to a reduced rate of chitin synthesis. In addition, <italic>chs7</italic> null mutants show the yeast phenotypes  associated with a lack of chitin: reduced mating efficiency and lack of the chitosan ascospore layer, clear indications of Chs7p function throughout the <italic>S</italic>. <italic>cerevisiae</italic>  biological cycle.</p><p><italic>CHS3</italic> overexpression does not lead to increased levels of CSIII because the Chs3p excess is retained in the  ER. However, joint overexpression of <italic>CHS3</italic> and <italic>CHS7</italic>  increases the export of Chs3p from the ER and this is  accompanied by a concomitant increase in CSIII activity, indicating that the amount of Chs7p is a limiting factor for CSIII activity. Accordingly, <italic>CHS7</italic> transcription  is increased when elevated amounts of chitin synthesis  are detected.</p><p>These results show that Chs7p forms part of a new  mechanism specifically involved in Chs3p export from  the ER and consequently, in the regulation of CSIII activity.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>chitin synthesis</kwd><kwd>chitin synthase III</kwd><kwd>endoplasmic reticulum export</kwd><kwd>morphogenesis</kwd><kwd>cell wall</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p>C<sc>hitin</sc> is a structural polymer present in most fungal  cell walls. Although its amount varies from 1&#x02013;30%  of the cell wall, it has been shown to be indispensable for the maintenance of the fungal cell (reviewed in  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Cabib et al., 1996</xref>). In <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>, chitin accounts for only 3% of the cell wall mass. However, some  evidence indicates that <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> cannot survive without  chitin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Bowers et al., 1974</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">Shaw et al., 1991</xref>). <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>  contains three different chitin synthases (CSs)<sup>1</sup> responsible for the synthesis of this polymer: CSI acts as a repair  enzyme at the time of cytokinesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Cabib et al., 1989</xref>,  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">1992</xref>); CSII makes the chitin disk of the primary septum  that separates mother and daughter cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">Sburlati and  Cabib, 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">Shaw et al., 1991</xref>); and CSIII makes 90&#x02013;95%  of the cellular chitin, including the chitin synthesized  during mating and sporulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">Roncero et al., 1988b</xref>;  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">Valdivieso et al., 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Pammer et al., 1992</xref>). Each CS contains at least one catalytic subunit encoded respectively by  <italic>CHS1</italic>, <italic>CHS2</italic>, and <italic>CHS3</italic> gene products (reviewed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Bulawa, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Cabib et al., 1996</xref>). These genes show significant similarity, but the differences among them should  account for the different kinetics and regulatory requirements of each CS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Choi and Cabib, 1994</xref>).</p><p>The fact that each CS has a different cellular function  suggests that the activity of each enzyme must be spatially  and temporally regulated. In the case of CSI and CSII, it  has been proposed that these would be regulated at the  transcriptional (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Pammer et al., 1992</xref>) and posttranslational  (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Choi et al., 1994a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">Uchida et al., 1996</xref>) levels, the latter  mechanism achieved through proteolytic processing (reviewed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Cabib et al., 1996</xref>). By contrast, CSIII is not  proteolytically regulated and transcriptional regulation of  <italic>CHS3</italic>, although it does exist (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Pammer et al., 1992</xref>), does  not control CSIII activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Choi et al., 1994a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Chuang and  Schekman, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Cos et al., 1998</xref>). In addition to <italic>CHS3</italic>,  three other genes, <italic>CHS4</italic>, <italic>CHS5</italic>, and <italic>CHS6</italic>, have been  shown to be required for CSIII activity (reviewed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Bulawa, 1993</xref>). Chs4p has a dual function: it is a direct activator of CSIII activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">Trilla et al., 1997</xref>) and at the same  time is responsible for anchoring, through Bni4p, of Chs3p  to the septin ring (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">DeMarini et al., 1997</xref>). Chs5p is involved in the polarized transport of Chs3p in specialized  vesicles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">Santos and Snyder, 1997</xref>). However, its function  is not restricted to Chs3p transport, since it is also involved  in the transport of other proteins during mating (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">Santos et al.,  1997</xref>). Chs6p is required for Chs3p transport in a later step  than Chs5p (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">Ziman et al., 1998</xref>). It also has been shown  that Chs3p is subject to endosomal internalization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">Ziman  et al., 1996</xref>), although the biological meaning of this process is not known. It therefore seems clear that the function of CSIII mainly depends on proper Chs3p transport  and localization.</p><p>In addition to temporally and spatially regulated chitin  synthesis during vegetative growth, there are several circumstances in the life cycle of <italic>S</italic>. <italic>cerevisiae</italic> where chitin  synthesis is altered. Chitin synthesis is significantly increased during mating and Calcofluor treatment and in  both instances this increase depends on CSIII activity  (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">Roncero et al., 1988a</xref>,b). During sporulation, CSIII is required to make chitin the precursor of chitosan, a component of the outermost layer of the ascospore wall (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Pammer  et al., 1992</xref>). However, it is not yet known if chitin/chitosan  synthesis is increased during this process. Despite all these  findings, there is still no clear picture of how <italic>CHS</italic> genes  can regulate chitin synthesis in vivo, and to date only  Chs4p can be envisaged as a direct regulator of CSIII activity.</p><p>This paper addresses <italic>CHS7</italic>, a new <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> gene required for CSIII activity. <italic>CHS7</italic> is involved in the regulation of CSIII activity by controlling Chs3p export from the  ER. The significance of this specific control mechanism is  discussed within the framework of the hierarchy of proteins involved in the control of CSIII activity.</p><sec id="MaterialsMethods" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Strains, Growth Conditions, and Genetic Methods</title><p>Yeast strains used in this study are listed in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="TI">I</xref>. <italic>S</italic>. <italic>cerevisiae</italic> strains  were grown in YEPD (1% Bacto yeast extract, 2% peptone, 2% glucose)  or SD medium (2% glucose, 0.7% Difco yeast nitrogen base without  amino acids, 0.07% amino acids solid mix). Growth supplements were added  to SD medium when required. <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> was grown in LB medium  (1% bactotriptone, 0.5% bacto yeast extract, 1% NaCl) supplemented  with 100 &#x003bc;g/ml ampicillin. Standard methods were used for DNA manipulations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">Sambrook et al., 1989</xref>) and yeast genetics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Rose et al., 1990</xref>). </p><p>Calcofluor resistance was tested by a plate assay (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">Valdivieso et al.,  1991</xref>) in SD medium buffered with 50 mM potassium hydrogen phthalate,  pH 6.1, and supplemented with different Calcofluor concentrations (50&#x02013; 1,000 &#x003bc;g/ml; Bayer Industrial Corporation). Calcofluor staining was observed after growing cells in the presence of 75 &#x003bc;g/ml Calcofluor for 2 h at  30&#x000b0;C.</p></sec><sec><title>Construction of Plasmids and Strains</title><p>Gene replacement was performed basically as described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">Rothstein  (1983)</xref>. The &#x00394;<italic>chs7-1</italic> disruption was constructed by replacing the 1.2-kb  NdeI&#x02013;NdeI fragment containing the <italic>CHS7</italic> coding region (from nucleotide  &#x0002b;24&#x02013;297, downstream from the stop codon) with the <italic>HIS3</italic> gene, thus creating pTM10. The NdeI downstream site is still 724 bp ahead of the next  ATG, therefore this deletion should not affect the YHR143 open reading  frame (ORF). Strains W303-1A and Y1306 were transformed with a linear  3.5-kb EcoRV&#x02013;EcoRV fragment from pTM10, containing the <italic>chs7</italic>::<italic>HIS3</italic>  gene, giving rise to strains JAY6 and JAY27. The &#x00394;<italic>chs7-2</italic> disruption was  constructed by replacement of the 1.2-kb NdeI&#x02013;NdeI fragment with the  <italic>HIS2</italic> gene, affording pTM100. By digestion of pTM100 with SacI, a 4.1-kb  fragment containing the <italic>chs7</italic>::<italic>HIS2</italic> gene was used to transform strains  HVY374 and HVY376, creating strains JAY25 and JAY26. The &#x00394;<italic>chs6-1</italic>  disruption was constructed using a pGEM-<italic>CHS6</italic> plasmid, in which the  1.6-kb BalI&#x02013;EcoRI internal fragment of <italic>CHS6</italic> was replaced with the  <italic>URA3</italic> gene, thus creating pTM12. By digestion of pTM12 with SalI&#x02013;SphI,  a 3.0-kb fragment containing the <italic>chs6</italic>::<italic>URA3</italic> gene was used to transform  strain Y1306, obtaining JAY28. Correct replacement of the <italic>CHS7</italic> and  <italic>CHS6</italic> loci was determined by PCR analysis and tests of Calcofluor resistance. To construct a fusion gene encoding the full-length Chs7p fused to  the green fluorescent protein (GFP; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">Martin-Chalfie et al., 1994</xref>), a NotI  site was created by directed mutagenesis at the end of the <italic>CHS7</italic> coding  region to give pTM14. A 0.7-kb NotI&#x02013;NotI fragment from pTM13 containing the GFP-encoding sequence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Fernandez-Abalos et al., 1998</xref>) was  ligated into NotI-digested pTM14, thus creating pTM15 (pRS316::<italic>CHS7-GFP</italic>). <italic>CHS7</italic>::<italic>3XHA</italic> construction (pTM16) was achieved by inserting a  115-bp NotI&#x02013;NotI DNA fragment containing three copies of the hemagglutinin epitope (HA) at the same NotI site of pTM14. The functionality  of the hybrid proteins was determined by complementation of the phenotypes associated with &#x00394;<italic>chs7</italic>. For intracellular localization of Sec63p,  15Daub cells were transformed with plasmid pRS315::<italic>SEC63-MYC</italic>,  kindly provided by R. Schekman (University of California, Berkeley, CA;  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">Lyman and Schekman, 1997</xref>).</p><p>Multicopy plasmids pRS423::<italic>CHS3</italic> or pRS423::<italic>CHS3-3XHA</italic> were obtained by inserting the EcoRI&#x02013;SalI fragment of pHV7 that contains either  <italic>CHS3</italic> or <italic>CHS3-3XHA</italic> genes into pRS423 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Cos et al., 1998</xref>). pRS425:: <italic>CHS4</italic> was done by cloning the <italic>CHS4</italic> gene as a BamHI fragment into  pRS425 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">Trilla et al., 1997</xref>). Similarly, for construction of pRS426::<italic>CHS7</italic>,  <italic>CHS7</italic> gene was cloned as a EcoRV&#x02013;StuI fragment (pTM11; this work)  into pRS426. Plasmids pRS423, pRS425, and pRS426 have been previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Christianson et al., 1992</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Chitin and Chitin Synthase Activity Determinations</title><p>Chitin measurements were performed as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Bulawa et al., 1986</xref>)  using chitinase from <italic>Serratia marcescens</italic> (<named-content content-type="company" xlink:href="sigma">Sigma Chemical Co.</named-content>). GlcNAc  release was determined colorimetrically by the method of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">Reissig et al.  (1955)</xref>. Total amounts of chitin are expressed as nanomoles of GlcNAc  liberated per 100 mg of cells. For CS activity assays, total cell membranes  were prepared from 250 ml of exponentially growing cells (2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>7</sup> cells/ml)  as described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">Valdivieso et al. (1991)</xref>. CS activity was measured essentially as described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Choi and Cabib (1994)</xref>: CSI activity was assayed in  50 mM Tris-HCl, pH 6.5, and 5 mM magnesium acetate; CSII activity was  assayed in 50 mM Tris-HCl, pH 8.0, and 5 mM cobalt acetate; and CSIII  was assayed in 50 mM Tris-HCl, pH 8.0, with 5 mM cobalt acetate and  nickel acetate. For the proteolytic activation step, 2 &#x003bc;l of trypsin (1&#x02013;3 mg/ml)  was added to the reaction medium and proteolysis activation was stopped  after 15 min of incubation by adding 2 &#x003bc;l of soybean trypsin inhibitor solution. 1.1 mM UDP[<sup>14</sup>C]GlcNAc (Nycomed <named-content content-type="company" xlink:href="amersham">Amersham</named-content>; 400 cpm/nmol)  was used as substrate for the reaction. Newly synthesized chitin was determined by measuring the radioactivity incorporated into the insoluble material after the addition of 10% trichloroacetic acid and filtration through  glass fiber filters (Whatman Inc.; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Choi and Cabib, 1994</xref>). Specific activity  is expressed as nanomoles of GlcNAc incorporated per hour per milligram of protein.</p></sec><sec><title>Direct and Indirect Immunofluorescence</title><p>Localization of Chs7p-GFP was observed in exponentially growing cells  containing pTM15. After mounting, images were captured with a <named-content content-type="company" xlink:href="zeiss">Zeiss</named-content> laser-confocal microscope (LSM 510) with a 63&#x000d7; objective and processed  with Adobe Photoshop software. Localization of Chs3p-3XHA by indirect immunofluorescence was carried out as described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">B&#x000e4;hler and Pringle (1998)</xref> with slight modifications. Spheroplasts were obtained by treatment with 5 &#x003bc;g/ml Zymolyase 100T (Seikagaku) for 30&#x02013;45 min at 30&#x000b0;C in  PEMS (100 mM Pipes, 1 mM EGTA, 1 mM MgSO<sub>4</sub>, 1.2 M sorbitol, pH  6.9) buffer. Mouse HA.11 anti-HA mAb (Berkeley Antibody Co.) was  used at a 1:100 dilution for 16 h at 4&#x000b0;C. Cy3-conjugated anti-mouse secondary antibody (<named-content content-type="company" xlink:href="sigma">Sigma Chemical Co.</named-content>) was used at a 1:300 dilution for 45  min at 25&#x000b0;C. After mounting, images were captured with a <named-content content-type="company" xlink:href="zeiss">Zeiss</named-content> laser-confocal microscope (LSM 510) with a 63&#x000d7; objective. For these experiments,  an epitope-tagged version of Chs3p in cells whose chromosomal locus had  been replaced with <italic>CHS3-3XHA</italic> was used (Strain Y1306; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">Santos and Snyder, 1997</xref>). All strains used for immunofluorescence were derived from  Y1306. Sec63p-Myc was immunolocalized with a similar protocol, but using supernatants of 9E10 hybridome at 1:100 dilution as primary antibodies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Evan et al., 1985</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Northern Blot Analysis</title><p>For Northern blot analysis, total RNA was prepared as described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">Sambrook et al. (1989)</xref> from cells grown under different conditions. 12.5 &#x003bc;g of  total RNA was loaded per lane and after electrophoresis, transferred to  Hybond membranes (Nycomed <named-content content-type="company" xlink:href="amersham">Amersham</named-content>). Hybridization was carried  out as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">Sambrook et al., 1989</xref>) using a 1.2-kb NdeI&#x02013;NdeI fragment from <italic>CHS7</italic> as a probe. For quantitative analysis, Northern blots  were exposed to PhosphorImager screens (BASS 1500; FujiFilm). &#x003b1;-Factor treatment for Northern blot experiments was carried out in exponentially growing cells using YEPD medium supplemented with 5 &#x003bc;M &#x003b1;-factor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Choi et al., 1994a</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Subcellular Fractionation Experiments</title><p>Cell lysates were prepared (as described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">Santos and Snyder, 1997</xref>) from  a JAY25 strain transformed with pRS315::<italic>SEC63-MYC</italic> and pRS316:: <italic>CHS7-3XHA</italic> plasmids. In brief, exponentially growing cells in SD medium (1.5 g wet wt), were resuspended in 5 ml of 17% sucrose (wt/vol) in  50 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.5, and 1 mM EDTA containing the protease inhibitor cocktail (1 mM phenylmethanesulfonil fluoride and 1 mg/ml each of  leupeptin, pepstatin, and aprotinin), and broken by vortexing with glass  beads. Lysated cells were centrifuged at 1,500 <italic>g</italic> for 10 min. The cleared  supernatant was layered on top of 33 ml of a linear sucrose gradient (10&#x02013; 65% wt/vol) in 50 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.5, 1 mM EDTA, and centrifuged in  a SW28 rotor at 25,000 rpm for 20 h at 4&#x000b0;C. 1.25 ml fractions were collected from the bottom using a peristaltic pump. Equal volumes of each  fraction were examined for their content of Pma1p, Kre2p, Sec63p-MYC,  and Chs7p-HA, determined by SDS-PAGE and immunoblot with their  respective antibodies. Rabbit polyclonal antibodies (1:30,000 dilution;  kindly provided by Dr. R. Serrano, Universidad de Valencia, Valencia,  Spain) were used to detect Pma1p, a typical plasmatic membrane marker.  Kre2p, a medial-Golgi compartment protein (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">Lussier et al., 1995</xref>), was detected using polyclonal antibodies (1:1,000 dilution) kindly supplied by H.  Bussey (McGill University, Montreal, Q&#x000fa;ebec, Canada). Sec63-MYC, an  ER marker, was detected using monoclonal anti-MYC antibodies (supernatants of 9E10 hybridome, 1:5,000 dilution). Mouse HA.11 anti-HA  mAb (Berkeley Antibody Co.; 1:2,000 dilution) was used to detect Chs7p-HA. In all cases, Western blots were developed using ECL (Nycomed  <named-content content-type="company" xlink:href="amersham">Amersham</named-content>).</p></sec><sec><title>Western Blot Analysis of Chs3p</title><p>Chs3p-3XHA expression levels were determined in total cellular extracts  by Western blot analysis as described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Cos et al. (1998)</xref>. Blotted proteins  were incubated with mouse HA.11 anti-HA antibody (Berkeley Antibody  Co.; 1:2,000 dilution) and developed using ECL (Nycomed <named-content content-type="company" xlink:href="amersham">Amersham</named-content>).</p><p>Endoglycosidase H (EndoH) treatment was carried out on Chs3p-3XHA after immunoprecipitation under denaturing conditions as described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Cos et al. (1998)</xref>. The immunoprecipitated complex was subjected to Western blot analysis.</p></sec><sec><title>Other Methods</title><p>Protein was measured by the method of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Lowry et al. (1951)</xref>. Yeast strains  were mated quantitatively as described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">Santos et al. (1997)</xref>. The frequency of diploid formation was estimated as the number of diploids  formed out of the total number of cells. Exoglucanase activity was assayed  as described by San Segundo et al. (1993); the method is based on the release of reducing sugar groups from laminarin, which were quantified by  the method of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">Somogyi (1952)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Nelson (1957)</xref>. The &#x003b1;-factor secretion  assay was developed as described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">Michaelis and Herskowitz (1988)</xref>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Isolation of CHS7</title><p>A new screening for <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> mutants resistant to Calcofluor was carried out to identify new genes involved in  chitin synthesis. Ethyl methanesulfonate-mutagenized JAY1  cells (&#x0223c;20% of survival) were plated in YEPD media supplemented with 1 mg/ml Calcofluor exactly as described in  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">Roncero et al. (1988b)</xref>. After 4 d of incubation, 53 bona  fide independent clones which were able to grow were selected (mutation frequency 1.1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup>). These mutants  were back-crossed with previously known Calcofluor resistant and chitin-deficient mutants (<italic>chs3</italic>, <italic>chs4</italic>, and <italic>chs5</italic>).  Diploid analysis indicated that most mutants belonged to  <italic>chs3</italic> (83%), <italic>chs4</italic> (5.7%), or <italic>chs5</italic> (5.7%) complementation  groups. Only three of them, <italic>cwr6</italic>, <italic>cwr12</italic>, and <italic>crw19</italic> (Calcofluor white resistant), defined new complementation  groups. Further genetic testing indicated that mutants  <italic>cwr12</italic> and <italic>cwr19</italic> belonged to the same group. A preliminary characterization of these mutants indicated that all  showed defects in chitin synthesis.</p><p>The genes affected in <italic>cwr12</italic> and <italic>cwr6</italic> mutants were  cloned by complementation of the Calcofluor resistant  phenotype after transformation with a centromeric library  (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">Rose et al., 1987</xref>). Complementation was confirmed to be  dependent on the presence of plasmid and complementing  plasmids were isolated in <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic> for further work. Originally isolated plasmids were subjected to endonuclease restriction mapping and the results obtained indicated that  the plasmid complementing <italic>cwr12</italic> contained the previously described <italic>CHS6/CSD3</italic> gene (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Bulawa, 1992</xref>). Therefore, its study was discontinued. The DNA fragment that  complemented the <italic>cwr6</italic> mutant contains several ORFs  (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref> A). Subcloning experiments indicated that the minimum fragment able to complement was the StuI&#x02013;EcoRV  fragment included in pTM11. With these results, we were  able to obtain a preliminary identification of YHR0142w  as the gene that complements <italic>cwr6</italic> mutation. Due to the  defect in CS observed in <italic>cwr6</italic> mutant, we named this gene  <italic>CHS7</italic> following accepted nomenclature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Cabib, 1994</xref>). </p><p><italic>CHS7</italic> encodes a protein of 316 amino acids that contains six or seven putative transmembrane domains (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>,  B and C). It has no significant homology with any known  protein, although the search programs showed limited homologies with other transmembrane regions.</p></sec><sec><title>Characterization of chs7 Mutants</title><p>We made several <italic>chs7</italic> null mutants by replacing the <italic>CHS7</italic>  ORF by different auxotrophic markers (Materials and  Methods). Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="TII">II</xref> shows some of the characteristic phenotypes associated with this mutation. <italic>chs7</italic> null mutants  had only 13.6% of the wild-type chitin, a defect that was  associated with a comparable decrease in CSIII activity.  Due to this defect in chitin synthesis, <italic>chs7</italic> cells were resistant to 1 mg/ml Calcofluor and they did not show enlarged  septa after Calcofluor treatment. In addition, &#x00394;<italic>chs7/</italic>&#x00394;<italic>chs7</italic>  diploids showed compact ascospores, a defect associated  with the absence of the chitosan layer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Pammer et al.,  1992</xref>). <italic>chs7</italic> mutations also reduced their mating efficiency  to a level similar to that of <italic>chs3</italic> mutants (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="TII">II</xref>). It  should be noted that the original <italic>cwr6</italic> mutants showed  similar, but less pronounced phenotypes. As expected,  wild-type <italic>CHS7</italic> (YHR0142w) in a centromeric plasmid  complemented the phenotypes observed in the null (Table  <xref ref-type="table" rid="TII">II</xref>, last column) or point (not shown) <italic>chs7</italic> mutants. Once  we had constructed null mutants, we confirmed the allelism between YHR142w and <italic>CHS7</italic> genetically. Diploid  strain <italic>yhr142</italic>::<italic>HIS3</italic>/<italic>cwr6</italic> was resistant to Calcofluor and  analysis of 18 tetrads in this cross showed a Calcofluor  resistance segregation of 4:0. Therefore, <italic>CHS7</italic> and YHR142w must be the same gene. </p></sec><sec><title>Analysis of CHS7 Expression</title><p>To analyze <italic>CHS7</italic> expression levels, we determined <italic>CHS7</italic>  mRNA levels in cells harvested after growth under different conditions. <italic>CHS7</italic> was detected in all conditions (Fig.  <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>) as a single band of &#x0223c;1.1 kbp, in clear agreement with sequence data. Therefore, <italic>CHS7</italic> is expressed constitutively.  However, as shown in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> A, &#x003b1;-factor treatment (mimicking the mating process) increased <italic>CHS7</italic> expression 3.5  times after only 15 min; shortly after, vegetative levels  were resumed. Calcofluor treatment also increased <italic>CHS7</italic>  expression twofold (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> A, right). Despite its constitutive expression during vegetative growth, <italic>CHS7</italic> mRNA  levels were strongly increased during sporulation, reaching  a maximum (&#x0223c;24-fold more) after 10 h of sporulation  induction. Thereafter, <italic>CHS7</italic> mRNA levels slowly decreased. The typical expression pattern observed resembled that of a middle sporulation gene (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Krisak et al., 1994</xref>;  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Hepworth et al., 1998</xref>). These results allowed us to conclude that the expression of <italic>CHS7</italic> is transcriptionally regulated. In addition, <italic>CHS7</italic> transcription increased under all  growth conditions in which chitin synthesis was increased. </p></sec><sec><title>Chs7p Is a Membrane Protein Localized in the ER</title><p>Chs7p was tagged at the COOH terminus either with the  3XHA epitope or GFP (Materials and Methods) to determine the subcellular localization of Chs7p. Chimeric proteins Chs7p-3XHA or Chs7p-GFP complemented the Calcofluor resistance phenotype of <italic>chs7</italic> null mutant (JAY6  strain). In addition, the chimeric proteins restored wild-type levels of chitin synthesis in this strain, as determined  by chitin staining with Calcofluor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Cos et al., 1998</xref>). It can  be concluded that Chs7p-3XHA and Chs7p-GFP are fully  functional. Western blot analysis indicated that Chs7p-3XHA runs as a 35-kD protein that is localized in the particulate fraction (data not shown). Molecular size and  subcellular localization are in clear agreement with sequence predictions. Logarithmically growing cells expressing Chs7p-GFP from its own promoter showed the fluorescent staining depicted in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref> A. Chs7p-GFP was  uniformly localized in the nuclear periphery and in discrete patches associated with the cytoplasmic membrane.  This pattern coincides with that of Sec63p-Myc (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref> B),  a typical ER marker (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">Sadler et al., 1989</xref>). The vacuolar  staining observed seems to be an artifact because it does  not appear in all the cells and it does not show the typical  green color of GFP (data not shown). A similar distribution in the ER was observed by indirect immunofluorescence in cells expressing Chs7p-3XHA (data not shown).  No polarized distribution of Chs7p was observed in either  case. To confirm the immunofluorescence results a subcellular fractionation experiment was carried out. Total cellular extract were loaded into the top of a linear sucrose  density gradient and after centrifugation, Pma1p, Sec63p-MYC, Kre2p, and Chs7p-3XHA distribution was analyzed  by Western blot as described in Materials and Methods.  Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref> C shows that membrane protein Pma1p is localized  at the bottom of the gradient, mainly between fraction 1 to  4. Sec63p is localized from fractions 5 to 17, with a significant peak between the 11 to 15 fractions. Chs7p distribution is quite similar with that of Sec63, also showing maximum accumulation between 11 to 15 fractions. Golgi  compartment distribution, marked by Kre2p (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">Lussier et  al., 1995</xref>), is displaced to lighter fractions. Therefore, it can  be concluded that Chs7p is an ER membrane protein. </p></sec><sec><title>Chs7p Is Required for Chs3p Export from the ER</title><p>Functional CSIII activity depends on the appropriate synthesis and transport of Chs3p, its catalytic subunit. Chs7p  does not seem involved in the synthesis of Chs3p, since  Chs3p levels in &#x00394;<italic>chs7</italic> mutants are similar to those observed in wild-type (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref> A). Therefore, Chs7p could be  involved in the transport of Chs3p, a process that is mediated by Chs4p, Chs5p, and Chs6p. Following a strategy  similar to that used in the characterization of these genes,  we localized an HA-tagged version of Chs3p (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">Santos and  Snyder, 1997</xref>) in wild-type and <italic>chs7</italic>-null mutants. As previously reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Chuang and Schekman, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">Santos  and Snyder, 1997</xref>), Chs3p-3XHA localized in the base of  the emerging bud in wild-type strains (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref> C, a). However, in &#x00394;<italic>chs7</italic> mutants all the Chs3p-3XHA remained in  the ER, showing a perinuclear localization with partial association with the plasma membrane (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref> C, b, compare  to Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref> A). No polarized distribution of Chs3p-3XHA  was observed in &#x00394;<italic>chs7</italic> mutants. Higher magnification  (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref> C, c) indicated that the perinuclear staining was  punctuated, suggesting possible Chs3p aggregation. In addition, it is important to notice that although retained in  the ER, Chs3p-3XHA is correctly core-glycosylated in  <italic>chs7</italic> mutants (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref> B). Therefore, it can be concluded  that Chs7p is required for Chs3p export from the ER and  Chs7p must be the initial step in the hierarchy of proteins  required for CSIII activity. To confirm this hypothesis, we  analyzed the localization of Chs3p-3XHA in &#x00394;<italic>chs4</italic> &#x00394;<italic>chs7</italic>,  &#x00394;<italic>chs5</italic> &#x00394;<italic>chs7</italic>, or &#x00394;<italic>chs6</italic> &#x00394;<italic>chs7</italic> double mutants (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>, B, D,  and F). In all cases, Chs3p was retained in the ER and did  not show the localization described for &#x00394;<italic>chs4</italic>, &#x00394;<italic>chs5</italic>, or  &#x00394;<italic>chs6</italic> single mutants. As previously reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">DeMarini  et al., 1997</xref>), the distribution of Chs3p in &#x00394;<italic>chs4</italic> mutant was  polarized (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref> A). However, it was not as densely  packed at the base of the bud as in the wild-type (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref> C,  a). In &#x00394;<italic>chs5</italic> and &#x00394;<italic>chs6</italic> mutants, Chs3p was localized in internal vesicles (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>, C and E) without polarized distribution (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">Santos and Snyder, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">Ziman et al., 1998</xref>). From  these results, we conclude that the <italic>chs7</italic> mutation is epistatic to the <italic>chs</italic> mutations and that Chs7p is necessary for  Chs3p export from the ER.  </p></sec><sec><title>Chs7p Is Not Required for the Transport of other Proteins</title><p>Chs7p could play a general role in secretion or protein  sorting rather than being specific for chitin synthesis. To  test this hypothesis, we analyzed the behavior of several  secreted or sorted proteins in &#x00394;<italic>chs7</italic> mutants. &#x003b1;-factor and  exo-&#x003b2;(1-3)glucanase are two extracellular <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>  proteins that follow the normal secretion route. Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>  shows that the expression levels of these two proteins are  unaffected in &#x00394;<italic>chs7</italic> mutants. Similarly, CSI and CSII, the  other two CS activities present in <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>, showed  wild-type levels in &#x00394;<italic>chs7</italic> mutants. Apparently, Chs7p is  not required for secretion or sorting of other cellular proteins. </p><p>In addition to the regular secretion mechanism, <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> contains several other mechanisms involved in the  specific assembly and transport of certain proteins. Sorting  of vacuolar ATPase (v-ATPase) or several amino acid  permeases to cytoplasmic membrane has been shown to  depend on specific mechanisms of export from the ER (reviewed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Kaiser et al., 1997</xref>), raising the possibility of the  involvement of Chs7p is such processes. However, <italic>chs7</italic>  null mutants grew in glycerol and did not show synthetic  lethality with other amino acid auxotrophies, clear indications that v-ATPase and amino acid permeases function  properly in &#x00394;<italic>chs7</italic> mutants.</p></sec><sec><title>Chs7p Is a Limiting Factor in the Constitution of  Functional CSIII Activity</title><p>So far we have shown that Chs7p is required for Chs3p export. However, from Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> it is also apparent that <italic>CHS7</italic>  expression increases when more chitin is synthesized.  These observations suggest that the level of expression of  <italic>CHS7</italic> could be involved in the control of CSIII activity. If  so, this would explain why overexpression of <italic>CHS3</italic> does  not increase CSIII levels. To confirm this possibility, we  measured CSIII activity in strains overexpressing <italic>CHS</italic>  genes in different combinations. Overexpression of <italic>CHS3</italic>  (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Cos et al., 1998</xref>) or <italic>CHS7</italic> (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>) alone had no significant  effect on CSIII. As previously reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">Trilla et al.,  1997</xref>), overexpression of <italic>CHS4</italic> increased CSIII activity  and reduced its trypsin dependence. Joint overexpression  of <italic>CHS4</italic> and <italic>CHS3</italic> or <italic>CHS4</italic> and <italic>CHS7</italic> did not alter the  effect of <italic>CHS4</italic> on CSIII (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>). Cooverexpression of  <italic>CHS3</italic> and <italic>CHS7</italic> increased total CSIII almost four times.  However, basal activity was only increased 1.3 times and,  as a consequence, the activation factor by trypsin treatment was almost five times, in comparison with 1.6&#x02013;2  times, for the controls. Joint overexpression of <italic>CHS4</italic>,  <italic>CHS3</italic>, and <italic>CHS7</italic> did not further increase total CSIII activity. However, basal activity was increased more than  twofold. Therefore, activation by trypsin treatment was reduced to 2.5 in this case. Taken together, these results indicate that the amounts of Chs7p and Chs3p act as limiting  factors to total CSIII activity. In addition, Chs4p levels are  also limiting in the reconstitution of an in vitro fully active  CSIII. Overexpression of <italic>CHS3</italic>, <italic>CHS4</italic>, and <italic>CHS7</italic> genes  also induced a modest, but significant, increase in chitin  synthesis in vivo because a strain overexpressing these  three genes contained &#x0223c;68 &#x000b1; 11% more chitin than the  corresponding wild-type. This increase in chitin synthesis  was not observed if only <italic>CHS3</italic> and <italic>CHS7</italic> were overexpressed (not shown). </p><p>These results clearly suggest that the amount of Chs7p is  a limiting factor in vivo for CSIII activity and therefore,  could be the reason for the absence of an increase in CSIII  activity after <italic>CHS3</italic> overexpression. In fact, immunostaining of cells overexpressing <italic>CHS3-3XHA</italic> alone revealed a  severe retention of Chs3p in the ER even in the presence  of normal amounts of Chs7p (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref> A). Cooverexpression  of <italic>CHS3</italic> with <italic>CHS7</italic> dramatically reduced Chs3p accumulation in the ER (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref> B) and only residual staining was  observed at ER level. In this case, Chs3p was mainly localized in discrete patches in the cytoplasm, which in some  cells showed a polarized distribution (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref> B, arrows).  This distribution resembled an intermediate stage between &#x00394;<italic>chs6</italic>, &#x00394;<italic>chs5</italic>, and &#x00394;<italic>chs4</italic> mutants (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>, A, C, and  E). In sum, Chs3p excess is not retained in the ER in the  presence of high levels of Chs7p and hence, higher levels  of functional CSIII activity are achieved. </p></sec></sec><sec id="Discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Chitin is a minor, but essential polymer in the <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>  cell wall. Despite its low abundance, three different CS activities have been described in this yeast (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Cabib et al.,  1996</xref>). From a quantitative point of view, CSIII activity is  the most important, since it is involved in the synthesis of  90&#x02013;95% of cell wall chitin during vegetative growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">Roncero et al., 1988b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">Valdivieso et al., 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Bulawa, 1992</xref>). In  addition, it is required for the synthesis of new chitin that  takes place during the mating and sporulation processes  (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">Roncero et al., 1988b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Pammer et al., 1992</xref>).</p><p>Recently, it has been shown that the transcriptional regulation of <italic>CHS3</italic>, the gene that encodes the catalytic subunit of CSIII, is not the control mechanism for CSIII activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Choi et al., 1994a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Chuang and Schekman, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Cos  et al., 1998</xref>). Therefore, the identification of genes involved in the control of CSIII and chitin synthesis gains interest. Three proteins, Chs4p, Chs5p, and Chs6p, have  been identified, so far, as factors involved in the control of  CSIII activity. This report deals with the isolation of a new  gene, <italic>CHS7</italic>, also involved in the control of CSIII activity.  <italic>CHS7</italic> was isolated by complementation of a mutant resistant to Calcofluor, showing that this strategy still has potential, although most (83%) of the mutants isolated belong to the <italic>chs3</italic> complementation group.</p><p>&#x00394;<italic>chs7</italic> mutants have reduced levels of CSIII activity and  chitin in their cell walls (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="TII">II</xref>). This defect is comparable to that observed in <italic>chs3</italic> null mutants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Cos et al., 1998</xref>)  and stronger than that detected in <italic>chs4</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">Trilla et al., 1997</xref>),  <italic>chs5</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">Santos et al., 1997</xref>), or <italic>chs6</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Bulawa, 1993</xref>),  underscoring the relevance of this gene in the control of  CSIII activity. <italic>CHS7</italic> encodes a small protein with six or  seven putative transmembrane domains (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Kyte and Doolittle, 1982</xref>). Repeated database searches using different algorithms did not reveal any protein with significant homology to this protein. Some Chs7p regions with similarity  to other integral membrane proteins probably reflect the  hydrophobicity of the membrane-spanning domains rather  than protein conservation. Chs7p colocalized with Chs3p  in a crude particulate cell fraction and we therefore expected to find colocalization of Chs3p and Chs7p in the  plasma membrane. However, Chs7p was localized exclusively in the ER (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>), showing the typical localization  of other ER proteins such as Sec63p (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">Sadler et al., 1989</xref>;  Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref> B). This localization does not seem to be an artifact  of the chimeric Chs7p-GFP because similar results were  obtained with Chs7p-3XHA either in immunofluorescence (data not shown) or in subcellular fractionation (Fig.  <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref> C) experiments.</p><p>A functional explanation to account for this localization,  unique among Chs proteins, became apparent when we  observed that Chs3p accumulates at the ER in the absence  of Chs7p (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref> C, b). However, the Chs3p protein accumulated in the <italic>chs7</italic> mutant is correctly core-glycosylated  (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref> B), a clear indication that Chs3p is translocated and  correctly localized in the ER compartment in this mutant.  Therefore, Chs7p should be required for Chs3p export  from the ER. Moreover, the <italic>chs7</italic> mutation is epistatic  over other <italic>chs</italic> mutations, suggesting that Chs7p is the initial element in the hierarchy of proteins involved in CSIII  activity. These results explain the stronger defect in CSIII  activity observed in &#x00394;<italic>chs7</italic>, as compared with &#x00394;<italic>chs4</italic>, &#x00394;<italic>chs5</italic>,  or &#x00394;<italic>chs6</italic> mutants. It should be noted that Chs4p, Chs5p, or  Chs6p is not required for Chs3p export from the ER (Fig.  <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>). At this point, all the data points to the specific involvement of Chs7p in the export of Chs3p from the ER. However, the concomitant participation of other <italic>CHS</italic> products  in this export cannot be ruled out. Despite this, preliminary evidence indicates that Chs5p and Chs4p are efficiently exported in &#x00394;<italic>chs7</italic> mutants (data not shown) and  therefore, their participation is rather unlikely.</p><p>To date, there is no clear relationship between the levels  of expression of different <italic>CHS</italic> genes and chitin levels, although regulation of chitin synthesis has been observed  during the yeast life cycle (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">Roncero et al., 1988a</xref>,b; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Pammer et al., 1992</xref>). It should especially be stressed that overexpression of <italic>CHS3</italic> several times (&#x0223c;30) did not increase  CSIII activity or chitin levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Cos et al., 1998</xref>) and that  Chs3p levels remain stable during vegetative growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Choi  et al., 1994a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Chuang and Schekman, 1996</xref>). Under these  circumstances, only Chs4p can be envisaged as a controller  of CSIII activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Bulawa, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">Trilla et al., 1997</xref>). Might  Chs7p also be involved in the control of CSIII? Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>  shows some results in favor of this hypothesis, since <italic>CHS7</italic>  is the only <italic>CHS</italic> gene whose transcription is increased under all conditions in which chitin synthesis is seen to be increased: mating, Calcofluor treatment, and sporulation.  The increase in <italic>CHS7</italic> expression during sporulation is especially relevant and its pattern of induction resembles  that of a middle-late sporulation gene (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Hepworth et al.,  1998</xref>). The timing of expression places <italic>CHS7</italic> among  the sporulation genes involved in spore wall formation  (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Krisak et al., 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Hepworth et al., 1998</xref>). Further and  more direct confirmation of this hypothesis was achieved  after joint overexpression of <italic>CHS3</italic> and <italic>CHS7</italic> genes. CSIII  activity rose dramatically after the overexpression (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>),  reaching values several-fold higher than those of the control strain. This increase depends on joint overexpression,  suggesting the requirement of a balanced expression of  both genes.</p><p>Biochemically, we have shown that Chs7p acts as a limiting factor when Chs3p levels are increased, but the reason  at an intracellular level for this limitation remains unknown. As shown in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref> A, the cells cannot process an  excess of Chs3p and therefore, overexpression of <italic>CHS3</italic>  leads to Chs3p retention in the ER. However, if <italic>CHS7</italic> is  overexpressed in strains with high levels of Chs3p, this  protein is released from the ER (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref> B). In addition, the  localization of Chs3p in this strain resembles that observed  in &#x00394;<italic>chs6</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">Ziman et al., 1998</xref>) or &#x00394;<italic>chs5</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">Santos and Snyder,  1997</xref>) mutants (bright internal spots) with partial polarization (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref> B, arrows), as in <italic>chs4</italic> mutants (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref> B; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">DeMarini et al., 1997</xref>). These results indicate that although  Chs3p is efficiently exported from the ER, its transport to  its physiological site of action is impaired, probably due to  some other limiting factors. In this condition, the high  amount of active CSIII detected suggests that the limiting  factor, if it exists, should appear at the time of or after  <italic>CHS6</italic> participation, because mutations in genes that function early on the pathway show severe defects in CSIII activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Bulawa, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">Santos et al., 1997</xref>).</p><p>Chitin synthesis increases in <italic>S</italic>. <italic>cerevisiae</italic> during &#x003b1;-factor  treatment and this process is associated with the increase  in CSIII activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">Roncero et al., 1988a</xref>). Recently, it has  been shown that during &#x003b1;-factor treatment Chs3p levels  increase significantly (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Cos et al., 1998</xref>). However, no  Chs3p is localized at the ER (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">Santos and Snyder, 1997</xref>).  We have shown that the effect of increased Chs3p levels  on chitin synthesis depends mainly on correct Chs3p export from the ER. Therefore, the increase in <italic>CHS7</italic> transcription observed during &#x003b1;-factor treatment (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> A)  guarantees the export of excess Chs3p and the increase in  chitin synthesis required during this process.</p><p>Overexpression of <italic>CHS3</italic> and <italic>CHS7</italic> leads to a significant increase in CSIII activity. However, the activity  obtained under these conditions was highly zymogenic.  When we increased Chs4p levels in the same experiment,  the CSIII dependence on trypsin decreased significantly.  Therefore, it seems that Chs4p is also a limiting factor for  this activity. We cannot be sure if Chs4p function is mediated by proteolytic processing of CSIII, but it does seem  clear that in vitro trypsin treatment of CSIII resembles the  activation carried out in vivo by Chs4p. Moreover, the  strain carrying the triple overexpression also showed a significant increase in cellular chitin levels (68% higher than  controls) indicating that these genes not only participate in  the control of CSIII, but also in the in vivo control of chitin  synthesis. We cannot expect a perfect correlation between  CSIII and chitin levels, since there could be as yet undescribed cellular determinants participating in this process.  In addition, problems of interference could arise in the  replication of three independent plasmids that could mask  quantitative interpretation of these data. By contrast,  strains overexpressing only <italic>CHS3/CHS7</italic>, although they  showed high CSIII activity, did not show any increase in  chitin levels. This result is the first experimental evidence  that Chs4p is an in vivo regulator of chitin synthesis because until now, the Chs4p function has only been determined in CSIII measurements in vitro (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Bulawa, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Choi  et al., 1994b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">Trilla et al., 1997</xref>).</p><p>With this evidence in mind, it can be concluded that the  extent of CSIII activity in vivo depends on a delicate balance between the levels of Chs3p, Chs4p, and Chs7p proteins, a balance that ensures the level of chitin synthesis required at each moment of the <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> life cycle,  besides the specific roles of CSI and CSII activities.</p><p>At this point, we are still unable to pinpoint the exact  role of Chs7p in the export of Chs3p. However, we can  compare this system with the assembly of v-ATPase or the  transport of amino acid permeases, the two previously reported cases in <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> that involve specific proteins  in their exit from the ER (reviewed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Kaiser et al., 1997</xref>).  v-ATPase mature complex is assembled in the ER with  the help of several proteins, such as Vma12p or Vma22p,  which do not leave the ER and therefore do not participate in the active v-ATPase complex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Graham et al.,  1998</xref>). Likewise, Shr3p is required for the release of several amino acid permeases from the ER (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Ljungdahl et al.,  1992</xref>). If this protein is not present, the amino acid permeases cannot be loaded into COPII vesicles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Kuehn et al.,  1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">1998</xref>). We can exclude the participation of <italic>CHS7</italic> in  any of these processes because <italic>chs7</italic> mutants did not show  phenotypes associated with the lack of v-ATPase or the  amino acid permeases. The role of Chs7p in the export of  Chs3p could be similar to that reported in any of these  cases. In the absence of Chs7p, the CSIII complex, including Chs3p, is either not assembled or not loaded into  secretory vesicles. There is indirect evidence suggesting  that Chs7p could have a similar role to Shr3p. First of all,  Shr3p and Chs7p, although lacking significant homology,  have a very similar secondary structure with several transmembrane domains. This type of secondary structure is  typical of resident ER proteins (outfitters) rather than  proteins loaded into cargo vesicles (escorts or guides; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Herrmann et al., 1999</xref>). Chs7p also lacks the protein sequences  involved in COPI mediated retrograde transport. In addition, we have been unable to detect Chs7p outside of  the ER compartment. However, we cannot exclude that  Chs7p is rapidly recycled between the ER and Golgi compartments. The answer to this question will have to await  the description of the nature of the secretory vesicles involved in the transport of Chs3p.</p><p>The results reported here indicate that <italic>CHS7</italic> is part of a  specific mechanism for CS export and its presence in vertebrates is therefore unlikely. This opens a new possibility  in the design of an antifungal agent that selectively inhibits  chitin synthesis.</p></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="display-objects"><title>Figures and Tables</title><table-wrap position="float" id="TI"><label>Table I</label><caption><p>S. cerevisiae Strains Used in this Study </p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Strain</th><th/><th>Relevant genotype</th><th/><th>Source</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">X2180-1A</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"><italic>MAT<bold>a</bold>, SUC2, mal, mel, gal2, CUP1</italic></td><td align="left"/><td align="left">American Type Culture Collection</td></tr><tr><td align="left">JAY1</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">X2180-1A <italic>ura3</italic></td><td align="left"/><td align="left">This study</td></tr><tr><td align="left">W303-1A</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"><italic>MAT<bold>a</bold> can1-100 ade2-1 his3-11,15 leu2-3,12 trp1-1 ura3-1</italic></td><td align="left"/><td align="left">Lab Collection</td></tr><tr><td align="left">JAY6</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">W303-1A <italic>chs7</italic>::<italic>HIS3</italic></td><td align="left"/><td align="left">This study</td></tr><tr><td align="left">YPA24</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"><underline><italic>MAT</italic>&#x003b1; <italic>ade2 ura3 leu1 cyh2 can1</italic></underline></td><td align="left"/><td align="left">Lab Collection</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"><italic>MATa ade2-1 ura3-1 leu2-3 his3-11 can1-100</italic></td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">15D</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"><italic>MAT<bold>a</bold> leu2 ade1 his1 trp1</italic></td><td align="left"/><td align="left"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">Richardson et al., 1989</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">15Daub</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">15D &#x00394;<italic>bar1 ura3</italic> &#x00394;<italic>ns</italic></td><td align="left"/><td align="left"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">Richardson et al., 1989</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">HVY374</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">15D <italic>ura3</italic> &#x00394;<italic>ns ADE1</italic></td><td align="left"/><td align="left">Dr. Valdivieso<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFI-150">&#x0002a;</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">HVY376</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">15D<italic>MAT</italic> &#x003b1; <italic>ura3</italic> &#x00394;<italic>ns TRP1</italic></td><td align="left"/><td align="left">Dr. Valdivieso<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFI-150">&#x0002a;</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">JAY21</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">HVY374 <italic>chs3</italic>::<italic>LEU2</italic></td><td align="left"/><td align="left">This study</td></tr><tr><td align="left">JAY22</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">HVY376 <italic>chs3</italic>::<italic>LEU2</italic></td><td align="left"/><td align="left">This study</td></tr><tr><td align="left">JAY25</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">HVY374 <italic>chs7</italic>::<italic>HIS2</italic></td><td align="left"/><td align="left">This study</td></tr><tr><td align="left">JAY26</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">HVY376 <italic>chs7</italic>::<italic>HIS2</italic></td><td align="left"/><td align="left">This study</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Y604</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"><italic>MAT<bold>a</bold> ura3-52 lys2-801 ade2-101 trp1-901 his3 &#x00394;200</italic></td><td align="left"/><td align="left">Dr. Santos<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFI-152">&#x02021;</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">Santos and Snyder, 1997</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Y1306</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">Y604 <italic>CHS3</italic>::<italic>3xHA</italic></td><td align="left"/><td align="left">Dr. Santos<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFI-152">&#x02021;</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">Santos and Snyder, 1997</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">JAY27</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">Y1306 <italic>chs7</italic>::<italic>HIS3</italic></td><td align="left"/><td align="left">This study</td></tr><tr><td align="left">JAY28</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">Y1306 <italic>chs6</italic>::<italic>URA3</italic></td><td align="left"/><td align="left">This study</td></tr><tr><td align="left">JAY29</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">Y1306 <italic>chs4</italic>::<italic>URA3</italic></td><td align="left"/><td align="left">This study</td></tr><tr><td align="left">JAY30</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">Y1306 <italic>chs5</italic>::<italic>ADE2</italic></td><td align="left"/><td align="left">This study</td></tr><tr><td align="left">JAY31</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">Y1306 <italic>chs4</italic>::<italic>URA3 chs7::HIS3</italic></td><td align="left"/><td align="left">This study</td></tr><tr><td align="left">JAY32</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">Y1306 <italic>chs6</italic>::<italic>URA3chs7::HIS3</italic></td><td align="left"/><td align="left">This study</td></tr><tr><td align="left">JAY33</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">Y1306 <italic>chs5</italic>::<italic>ADE2 chs7::HIS3</italic></td><td align="left"/><td align="left">This study</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TFI-150"><label>&#x0002a;</label><p>&#x02009;Departmento de Microbiolog&#x000ed;a y Gen&#x000e9;tica/Instituto de Microbiolog&#x000ed;a Bioqu&#x000ed;mica, Consejo Superior de Investigaciones Cientificas/Universidad de Salamanca.  &#x000a0;</p></fn><fn id="TFI-152"><label>&#x02021;</label><p>&#x02009;&#x02009;Yale University, New Haven, CT.    &#x000a0;</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Identification and characteristics of Chs7p. (A) Subcloning strategy used in the identification of YHR142 as complementing gene for the <italic>cwr6</italic> mutants. Complementation was determined by analyzing the reversal of Calcofluor resistance in <italic>cwr6</italic>  cells. Useful restriction sites are indicated: E, EcoRI; C, ClaI; V,  EcoRV; X, XbaI; St, StuI; B, BamHI; P, PstI; K, KpnI; and S,  SalI. (B) Amino acid sequence of Chs7p. Membrane-spanning  domains are underlined. (C) Kyte-Doolittle hydrophobicity plot  of Chs7p.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JCB9812082.f1"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="TII"><label>Table II</label><caption><p>Characteristic Phenotypes of cwr6 (chs7) Mutants </p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Phenotype</th><th rowspan="2"/><th colspan="9">Strains<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFII-150">&#x0002a;</xref></th></tr><tr><th>WT</th><th/><th>&#x00394;<italic>chs3</italic></th><th/><th><italic>cwr6</italic> (<italic>chs7</italic>)</th><th/><th>&#x00394;<italic>chs7</italic></th><th/><th>&#x00394;<italic>chs7</italic> (<italic>CHS7</italic>)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Calcofluor resistance<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFII-152">&#x02021;</xref></td><td/><td>&#x02212;</td><td/><td>&#x0002b;</td><td/><td>&#x0002b;</td><td/><td>&#x0002b;</td><td/><td>&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Septa enlargement<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFII-153">&#x000a7;</xref></td><td/><td>&#x0002b;</td><td/><td>&#x02212;</td><td/><td>&#x02212;</td><td/><td>&#x02212;</td><td/><td>&#x0002b;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Chitin<bold/><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFII-154">&#x000b6;</xref></td><td/><td>100</td><td/><td>&#x000a0;6.5</td><td/><td>21.6</td><td/><td>13.6</td><td/><td>&#x000a0;87.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CSIII<bold/><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFII-154">&#x000b6;</xref></td><td/><td>100</td><td/><td>15.8</td><td/><td>28.2</td><td/><td>14.6</td><td/><td>103.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mating efficiency<bold/><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFII-154">&#x000b6;</xref></td><td/><td>100</td><td/><td>69.3</td><td/><td>ND</td><td/><td>65.3</td><td/><td>ND</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Compact ascospores<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFII-155">&#x02016;</xref></td><td/><td>No</td><td/><td>Yes</td><td/><td>ND</td><td/><td>Yes</td><td/><td>ND</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TFII-150"><label>&#x0002a;</label><p>&#x02009;All strains used, except the original <italic>cwr6</italic> mutant, are isogenic derivatives of  HVY374 obtained by gene replacement (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="TI">I</xref>).  &#x000a0;</p></fn><fn id="TFII-152"><label>&#x02021;</label><p>&#x02009;Growth in buffered minimal media supplemented with 1 mg/ml Calcofluor.  &#x000a0;</p></fn><fn id="TFII-153"><label>&#x000a7;</label><p>&#x02009;Presence (&#x0002b;) or absence (&#x02212;) of enlarged septa after 2 h of growth in YEPD media  supplemented with 75 &#x003bc;g/ml Calcofluor.  &#x000a0;</p></fn><fn id="TFII-154"><label>&#x000b6;</label><p>&#x02009;Numeric values represent the percentage of the values obtained for each strain compared to that of wild-type. Chitin, CSIII, and mating efficiency were determined as described in Materials and Methods.  &#x000a0;</p></fn><fn id="TFII-155"><label>&#x02016;</label><p>&#x02009;Determined by observation under phase-contrast microscope.          &#x000a0;</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Transcription levels of <italic>CHS7</italic>. Northern blots were  done with RNAs obtained from cells grown under different conditions and loaded in equivalent amounts. <italic>CHS7</italic> mRNA was detected using the NdeI&#x02013;NdeI fragment as a probe (Materials and  Methods). In all cases, autoradiographic images and quantitative  determinations by PhosphorImager (Materials and Methods) are  shown. Relative amounts of <italic>CHS7</italic> mRNA are referred to actin  levels (not shown) and normalized with respect to the value obtained at the respective control points (left lane of each figure).  (A) RNA was obtained from X2180-1A cells incubated for the  indicated times on 5 &#x003bc;M &#x003b1;-factor (left) or from cells grown for  2 h in the absence (&#x02212;) or presence (&#x0002b;) of 50 &#x003bc;g/ml Calcofluor.  (B) RNA was obtained from YPA24 diploid strain incubated in  sporulation medium for the indicated times.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JCB9812082.f2"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Localization of Chs7p. (A) JAY25 cells transformed  with pTM15 (pRS316::<italic>CHS7-GFP</italic>) were visualized directly in a  <named-content content-type="company" xlink:href="zeiss">Zeiss</named-content> laser-confocal microscope under appropriate excitation  conditions. Note the continuous staining along the nuclear periphery and the patches associated with cytoplasmic membrane.  Cells shown on the lower part of the figure are in the process of  nuclear division. (B) Indirect immunofluorescence localization of  Sec63p-Myc in wild-type (15Daub) cells transformed with  pRS315::<italic>SEC63-MYC</italic>. (C) Western blot experiments showing  subcellular distribution of several proteins after equilibrium centrifugation in a sucrose gradient. Fractions were collected from  the bottom (lower fractions, higher densities). Equal volumes of  each fraction were loaded per lane (Materials and Methods).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JCB9812082.f3"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Characterization of  Chs3p in wild-type and &#x00394;<italic>chs7</italic>  mutants. (A) Expression levels  of Chs3p-3XHA in wild-type  and &#x00394;<italic>chs7</italic> strains. (B) Mobility  of Chs3p-3XHA from wild-type  and &#x00394;<italic>chs7</italic> before (&#x02212;) and after  (&#x0002b;) EndoH treatment. Chs3p*  indicates mobility of the protein  after N-glycosylation removal.  Protein extracts (A and B) were  prepared from HVY374 (wild-type) and JAY25 (&#x00394;<italic>chs7</italic>) strains  transformed with plasmid  pHV7-<italic>CHS3</italic>::<italic>3XHA</italic> and detected by Western blot (Materials and Methods). (C) Chs3p-3XHA detected by indirect  immunofluorescence with  HA.11 antibody. Early logarithmically growing cells were processed as described in Materials  and Methods. Strains: a, Y1306  (<italic>CHS3</italic>::<italic>3XHA</italic>); b and c, JAY27  (<italic>CHS3</italic>::<italic>3XHA</italic>, <italic>chs7</italic>::<italic>HIS3</italic>). (a)  Polarized Chs3p distribution in  wild-type cells. (b and c) Typical  ER distribution of Chs3p in  &#x00394;<italic>chs7</italic> mutant. Note the irregular distribution (dotted staining) observed after higher magnification in c. Bars, 2 &#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JCB9812082.f4"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Immunolocalization of Chs3p-3XHA in <italic>chs</italic> mutants.  All cells are Y1306 (<italic>CHS3</italic>::<italic>3XHA</italic>) with different <italic>chs</italic> mutations.  (A) JAY29, <italic>chs4</italic>::<italic>URA3</italic>. (B) JAY31, <italic>chs4</italic>::<italic>URA3 chs7</italic>::<italic>HIS3</italic>.  (C) JAY30, <italic>chs5</italic>::<italic>ADE2</italic>. (D) JAY33, <italic>chs5</italic>::<italic>ADE2 chs7</italic>::<italic>HIS3</italic>.  (E) JAY28, <italic>chs6</italic>::<italic>URA3</italic>. (F) JAY32, <italic>chs6</italic>::<italic>URA3 chs7</italic>::<italic>HIS3</italic>. (A,  C, and E) Polarized distribution of Chs3p at the base of the  emerging bud (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref> A) is lost in <italic>chs</italic> mutants. Each <italic>chs</italic> mutant  shows the typical Chs3p localization as described. (B, D, and F)  In &#x00394;<italic>chs7</italic> mutants, Chs3p-3XHA shows ER localization.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JCB9812082.f5"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Secretion phenotypes of &#x00394;<italic>chs7</italic> mutants. (A) Production of &#x003b1;-factor measured by the size of the growth inhibition  halo. (B) Activities of several enzymatic activities in wild-type  and <italic>chs7</italic> null mutants. Activities were determined in HVY374  (WT) and JAY25 (<italic>chs7</italic>::<italic>HIS2</italic>) isogenic strains and expressed as  described in Materials and Methods.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JCB9812082.f6"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F7"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>CSIII activity in strains overexpressing <italic>CHS</italic> genes.  CSIII activity was determined in cell extracts with (total activity)  or without (basal activity) trypsin activation (Materials and  Methods). Numbers indicate the ratio between total and basal activity. The results are the average of three independent experiments. Standard deviation bars are shown. On the abscissa, the  names of overexpressed <italic>CHS</italic> genes are indicated in each case.  Overexpression was achieved by transforming wild-type  (15Daub) cells with multicopy plasmids: pRS423::<italic>CHS3</italic>, pRS425::  <italic>CHS4</italic>, or pRS426::<italic>CHS7</italic> (Materials and Methods).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JCB9812082.f7"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F8"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Immunolocalization of overexpressed Chs3p-3XHA.  (A) Characteristic ER staining of strain Y604 transformed with  pRS423::<italic>CHS3-3XHA</italic> after immunodetection of Chs3p-3XHA.  (B) Chs3p-3XHA localization in Y604 cotransformed with  pRS423::<italic>CHS3-3XHA</italic> and pRS426::<italic>CHS7</italic>. Note the dotted  staining in most cells, some showing polarized staining (arrows).  Some cells also show residual perinuclear staining.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JCB9812082.f8"/></fig></sec><ack><p>We thank M.H. Valdivieso, B. Santos, and R. Schekman for plasmids and  strains, A. Pandiella and members of the A. Dur&#x000e1;n laboratory for critical  comments on the manuscript, and N. Skinner for language revision. Special thanks are due to D. Baggot (R. Schekman Laboratory) for informing  us that Chs3p is retained in the ER when overexpressed and to H. Bussey  for providing the anti-Kre2p antibody. </p><p>This work has been supported by a Ministerio de Educacion y Ciencia  predoctoral fellowship to J.A. Trilla and Comision Interministerial de  Ciencia y Tecnologia grants BIO95-0500 and BIO98-0814 to C. Roncero.</p></ack><glossary><title>Abbreviations used in this paper</title><def-list><def-item><term>CS</term><def><p>chitin synthase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>cwr</italic></term><def><p>Calcofluor  white resistant</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GFP</term><def><p>green fluorescent protein</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HA</term><def><p>hemagglutinin  epitope</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ORF</term><def><p>open reading frame</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>v-ATPase</term><def><p>vacuolar ATPase</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>B&#x000e4;hler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pringle</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pom1p, a fission yeast protein kinase that provides positional information for both polarized growth and cytokinesis</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>1998</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1356</fpage><lpage>1370</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9573052</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bowers</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Cabib</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of polyoxin D on chitin synthesis and septum formation in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae. </italic></article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>1974</year><volume>119</volume><fpage>564</fpage><lpage>575</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4604393</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bulawa</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>CSD2</italic>, <italic>CSD3</italic>, and <italic>CSD4</italic>, genes required for chitin synthesis  in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>: the <italic>CSD2</italic> gene product is related to chitin synthases and to developmentally regulated proteins in <italic>Rhizobium</italic> species and  <italic>Xenopus laevis. </italic></article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>1992</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1764</fpage><lpage>1776</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1532231</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bulawa</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetics and molecular biology of chitin synthesis in fungi</article-title><source>Annu Rev Microbiol</source><year>1993</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>505</fpage><lpage>534</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8257107</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bulawa</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Slater</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cabib</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Au-Young</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sburlati</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Adair</surname><given-names>WL</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Robbins</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>structural gene for chitin synthase is not required for chitin synthesis in vivo</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1986</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>213</fpage><lpage>225</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2941152</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="other">Cabib, E. 1994. Nomenclature of genes related to chitin synthesis. <italic>Yeast Newsl.</italic>  XLIII:58.</citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cabib</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Sburlati</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowers</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Silverman</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chitin synthase 1,  an auxiliary enzyme for chitin synthesis in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae. </italic></article-title><source>J Cell  Biol</source><year>1989</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>1665</fpage><lpage>1672</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2523889</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cabib</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Silverman</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chitinase and chitin synthase 1:  counterbalancing activities in cell separation of <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae. </italic></article-title><source>J  Gen Microbiol</source><year>1992</year><volume>138</volume><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1556560</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="other">Cabib, E., J.A. Shaw, P.C. Mol, B. Bowers, and W.J. Choi. 1996. Chitin biosynthesis and morphogenetic processes. <italic>In</italic> The Mycota. Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, Vol. III. R. Brambl, G.A. Marzluf, editors. Springer-Verlag,  Berlin. 243&#x02013;267.</citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Cabib</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The use of divalent cations and pH for the determination of specific yeast chitin synthases</article-title><source>Anal Biochem</source><year>1994</year><volume>219</volume><fpage>368</fpage><lpage>372</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8080094</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Duran</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cabib</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Are yeast chitin synthases  regulated at the transcriptional or the posttranslational level? </article-title><source>Mol Cell  Biol</source><year>1994a</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>7685</fpage><lpage>7694</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7969112</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Sburlati</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cabib</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chitin synthase 3 from yeast has zymogenic properties that depend on both the <italic>CAL1</italic> and <italic>CAL3</italic>genes</article-title><source>Proc  Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>1994b</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>4727</fpage><lpage>4730</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8197125</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Christianson</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name><surname>Sikorski</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Dante</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shero</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hieter</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multifunctional yeast high-copy-number shuttle vectors</article-title><source>Gene</source><year>1992</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>119</fpage><lpage>122</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1544568</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chuang</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Schekman</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential trafficking and timed localization of two chitin synthase proteins, Chs2p and Chs3p</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>1996</year><volume>135</volume><fpage>597</fpage><lpage>610</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8909536</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cos</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Trilla</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Duran</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cabib</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Roncero</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular analysis of Chs3p participation in chitin synthase III activity</article-title><source>Eur J  Biochem</source><year>1998</year><volume>256</volume><fpage>419</fpage><lpage>426</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9760183</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>DeMarini</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>AEM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fares</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>De Virgilio</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Valle</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Chuang</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Pringle</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A septin-based hierarchy of proteins required for localized deposition of chitin in the <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>cell wall</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>1997</year><volume>139</volume><fpage>75</fpage><lpage>93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9314530</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Evan</surname><given-names>GI</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramsay</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation of monoclonal antibodies specific for human c-myc proto-oncogen product</article-title><source>Mol  Cell Biol</source><year>1985</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>3610</fpage><lpage>3616</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3915782</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fernandez-Abalos</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Pitt</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Doonan</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant-adapted green fluorescent protein is a versatile vital reporter for gene  expression, protein localization and mitosis in the filamentous fungus, <italic>Aspergillus nidulans. </italic></article-title><source>Mol Microbiol</source><year>1998</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>121</fpage><lpage>130</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9466261</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assembly of the yeast vacuolar H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>-ATPase occurs in the endoplasmic reticulum and requires a Vma12p/Vma22p assembly complex</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>1998</year><volume>142</volume><fpage>39</fpage><lpage>49</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9660861</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hepworth</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Friesen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Segall</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>NDT80</italic> and the meiotic recombination checkpoint regulate expression of middle sporulation-specific genes  in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae. </italic></article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>1998</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>5750</fpage><lpage>5761</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9742092</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herrmann</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Malkus</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Schekman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Out of the ER: outfitters, escorts and guides</article-title><source>Trends Cell Biol</source><year>1999</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10087610</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><citation citation-type="other">Kaiser, C.A., R.E. Gimeno, and D.A. Shaywitz. 1997. Proteins secretion, membrane biogenesis, and endocytosis. <italic>In</italic> The Molecular and Cellular Biology of  the Yeast <italic>Saccharomyces</italic>, Vol. III. J. Pringle, J.R. Broach, E.W. Jones, editors. Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press, Cold Spring Harbor, NY. 91&#x02013;228.</citation></ref><ref id="B23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krisak</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Strich</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Winters</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Mallory</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kreitzer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Tuan</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Winter</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>SMK1</italic>, a developmentally regulated MAP kinase, is required for spore wall assembly in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae. </italic></article-title><source>Genes  Dev</source><year>1994</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>2151</fpage><lpage>2161</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7958885</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuehn</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schekman</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Ljungdahl</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Amino acid permeases require COPII components and the ER resident Shr3p for packaging into transport vesicles in vitro</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>1996</year><volume>135</volume><fpage>585</fpage><lpage>595</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8909535</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuehn</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Herrmann</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Schekman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>COPII-cargo interactions direct protein sorting into ER-derived transport vesicles</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1998</year><volume>391</volume><fpage>187</fpage><lpage>190</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9428766</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kyte</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Doolittle</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A simple method for displaying the hydropathy of a protein</article-title><source>J Mol Biol</source><year>1982</year><volume>157</volume><fpage>105</fpage><lpage>132</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7108955</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ljungdahl</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name><name><surname>Gimeno</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Styles</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fink</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>SHR3:</italic>a novel component of the secretory pathway specifically required for localization of amino acid permeases in yeast</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1992</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>463</fpage><lpage>478</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1423607</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lowry</surname><given-names>OH</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosebrough</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Farr</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Randall</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protein measurement with the Folin phenol reagent</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1951</year><volume>193</volume><fpage>265</fpage><lpage>275</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14907713</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lussier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sdicu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ketela</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Bussey</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Localization and targeting of the <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> Kre2p/Mnt1 &#x003b1;1,2-mannosyltransferase  to a <italic>medial</italic>-Golgi compartment</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>1995</year><volume>131</volume><fpage>913</fpage><lpage>927</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7490293</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lyman</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Schekman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Binding of secretory precursor polypeptides to a translocon subcomplex is regulated by BiP</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1997</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9019409</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martin-Chalfie</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name><name><surname>Euskirchen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>Prasher</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Green fluorescent protein as a marker for gene expression</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1994</year><volume>263</volume><fpage>802</fpage><lpage>805</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8303295</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Michaelis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Herskowitz</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The a-factor pheromone of <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>is essential for mating</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>1988</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1309</fpage><lpage>1318</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3285180</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Colorimetric analysis of sugars</article-title><source>Methods Enzymol</source><year>1957</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>86</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pammer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Briza</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellinger</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuster</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Stucka</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Brteintenbach</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>DIT101 (CSD2</italic>, <italic>CAL1)</italic>, a cell cycle-regulated yeast gene required for synthesis of chitin in cell walls and chitosan in spore walls</article-title><source>Yeast</source><year>1992</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1089</fpage><lpage>1099</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1293886</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reissig</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Strominger</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Leloir</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A modified colorimetric method for the estimation of N-acetyl-aminosugars</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1955</year><volume>217</volume><fpage>959</fpage><lpage>966</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13271455</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name><surname>Wittenberg</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Cross</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An essential G1 function for cyclin-like proteins in yeast</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1989</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>1127</fpage><lpage>1133</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2574633</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roncero</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Valdivieso</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ribas</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Duran</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of Calcofluor white on chitin synthases from <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae. </italic></article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>1988a</year><volume>170</volume><fpage>1945</fpage><lpage>1949</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2965145</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roncero</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Valdivieso</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ribas</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Duran</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation and  characterization of <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>mutants resistant to Calcofluor white</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>1988b</year><volume>170</volume><fpage>1950</fpage><lpage>1954</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3280554</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Novick</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bostein</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Fink</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>genomic plasmid bank based on a centromere-containing shuttle vector</article-title><source>Gene</source><year>1987</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>237</fpage><lpage>243</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3327750</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B40"><citation citation-type="other">Rose, M.D., F. Wisnton, and P. Hieter. 1990. Methods in Yeast Genetics: A  Laboratory Course Manual. Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press, Cold  Spring Harbor, NY.</citation></ref><ref id="B41"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rothstein</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>One-step gene disruption in yeast</article-title><source>Methods Enzymol</source><year>1983</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>202</fpage><lpage>211</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6310324</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sadler</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurihara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Rothblatt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Way</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Silver</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A  yeast gene important for protein assembly into the endoplasmic reticulum  and the nucleus has homology to DnaJ and <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>heat shock protein</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>1989</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>2665</fpage><lpage>2675</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2556404</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B43"><citation citation-type="other">Sambrook, J., E.F. Fritsch, and T. Manniatis. 1989. Molecular Cloning: A Laboratory Manual. Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press, Cold Spring Harbor, NY.</citation></ref><ref id="B44"><citation citation-type="journal"><collab>San Segundo, P., J. Correa, C.R. Vazquez de Aldana, and F. del Rey</collab><article-title><italic>SSG1</italic>, a gene encoding a sporulation-specific 1,3-B-glucanase in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae. </italic></article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>1993</year><volume>175</volume><fpage>3823</fpage><lpage>3837</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8509335</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B45"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Targeting of chitin synthase 3 to polarized growth sites in yeast requires Chs5p and Myo2p</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>1997</year><volume>136</volume><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9008706</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B46"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Duran</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Valdivieso</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>CHS5</italic>, a gene involved in  chitin synthesis and mating in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae. </italic></article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>1997</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>2485</fpage><lpage>2496</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9111317</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B47"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sburlati</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cabib</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chitin synthase 2, a presumptive participant in  septum formation in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae. </italic></article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1986</year><volume>261</volume><fpage>15147</fpage><lpage>15152</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2945823</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B48"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mol</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowers</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Silverman</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Valdivieso</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Duran</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cabib</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The function of chitin synthases 2 and 3 in the <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>cell cycle</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>1991</year><volume>114</volume><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>123</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2050738</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B49"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Somogyi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Notes on sugar determination</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1952</year><volume>195</volume><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14938350</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B50"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trilla</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cos</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Duran</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Roncero</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterisation of <italic>CHS4  (CAL2)</italic>, a gene of <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> involved in chitin biosynthesis  and allelic to <italic>SKT5</italic> and <italic>CSD4. </italic></article-title><source>Yeast</source><year>1997</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>795</fpage><lpage>807</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9234668</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B51"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Uchida</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimmi</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Sudoh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Arisawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamada-Okabe</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of Chitin synthase 2 of <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>II: both full size and processed enzymes are active for chitin synthesis</article-title><source>J Biochem</source><year>1996</year><volume>119</volume><fpage>659</fpage><lpage>666</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8743566</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B52"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valdivieso</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Mol</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cabib</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Duran</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>CAL1</italic>, a  gene required for activity of chitin synthase 3 in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae. </italic></article-title><source>J  Cell Biol</source><year>1991</year><volume>114</volume><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>109</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2050737</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B53"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ziman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chuang</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Schekman</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chs1p and Chs3p, two proteins involved in chitin synthesis, populate a compartment of the <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>endocytic pathway</article-title><source>Mol Biol Cell</source><year>1996</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1909</fpage><lpage>1919</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8970154</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B54"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ziman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chuang</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsung</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamamoto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Schekman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chs6p-dependent anterograde transport of Chs3p from the chitosome to the  plasma membrane in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae. </italic></article-title><source>Mol Biol Cell</source><year>1998</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1565</fpage><lpage>1576</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9614194</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>


