<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Cell Biol</journal-id><journal-title>The Journal of Cell Biology</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0021-9525</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1540-8140</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Rockefeller University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">3528171</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2114296</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">86304552</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Monoclonal antibodies to the light-harvesting chlorophyll a/b protein complex of photosystem II</article-title></title-group><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>1</day><month>9</month><year>1986</year></pub-date><volume>103</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>733</fpage><lpage>740</lpage><permissions></permissions><abstract><p>A collection of 17 monoclonal antibodies elicited against the light- harvesting chlorophyll a/b protein complex which serves photosystem II (LHC-II) of Pisum sativum shows six classes of binding specificity. Antibodies of two of the classes recognize a single polypeptide (the 28- or the 26- kD polypeptides), thereby suggesting that the two proteins are not derived from a common precursor. Other classes of antibodies cross-react with several polypeptides of LHC-II or with polypeptides of both LHC-II and the light-harvesting chlorophyll a/b polypeptides of photosystem I (LHC-I), indicating that there are structural similarities among the polypeptides of LHC-II and LHC-I. The evidence for protein processing by which the 26-, 25.5-, and 24.5-kD polypeptides are derived from a common precursor polypeptide is discussed. Binding studies using antibodies specific for individual LHC- II polypeptides were used to quantify the number of antigenic polypeptides in the thylakoid membrane. 27 copies of the 26-kD polypeptide and two copies of the 28-kD polypeptide were found per 400 chlorophylls. In the chlorina f2 mutant of barley, and in intermittent light-treated barley seedlings, the amount of the 26-kD polypeptide in the thylakoid membranes was greatly reduced, while the amount of 28-kD polypeptide was apparently not affected. We propose that stable insertion and assembly of the 28-kD polypeptide, unlike the 26-kD polypeptide, is not regulated by the presence of chlorophyll b.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article>


