<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="news"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Exp Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">jem</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Journal of Experimental Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0022-1007</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1540-9538</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Rockefeller University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2715131</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2064iti3</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.2064iti3</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>In This Issue</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Save yourself, cancer cell</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Leslie</surname><given-names>Mitch</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp><email>mitchleslie@comcast.net</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>13</day><month>4</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>206</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage seq="c">726</fpage><lpage>727</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2009 The Rockefeller University Press</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2009</copyright-year></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="JEM_2064iti.pdf"/></article-meta></front><body><p><fig id="fig1" fig-type="figure" position="anchor"><caption><p>Blocking netrin-1 (left panel) reduced neuroblastoma growth in chicks.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jem.2064iti3fig1"/></fig>Some neuroblastoma tumors are addicts, Delloye-Bourgeois et al. report on <related-article related-article-type="article-reference" vol="206" page="833" id="d32e68" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="19349462" ext-link-type="pubmed">page 833</related-article>. The tumor cells need a steady supply of a molecule called netrin-1, and they get their fix by making the compound themselves. Forcing the cells to go cold turkey could provide a new treatment for neuroblastoma, one of the most common childhood cancers.</p><p>Even healthy cells are often poised on the verge of death. Unless so-called dependence receptors receive continual stimulation, the cells kill themselves. One molecule that activates these receptors is netrin-1, a protein that is needed for normal neural development. Previous studies showed that certain breast and lung tumors pump out large amounts of netrin-1, suggesting that they rely on the molecule for survival.</p><p>Delloye-Bourgeois et al. now show that netrin-1 is also necessary for neuroblastoma. The most aggressive tumors manufactured extra netrin-1, the researchers found, and production of the molecule affected patients&#x02019; prognosis. Ninety percent of infants with tumors that made little netrin-1 were alive after five years, but only 48% of infants with tumors that produced copious netrin-1 survived that long.</p><p>These findings suggest that blocking netrin-1 curbs tumor growth. Indeed, eliminating netrin-1 in tumor cell lines led to their demise. And when the team implanted neuroblastoma tumors into chicken embryos and then neutralized netrin-1, the tumors shrank and were less likely to metastasize.</p><p>Cancers sometimes break their dependence on receptor stimulation by jettisoning the receptors. But neuroblastoma tumors didn't do that. Instead, some neuroblastomas feed their own addiction by manufacturing more netrin-1, thus preventing apoptosis. The researchers have recently begun preclinical studies on two netrin-1&#x02013;blocking compounds that might provide an alternative to chemotherapy and radiation.</p></body></article>