<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Exp Med</journal-id><journal-title>The Journal of Experimental Medicine</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0022-1007</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1540-9538</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Rockefeller University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">6447750</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2185922</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">81008375</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Differential major histocompatibility complex-related activation of idiotypic suppressor T cells. Suppressor T cells cross-reactive to two distantly related lysozymes are not induced by one of them</article-title></title-group><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>1</day><month>9</month><year>1980</year></pub-date><volume>152</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>521</fpage><lpage>531</lpage><permissions></permissions><abstract><p>B10 (H-2b) mice are genetic nonresponders to hen egg-white lysozyme (HEL) and the distantly related human lysozyme (HUL). However, anti-HEL or anti-HUL primary antibody responses in vivo or in vitro can be obtained in B10 mice by immunization with the appropriate lysozyme coupled to erythrocytes. T cells able to suppress either anti-lysozyme plaque-forming cells (PFC) response are induced in B10 mice after immunization with HEL-complete Freund's adjuvant (CFA) or HUL-CFA. This cross-reactivity of HEL and HUL in the induction and the expression of suppressive activity is in marked contrast to their very low cross- reactivity at the PFC level. These results suggest that either HEL or HUL can stimulate a suppressor T cell which recognizes a particular epitope present on both lysozymes. Suppressor cells induced by HEL or HUL bear the same predominant idiotype found on the majority of anti- HEL antibodies, and on the small proportion of anti-HUL antibodies cross-reactive with HEL. B10.Q (H-2q) mice are responders in vivo to HEL-CFA, but not to HUL-CFA. In contrast to B10, HEL-CFA priming in B10.Q micr induces helper cells whereas HUL-CFA priming induces suppressor cells. These suppressor cells are cross-reactive with HEL and are fully able to suppress HEL-specific helper cells. The presence of HEL-specific suppressor cell precursors in B10.Q mice which are not activated by HEL, seems to implicate differential choice by the antigen presenting system as a basis for Ir gene control, rather than the absence of a regulatory cell type from the T cell repertoire.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article>


