<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Foot Ankle Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Foot Ankle Res</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Foot and Ankle Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1757-1146</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24708560</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4108129</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1757-1146-7-23</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1757-1146-7-23</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Foot orthoses for adults with flexible pes planus: a systematic review</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A1"><name><surname>Banwell</surname><given-names>Helen A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>helen.banwell@mymail.unisa.edu.au</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A2"><name><surname>Mackintosh</surname><given-names>Shylie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>shylie.mackintosh@unisa.edu.au</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A3"><name><surname>Thewlis</surname><given-names>Dominic</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>dominic.thewlis@unisa.edu.au</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>International Centre for Allied Health Evidence (iCAHE) School of Health Sciences, University of South Australia, Adelaide, SA 5001, Australia</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Biomechanics and Neuromotor Lab. School of Health Sciences, University of South Australia, Adelaide, SA 5001, Australia</aff><aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Sansom Institute for Health Research, University of South Australia, Adelaide, SA 5001, Australia</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>5</day><month>4</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>25</day><month>10</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>3</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2014 Banwell et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Banwell et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jfootankleres.com/content/7/1/23"/><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Foot orthoses are widely used in the management of flexible pes planus, yet the evidence to support this intervention has not been clearly defined. This systematic review aimed to critically appraise the evidence for the use of foot orthoses for flexible pes planus in adults.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>Electronic databases (Medline, CINAHL, Cochrane, Web of science, SportDiscus, Embase) were systematically searched in June 2013 for randomised controlled, controlled clinical and repeated measure trials where participants had identified flexible pes planus using a validated and reliable measure of pes planus and the intervention was a rigid or semi-rigid orthoses with the comparison being a no-orthoses (shoes alone or flat non-posted insert) condition. Outcomes of interest were foot pain, rearfoot kinematics, foot kinetics and physical function.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Of the 2,211 articles identified by the searches, 13 studies met the inclusion criteria; two were randomised controlled trials, one was a controlled trial and 10 were repeated measure studies. Across the included studies, 59 relevant outcome measures were reported with 17 calculated as statistically significant large or medium effects observed with use of foot orthoses compared to the no orthoses condition (SMD range 1.13 to -4.11).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>No high level evidence supported the use of foot orthoses for flexible pes planus. There is good to moderate level evidence that foot orthoses improve physical function (medial-lateral sway in standing (level II) and energy cost during walking (level III)). There is low level evidence (level IV) that foot orthoses improve pain, reduce rearfoot eversion, alter loading and impact forces; and reduce rearfoot inversion and eversion moments in flexible pes planus. Well-designed randomised controlled trials that include appropriate sample sizes, clinical cohorts and involve a measure of symptom change are required to determine the efficacy of foot orthoses to manage adult flexible pes planus.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Pes planus</kwd><kwd>Flat feet</kwd><kwd>Orthoses</kwd><kwd>Foot</kwd><kwd>Shoe inserts</kwd><kwd>Orthotic</kwd><kwd>Kinematics</kwd><kwd>Kinetics</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Pes planus (flat foot) is an umbrella term to describe feet with a visually lowered medial longitudinal arch often in association with rearfoot eversion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. Pes planus presents in two forms, described as rigid or flexible [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. The World Health Organisation defines rigid pes planus as a congenital, rigid or spastic deformity of the foot and flexible pes planus as an acquired joint disorder resulting in a valgus foot deformity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. Rigid pes planus affects less than 1% of the population and leads to significant pain and disability often requiring surgical intervention [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. Flexible pes planus reportedly affects between 2 to 23% of the U.S. adult population [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>] with prognoses and intervention pathways remaining predominantly unclear, undefined and controversial [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. Although well recognised within clinical practice and orthopaedic literature, no universally accepted classification and standardised measure of flexible pes planus exists [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. Radiographic investigations are the reference standard to determine magnitude of pes planus; however, it is measured clinically using a variety of static foot posture indices, each with their own limitations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>].</p><p>Painful symptomatic presentations associated with flexible pes planus include: generalised lower limb pain; increased lower limb fatigue, Achilles tendinopathy, osteoarthritis, patellofemoral disorders and hip pain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. No agreement exists on the aetiology of flexible pes planus; however, frequently reported signs include abnormal rearfoot kinematics (e.g. excessive rearfoot eversion or increased range of rearfoot eversion), abnormal foot and ankle kinetics (e.g. elevated joint moments or abnormal loading forces) and altered physical function (e.g. altered muscle activation and timing or increased energy consumption) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>]. The symptoms of flexible pes planus have been attributed to the functional consequences of these signs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>] and intervention should be aimed at addressing these abnormalities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>].</p><p>Foot orthoses (FOs) are frequently prescribed interventions for flexible pes planus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]. The most commonly prescribed FOs in Australia, the &#x02018;modified Root device&#x02019; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>], were originally developed to influence the position of the subtalar joint towards a neutral position and reduce abnormal motion around this joint [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>]. Subsequent views on the reported mechanism of how FOs affect the foot has evolved and, while variations exist, Kirby&#x02019;s definition of &#x0201c;<italic>an in-shoe medical device that alters magnitudes and temporal patterns of the reaction forces&#x02026; and thus allowing for a more normal foot and lower extremity function that decreases pathological loading forces</italic>&#x0201d; is often cited [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>]. Therefore, based on these definitions, the use of FOs to alter the signs of flexible pes planus and ameliorate symptoms is plausible. The question is; does research evidence exist to support this notion? To our knowledge a systematic review investigating the use of FOs for a targeted adult flexible pes planus population has not been undertaken. With a limited understanding on how FOs impact on the signs and symptoms associated with flexible pes planus, there remains some controversy as to when and how clinicians determine if FOs are required [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. Therefore, the aim of this systematic review was to assess the effectiveness of FOs to reduce foot pain, alter rearfoot kinematics and kinetics and improve physical function for adults with flexible pes planus.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Search strategy</title><p>The following databases were searched from inception to June 2013: Ovid Medline&#x000ae; (from January 1966 to date); CINAHL (from 1982 to date); Cochrane Central Register of Controlled Trials (CENTRAL) (issue 5, May 2013); Web of Science (from inception to date); SportDiscus (from inception to date); and Ovid Embase (1988 to date). Medical subject headings (MeSH) were exploded and combined with relevant keywords that were truncated where required. The search was limited to adult human subjects with no language restrictions applied. An example search strategy for Ovid Medline is outlined (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>). Further articles were sought from review of reference lists, conference proceedings and personal communications with content experts (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>).</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Flow chart of study selection.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1757-1146-7-23-1"/></fig><p>Two authors independently reviewed titles and abstracts of all studies generated by the search strategy using the inclusion and exclusion criteria. Consensus was reached for included studies through discussion with all three authors.</p></sec><sec><title>Eligibility criteria</title><p>Studies were included if:</p><p>1. The study was published in a peer-reviewed journal.</p><p>2. The study design was a randomised controlled trial (RCT), controlled clinical trial (non-randomised intervention trial with a separate control group) or repeated measure intervention trial where participants acted as their own control.</p><p>3. Participants were adults with flexible pes planus defined using a reliable and validated foot morphology or posture index (median of available published reliability data of ICC &#x02265; 0.50) (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref>).</p><p>4. The intervention was a rigid or semi-rigid FO where the orthoses were required to meet the standards defined by the Australian Podiatry Council for pre-formed or pre-moulded, moulded non-cast, moulded cast, or customised kinetic orthoses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>].</p><p>5. The comparison included a no-FO (shoes alone or flat non-posted insert) condition.</p><p>6. Outcome measures included a measure of foot pain/fatigue and/or functional changes in relation to: rearfoot kinematics (excessive rearfoot eversion, increased range or angular velocity of rearfoot eversion); foot kinetics (reduction of force, rearfoot joint moment or change in timing of force or moment) or physical function (changes in energy cost, lower limb muscle activation and timing, or postural control) during weight bearing, bipedal activities (standing, walking or running).</p><p>Studies were excluded if the participants had: a history of significant trauma, disease, inflammatory or systemic condition that may affect lower limb function (e.g. diabetes, neurological dysfunction, rheumatoid arthritis); had previously worn orthoses in the past six months; or the risk of bias of the study was deemed unacceptable (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Risk of bias assessment</title><p>Risk of bias was assessed using the McMaster critical review form &#x02013; Quantitative studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>] and descriptive guidelines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>] which is applicable to RCTs, controlled clinical trials and repeated measure intervention trials. The tool has fifteen individual assessment points within eight domains. These are the study purpose, literature review, sample (described, justified, reliable), outcomes (reliable, valid), intervention (described, not contaminated, co-intervention/s avoided), results (statistically significant, appropriate analyses, clinically important), drop outs and conclusions (including clinical implications). The reporting of drop outs was not applicable for repeated measure trials and therefore was excluded from the critical review. Studies were awarded a &#x02018;yes&#x02019; or &#x02018;no&#x02019; rating for each individual assessment point of the remaining seven domains. A &#x02018;yes&#x02019; rating was applied if the study completely fulfilled the criterion and a &#x02018;no&#x02019; rating if the criterion was not completely fulfilled. Domains were required to have a &#x02018;yes&#x02019; rating for a minimum of 50% of the individual assessment points to be considered acceptable. An <italic>a priori</italic> decision was set to include only studies deemed acceptable in four or more of the seven domains (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3">3</xref>). Risk of bias assessment was completed by two reviewers independently and discussions held until consensus.</p><p>The Australian National Health and Medical Research Council&#x02019;s (NHMRC) evidence hierarchy was used to determine the level of evidence for each study with systematic reviews of RCTs considered high (level I) evidence, RCTs good (level II) evidence, pseudo-RCTs (controlled clinical trials) moderate (level III) evidence and repeated measure trials low (level IV) evidence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Data management</title><p>Data describing the sample characteristics, intervention characteristics, study protocol and adverse effects were extracted by two reviewers independently, from all studies, with consensus on results. Two reviewers independently extracted data with consensus on results. Novel measures, with no independent reliability or validity data, outcomes that were repetitious (within the same study) and those considered outside the scope of this review (extraneous) were excluded by consensus of three reviewers (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S4">4</xref>). Means and standard deviations (SD) for each group were extracted where data were provided or supplied on request [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>].</p><p>When more than one type or prescription approach of FOs were investigated, each device within the study was allocated simple identification (Device A, B etc.). Device A from one study is not comparable with Device A from an alternative study (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Table of included studies; level of evidence, cohort characteristics and type of FOs used</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/></colgroup><thead valign="top"><tr><th rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top"><bold>Study</bold></th><th rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top"><bold>Level of evidence</bold></th><th rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top"><bold>Study design</bold></th><th rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top"><bold>
<italic>N</italic>
</bold></th><th rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top"><bold>Cohort</bold></th><th rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top"><bold>Mean age (SD)</bold></th><th rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top"><bold>Pes planus measure</bold></th><th rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top"><bold>Domain of outcome measures</bold></th><th rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top"><bold>FOs brand or type</bold></th><th rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top"><bold>FOs shell material</bold></th><th colspan="2" align="center" valign="bottom"><bold>FOs posting</bold><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="center"><bold>RF</bold></th><th align="center"><bold>FF</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Rome and Brown [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>]<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">II<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">RCT<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">50 (25/25)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Excessive pronators<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">23.8 (2.2)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">FPI-8<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Physical function<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Talar made &#x000a9;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">EVA<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">5&#x000b0;<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0&#x000b0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Esterman and Pilotto [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">II<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">RCT<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">47 (25/22)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Air force recruits<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">21.6 (3.9)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">AI<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Pain<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">AOL&#x000ae;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Plastic<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">4&#x000b0;<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">4&#x000b0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Otman et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>]<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">III-2<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">CCT<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">20 (20/20)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Female adults<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">25.8 (1.3)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Radiographs<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Physical function<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Arch supports<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Polypropylene<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0&#x000b0;<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0&#x000b0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">Zifchock and Davis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>]<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">IV<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">RM<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">19<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">Low arched recreation runners<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">23.6 (6.4)<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">AHI<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">Rearfoot kinematics<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">A. Modified Root device<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Graphite<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0 &#x02013; 7&#x000b0;<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0&#x000b0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">B. KLM&#x000ae;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Graphite<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">NR<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">NR<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="top">M&#x000fc;ndermann et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>]<hr/></td><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="top">IV<hr/></td><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="top">RM<hr/></td><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="top">21<hr/></td><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="top">Recreational runners<hr/></td><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="top">25.4 (5.6)<hr/></td><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="top">RE<hr/></td><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="top">Rearfoot kinematics and kinetics<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">A. Modified Root device<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Polypropylene<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">6&#x000a0;mm<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">6&#x000a0;mm<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">B. Modified Root device<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Polypropylene<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0&#x000b0;<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0&#x000b0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">C. Pre-made Insert<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">EVA<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">6&#x000a0;mm<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">6&#x000a0;mm<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">Cobb et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>]<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">IV<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">RM<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">16<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">Low mobile arch adults<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">25.4 (6.5)<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">AHI<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">Rearfoot kinematics<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">A. MASS Device<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Polyethylene composite<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0&#x000b0;<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0&#x000b0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">B. Modified Root device<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Leather and composite material<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">NR<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">NR<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">Murley et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>]<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">IV<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">RM<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">30<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">Adults<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">21.8 (4.3)<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">AI &#x00026; NH<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">Physical function<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">A. Inverted (Blake) device<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Polypropylene<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">20 &#x000b0;<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0&#x000b0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">B. Formthotic &#x000ae;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Duel density polyethylene foam<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">6&#x000a0;mm<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0&#x000b0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">Redmond et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>]<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">IV<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">RM<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">22<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">Excessive pronators<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">24<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">RE<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">Kinetics<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">A. Modified Root device<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Polypropylene<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">6&#x000b0;<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0&#x000b0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">B. Pre-made Insert<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Thin card with EVA posts<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">6&#x000b0;<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0&#x000b0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Zammit and Payne [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>]<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">IV<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">RM<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">22<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Excessive RF pronators (clinical practice)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">44.3 (16.7)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">FPI-8<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Pain and physical function<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Independently prescribed<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Variable<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">IP<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">IP<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="top">Murley and Bird [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>]<hr/></td><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="top">IV<hr/></td><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="top">RM<hr/></td><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="top">17<hr/></td><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="top">Adults<hr/></td><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="top">23.0 (5.0)<hr/></td><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="top">FPI-6<hr/></td><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="top">Physical function<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">A. Inverted (Blake) device<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">NR<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">30 &#x000b0;<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0&#x000b0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">B. Inverted (Blake) device<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">NR<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">15&#x000b0;<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0&#x000b0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">C. Inverted (Blake) device<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">NR<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0&#x000b0;<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0&#x000b0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">Hurd et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>]<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">IV<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">RM<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">15<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">Recreational runners<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">34.0 (10.0)<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">FF to RF<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">Rearfoot kinematics and kinetics<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">A. Flat foot Insert &#x000a9;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Polyurethane with a poron layer<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0&#x000b0;<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">4&#x000b0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">B. SofSole&#x000ae;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Graphite Polyurethane<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0&#x000b0;<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0&#x000b0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="top">Johanson et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>]<hr/></td><td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="top">IV<hr/></td><td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="top">RM<hr/></td><td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="top">22<hr/></td><td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="top">Physical therapy attendees (clinical practice)<hr/></td><td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="top">30.5 (8.0)<hr/></td><td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="top">FF to RF<hr/></td><td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="top">Rearfoot kinematics<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">A. Orthofeet Biothotics&#x000a9;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Water injected polyurethane shells with EVA posting<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">80% of FF post<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">Up to 7&#x000a0;mm<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">B. Orthofeet Biothotics&#x000a9;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">As above<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">80% of FF post<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0&#x000b0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">C. Orthofeet Biothotics&#x000a9;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">As above<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0&#x000b0;<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">Up to 7&#x000a0;mm<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">D. Orthofeet Biothotics&#x000a9;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">As above<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0&#x000b0;<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0&#x000b0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Chen et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>]</td><td align="left">IV</td><td align="left">RM</td><td align="left">11</td><td align="left">Adults</td><td align="left">45.9 (15.7)</td><td align="left">AI</td><td align="left">Kinetics and physical function</td><td align="left">NR</td><td align="left">Vinyl-acetate &#x00026; 12% far-infrared nanopowders</td><td align="center">NR</td><td align="center">NR</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>RM &#x02013; repeated measure. CCT &#x02013; controlled clinical trial. AHI &#x02013; arch height index, AI &#x02013; arch index, FF to RF &#x02013; forefoot to rearfoot relationship, NH &#x02013; navicular height, FPI-8 &#x02013; Foot Posture Index &#x02013; 8- item version, FPI-6 &#x02013; Foot Posture Index &#x02013; 6- item version, RE- rearfoot eversion. MASS &#x02013; maximum subtalar supination position, NR &#x02013; not reported, FF &#x02013; forefoot, EVA -ethyl vinyl acetate.</p><p>Orthotic Labs: Formthotic (Foot Science International, Christchurch, New Zealand) Flatfoot insert, (Hickory Brands, Inc, Hickory, NC, USA), Sofsole, LLC, Durham, NC), KLM (KLM Orthotic Laboratories; Valencia, CA, USA), AOL (Australian Orthotics Laboratory, International, Kirrance, NSW, Australia), Talar made (Talar Made Orthotics, Chesterfield, UK), Orthofeet Biothotics (Orthofeet Inc, Hillsdale, NJ, USA).</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Outcomes are reported for pain, rearfoot kinematics, foot kinetics and physical function. All tabled data are displayed in descending level of evidence, followed by descending levels of assessed risk of bias concerns, followed by alphabetical order unless otherwise noted.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical methods</title><p>Sample size weighted standardised mean differences (SMD) and 95% confidence interval (CI) were calculated using Cochrane Review Manager (V.5) using the difference in mean scores between the FO and no-FO condition divided by the pooled standard deviation. Where the mean and standard deviations were not available for each condition, SMDs were calculated on mean difference divided by standard deviation of the mean difference, multiplied by the square root of two [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>]. SMDs were considered statistically significant if the CI did not cross zero. Results are presented in forest plots where negative numbers favour the FO over the no-FO condition. Interpretations of the strength of the SMDs statistics were based on Cohen&#x02019;s guidelines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>] with small effect &#x02265; 0.2, medium effect &#x02265; 0.5 and large effect &#x02265; 0.8. Statistically significant SMDs of less than 0.2 were considered very small.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Study selection and design</title><p>Initial searches identified 2,211 studies. Two thousand, one hundred and sixty three (2,163) were excluded based on title and abstract. Forty eight studies were reviewed in full for eligibility, of which 35 studies were excluded based on inclusion and exclusion criteria (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>) leaving 13 included studies (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). No studies were high level of evidence, two studies were good level of evidence (RCTs), one study was moderate level of evidence (controlled clinical trial) and ten studies were low level evidence (repeated measure intervention trials).</p></sec><sec><title>Risk of bias assessment</title><p>All studies had identified risk of bias (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3">3</xref>). While all included studies clearly stated their study purpose and the level of statistical significance, of the 13 included studies, only one justified the sample size [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>]. Four studies had potential bias of co-interventions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>]. Individual studies had a risk of bias within the literature review [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>], sample description [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>], outcome measure reliability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>], outcome measure validity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>], intervention description [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>], intervention contamination [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>], appropriate analysis of results [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>], clinical importance of results [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>] and overall conclusion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Participants</title><p>In total, 312 participants were included in the 13 studies (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). Most participants were young adults with 10 of the 13 included studies using cohorts aged 40&#x000a0;years or less. One study only recruited females [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>]. Zammit and Payne [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>] and Johanson et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>] recruited participants from clinical practice. Esterman and Pilotto [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>] recruited air force cadets during basic training. Zifchock and Davis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>] and M&#x000fc;ndermann et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>] both targeted recreational runners. Johanson et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>] and Hurd et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>] did not recruit from a specific population but required their participants to have forefoot varus of at least eight or five degrees respectively. The remaining studies did not report recruiting from specific cohorts. All studies recruited people with pes planus based on static foot posture. All studies involved 50 or less participants. Zifchock and Davis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>] had both high and low arch participants and did not report the low arch group separately. The authors kindly supplied data to isolate the low arch cohort.</p></sec><sec><title>Types of foot orthoses</title><p>No two studies used the same FOs or approach to prescription (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). Eight of the 13 studies involved two or more types of FOs with three of those comparing the same orthoses with different levels of customisation and/or posting (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). Ten standardised the shell type and the level of rearfoot and forefoot posting across the cohort [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>]. Two studies independently prescribed post levels, based on foot morphology, using different approaches [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>]. One study investigated a combination of customised and prefabricated FOs individually prescribed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>] (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Outcome measures</title><p>All of the included studies used different outcome measures and measurement approaches (Tables&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">5</xref>). No study reported on adverse effects. The comparisons (SMD) between FO and no FO conditions for all relevant outcome measures are presented in Figures&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Relevant outcome measures related to the domain of pain (significant SMD results are bolded)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/></colgroup><thead valign="top"><tr><th align="left"><bold>Study</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Activity</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Outcome</bold></th><th align="center"><bold>No FO (mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD)</bold></th><th align="center"><bold>Device</bold></th><th align="center"><bold>FO (mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD)</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Esterman and Pilotto [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">10&#x000a0;week basic air force training recorded at baseline and 8&#x000a0;weeks<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">VAS 0 &#x02013; 10, pain previous 24&#x000a0;hours following 8&#x000a0;weeks of FO use<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">1.14 (2.4)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0.68 (1.5)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Zammit and Payne [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>]</td><td align="left">FHSQ reported at baseline and 4&#x000a0;weeks</td><td align="left">Increase in FHSQ pain subscale following 4&#x000a0;weeks of FO use (reduction in pain)</td><td align="center">49.84 (24.8)</td><td align="center">NA</td><td align="center"><bold>70.86 (19.5)</bold></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>VAS &#x02013; visual analogue scale, FO &#x02013; foot orthoses, FHSQ &#x02013; foot health status questionnaire, NA &#x02013; not applicable.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Relevant outcome measures related to the domain of rearfoot kinematics (significant SMD results are bolded) - walking unless otherwise noted</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/></colgroup><thead valign="top"><tr><th align="left"><bold>Study</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Activity</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Outcome</bold></th><th align="center"><bold>No FO (mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD)</bold></th><th align="center"><bold>Device</bold></th><th align="center"><bold>FO (mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD)</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td rowspan="6" align="left" valign="top">Zifchock and Davis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>]<hr/></td><td rowspan="6" align="left" valign="top">Over-ground walking (2.0&#x000a0;m/s) in low arch cohort<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">Peak RF eversion (&#x000b0;)<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top">4.31 (2.5)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">5.45 (5.1)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">B<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">4.38 (2.2)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">RF eversion excursion (&#x000b0;)<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top">10.60 (2.8)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">9.47 (1.9)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">B<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">9.68 (1.8)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">Peak RF eversion velocity (&#x000b0;/s)<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top">155.65 (46.9)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">141.50 (47.2)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">B<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">144.78 (46.5)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="6" align="left" valign="top">M&#x000fc;ndermann et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>]<hr/></td><td rowspan="6" align="left" valign="top">Over-ground running (4.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2&#x000a0;m/s) in recreational runners with everted rearfoot.<hr/></td><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="top">Peak foot eversion (&#x000b0;) *<hr/></td><td rowspan="3" align="center" valign="top">16.00 (2.3)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">16.90 (3.6)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">B<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">16.60 (2.5)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">C<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom"><bold>13.70 (2.7)</bold><hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="top">Peak foot eversion velocity (&#x000b0;/s) *<hr/></td><td rowspan="3" align="center" valign="top">464.70 (155.2)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">484.40 (141.1)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">B<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">476.80 (145.0)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">C<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">392.90 (135.0)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">Cobb et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>]<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">Over-ground walking (1.3 to 1.4&#x000a0;m/s) in low arch cohort<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">RF eversion excursion (terminal stance (&#x000b0;)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0.85 (0.8)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0.28 (0.5)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">0.02 (0.4)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">B<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0.18 (0.3)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="8" align="left" valign="top">Hurd et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>]<hr/></td><td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="top">Over-ground walking (1.2&#x000a0;m/s&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5%) in forefoot varus cohort<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">RF eversion (initial contact) (&#x000b0;)<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top">-1.60 (3.6)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">-1.00 (3.1)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">B<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">-0.30 (4.0)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">Peak RF eversion (loading) (&#x000b0;)<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top">-3.40 (3.7)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">-2.80 (5.6)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">B<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">-2.70 (5.3)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="top">Over-ground running (1.7&#x000a0;m/s&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5%) in forefoot varus cohort<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">RF eversion (initial contact) (&#x000b0;) *<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top">-3.30 (4.0)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">-2.50 (5.0)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">B<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">-2.30 (4.5)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">Peak RF eversion (loading) (&#x000b0;) *<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top">-5.60 (3.5)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">-5.30 (10.5)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">B<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">-5.60 (11.1)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="top">Johanson et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>]</td><td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="top">Treadmill walking (1.11&#x000a0;m/s) in forefoot varus cohort</td><td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="top">Peak RF eversion (&#x000b0;)</td><td rowspan="4" align="center" valign="top">0.80 (3.0)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom"><bold>-1.35 (2.8)</bold><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">B<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">-0.88 (3.3)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">C<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">-0.44 (3.3)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center">D</td><td align="center">-0.36 (3.0)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>FO &#x02013; foot orthoses, RF &#x02013; rearfoot, FF &#x02013; forefoot, *during running.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Relevant outcome measures related to the domain of kinetics (force and joint moment change) (significant SMD results are bolded) &#x02013;during walking unless otherwise noted</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/></colgroup><thead valign="top"><tr><th align="left"><bold>Study</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Activity</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Outcome</bold></th><th align="center"><bold>No FO (mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD)</bold></th><th align="center"><bold>Device</bold></th><th align="center"><bold>FO (mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD)</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td rowspan="6" align="left" valign="top">M&#x000fc;ndermann et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>]<hr/></td><td rowspan="6" align="left" valign="top">Over-ground running (4.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2&#x000a0;m/s)<hr/></td><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="top">Vertical impact peak (N)<hr/></td><td rowspan="3" align="center" valign="top">1499.10 (255.6)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">1352.30 (233.6)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">B<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">1400.40 (242.5)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">C<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">1519.40 (265.9)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="top">Peak loading rate (N/s)<hr/></td><td rowspan="3" align="center" valign="top">52.50 (11.1)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom"><bold>42.0 (10.9)</bold><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">B<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom"><bold>44.8 (11.1)</bold><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">C<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">53.5 (11.9)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="20" align="left" valign="top">Redmond et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>]<hr/></td><td rowspan="20" align="left" valign="top">Over-ground walking (self-selected speed)<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">Peak force (heel) (N)<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top">544.50 (104.3)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">501.90 (97.3)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">B<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">543.80 (100.6)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">Peak force (midfoot) (N)<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top">195.30 (62.7)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom"><bold>234.20 (58.8)</bold><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">B<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">156.20 (73.9)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">Peak force (lateral FF) (N)<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top">426.90 (12.1)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">396.90 (110.3)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">B<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">429.90 (122.0)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">Peak force (medial FF) (N)<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top">188.50 (62.9)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">173.20 (65.4)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">B<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">190.00 (72.2)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">Peak force (hallux) (N)<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top">148.90 (63.1)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">161.40 (54.9)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">B<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">159.90 (53.9)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">Force-time integral (heel) (N/s)<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top">1436.20 (462.2)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">1285.00 (385.3)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">B<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">1488.90 (441.1)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">Force-time integral (midfoot) (N/s)<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top">527.70 (224.4)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom"><bold>812.30 (267.0)</bold><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">B<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">454.40 (253.5)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">Force-time integral (lateral FF) (N/s)<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top">1394.70 (575.1)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom"><bold>1056.90 (436.3)</bold><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">B<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">1317.00 (520.5)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">Force-time integral (medial FF) (N/s)<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top">468.50 (212.1)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom"><bold>340.30 (175.9)</bold><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">B<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">423.50 (202.5)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">Force-time integral (hallux) (N/s)<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top">294.90 (141.5)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">304.60 (155.7)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">B<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">317.70 (145.3)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="6" align="left" valign="top">M&#x000fc;ndermann et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>]<hr/></td><td rowspan="6" align="left" valign="top">Over-ground running (4.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2&#x000a0;m/s)<hr/></td><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="top">Peak ankle inversion moment (Nm.kg<sup>-1</sup>)<hr/></td><td rowspan="3" align="center" valign="top">0.47 (0.1)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0.40 (0.1)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">B<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0.43 (0.1)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">C<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom"><bold>0.38 (0.1)</bold><hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="top">Time of ankle inversion moment (% of gait cycle)<hr/></td><td rowspan="3" align="center" valign="top">41.00 (5.5)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">39.90 (6.5)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">B<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">41.40 (6.7)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">C<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">40.20 (5.5)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="8" align="left" valign="top">Hurd et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>]</td><td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="top">Over-ground walking (1.2&#x000a0;m/s&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5%)<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">Peak RF moment (Nm.kg<sup>-1</sup>)<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top">0.78 (0.4)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0.74 (0.5)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">B<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0.88 (0.3)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">Mean RF moment (Nm.kg<sup>-1</sup>)<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top">0.04 (0.4)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">-0.18 (0.5)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">B<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0.19 (0.5)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="top">Over-ground running (1.7&#x000a0;m/s&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5%)</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">Peak RF moment (Nm.kg<sup>-1</sup>)<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top">1.75 (0.7)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom"><bold>1.23 (0.6)</bold><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">B<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">1.76 (0.7)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">Mean RF moment (Nm.kg<sup>-1</sup>)</td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top">0.71 (1.0)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0.09 (1.0)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center">B</td><td align="center">0.92 (0.8)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>FO &#x02013; foot orthoses, DF &#x02013; dorsiflexion, PF &#x02013; plantarflexion, RF &#x02013; rearfoot, NA &#x02013; not applicable.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Relevant outcome measures related to changes in: physical function (significant SMD results are bolded) &#x02013; outcomes are measured during walking unless otherwise noted</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/></colgroup><thead valign="top"><tr><th align="left"><bold>Study</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Activity</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Outcome</bold></th><th align="center"><bold>No FO (mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD)</bold></th><th align="center"><bold>Device</bold></th><th align="center"><bold>FO (mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD)</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="top">Rome and Brown [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>]<hr/></td><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="top">Quiet standing<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Mean of the 300 balance points measured over 30&#x000a0;seconds (%)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">49.40*^<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">46.10*^<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Medial to lateral sway - rate of deviation from the mean balance over 30&#x000a0;seconds (%)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">1.90*^<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom"><bold>1.30</bold>*^<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Anterior to posterior sway - rate of deviation from the mean balance over 30&#x000a0;seconds (%)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">4.60*^<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">4.80*^<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Otman et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>]<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Walking on treadmill at 1.34&#x000a0;m/s<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Energy cost (ml/kg/min)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">13.90*<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom"><bold>12.76*</bold><hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="30" align="left" valign="top">Murley et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>]<hr/></td><td rowspan="30" align="left" valign="top">Over-ground walking (self-selected&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5%)<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">TP EMG peak amplitude (initial contact and loading)%<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top">101.91 (33.9)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">89.51 (36.8)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">B<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom"><bold>82.48 (31.8)</bold><hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">TP EMG RMS amplitude (initial contact and loading)%<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top">101.94 (30.9)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">89.37 (33.6)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">B<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom"><bold>80.01 (25.7)</bold><hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">TP EMG peak amplitude (midstance, terminal and pre-swing) (% of gait cycle)<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top">90.96 (28.8)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">89.62 (22.2)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">B<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">87.34 (27.3)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">TP EMG RMS amplitude (midstance, terminal and pre-swing)%<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top">89.60 (24.1)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">86.92 (17.83)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">B<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">85.84 (23.9)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">PL EMG peak amplitude (initial contact and loading)%<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top">80.16 (35.6)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">84.70 (42.1)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">B<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">90.48 (47.3)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">PL EMG RMS amplitude (initial contact and loading)%<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top">79.44 (27.6)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">84.25 (37.5)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">B<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">98.10 (44.6)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">PL EMG peak amplitude (midstance, terminal and pre-swing) (% of gait cycle)<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top">62.71 (32.6)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">67.78 (33.9)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">B<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom"><bold>83.76 (41.9)</bold><hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">PL EMG RMS amplitude (midstance, terminal and pre-swing)%<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top">71.90 (39.9)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">79.86 (46.0)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">B<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom"><bold>96.07 (47.9)</bold><hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">TA EMG peak amplitude (initial contact and loading)%<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top">116.32 (15.8)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">113.49 (15.3)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">B<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">111.50 (17.4)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">TA EMG RMS amplitude (initial contact and loading)%<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top">122.02 (19.8)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">119.79 (22.0)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">B<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">113.00 (22.3)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">TP EMG time of peak amplitude (initial contact and loading) (% of gait cycle)<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top">10.94 (1.7)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">11.37 (2.1)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">B<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">11.10 (2.2)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">TP EMG time of peak amplitude (midstance, terminal and pre-swing) (% of gait cycle)<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top">44.95 (4.3)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">44.92 (3.69)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">B<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">45.55 (4.1)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">PL EMG time of peak amplitude (initial contact and loading) (% of gait cycle)<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top">10.65 (3.4)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">10.52 (3.5)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">B<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">10.23 (4.6)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">PL EMG time of peak amplitude (midstance, terminal and pre-swing) (% of gait cycle)<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top">51.65 (7.0)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">50.55 (7.91)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">B<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">50.26 (7.61)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">TA EMG time of peak amplitude (initial contact and loading) (% of gait cycle)<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top">6.63 (1.4)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">6.28 (1.3)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">B<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">6.39 (1.4)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Zammit and Payne [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>]<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">FHSQ reported at baseline and 4&#x000a0;weeks<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Increase in FHSQ function subscale (increase in function)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">64.94 (24.0)*<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom"><bold>85.32 (17.7)*</bold><hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="9" align="left" valign="bottom">Murley and Bird [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>]<hr/></td><td rowspan="9" align="left" valign="bottom">Over-ground walking (self-selected speed)<hr/></td><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="top">PL EMG amplitude (% MVIC)<hr/></td><td rowspan="3" align="center" valign="top">88.00 (26.5)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">98.00 (32.9)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">B<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">107.00 (35.8)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">C<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">99.00 (32.6)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="top">TA EMG amplitude (% MVIC)<hr/></td><td rowspan="3" align="center" valign="top">122.00 (38.4)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">123.00 (42.2)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">B<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">129.00 (43.1)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">C<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">125.00 (30.0)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="top">Soleus EMG amplitude (% MVIC)<hr/></td><td rowspan="3" align="center" valign="top">256.60 (89.6)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">251.93 (95.7)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">B<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">255.70 (94.5)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">C<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">260.92 (98.4)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5" align="left" valign="top">Chen et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>]</td><td rowspan="5" align="left" valign="top">Over-ground walking (1.09&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.11&#x000a0;m/s)</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Velocity (cm/s)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">108.57 (11.3)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">109.39 (11.1)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Cadence (steps/min)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">103.98 (6.8)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">104.73 (5.8)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Step width(cm)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">15.44 (5.2)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">15.44 (5.0)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Step length(cm)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">63.09 (4.9)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">61.81 (4.4)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Stance time (%)</td><td align="center">63.72 (1.7)</td><td align="center">NA</td><td align="center">63.93 (1.9)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>FO &#x02013; foot orthoses, EMG &#x02013; electromyography, TP &#x02013; tibialis posterior, PL &#x02013; peroneus longus, TA &#x02013; tibialis anterior, RMS &#x02013; root mean square, MVIC &#x02013; maximum voluntary isometric contraction, FHSQ &#x02013; foot health status questionnaire, NA &#x02013; not applicable, N/A &#x02013; not available, *No FO condition was prior to orthoses dispense, the FO condition was following four weeks of orthoses use, ^ Median results and significance tabled as per original article&#x02013; means and standard deviations unavailable.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Forest plot of data pooling for the use of FOs for the domain of pain.</bold> FHSQ &#x02013; foot health status questionnaire.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1757-1146-7-23-2"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>Forest plot for data pooling for the domain of rearfoot kinematics.</bold> RF &#x02013; rearfoot, ever &#x02013; eversion, ft &#x02013; foot, excur &#x02013; excursion, vel &#x02013; velocity, *observed during running.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1757-1146-7-23-3"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><bold>Forest plot of data pooling for the domain of kinetics.</bold> Pk &#x02013; peak, FF &#x02013; forefoot, lat &#x02013; lateral, med &#x02013; medial, vert &#x02013; vertical, F-t integ &#x02013; force time integral, RF &#x02013; rearfoot, mo &#x02013; moment, inv &#x02013; inversion, *observed during running.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1757-1146-7-23-4"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><bold>Forest plot of data pooling for the domain of physical function.</bold> EMG &#x02013; electromyography, TP &#x02013; tibialis posterior, RMS &#x02013; root mean square, PL &#x02013; peroneus longus, TA &#x02013; tibialis anterior, MVIC &#x02013; maximum voluntary isometric contraction, amp &#x02013; amplitude, (1) &#x02013; initial contact and loading, (M) &#x02013; midstance, terminal and pre-swing.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1757-1146-7-23-5"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Pain</title><p>Two studies measured pain changes. One study (level II) reported no significant change in pain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>] and the other study (level IV) reported significant improvement in pain scores with FO use [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>] (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). Esterman and Pilotto [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>] had a small, non-significant SMD for reducing &#x02018;lower limb pain in previous 24&#x000a0;hours&#x02019; when comparing their intervention and control groups over eight weeks of basic training in air force recruits (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). Data from Zammit and Payne [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>] indicated a large SMD (mean difference of 21.02 points on the foot health status questionnaire (FHSQ) in reducing foot pain following four weeks of FOs use within a clinical cohort (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Function change</title><sec><title><italic>Rearfoot kinematics</italic></title><p>Five studies (level IV) analysed rearfoot kinematics during walking or running [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>] with two studies reporting significant changes in kinematics with FOs use (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>).</p><p>Rearfoot eversion changes (peak and mean rearfoot eversion) were reported in four studies comparing eleven different types of FOs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>]. Significant decreases in rearfoot eversion were reported in two studies. Johanson et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>], noted peak rearfoot eversion was statistically significantly decreased (mean difference 2.15&#x000b0;) for device A during treadmill walking, with device B, C and D showing medium and small SMDs that were not statistically significant (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). M&#x000fc;ndermann et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>] reported measures based on the foot modelled as a single rigid segment during overground running. Within this study, device C reduced foot eversion with a large SMD observed (mean difference 2.30&#x000b0;) in a cohort of recreational runners (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>).</p><p>Two other studies investigated rearfoot eversion with non-significant results. Zifchock and Davis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>] during walking trials and Hurd et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>], during walking and running trials (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>).</p><p>Rearfoot eversion excursions were reported in three studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>] (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>). Zifchock and Davis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>] observed non-significant SMDs for both device A and B to reduce rearfoot eversion excursion (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). Cobb et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>] reported non-significant SMDs for rearfoot eversion excursion changes during terminal stance for both device A and B (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). Johanson et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>] reported no change to rearfoot excursion across all four FOs employed; however, data were not available to calculate SMDs.</p><p>Rearfoot eversion velocity was reported in two studies comparing five FOs (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>). Zifchock and Davis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>] observed non-significant SMD decreases during overground walking for device A and B (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). M&#x000fc;ndermann et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>], during overground running, observed non-significant increases for device A and B, with a non-significant decrease observed with device C (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title><italic>Kinetics</italic></title><p>Kinetics of the foot were reported in four (level IV) studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>] investigating change in loading forces and joint moments. Three of these studies reported at least one statistically significant change with FO use (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref>).</p><p>Changes in force and its derivatives across the foot were reported in two studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>]. M&#x000fc;ndermann et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>] reported no significant change in vertical impact forces with all three devices (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). Peak loading rates were significantly altered for two of the three FOs used during overground running (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). A large SMD, which represented a reduction in loading rate, was observed with device A (mean difference 146.8&#x000a0;N/s). A medium SMD, which also represented a reduction, was observed with device B (mean difference 98.7&#x000a0;N/s). Device C had no effect (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). M&#x000fc;ndermann et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>] also reported peak vertical ground reaction forces with similar results (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S4">4</xref>). When using plantar pressure instrumentation, Redmond et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>] reported a significant, medium SMD, increase in peak force across the midfoot (mean difference 38.9&#x000a0;N) using device A (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). No significant results were reported across the heel, lateral and medial forefoot or hallux with device A during overground walking (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref>). No significant changes across all foot regions were reported using device B (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref>).</p><p>Force-time integrals from plantar pressure instrumentation were reported in one study comparing two FOs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>] (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref>). Device A had a statistically significant large SMD effect in increasing the force-time integral across the midfoot (mean difference 284.6&#x000a0;N.s) and medium SMD reduction in the force-time integral at the forefoot (medial and lateral) (mean difference 128.2 and 337.7&#x000a0;N.s respectively)(Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). Device B had no significant effects (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref>). This study also reported mean force, peak pressures, mean peak pressures and pressure&#x02013;time integrals (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S4">4</xref>).</p><p>Changes in rearfoot joint moments were reported on in two studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>] (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref>). M&#x000fc;ndermann et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>] reported reductions in peak ankle inversion moments during running for all three devices; however, only the medium SMD reduction effect observed for device C (mean difference 0.09&#x000a0;Nm.kg<sup>-1</sup>) was statistically significant (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). No significant differences were observed for the timing of the moment within the same study (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref>). Hurd et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>], reported a significant reduction in peak rearfoot eversion moments during running with device A (mean difference 0.62&#x000a0;Nm.kg<sup>-1</sup>) of a large SMD; whereas device B had no significant effect (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). The same protocol, during walking, produced no significant differences using either FOs. Mean rearfoot eversion moments were altered with device A, with (non-significant) a small SMD reduction during walking (mean difference 0.53&#x000a0;Nm.kg<sup>-1</sup>) and (non-significant) a medium SMD reduction during running observed (mean difference 1.34&#x000a0;Nm.kg<sup>-1</sup>) (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). Conversely, using device B, small SMD increases were noted for both walking and running that were not statistically significant (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title><italic>Physical function</italic></title><p>Six studies reported on physical function changes. Outcome measures included postural sway [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>], energy expenditure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>], electromyography (EMG) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>], FHSQ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>] and spatiotemporal gait variables [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>]. One was level II [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>], one was level III [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>] and five were level IV [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>]. Four of these studies reported significant changes in at least one outcome with FOs use (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">5</xref>).</p><p>Postural sway in quiet standing was reported in Rome and Brown [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>] in a RCT comparing FOs to shoes alone in two separate groups. Both groups were assessed in a shoes alone condition (session one) and again four weeks later (session two) where the intervention group were tested in FOs. A significant reduction in medial-lateral sway (32% improvement) was reported in the FOs group; however, data were not available to calculate SMDs (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">5</xref>).</p><p>Energy expenditure changes were reported in a controlled clinical trial [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>], with a large SMD observed within the pes planus group (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>) indicating significant decreases in total energy cost during treadmill walking (mean difference 1.14&#x000a0;ml.kg.min<sup>-1</sup>) in comparison to the no-FO condition (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">5</xref>). The non-pes planus (control) group remained consistent over the two testing sessions. This study also reported large energy expenditure savings during walking on inclines and positive effects for oxygen consumption for the pes planus group when using FOs during the same testing sessions (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S4">4</xref>).</p><p>Changes in EMG of lower limb muscles during overground walking were reported in two studies, one measuring muscle activation and timing for two different FOs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>] and one measuring activation only for three different FOs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>] (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">5</xref>). Murley et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>] reported a reduced tibialis posterior peak and root mean square (RMS) EMG amplitude at initial contact and loading (mean difference 19.4 and 21.9% respectively) with device B. Both these outcomes were calculated as a statistically significant medium SMD reduction in EMG amplitude (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>). This was in conjunction with an increased peroneus longus peak and RMS EMG amplitude during midstance, terminal stance and pre-swing (mean difference 21.0 and 24.2% respectively) and RMS EMG amplitude during initial contact and loading (mean difference 18.6%) when using the same FOs (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">5</xref>). These results were not reported with device A, nor were any other statistically significant SMDs reported using device A or B for tibialis anterior (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>). This study also reviewed both devices influence on medial gastrocnemius (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S4">4</xref>). In another EMG study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>], no statistically significant SMDs were observed for changes in amplitude of tibialis anterior, peroneus longus or soleus using three FOs with different posting levels (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>).</p><p>Increases in self-reported function were reported (mean change 20.38 points on the FHSQ function subscale) (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">5</xref>). A statistically significant medium SMD improvement was observed following four weeks of use of individually prescribed FOs in a cohort recruited from clinical practice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>] (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>). Another study investigated gait velocity, step length and cadence and reported non-significant changes with FO use [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>] (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">5</xref>). This study also investigated stride length, reporting no effect (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S4">4</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Summary of results</title><p>From the 13 studies included, data were extracted for 59 relevant outcome measures related to the signs (rearfoot kinematics, foot kinetics and physical function) and symptoms (pain) associated with flexible pes planus (Tables&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">5</xref>). From these 59 outcome measures, 41 results reported across 13 studies were not statistically significant. Of the 13 studies reporting non-significant results, one was a level 11 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>] and 11 were level IV evidence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>]. Eighteen outcomes reported across eight studies were statistically significant (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T6">6</xref>). Of the eight studies reporting statistically significant results, one was level 11 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>], one was level III [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>] and six were level IV evidence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>]. Available data demonstrated that all statistically significant outcomes were a large or medium SMD effect when comparing the FO to the no FO condition (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T6">6</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T6"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Outcomes and device review categories of FOs where statistically significant SMDs were observed^ (in descending effect size) (during walking unless otherwise noted)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/></colgroup><thead valign="top"><tr><th align="left"><bold>Study</bold></th><th align="center"><bold>Level of evidence</bold></th><th align="center"><bold>SMD</bold></th><th align="center"><bold>95% CI</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Domain</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Specific outcome</bold></th><th align="center"><bold>Device</bold></th><th align="center"><bold>Difference in mean</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Otman et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>]<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">III<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">-4.11<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">-5.24 to -2.98<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Physical function<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02193; energy cost at 1.34&#x000a0;m/s, 0 incline (ml.kg.min-<sup>1</sup>)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">1.14<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Redmond et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>]<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">IV<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">1.13<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0.49 to 1.77<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Kinetics<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02191; force-time integral (midfoot) (N/s)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">284.60<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">M&#x000fc;ndermann et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>]<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">IV<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">-0.94*<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">-1.58 to -0.30<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Kinetics<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02193; peak loading rate (N/s)*<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">10.50<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Zammit and Payne [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>]<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">IV<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">-0.93<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">-1.55 to -0.30<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Pain<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02193; FHSQ pain subscale following 4&#x000a0;weeks of use (%)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">21.00<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">M&#x000fc;ndermann et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>]<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">IV<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">-0.90*<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">-1.54 to -0.26<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Rearfoot kinematics<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02193; peak foot eversion (&#x000b0;) *<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">C<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">2.30<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Hurd et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>]<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">IV<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">-0.78*<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">-1.52 to -0.03<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Kinetics<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02193; peak RF eversion moments (Nm.kg-<sup>1</sup>) *<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0.52<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">M&#x000fc;ndermann et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>]<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">IV<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">-0.75<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">-1.38 to -0.13<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Kinetics<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02193; peak ankle inversion moment (Nm)*<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">C<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">6.00<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Murley et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>]<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">IV<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">-0.76<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">-1.29 to -0.24<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Physical function<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02193; TP EMG RMS amplitude (initial) (%)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">B<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">21.93<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Zammit and Payne [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>]<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">IV<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">-0.76<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">-1.37 to -0.14<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Physical function<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02193; FHSQ function subscale following 4&#x000a0;weeks of use (%)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">20.40<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Johanson et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>]<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">IV<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">-0.72<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">-1.33 to -0.11<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Rearfoot kinematics<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02193; peak RF eversion (&#x000b0;)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">2.15<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">M&#x000fc;ndermann et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>]<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">IV<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">-0.68<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">-1.30 to -0.06<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Kinetics<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02193; peak loading rate (N/s)*<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">B<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">7.70<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="top">Redmond et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>]<hr/></td><td rowspan="3" align="center" valign="top">IV<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">-0.65<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">-1.26 to -0.04<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Kinetics<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02193; force-time integral (lateral FF) (N/s)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">337.80<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">-0.65<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">-1.25 to -0.04<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Kinetics<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02193; force-time integral (medial FF) (N/s)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">128.20<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">0.63<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0.02 to 1.24<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Kinetics<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02191; force at midfoot (N)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">38.90<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Murley et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>]<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">IV<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">-0.58<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">-1.10 to -0.07<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Physical function<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02193; TP EMG peak amplitude (initial) (%)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">B<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">19.43<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Murley et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>]<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">IV<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">-0.55<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">-1.07 to -0.04<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Physical function<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02191; PL EMG peak amplitude (midstance +) (%)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">B<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">21.05<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Murley et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>]</td><td align="center">IV</td><td align="center">-0.54</td><td align="center">-1.06 to -0.03</td><td align="left">Physical function</td><td align="left">&#x02191; PL EMG RMS amplitude (midstance +) (%)</td><td align="center">B</td><td align="center">18.66</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>SMD values to the negative favour the FO condition over the no-FO condition.</p><p>FO &#x02013; foot orthoses, RF &#x02013; rearfoot, EMG &#x02013; electromyography, TP &#x02013; tibialis posterior, PL &#x02013; peroneus longus, RMS &#x02013; root mean square, FHSQ &#x02013; foot health status questionnaire, NA &#x02013; not applicable, *outcomes observed during running. ^Rome and Brown [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>] SMDs unavailable.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The largest SMD (-4.11, CI -5.24 to -2.98) was observed in the domain of physical function (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T6">6</xref>) in Otman et al.&#x02019;s [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>] controlled clinical trial that investigated changes in energy cost during treadmill walking, in a female pes planus group, with and without FOs (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T6">6</xref>). These results favour the FO condition (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>). The next largest SMD (1.13, CI 0.49 to 1.77) was within the domain of kinetics where Redmond et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>] investigated changes in the force-time integral at the midfoot (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T6">6</xref>). This result favoured the no FO condition (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). This was the only statistically significant SMD effect that favoured the no FO condition (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T6">6</xref>). Large effects within individual studies were also observed for reducing peak loading rates, pain and peak foot eversion (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T6">6</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>The aim of this systematic review was to assess the effectiveness of FOs to alter signs (abnormal rearfoot kinematics, abnormal kinetics and altered physical function) and symptoms (pain and fatigue) associated with flexible pes planus in adults. Key outcomes of this systematic review are that there are only two RCTs investigating the use of FOs for adults with flexible pes planus and that all studies had identified risk of bias issues (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3">3</xref>) and concerns regarding participant recruitment, choice of FOs or the outcome measures.</p><sec><title>Pes planus and participant recruitment</title><p>Each study used a different measure of pes planus and there was no consistency in recruitment criteria among studies. The majority of studies recruited cohorts of convenience based on static pes planus measures. It would seem more appropriate to investigate effectiveness of an intervention within a participant group who have recognised symptoms associated with the condition. One of the two studies that recruited from clinical practice reported large and medium SMD effects on pain and self-reported function [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>] (Figures&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>). These outcomes could, arguably, be the most clinically important measures included within this review.</p></sec><sec><title>Approach to FOs</title><p>Concerns around the type of FOs employed were noted. The type of FOs selected for investigation in a study was rarely justified and often not described in detail. Ten of the included studies standardised the shell and approach to posting [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>], only three studies individualised their approach [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>]. A criticism of FOs intervention studies, anecdotally at least, is the justification of the FOs used and the apparent ad hoc approach to prescription options. This may be related to an absence of appropriate prescription guidelines to direct the researcher [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">53</xref>]. Currently there is no evidence to suggest that individually prescribing FOs offers any benefits over standardised devices, however if the FOs investigated in research are not mirroring those used in clinical practice then the evidence may also not be easily translated to clinical situations. The effect of the diversity of FOs used in the studies on the overall results of this review is unknown, and requires a further review with separate analyses. Further research into the impact of different approaches to the FOs used across all foot types is recommended along with the development of appropriate prescription guidelines to ensure future research outcomes are a genuine reflection of clinical practice results.</p></sec><sec><title>Choice of outcome measures</title><p>The symptom of fatigue was not measured in any study and changes in pain levels were only investigated in two studies. This was surprising given that pain and fatigue are assumed to be common drivers for people with flexible pes planus to seek podiatric intervention [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">54</xref>]. Within this review, pain was significantly reduced when FOs were independently prescribed within a clinical cohort (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>); however, with no separate control group (or &#x02018;sham device&#x02019; group) improvements in pain levels cannot be attributed to the FOs alone and may simply reflect pain resolving over time, a placebo or a Hawthorne effect [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>].</p><p>Changes in rearfoot kinematics were frequently investigated (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>). Changes were noted predominantly in rearfoot eversion during walking with the measured reduction being significant (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). It is important to note that the actual magnitude of change is small (1.28 to 2.30&#x000b0;) and falls within accepted levels of measurement error [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">55</xref>]. It has also been suggested that this magnitude of effect on rearfoot kinematics is clinically meaningless and a direct link between rearfoot positioning and functioning has yet to be established [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>]. Overall, the majority of rearfoot kinematic measures were not significant (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>).</p><p>Within the domain of kinetics, only two reported outcome measures demonstrated a statistically significant reduction for loading forces, both observed during running trials (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). Loading forces during walking were increased across the midfoot with the use of FOs and there was not a lateral shift of force demonstrated as expected (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). Results may have been influenced by both the use of an in shoe insole placed over the top of the orthoses and by the methods adopted for the quantitative analysis within this domain. The assumption was made that the goal of FO therapy was to reduce the overall force and decrease the time the force was applied [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. Therefore, the increase in the amount and time of force measured across the midfoot was allocated as favouring the no FO condition (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). In essence, the actual clinical consequences of the changes in measured force and timing reported is not clearly understood [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>] and interpretation of results should be viewed accordingly.</p><p>The impact on physical function is where the highest level of evidence was found (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">5</xref>). Both medial-lateral sway during quiet standing and energy cost were positively affected with the use of FOs and offer good and moderate levels of evidence. This supports the historical belief that people with pes planus had reduced efficiency in gait, a belief that restricted entry into military service in the Australian, British and US armed forces for both World Wars [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. Interestingly, while the use of FOs for improved stability in stance is supported within the literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">57</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">58</xref>], energy cost studies using FOs in other populations do not concur with the outcomes reported within this review. Hennacy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">59</xref>] concluded that FOs, within a &#x02018;foot problem&#x02019; group, induced an initial increase in energy consumption that returned to normal within three months. In a more recent study, Kelly [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">54</xref>] reported that no statistically significant changes were noted in energy cost during, and following, a one hour run with and without FOs in a non-pes planus cohort. Based on the outcomes of this systematic review, further investigations of energy cost and postural control within a flexible pes planus adult population is warranted.</p></sec><sec><title>Limitations</title><p>Only a small number of studies were included in this review. All of the included studies had identified risk of bias with the assessment of risk of bias undertaken with a tool that allocated equal weight to all criteria (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3">3</xref>). Ten of the included studies are low level evidence (level IV) (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>) with all 10 being a repeated measure study design and eight of the 10 studies investigating two or more types of FOs. These studies met the required inclusion criteria; however, their inclusion may have affected the conclusions. To manage data levels and reduce errors from the same participants appearing repeatedly in analyses, several outcome measures were excluded on the basis they were considered repetitious or extraneous (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S4">4</xref>), the effect of excluding these data on the results reported remain unknown.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Within the limits of this systematic review it was determined that low level evidence exists that FOs positively impact on rearfoot kinematics, kinetics and physical function in adults with flexible pes planus. The small number of studies included and the risk of bias within the studies mean the clinical implications of the results of this review are not known. There is little evidence that FOs reduce pain and no evidence that FOs reduce fatigue.</p><p>Without high level evidence to support the purported effects of FOs podiatric clinicians are faced with the quandary of working within the bounds of evidence based practice, balanced against potentially conflicting clinical experience. Foot orthoses, specifically Root and modified Root devices, have been used for over 40&#x000a0;years with &#x02018;arch inserts&#x02019; pre-dating them by over a century [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. This review indicates that there are measurable consequences to FO use for the flexible pes planus in adults but these impacts are minimal. Quality research with clinically relevant outcomes, based on protocols that mirror clinical practice is required. This will allow future research to direct the development of robust and effective intervention pathways that offer the best possible outcome to the flexible pes planus adult population.</p></sec><sec><title>Abbreviations</title><p>FOs: Foot orthoses; NR: Not recorded; N/A: Not available; NA: Not applicable; RCT: Randomised controlled trial; RM: Repeated measure; CCT: Controlled clinical trial; AI: Arch index; AHI: Arch height index; FF: Forefoot; RF: Rearfoot; NH: Navicular height; FPI-6: Foot posture index &#x02013; 6- item version; FPI-8: Foot posture index &#x02013; 8- item version; RE: Rearfoot eversion; MASS: Maximum subtalar supination position; FV: Forefoot varus; EVA: Ethyl vinyl acetate; SMD: Standardised mean difference; CI: Confidence interval; FHSQ: Foot health status questionnaire; DF: Dorsiflexion; PF: Plantarflexion; EMG: Electromyography; TP: Tibialis posterior; PL: Peroneus longus; TA: Tibialis anterior; RMS: Root mean square; MVIC: Maximum voluntary isometric contraction; IP: Independently prescribed; SE: Standard error; MG: Medial gastrocnemius; LoE: Level of evidence; Amp: Amplitude; Ever: Eversion; Ft: Foot; Excur: Excursion; Vel: Velocity; Pk: Peak; Lat: Lateral; Med: Medial; Vert: Vertical; f-t integ: Force time integral; mo: Moment; inv: Inversion.</p></sec><sec><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>The protocol for the review was written by HB. Risk of bias, data extraction and analysis was undertaken by HB, SM &#x00026; DT. All authors contributed to and approved of the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors&#x02019; information</title><p>HB was funded by an Australian Postgraduate Awards scholarship during the course of this study.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S1"><caption><title>Additional file 1</title><p>Search strategy example, Ovid MEDLINE.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1757-1146-7-23-S1.docx"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S2"><caption><title>Additional file 2</title><p>Intra- and inter-rater reliability for commonly used measures of pes planus.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1757-1146-7-23-S2.docx"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S3"><caption><title>Additional file 3</title><p><bold>Risk of bias of included studies (alphabetical order).</bold> McMaster critical review tool &#x02013; quantitative studies.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1757-1146-7-23-S3.docx"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S4"><caption><title>Additional file 4</title><p>Excluded data based on novel, repetitious or extraneous outcome measures (results reported as significant are bolded).</p></caption><media xlink:href="1757-1146-7-23-S4.docx"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ref-list><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shibuya</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Jupiter</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ciliberti</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>VanBuren</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>La Fontaine</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>Characteristics of adult flatfoot in the United States</article-title><source>Foot Ankle Surg</source><year>2010</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>363</fpage><lpage>368</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.jfas.2010.04.001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Esterman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pilotto</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><article-title>Foot shape and its effect on functioning in Royal Australian Air Force recruits. Part 1: Prospective cohort study</article-title><source>Mil Med</source><year>2005</year><volume>170</volume><fpage>623</fpage><lpage>628</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16130646</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Luhmann</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rich</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Schoenecker</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><article-title>Painful idiopathic rigid flatfoot in children and adolescents</article-title><source>Foot Ankle Int</source><year>2000</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>66</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10710264</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>WHO</collab><source>ICD-10 Diseases of the musculoskeletal system and connective tissue</source><year>2010</year><publisher-name>Geneva: World Health Organisation</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pfeiffer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kotz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ledl</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hauser</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Sluga</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Prevalence of flat foot in preschool-aged children</article-title><source>Pediatrics</source><year>2006</year><volume>118</volume><fpage>634</fpage><lpage>639</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.2005-2126</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16882817</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cowell</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name><surname>Elener</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><article-title>Rigid painful flatfoot secondary to tarsal coalition</article-title><source>Clin Orthop Relat Res</source><year>1983</year><volume>177</volume><fpage>54</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6861407</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Link</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Felson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Crincoli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Keysor</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>McKinlay</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>Prevalence of foot and ankle conditions in a multiethnic community sample of older adults</article-title><source>Am J Epidemiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>159</volume><fpage>491</fpage><lpage>498</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aje/kwh071</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14977645</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kosashvili</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Fridman</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Backstein</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Safir</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Bar Ziv</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><article-title>The correlation between pes planus and anterior knee or intermittent low back pain</article-title><source>Foot Ankle Int</source><year>2008</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>910</fpage><lpage>913</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3113/FAI.2008.0910</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18778669</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Golightly</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hannan</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Dufour</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><article-title>Racial differences in foot disorders and foot type</article-title><source>Arthritis Care Res (Hoboken)</source><year>2012</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>1756</fpage><lpage>1759</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22674897</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Staheli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><article-title>Planovalgus foot deformity. Current status</article-title><source>J Am Podiatr Med Assoc</source><year>1999</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>94</fpage><lpage>99</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10063780</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Mak</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><article-title>Biomedical gait evaluation of the immediate effect of orthotic treatment for flexible flat foot</article-title><source>Prosthet Orthot Int</source><year>1998</year><volume>22</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9604273</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Copper</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Scharfbillig</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Scutter</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Reliability of the Foot Posture Index and traditional measures of foot position</article-title><source>J Am Podiatr Med Assoc</source><year>2003</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>203</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12756311</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Scharfbillig</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Copper</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Scutter</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Iasiello</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Redmond</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Criterion validation of four criteria of the foot posture index</article-title><source>J Am Podiatr Med Assoc</source><year>2004</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>38</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14729988</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><name><surname>Ashford</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Kippen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Rome</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><article-title>Interventions for pes planus (protocol)</article-title><source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source><year>2005</year><issue>Issue 1</issue><comment>Art. No.: CD005120. DOI: 101002/14651858CD005120</comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>McPoil</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Cornwall</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vicenzino</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Teyhen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Molloy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Christie</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><article-title>Effect of using truncated versus total foot length to calculate the arch height ratio</article-title><source>Foot</source><year>2008</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>220</fpage><lpage>227</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foot.2008.06.002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Franco</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><article-title>Pes cavus and pes planus: analyses and treatment</article-title><source>Phys Ther</source><year>1987</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>688</fpage><lpage>693</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3575426</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>DY</given-names></name><name><surname>Koh</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>OY</given-names></name><article-title>Effect of foot orthoses and short-foot exercise on the cross-sectional area of the abductor hallucis muscle in subjects with pes planus: a randomized controlled trial</article-title><source>J Back Musculoskelet Rehabil</source><year>2011</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>231</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22142711</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Kirby</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><article-title>Introduction</article-title><source>Recent Advances in Orthotic Therapy: Improving Clinical Outcomes with a Pathology-Specific Approach</source><year>2011</year><publisher-name>Albany, New York: Lower Extremity Review, LLC</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Use of the Tissue Stress Model as a paradigm for developing an examination and management plan for a patient with plantar fasciitis</article-title><source>J Am Podiatr Med Assoc</source><year>2002</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>499</fpage><lpage>506</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12381799</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dananberg</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><article-title>Sagittal plane biomechanics. American Diabetes Association</article-title><source>J Am Podiatr Med Assoc</source><year>2000</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10659532</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Root</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Orien</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Weed</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><source>Normal and Abnormal Function of the Foot</source><year>1977</year><publisher-name>Los Angeles: Clinical Biomechanics Corp.</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Farmani</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Sadeghi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Saeedi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamali</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>The effect of foot orthoses on energy consumption in runners with flat foot</article-title><source>Indian J Physiol Occup Ther</source><year>2011</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>60</fpage><lpage>62</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hawke</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Burns</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Radford</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>du Toit</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><article-title>Custom foot orthoses for the treatment of foot pain: a systematic review</article-title><source>J Foot Ankle Res</source><year>2008</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>046</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1757-1146-1-S1-O46</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hume</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hopkins</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Rome</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Maulder</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Coyle</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Nigg</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><article-title>Effectiveness of foot orthoses for treatment and prevention of lower limb injuries: a review</article-title><source>Sports Med</source><year>2008</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>759</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2165/00007256-200838090-00005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18712943</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Blanch</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>McPoil</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><name><surname>Vicenzino</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><article-title>Foot orthoses and gait: a systematic review and meta-analysis of literature pertaining to potential mechanisms</article-title><source>Br J Sports Med</source><year>2010</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>1035</fpage><lpage>1046</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bjsm.2009.066977</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19996330</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Bisset</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>McPoil</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Vicenzino</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><article-title>Foot Orthoses in lower limb overuse conditions: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Foot Ankle Int</source><year>2007</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>396</fpage><lpage>410</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3113/FAI.2007.0396</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17371668</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Landorf</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Keenan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rushworth</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><article-title>Foot orthosis prescription habits of Australian and New Zealand podiatric physicians</article-title><source>J Am Podiatr Med Assoc</source><year>2001</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>174</fpage><lpage>183</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11319247</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Root</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Development of the functional orthosis</article-title><source>Clin Podiatr Med Surg</source><year>1994</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>183</fpage><lpage>210</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8205507</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nester</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Lundgren</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lundberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Arndt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><article-title>Effect of an antipronation foot orthosis on ankle and subtalar kinematics</article-title><source>Med Sci Sports Exerc</source><year>2012</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>2384</fpage><lpage>2391</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22968307</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chevalier</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Chockalingam</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><article-title>Effects of foot orthoses: How important is the practitioner?</article-title><source>Gait Posture</source><year>2012</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>383</fpage><lpage>388</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gaitpost.2011.10.356</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22104292</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Kirby</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><source>Foot and Lower Extremity Biomechanics. A Ten Year Collection of Prescision Intricast, Inc. newsletters</source><year>1997</year><publisher-name>Payson, Arizona: Precision Intricast, Inc</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>The flat-footed child - to treat or not to treat. What is the clinician to do?</article-title><source>J Am Podiatr Med Assoc</source><year>2009</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>179</fpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tudor</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruzic</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sestan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Sirola</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Prpi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><article-title>Flat-footedness is not a disadvantage for athletic performance in children aged 11 to 15&#x000a0;years</article-title><source>Pediatrics</source><year>2009</year><volume>123</volume><fpage>e386</fpage><lpage>e392</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.2008-2262</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19254974</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Esterman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pilotto</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><article-title>Foot shape and its effect on functioning in Royal Australian Air Force recruits. Part 2: Pilot, randomized, controlled trial of orthotics in recruits with flat feet</article-title><source>Mil Med</source><year>2005</year><volume>170</volume><fpage>629</fpage><lpage>633</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16130647</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>Australian Podiatry Council</collab><article-title>Clinical guidelines for orthotic therapy provided by Podiatrists</article-title><source>Australian Podiatry Manual Supplement</source><year>1998</year><publisher-name>Collingwood Victoria: Australian Podiatry Council</publisher-name><fpage>18</fpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Law</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pollock</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Letts</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bosch</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Westmorland</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><source>McMaster critical review form - Quantitative studies</source><year>1998</year><publisher-name>Hamilton, Ontario: McMaster University Occupational Therapy Evidence-Based Practice Research Group</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Law</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Pollock</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Letts</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bosch</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Westmorland</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><source>Guidelines for critical review form - Quantitative Studies</source><year>1998</year><publisher-name>Hamilton, Ontario: McMaster University Occupational Evidence-based Practice Research Group</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>Council NHaMR</collab><source>NHMRC levels of evidence and grades for recommendations for guideline developers</source><year>2009</year><publisher-name>Canberra: National Health and Medical Research Council</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lou</surname><given-names>SZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name><article-title>Effects of foot orthoses on gait patterns of flat feet patients</article-title><source>Clin Biomech</source><year>2010</year><volume>25</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>265</fpage><lpage>270</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clinbiomech.2009.11.007</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Murley</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name><surname>Landorf</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name><name><surname>Menz</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><article-title>Do foot orthoses change lower limb muscle activity in flat-arched feet towards a pattern observed in normal-arched feet?</article-title><source>Clin Biomech</source><year>2010</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>728</fpage><lpage>736</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clinbiomech.2010.05.001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zifchock</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><article-title>A comparison of semi-custom and custom foot orthotic devices in high- and low-arched individuals during walking</article-title><source>Clin Biomech</source><year>2008</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>1287</fpage><lpage>1293</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clinbiomech.2008.07.008</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zammit</surname><given-names>GV</given-names></name><name><surname>Payne</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><article-title>Relationship between positive clinical outcomes of foot orthotic treatment and changes in rearfoot kinematics</article-title><source>J Am Podiatr Med Assoc</source><year>2007</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17507529</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Murley</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bird</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>The effect of three levels of foot orthotic wedging on the surface electromyographic activity of selected lower limb muscles during gait</article-title><source>Clin Biomech</source><year>2006</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>1074</fpage><lpage>1080</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clinbiomech.2006.06.007</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Redmond</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lumb</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Landorf</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><article-title>Effect of cast and noncast foot orthoses on plantar pressure and force during normal gait</article-title><source>J Am Podiatr Med Assoc</source><year>2000</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>441</fpage><lpage>449</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11055169</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><source>Statistical Power Analysis for the Behavioural Sciences</source><year>1988</year><publisher-name>Hillsdale, N.J: L. Erlbaum Associates</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Portney</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name><surname>Watkins</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><source>Foundations of Clinical Research: Applications to Practice</source><year>2009</year><edition>3</edition><publisher-name>Upper Saddle River, N.J: Pearson/Prentice Hall</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>M&#x000fc;ndermann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nigg</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Neil Humble</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Stefanyshyn</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><article-title>Foot orthotics affect lower extremity kinematics and kinetics during running</article-title><source>Clin Biomech</source><year>2003</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>254</fpage><lpage>262</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0268-0033(02)00186-9</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rome</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><article-title>Randomized clinical trial into the impact of rigid foot orthoses on balance parameters in excessively pronated feet</article-title><source>Clin Rehabil</source><year>2004</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>624</fpage><lpage>630</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1191/0269215504cr767oa</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15473114</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Johanson</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Donatelli</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wooden</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrew</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Cummings</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><article-title>Effects of three different posting methods on controlling abnormal subtalar pronation</article-title><source>Phys Ther</source><year>1994</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>158</lpage><comment>discussion 158&#x02013;161</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8290620</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Otman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Basgoze</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Gokce-Kutsal</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><article-title>Energy cost of walking with flat feet</article-title><source>Prosthet Orthot Int</source><year>1988</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>76</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3174409</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hurd</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Kavros</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaufman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><article-title>Comparative biomechanical effectiveness of over-the-counter devices for individuals with a flexible flatfoot secondardy to forefoot varus</article-title><source>Clin J Sports Med</source><year>2010</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>428</fpage><lpage>435</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/JSM.0b013e3181fb539f</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cobb</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Tis</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Geil</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><article-title>Custom-molded foot-orthosis intervention and multisegment medial foot kinematics during walking</article-title><source>J Athl Train</source><year>2011</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>358</fpage><lpage>365</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21944067</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Menz</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><article-title>Foot orthoses: how much customisation is necessary?</article-title><source>J Foot Ankle Res</source><year>2009</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>23</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1757-1146-2-23</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19589160</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Girard</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Racinais</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>Impact of orthoses on changes in neuromuscular control and aerobic cost of a 1-H run</article-title><source>Med Sci Sports Exerc</source><year>2011</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>2335</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21552159</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Croce</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Cappozzo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerrigan</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><article-title>Pelvis and lower limb anatomical landmark calibration precision and its propagation to bone geometry and joint angles</article-title><source>Med Biol Eng Comput</source><year>1999</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>155</fpage><lpage>161</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02513282</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10396818</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Razeghi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Batt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Foot type classification: a critical review of current methods</article-title><source>Gait Posture</source><year>2002</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>282</fpage><lpage>291</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0966-6362(01)00151-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11983503</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cobb</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Tis</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><article-title>The effect of 6&#x000a0;weeks of custom-molded foot orthosis intervention on postural stability in participants with&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;or&#x02009;=&#x02009;7 degrees of forefoot varus</article-title><source>Clin J Sports Med</source><year>2006</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>316</fpage><lpage>322</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00042752-200607000-00006</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mattacola</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Dwyer</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Uhl</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>McCrory</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Malone</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><article-title>Effect of orthoses on postural stability in asymptomatic subjects with rearfoot malalignment during a 6-week acclimation period</article-title><source>Arch Phys Med Rehabil</source><year>2007</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>653</fpage><lpage>660</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apmr.2007.02.029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17466736</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hennacy</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><article-title>Metabolic eficiency of orthotic appliances measured by oxygen consumption</article-title><source>J Am Podiatr Med Assoc</source><year>1973</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>481</fpage><lpage>490</lpage></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>