<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Gen Physiol</journal-id><journal-title>The Journal of General Physiology</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0022-1295</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1540-7748</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Rockefeller University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">5651770</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2201162</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Osmotic Volume Flow in the Proximal Tubule of <italic>Necturus</italic> Kidney</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bentzel</surname><given-names>Carl J.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>Martin</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>Walter N.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zatzman</surname><given-names>Marvin</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Solomon</surname><given-names>A. K.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="N0x1c28ee0N0x3804240">From the Biophysical Laboratory, Harvard Medical School, Boston, Massachusetts 02115.</aff><author-notes><fn><p>Dr. Bentzel's present address is Department of Medicine, State University of New York at Buffalo, Buffalo, New York 14203. Dr. Davies's present address is Department of Biology, University of York, England. Dr. Scott's present address is School of Aerospace Medicine, Brooks Air Force Base, San Antonio, Texas 78235. Dr. Zatzman's present address is Department of Physiology, University of Missouri, Columbia, Missouri 65201</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>1</day><month>4</month><year>1968</year></pub-date><volume>51</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>517</fpage><lpage>533</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>8</month><year>1967</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 1968 by The Rockefeller University Press</copyright-statement></permissions><abstract><p> Volume changes due to osmotic flow in the distal portion of proximal tubules of <italic>Necturi</italic> were measured by the split oil drop technique. In agreement with previous findings no volume flow was induced by NaCl concentrations close to 60 m<sc>M</sc>. The tubule wall was found to be permeable to plasma electrolytes, which have an apparent reflection coefficient of 0.69. The mean apparent hydraulic conductivity was 0.33 x 10<sup>-11</sup> cm<sup>3</sup>/dyne sec, comparable with other epithelia. A number of lipid-insoluble nonelectrolytes of widely varying molecular size had apparent reflection coefficients of about 0.5. In view of the insensitivity to molecular size it seems likely that apparent reflection coefficients determined from tubular volume changes depend primarily on the porosity of the intercellular barrier closest to the lumen and give little information about the subsequent fate of the test substances. </p></abstract></article-meta></front></article>


