<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="other"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Indian Soc Periodontol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Indian Soc Periodontol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JISP</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Indian Society of Periodontology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0972-124X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">0975-1580</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Medknow Publications &#x00026; Media Pvt Ltd</publisher-name><publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25624619</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4296447</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">JISP-18-683</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0972-124X.147395</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Secretary's Message</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>ISP reloaded</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Manohar</surname><given-names>Balaji</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><italic>Secretary, Indian Society of Periodontology, Professor and Head, Department of Periodontology, Pacific Dental College and Hospital, Udaipur, Rajasthan, India. E-mail: <email xlink:href="manohar_balaji@hotmail.com">manohar_balaji@hotmail.com</email></italic></aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>Nov-Dec</season><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>18</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>683</fpage><lpage>683</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; Journal of Indian Society of Periodontology</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions></article-meta></front><body><p><graphic xlink:href="JISP-18-683-g001.jpg" position="float"/></p><disp-quote><p>The mind is not a vessel to be filled, but a fire to be kindled.</p><attrib><italic>-Plutarch</italic></attrib></disp-quote><p>Well!!! It is that time of the year when we change guards. And I must admit, what a wonderful year we had totally dedicated to the science of periodontology. Thank you Dr. Ashish Jain for leading us and providing us with wonderful opportunities to kindling our mind and not just merely filling it.</p><p>End of October saw the culmination of the scientific events and the grand annual event, a national conference at Jaipur where our new office took over under the leadership of Dr. Biju Thomas.</p><p>This year too as has been a trend in the previous years, the focus is on promoting the science of periodontology to the general dentist and the public at large. We intend to reach out to the general dentists in far-flung areas of the country through our now popular program &#x02013; Professional Enrichment Program in areas where we might be having very little presence as a specialist. Yes, we are, for the very first time, and if I may be allowed to say, the very first specialty dental organization to reach out to our colleagues in the North-Eastern part of the country &#x02013; Imphal in Manipur; the Northern most part of the country - Jammu in Jammu and Kashmir and in the East at Cuttack in Orissa. All this is not possible without the support and help of our fellow members who are actively supporting our endeavor.</p><p>The motto of our society is to Nuture the Science of Periodontology. What better way than to associate with other specialty dental organizations and propagate the same. The office is mulling on the idea of joining hands with a few specialty organization this year, the details of which will be given to you all at the appropriate time.</p><p>The regular programs and events of the society will continue this year too, and I request you to continue to give your full support and participate in these programs. The programs are being designed for the benefit of the life members as well as the student members.</p><p>Looking forward to having full support from you all.</p><disp-quote><p>Live as if you were to die tomorrow. Learn as if you were to live forever.</p><attrib><italic>-Mahatma Gandhi</italic></attrib></disp-quote></body></article>