<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Korean Med Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">jkms</journal-id><journal-title>Journal of Korean Medical Science</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">1011-8934</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1598-6357</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Korean Academy of Medical Sciences</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">10895976</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3054648</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Effects of oncostatin M on hormone release of rat pituitary cells in primary culture.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>D. S.</given-names></name><email>dskim@hmc.hanyang.ac.kr</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>H. S.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>Y. S.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>T. W.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Internal Medicine, Hanyang University College of Medicine, Seoul, Korea.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>6</month><year>2000</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>323</fpage><lpage>326</lpage><abstract><p>It has become increasingly clear that cytokines play an important role in modulating neuroendocrine regulation, especially in the secretion of corticotropin (ACTH) in the pituitary. Oncostatin M (OSM), a cytokine of IL-6 family has been reported to increase ACTH secretion and pro-opiomelanocortin (POMC) transcription in murine corticotroph pituitary tumor cells (AtT20 cells). The present study was undertaken to determine the effects of OSM on hormonal release in primary culture of rat pituitary cells. Growth hormone or prolactin release was not affected by OSM. OSM (1 nM) stimulated ACTH release (35.1% increase versus control, p&#x0003c;0.001) in dispersed pituitary cells of rat to a lesser extent than in AtT20 cells. Corticotropin releasing hormone (CRH) (10 nM) also induced a 2.3-fold increase of ACTH secretion (p&#x0003c;0.001), but co-treatment of OSM and CRH did not exhibit any synergistic effect on ACTH secretion. We conclude OSM has a stimulatory effect on ACTH secretion in normal rat pituitary cell cultures, and OSM acts mainly on corticotroph, supporting the potential role of OSM to modulate immune-endocrine regulation in the pituitary.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article>

