<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Pharm Bioallied Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Pharm Bioallied Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JPBS</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Pharmacy &#x00026; Bioallied Sciences</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0976-4879</issn><issn pub-type="epub">0975-7406</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Medknow Publications &#x00026; Media Pvt Ltd</publisher-name><publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23066290</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3467934</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">JPBS-4-358</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0975-7406.100271</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Dental Science - Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Comparative study of palatal rugae pattern in class II div 1 and class I individuals</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gandikota</surname><given-names>Chandrasekhar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Venkata</surname><given-names>Yudhister Palla</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Challa</surname><given-names>Padmalatha</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Juvvadi</surname><given-names>Shubhaker Rao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mathur</surname><given-names>Anirudh</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">2</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">Department of Orthodontics and Dentofacial Orthopedics, Panineeya Mahavidyalaya institute of Dental Sciences and Research Centre, Hyderabad, Andhra Pradesh, India</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>1</label>Department of Orthodontics and Dentofacial Orthopedics, Mamatha Dental College and Hospital, Khammam, Andhra Pradesh, India</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>2</label>Department of Orthodontics, HKDET Dental college, Humnabad, Karnataka, India</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold>Address for correspondence:</bold> Dr. Chandrasekhar Gandikota E-mail: <email xlink:href="gcsekhargc@gmail.com">gcsekhargc@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>8</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>4</volume><issue>Suppl 2</issue><fpage>S358</fpage><lpage>S363</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>01</day><month>12</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>02</day><month>1</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>26</day><month>1</month><year>2012</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; Journal of Pharmacy and Bioallied Sciences</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec id="st1"><title>Aims:</title><p>To determine if the palatal rugae have a characteristic pattern in untreated class II div 1 malocclusions compared to normal class I occlusions, and to provide a valuable insight whether palatal rugae can be taken up as additional criteria for classifying malocclusions.</p></sec><sec id="st2"><title>Materials and Methods:</title><p>The study was conducted on initial maxillary dental casts of 24 individuals with untreated class II div 1 malocclusion with an overjet of minimum of 5mm, of whom 12 were females and 12 were males, with age ranging from 16 to 24 years and compared with Class I patients casts.</p></sec><sec id="st3"><title>Results:</title><p>There was no statistically significant difference in the mean intermolar widths of the two groups. The first, second and third palatal rugae were shorter in class II div 1 patients than in class I patients which was statistically significant. All the patients with Angle's class I occlusion had good pattern of palatal rugae falling in the score range of 1&#x02013;3, whereas 22% of the patients with class II div 1 had poor pattern of palatal rugae, with score 4 and 2 patients exhibiting a score of 4 and 5, respectively, but this was not statistically significant.</p></sec><sec id="st4"><title>Conclusion:</title><p>There was a significant constriction of the palatal rugae in class II div 1 individuals as compared to class I individuals, though they were matched for the same intermolar widths. There was a distinct pattern of palatal rugae between the two groups.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><title>KEY WORDS</title><kwd>Palatal rugae</kwd><kwd>class II div 1 malocclusion</kwd><kwd>class I malocclusion</kwd><kwd>intermolar widths</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Palatal rugae are the ridges situated in the anterior part of the palatal mucosa on each side of the median palatal raphe and behind the incisive papilla [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>]. Goria[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>] defined the rugae as the ridges that extend at least one-half the distance from the median palatal raphe to the dental arch. The palatal rugae appear toward the 3<sup>rd</sup> month of intrauterine life, from the covering connective tissue in the palatine process of maxillary bone, and its development and growth is mutually controlled by epithelial&#x02013;mesenchymal interactions, where specific extracellular matrix molecules are spatiotemporally expressed during development.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>] The first rugae are distinguished in human embryos of 32-mm Crown-rump length (CRL) next to the incisive papilla.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>] Then, in the prenatal stage, they are relatively prominent,[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref>] the palatal rugae at birth are well traines with a typical orientation pattern and during adolescence they acquire the final feature shape of each individual.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref>] Once formed, they may experience changes in their size due to growth of the palate, but their shape is maintained.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref>] Physiologically, the palatal rugae are involved in the oral swallowing and help to improve the relationship between food and the taste receptors in the dorsal surface of the tongue.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>] They also participate in speech and in suction in children.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref>] The palatal rugae form elevations more or less prominent and take various configurations. The stability of palatal rugae as a landmark for dental cast analysis was reported by Almeida <italic>et al</italic>.,[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref>] Bailey <italic>et al</italic>.,[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>] and Patil <italic>et al</italic>.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref>] Form, layout, and characteristics are not affected by the eruption of the teeth or their loss, but sometimes palatal rugae adjacent to the alveolar arch slightly change their position after tooth extraction.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref>] However, some events may contribute to changes in the pattern of PR, such as finger sucking in childhood and persistent pressure due to orthodontic treatment. Furthermore, it has been reported that extractions can produce a local effect on the direction of the PR.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref>] The PR has been considered relevant for human identification due to its stability,[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref>] and being equivalent to the fingerprint, is unique for each individual.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref>] This study on the identification of persons is called palatoscopy or palate rugoscopy.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref>] The idea of this study was spurred whether this pattern of rugae can be mapped for a category of patients.</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Rugae</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JPBS-4-358-g001"/></fig><sec id="sec1-1"><title>Aims and Objectives</title><p>The aims of the study were the following:</p><p>
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p>To determine if the palatal rugae have a characteristic pattern in untreated class II div 1 malocclusions compared to normal class I occlusions.</p></list-item><list-item><p>To provide a valuable insight whether palatal rugae can be taken up as additional criteria for classifying malocclusions.</p></list-item></list>
</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec1-2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><p>The study was conducted on initial maxillary dental casts of 27 individuals with untreated class II div 1 malocclusion, of whom 14 were females and 13 were males, with age ranging from 16 to 24 years. Initial maxillary dental casts of 24 individuals (12 males and 12 females) with untreated class I occlusion matched to the same age group as above were taken up. Impressions were made of alginate and poured with type III dental stone.</p></sec><sec id="sec1-3"><title>Further Criteria of Selection</title><p>Class II div 1 samples with an overjet of a minimum of 5 mm were selected. Intermolar width measured from central fossae of molars was taken up as a standardization criterion.</p><p>The palatal rugae were carefully highlighted using 0.5-mm pencil and the precise measurements were done on a transparent measurement template. The traced palatal rugae were observed for size, shape, direction, and pattern.</p><p>A median palatal plane was constructed as a reference plane [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>]. Based on the length, the rugae were classified as: Primary, 5 mm and above; secondary, 3&#x02013;5 mm; and fragmentary, less than 2 mm [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>]. Primary rugae were then interpreted based on the classification given by Lysell <italic>et al</italic>.,[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref>] Shetty <italic>et al</italic>.,[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref>] and Nayak <italic>et al</italic>.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref>] Based on the shape, the primary rugae were classified as curved wavy straight circular [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>].</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Median palatal plane as a reference plane</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JPBS-4-358-g002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Length of rugae</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JPBS-4-358-g003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Classification based on shape</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JPBS-4-358-g004"/></fig><p>Based on the direction, they were classified as: (a) forward directed (a) and (b) backward directed [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>]. Based on the unification, the primary rugae were classified as (a) converging and (b) diverging [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>].</p><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Classification based on direction</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JPBS-4-358-g005"/></fig><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Classification based on unification</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JPBS-4-358-g006"/></fig><p>A final ordinal scale was put up [Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">12</xref>].</p><fig id="F7" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Final ordinal scale 1</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JPBS-4-358-g007"/></fig><fig id="F8" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Final ordinal scale 2</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JPBS-4-358-g008"/></fig><fig id="F9" position="float"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p>Final ordinal scale 3</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JPBS-4-358-g009"/></fig><fig id="F10" position="float"><label>Figure 10</label><caption><p>Final ordinal scale 4</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JPBS-4-358-g010"/></fig><fig id="F11" position="float"><label>Figure 11</label><caption><p>Final ordinal scale 5</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JPBS-4-358-g011"/></fig><fig id="F12" position="float"><label>Figure 12</label><caption><p>Ordinal scale index tabulation</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JPBS-4-358-g012"/></fig><sec id="sec2-1"><title>Statistical Methods Used</title><p>
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Unpaired <italic>t</italic>-test was used to compare differences between two means.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Chi-square test was used to find the distribution of proportions among the samples.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Analysis of variance (ANOVA) was used to find out if any relationship existed between the size andpattern of palatal rugae.</p></list-item></list>
</p></sec><sec id="sec2-2"><title>Software used &#x02013; SPSS Version 14.0</title><p>The following parameters were analyzed:</p><p>
<list list-type="alpha-lower"><list-item><p>Mean intermolar width and comparison between two groups.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The total widths of the primary rugae 1, 2, 3, and comparison between two groups.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Ordinal scale index of each cast and comparison between two groups.</p></list-item><list-item><p>ANOVA test to compare if any relationship existed between the size and pattern of palatal rugae.</p></list-item></list>
</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec1-4"><title>Results</title><p>With <italic>P</italic> value of 0.435, there was no statistically significant difference in the mean intermolar widths of the two groups [<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>].</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Inter molar width</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JPBS-4-358-g013"/></table-wrap><p>The first palatal rugae were shorter in class II div 1 patients than in class I patients by 1.43 mm and this difference was statistically significant as evident by a <italic>P</italic> value = 0.021 [<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>].</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Total transverse width of primary palatal rugae 1</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JPBS-4-358-g014"/></table-wrap><p>The second palatal rugae were shorter in class II div 1 patients than in class I patients by 3.1 mm and this difference was statistically significant as evident by a <italic>P</italic> value = 0.001 [<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>].</p><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Total transverse width of primary palatal rugae 2</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JPBS-4-358-g015"/></table-wrap><p>The third palatal rugae were evidently shorter in class II div 1 patients than in class I patients by 4.24 mm and this difference was statistically highly significant as evident by a <italic>P</italic> value = 0.000 [<xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">Table 4</xref>].</p><table-wrap id="T4" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Total transverse width of primary palatal rugae 3</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JPBS-4-358-g016"/></table-wrap><p>All the patients with Angle's class I occlusion had good pattern of palatal rugae falling in the range of 1&#x02013;3, whereas 22% of the patients with class II div 1 had poor pattern of palatal rugae, with 4 and 2 patients exhibiting a score of 4 and 5, respectively, but this was not statistically significant according to chi-square test with a <italic>P</italic> value = 0.12 [<xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">Table 5</xref>].</p><table-wrap id="T5" position="float"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Angle's class vs index cross tabulation</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JPBS-4-358-g017"/></table-wrap></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec1-5"><title>Discussion</title><p>The mean intermolar width was taken as a standardization for both the groups, with the mean intermolar width in class I sample being 47.25 &#x000b1; 2.06 mm and in class II div 1 sample being 46.81 &#x000b1; 1.88 mm. There was a significant difference in the total transverse widths of all the three palatal rugae between the two groups, with the third rugae showing a highly significant difference. This shows the constriction of the arch in class II div 1 individuals than in class I individuals, even with matched intermolar widths. The ordinal scale we have put up in this study has provided a method of categorizing the pattern for each group, though the palatal rugae possess unique patient characteristics. The results of the individual distribution of rugae pattern among the groups, though statistically not significant according to chi-square test, show that to some extent there is a near-normal pattern for the class I sample than the class II div 1 sample.</p><p>There were no significant differences between sexes for most of the above findings.</p><p>The findings of the ANOVA test showed no significant relationship between the size and pattern of the palatal rugae between the two groups. Hauser <italic>et al</italic>.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19">19</xref>] in 1989 stated that size of the palate affected rugae development. They reported that individuals with broader palates showed greater rugae development.</p><p>Most of the studies were done to establish the stability of palatal rugae as landmarks by Almeida <italic>et al</italic>.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref>] By comparing extraction and non-extraction cases, Bailey <italic>et al</italic>.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>] had studied the effects on palatal rugae, before and after orthodontic treatment in both children and adults. The transverse widths were taken into consideration and they were longitudinal studies comparing the treatment effects in the same cohort. In our study, an effort was made to compare the differences between two groups, namely class I occlusion and class II div 1 patients. Here, not only the transverse widths were taken into consideration, but also the pattern was observed. A new ordinal scale was put up to categorize the pattern. An effort was made to standardize both the groups and the selection criteria were followed. A simple method of recording the size of palatal rugae was followed rather than the reflex metrograph (RMG), a 3D digitizer as suggested by Scott,[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">20</xref>] and Richmond and Jones.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">21</xref>] Bansode and Kulkarni[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref22">22</xref>] found that some changes do occur in the rugae during orthodontic treatment and the morphology of palatal rugae remains stable throughout life. Paliwal <italic>et al</italic>.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref23">23</xref>] concluded that straight rugae pattern on the right side of the palate in the male subjects was found to be significantly predominant in the MP population, whereas wavy shape was predominant in Keralites; however, rugae patterns on the right side of the palate in female subjects exhibited no significant difference. Jibi <italic>et al</italic>.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref24">24</xref>] revealed with regard to shape and unification, females showed a significantly higher diverging rugae type while males had a significant number of circular and converging type of rugae.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusion" id="sec1-6"><title>Conclusion</title><p>There was a significant constriction of the palatal rugae in class II div 1 individuals as compared to class I individuals, though they were matched for the same intermolar widths. There was a distinct pattern of palatal rugae between the two groups. It is too premature to make a comment on the use of palatal rugae to classify malocclusions. Though an interrelationship between size and pattern was not obtained, further studies in this direction can provide a valuable insight.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="supported-by"><p><bold>Source of Support:</bold> Nil</p></fn><fn fn-type="conflict"><p><bold>Conflict of Interest:</bold> None declared.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goria</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>&#x0201c;Le Rughe del Palato in Speciale Rapporto coll&#x02019;Anthropologia Criminale e ]a Psichiatria&#x0201d;</article-title><source>Archives of Criminal Anthropology</source><year>1911</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>72</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Amasaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagasao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mutoh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ichihara</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Asari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Distributional changes of BrdU, PCNA, E2F1 and PAL31 molecules in developing murine palatal rugae</article-title><source>Ann Anat</source><year>2003</year><volume>185</volume><fpage>517</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14703996</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buchtov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tichy</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Putnov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000ed;sek</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The development of palatal rugae in the European pine vole, Microtus subterraneus (Arvicolidae, Rodentia)</article-title><source>Folia Zoo</source><year>2003</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>36</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Waterman</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Meller</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alteration in the epithelial surfaces of human palatal shelves prior to and during fusion: A scanning electron microscope study</article-title><source>Anat Rec</source><year>1974</year><volume>180</volume><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4411922</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamazaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cross-sectional study of plicae palatinae transversae in the Japanese</article-title><source>Anthropol Rep Niigata</source><year>1962</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>76</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jordanov</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Growth of the hard palate in man. Anthropological characteristics</article-title><source>Z Morphol Anthropol</source><year>1971</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>230</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5150374</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Baumeister</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Postnatal development of the width and height of the palate and the palate foramina</article-title><source>Anat Anz</source><year>1984</year><volume>155</volume><fpage>151</fpage><lpage>67</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6721177</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kotze</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Merwe</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An improved statistical method for the racial classification of man by means of palatal rugae</article-title><source>Arch Oral Biol</source><year>1987</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>315</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3478034</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Almeida</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kula</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tulloch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stability of the palatal rugae as landmarks for analysis of dental casts</article-title><source>Angle Orthod</source><year>1995</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7726462</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name><surname>Esmailnejad</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Almeida</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stability of the palatal rugae as landmarks for analysis of dental casts in extraction and nonextraction cases</article-title><source>Angle Orthod</source><year>1996</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8678349</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patil</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Patil</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Acharya</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Palatine rugae and their significance in clinical dentistry: A review of the literature</article-title><source>J Am Dent Assoc</source><year>2008</year><volume>139</volume><fpage>1471</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18978384</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peavy</surname><given-names>DC</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Kendrick</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effects of tooth movement on the palatine rugae</article-title><source>J Prosthet Dent</source><year>1967</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>536</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5234941</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Limson</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Julian</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Computerized recording of the palatal rugae pattern and an evaluation of its application in forensic identification</article-title><source>J Forensic Odontostomatol</source><year>2004</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16223024</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muthusubramanian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Limson</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Julian</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of rugae in burn victims and cadavers to simulate rugae identification in cases of incineration and decomposition</article-title><source>J Forensic Odontostomatol</source><year>2005</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>26</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16223023</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caldas</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name><surname>Magalh&#x000e3;es</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Afonso</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Establishing identityusing cheiloscopy and palatoscopy</article-title><source>Forensic Sci Int</source><year>2007</year><volume>165</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16725290</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lysell</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>(1955). Plicae palatinae transversae and papilla incisiva in man</article-title><source>Acta Odontol Scand</source><year>1989</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>137</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shetty</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalia</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Patil</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahima</surname><given-names>VG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Palatal Rugae pattern in Mysorean and Tibetian population</article-title><source>Indian J Dent Res</source><year>2009</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>51</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16372793</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nayak</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Acharya</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Padmini</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaveri</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differences in palatal rugae shape in two populations of India</article-title><source>Arch Oral Biol</source><year>2007</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>977</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17543270</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hauser</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Deponte</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Palatal Rugae</article-title><source>J Anat</source><year>1989</year><volume>165</volume><fpage>237</fpage><lpage>49</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17103618</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The reflex plotters: Measurement without photographs</article-title><source>Photogrammetric Rec</source><year>1981</year><volume>151</volume><fpage>304</fpage><lpage>305</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Richmond</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A comparision of two and three dimensional incisor angles</article-title><source>Br J Orthod</source><year>1985</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>90</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3859331</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bansode</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kulkarni</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Importance of palatal rugae in individual identification</article-title><source>J Forensic Dent Sci</source><year>2009</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>81</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paliwal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wanjari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Parwani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Palatal rugoscopy: Establishing identity</article-title><source>J Forensic Dent Sci</source><year>2010</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21189987</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jibi</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gautam</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Basappa</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Raju</surname><given-names>OS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Morphological Pattern of Palatal Rugae in Children of Davangere</article-title><source>J Forensic Sci</source><year>2011</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>1192</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21777237</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>