<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Korean J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Korean J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Korean Journal of Thoracic and Cardiovascular Surgery</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2233-601X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2093-6516</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Korean Society for Thoracic and Cardiovascular Surgery</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25207258</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4157512</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5090/kjtcs.2014.47.4.423</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">kjtcvs-47-423</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Surgical Resection of Thoracic Duct Lymphangioma</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bok</surname><given-names>Jin San</given-names></name><degrees>M.D.</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jun</surname><given-names>Jae Hyun</given-names></name><degrees>M.D.</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Hyun Joo</given-names></name><degrees>M.D., Ph.D.</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>In Kyu</given-names></name><degrees>M.D., Ph.D.</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>Chang Hyun</given-names></name><degrees>M.D., Ph.D.</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Young Tae</given-names></name><degrees>M.D., Ph.D.</degrees><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1-kjtcvs-47-423"/></contrib><aff id="af1-kjtcvs-47-423">Department of Thoracic and Cardiovascular Surgery, Seoul National University Hospital</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1-kjtcvs-47-423">Corresponding author: Young Tae Kim, Department of Thoracic and Cardiovascular Surgery, Seoul National University Hospital, 101 Daehak-ro, Jongno-gu, Seoul 110-744, Korea, (Tel) 82-2-2072-3161 (Fax) 82-2-764-3664 (E-mail) <email>ytkim@snu.ac.kr</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>8</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>05</day><month>8</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>47</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>423</fpage><lpage>426</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>10</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>25</day><month>11</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>26</day><month>11</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2014 by The Korean Society for Thoracic and Cardiovascular Surgery. All rights Reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><license><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>A 67-year-old male patient came to the hospital due to lung cancer and mediastinal cystic mass which was suspected to be esophageal duplication cyst. Video-assisted thoracoscopic surgery (VATS) was performed and intra-operative finding suggested it as a cystic mass along the thoracic duct. Thoracic duct was ligated and the cyst was completely resected. A 48-year-old female patient visited the hospital for dysphagia. Mediastinal cystic mass was suspected to be an esophageal duplication cyst. Intraoperative finding suggest a thoracic duct lymphangioma. After thoracic duct ligation, the mass was completely resected with VATS. Postoperative chylothorax did not develop in both cases.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Thoracic duct</kwd><kwd>Lymphangioma</kwd><kwd>Chylothorax</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>CASE REPORTS</title><sec><title>1) Case 1</title><p>A 67-year-old male patient presented to the hospital with a right lower lobe nodule and a paraesophageal cystic mass, which were discovered by regular chest computed tomography (CT). The 2.5-cm right lower lobe nodule was suspected to be a lung cancer. The 4-cm paraesophageal cystic mass was located on the left side of the esophagus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1-kjtcvs-47-423">Fig. 1</xref>). The mass was suspected to be an esophageal duplication cyst or a bronchogenic cyst.</p><p>Video-assisted thoracoscopic surgery (VATS) was performed. The right lower lobe nodule was proven to be adenocarcinoma by a frozen biopsy, and a right lower lobectomy and mediastinal lymph node dissection were carried out. After further dissection through the mediastinum, the mediastinal mass was located on the left side of the esophagus. However, rather than originating from the esophagus, it seemed that the mass was connected to the thoracic duct. On the basis of this finding, we suspected that the mass was a lymphangioma originating from the thoracic duct. To prevent chylothorax, the thoracic duct was carefully ligated with metal clips and the mass was resected. A 32-French chest tube was inserted into the right pleural cavity.</p><p>There was no sign of chylothorax, and the chest tube was removed on the 4th postoperative day. The patient was discharged from the hospital on the 5th postoperative day without complication. The mass was confirmed to be a lymphangioma by a pathologic examination and by immunohistochemistry, on which the mass was positive for CD31, CD34, factor VIII, and D2-40.</p></sec><sec><title>2) Case 2</title><p>A 48-year-old female patient presented to the hospital for dysphagia that had begun 1 month prior. Chest CT showed a 5.5-cm mediastinal cystic mass, which was located posterior to the lower esophagus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2-kjtcvs-47-423">Fig. 2</xref>). It was suspected to be an esophageal duplication cyst or a bronchogenic cyst. Endoscopic ultrasonography indicated that it may be a bronchogenic tumor or an esophageal duplication cyst.</p><p>An operation was performed by right-side VATS with the patient in a semi-prone position. The mass seemed to originate from the thoracic duct; therefore, the thoracic duct was clipped, and the mass was excised (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3-kjtcvs-47-423">Fig. 3</xref>). When the mass was dissected on a table, a milky fluid was found (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4-kjtcvs-47-423">Fig. 4</xref>). A 20-French chest tube was inserted into the patient&#x02019;s pleural cavity.</p><p>Chylothorax did not occur postoperatively. The chest tube was removed on the 2nd postoperative day. The patient was discharged from the hospital on the 5th postoperative day. In the pathologic examination, the mass was confirmed to be a 4.5&#x000d7;4.0&#x000d7;1.0 cm lymphangioma (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5-kjtcvs-47-423">Fig. 5</xref>). By immunohistochemistry, the mass was demonstrated to be positive for CD31 and negative for D2-40 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6-kjtcvs-47-423">Figs. 6</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f7-kjtcvs-47-423">7</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>The thoracic duct originates in the abdomen at the level of the diaphragm, penetrates through the posterior and superior mediastinum, and exits the thorax through the thoracic aperture, which is usually posterior to the left innominate vein and left of the common carotid artery [<xref rid="b1-kjtcvs-47-423" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Cysts of the thoracic duct can occur either above or below the diaphragm. Supradiaphragmatic thoracic duct cysts are typically found in the neck. However, mediastinal thoracic duct cysts are quite uncommon [<xref rid="b2-kjtcvs-47-423" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>].</p><p>The cysts are often symptomatic because of the pressure they exert on the adjacent structures. Symptoms such as coughing, dyspnea, and chest discomfort may be present. Symptoms of dysphagia are often associated with the ingestion of fatty foods. Furthermore, acute respiratory insufficiency after the ingestion of a fatty meal is also observed in some patients [<xref rid="b1-kjtcvs-47-423" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. In case 2, the patient experienced dysphagia, which may caused by the cystic mass.</p><p>Bronchogenic and esophageal duplication cysts account for a majority of the mediastinal cysts, and thoracic duct cysts are rarely included in the differential diagnosis. Magnetic resonance imaging is not routinely required for the management of mediastinal cysts but may be able to demonstrate the communication of the cyst with the thoracic duct or the cisterna chyli. The high signal intensity of the T2-weighted images is attributed to the high lipid and protein content in the cyst. Surgical resection of mediastinal cysts, including thoracic duct cysts, is indicated once they are discovered. These cysts are removed to relieve the symptoms and to prevent further growth, infection, and possible malignant transformation [<xref rid="b2-kjtcvs-47-423" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. CD-31 and D2-40 are the known markers of lymphangioma [<xref rid="b3-kjtcvs-47-423" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. In both cases, the mass was positive for CD-31, which is also called PECAM-1 and is an adhesion molecule that is expressed in the monocytes, granulocytes, and T-cell subsets [<xref rid="b4-kjtcvs-47-423" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. D2-40, a monoclonal antibody, which binds lymphatic epithelial cells, stained positive only in the mass from case 1 [<xref rid="b5-kjtcvs-47-423" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].</p><p>Surgical treatment for lymphangioma consists of the removal of the cyst and the ligation of all the lymphatics connected to it [<xref rid="b1-kjtcvs-47-423" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Kwak and Bae [<xref rid="b6-kjtcvs-47-423" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] reported that they ligated the thoracic duct and that the chylothorax was not observed thereafter. In the case of a mediastinal cystic mass that is adjacent to the esophagus, the mass may originate from the thoracic duct. As such, when removing the mass, the operator should note its relationship with the thoracic duct. If the mass seems to originate from the thoracic duct, it should be ligated to prevent chylothorax.</p><p>Here, we report two cases of thoracic duct lymphangioma. Initially, these cases were thought to be esophageal duplication cysts; however, they were found to be thoracic duct lymphangiomas. To prevent postoperative chylothorax, it is important to suspect thoracic duct lymphangioma if a cystic mass is present along the course of the thoracic duct.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn id="fn1-kjtcvs-47-423"><p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST</p><p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was reported.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="b1-kjtcvs-47-423"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Turkyilmaz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Eroglu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A giant thoracic duct cyst: an unusual cause of dysphagia</article-title><source>J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg</source><year>2007</year><volume>134</volume><fpage>1082</fpage><lpage>3</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17903550</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b2-kjtcvs-47-423"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mortman</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mediastinal thoracic duct cyst</article-title><source>Ann Thorac Surg</source><year>2009</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>2006</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19932278</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b3-kjtcvs-47-423"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhawan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Taungjaruwinai</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inconsistent immunohistochemical expression of lymphatic and blood endothelial cell markers in cutaneous lymphangiomas</article-title><source>J Cutan Pathol</source><year>2013</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>801</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23782346</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b4-kjtcvs-47-423"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Janeway</surname><given-names>CA</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group><source>Immunobiology: the immune system in health and disease</source><edition>6th ed</edition><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Garland Science</publisher-name><year>2005</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="b5-kjtcvs-47-423"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kahn</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Marks</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Monoclonal antibody D2-40, a new marker of lymphatic endothelium, reacts with Kaposi&#x02019;s sarcoma and a subset of angiosarcomas</article-title><source>Mod Pathol</source><year>2002</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>434</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11950918</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b6-kjtcvs-47-423"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kwak</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Thoracic duct cyst in mediastinum: a case report</article-title><source>Korean J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg</source><year>2011</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>83</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22263132</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="f1-kjtcvs-47-423" position="float"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Case 1. Chest computed tomography shows 4-cm sized mediastinal cystic mass adjacent to left side of the esophagus. The mass was suspected to be an esophageal duplication cyst or a bronchogenic cyst.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="kjtcvs-47-423f1"/></fig><fig id="f2-kjtcvs-47-423" position="float"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Case 2. Chest computed tomography shows 5.5-cm sized mediastinal cystic mass which was located on the posterior to the lower esophagus. It was suspected to be an esophageal duplication cyst or a bronchogenic cyst.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="kjtcvs-47-423f2"/></fig><fig id="f3-kjtcvs-47-423" position="float"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Case 2. Video-assisted thoracoscopic surgery image shows division of thoracic duct after clipping.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="kjtcvs-47-423f3"/></fig><fig id="f4-kjtcvs-47-423" position="float"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Case 2. Specimen of 4.5&#x000d7;4.0&#x000d7;1.0-cm sized thoracic duct lymphangioma. The cystic mass was filled with milky fluid and the probe is located in the thoracic duct.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="kjtcvs-47-423f4"/></fig><fig id="f5-kjtcvs-47-423" position="float"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Case 2. Lymphoid aggregates are observed (H&#x00026;E, &#x000d7;200).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="kjtcvs-47-423f5"/></fig><fig id="f6-kjtcvs-47-423" position="float"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Case 2. Lymphatic epithelial cells are stained with CD31 antibody (immunohistochemistry with CD31, &#x000d7;200).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="kjtcvs-47-423f6"/></fig><fig id="f7-kjtcvs-47-423" position="float"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Case 2. The cystic mass was negative for D2-40 (immunohistochemistry with D2-40, &#x000d7;200).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="kjtcvs-47-423f7"/></fig></floats-group></article>