<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Korean J Hepatobiliary Pancreat Surg</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Korean J Hepatobiliary Pancreat Surg</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">KJHBPS</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Korean Journal of Hepato-Biliary-Pancreatic Surgery</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1738-6349</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2288-9213</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Korean Association of Hepato-Biliary-Pancreatic Surgery</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26155245</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4492330</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14701/kjhbps.2014.18.1.33</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>AFP-producing acinar cell carcinoma treated by pancreaticoduodenectomy in a patient with a previous radical subtotal gastrectomy by gastric cancer</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Chang Young</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Sung Hwan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jeon</surname><given-names>Hyae Min</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Hyun Ki</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>Chang Moo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Woo Jung</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Surgery, Yonsei University College of Medicine, Seoul, Korea.</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Pathology, Yonsei University College of Medicine, Seoul, Korea.</aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Pancreaticobiliary Cancer Clinic, Institute of Gastroenterology, Yonsei University Severance Hospital, Seoul, Korea.</aff><author-notes><corresp>
Corresponding author: Chang Moo Kang. Department of Surgery, Yonsei University College of Medicine, Ludlow Faculty Research Building #204, 50 Yonsei-ro, Seodaemun-gu, Seoul 120-752, Korea. Tel: +82-2-2228-2100, Fax: +82-2-313-8289, <email>cmkang@yuhs.ac</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>2</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>24</day><month>2</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>18</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>37</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>11</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>10</day><month>12</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>12</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2014 by The Korean Association of Hepato-Biliary-Pancreatic Surgery</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>We report a case of alpha-fetoprotein (AFP)-producing acinar cell carcinoma (ACC) of the pancreas. The tumor was diagnosed in a 72 yearold female after radical subtotal gastrectomy (Billroth I) due to early gastric cancer six months before. The initial serum AFP levels were increased to 2,254.1 IU/ml and preoperative imaging studies showed a mass with approximately 2.5 cm in diameter near the neck of the pancreas. A pancreaticoduodenectomy was performed. The pathologic examination revealed an ill-defined lobulating tumor confined to the pancreas (T1 stage). Immunohistochemical study showed that the tumor cells expressed AFP. The Adenosine triphosphate-based chemotherapy response assay (ATP-CRA) suggested that cisplatin would be more desirable than gemcitabine in AFP-producing ACC of the pancreas as an adjuvant chemotherapy. However, the adjuvant chemotherapy was not performed due to the early pathological stage. The patient died from carcinomatosis and pneumonia. Even if the tumor was on a relatively early stage, an adjuvant treatment should be considered ACC.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Alpha-fetoprotein</kwd><kwd>Acinar cell carcinoma</kwd><kwd>Pancreatectomy</kwd><kwd>Gastric cancer</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>The acinar cell carcinoma (ACC) is compared with the ductal cell carcinoma a rare pancreas tumor.<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> ACCs account for less than 1% of primary pancreatic neoplasms.<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> In particular ,the pancreatic ACC associated with an elevated serum alpha-fetoprotein (AFP) is extremely rare.<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> AFP is a glycoprotein with a frequently increase in patients with hepatocellular carcinoma and yolk-sac tumors.<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> It is not widely known that AFP production can accompany pancreatic ACC.<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> A standard chemotherapy regimen for AFP-producing ACC has not been established yet.<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> In this report, a case of resected AFP-producing ACC of the pancreas is presented in a patient who underwent a radical subtotal gastrectomy due to an early gastric cancer. Also it is presented a potential chemotherapeutic regimen based on an in vitro adenosine triphosphate-based chemotherapy response assay (ATP-CRA).</p></sec><sec><title>CASE</title><p>A 72-year-old female patient was admitted to our hospital for the evaluation and proper management of a pancreatic mass. Six months ago, she underwent a radical subtotal gastrectomy with gastroduodenostomy (Billroth I) due to early gastric cancer. This pancreatic mass was incidentally identified on a postoperative follow-up abdominal-pelvic computed tomography (CT) scan. Her body weight was 39 kg and the height was 144 cm (body mass index, 18.8). A physical examination finding was an upper midline abdominal skin incision in the abdomen, which was soft and flat without palpable mass. All routine blood laboratory tests including amylase and lipase were within normal ranges. Also tumor markers, carcinoembryonic antigen (CEA), carbohydrate antigen 19-9 (CA 19-9) and carbohydrate antigen 125 (CA 125) were within normal limits. In the CT scan, an approximately 2.5 cm-sized mass near the neck of the pancreas with distal duct dilatation and a parenchyma atrophic change abutting to the portal vein was identified. No lymph node enlargement or distant metastasis was detected (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>).The 2-deoxy-2-[18F]-fluoro-D-glucose (FDG) positron emission tomography (PET) showed approximately 2.6 cm-sized low-attenuating pancreatic mass in the body portion without significantly increased FDG uptake in any other organs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B</xref>). Pancreaticobiliary magnetic resonance imaging with cholangiography showed about 2.5 cm-sized hypervascular, T2 low signal, fat-containing, well-defined mass in the neck area with distal parenchymal atrophy and duct dilatation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1C</xref>). The characteristics of the tumor seemed to be somewhat different from usual ductal adenocarcinoma of the pancreas, and serum AFP was checked. It was elevated to 2,254.1 IU/ml (reference range: 0-7.0 IU/ml).</p><p>The patient underwent a pancreaticoduodenectomy (PD). During the laparotomy, malignant ascites, peritoneal seeding or distant metastasis were not found, but severe peritoneal adhesions due to the previous radical subtotal gastrectomy were noted. The anatomic plane was obscured during the PD due to the previous lymph node dissection around the celiac axis, common hepatic artery and the proper hepatic artery. Therefore, a dissection between the neck of the pancreas and superior mesenteric vein-splenic vein-portal vein confluence was needed to identify the anatomic landmark (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref>). As previous lymph node dissection around major vessels was conducted already, a standard lymph node dissection was performed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B</xref>). Due to the previous gastroduodenostomy the reconstruction of gastrointestinal continuity was easy following the PD. All procedures, pancreaiticojejunostomy, hepaticojejunostomy and gastrojejunostomy were completed in a usual manner.</p><p>An 1.9&#x000d7;1.7 cm-sized ill-defined lobulating tumor confined to the pancreas was revealed in the macroscopic specimen examination (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A</xref>). An AFP-producing ACC of the pancreas (T1 stage) was classified based on the routine hematoxylin and eosin (H&#x00026;E) staining and immunohistochemical staining (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3B and 3C</xref>).</p><p>The postoperative recovery course was uneventful. The patient discharged 12 days postoperatively. For the potential possibility of application of chemotherapeutic agents in this rare case of pancreatic cancer, an ATP-CRA chemosensitivity test to anticancer drugs was performed (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). The result showed cisplatin would potentially be more applicable than gemcitabine which is usually used in pancreatic cancer. Although the serum level of AFP had been dropped into normal range immediately after PD, it was rebounded exponentially 17 month postoperative (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3D</xref>). The patient died due to carcinomatosis and pneumonia at 30 months after the surgery.</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>Benassai et al.<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> reported that AFP was elevated in only 6% of ACC patients. Lee et al.<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> reported that AFP was elevated in only 1 out of 29 Korean ACC patients. Kawamoto et al.<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> reported that liver metastases were identified in 21 of the 28 patients with AFP-producing pancreatic cancer (76% overall). In the most of the reported cases, the AFP-producing ACCs were found to be very aggressive and required systemic chemotherapy. In the reported case, the AFP-producing ACC presented this aggressive nature of malignant characteristics. During the radical subtotal gastrectomy, no pancreatic lesion was found: the tumor needed only 6 month to become a 2.5 cm-sized mass. In this case, resection could be conducted and T1 stage was reported due to the early tumor detection during regular CT scans as follow up after the previous surgery. Therefore an early detection of pancreatic cancers could be suggested due to certain regular screening strategies.</p><p>Due to the previous radical subtotal gastrectomy, several issues had to be considered before PD performance in the reported case. First, severe peritoneal adhesions were present, where dexterous skills are needed to expose the retroperitoneal organs adequately. In particular, the previous lymph nodes dissection around the celiac axis, the common hepatic artery and the proper hepatic artery resulted in a dense fibrous adhesion between the pancreas and the subhepatic area. The extensive dissection around these vessels lead to a potential vascular damage related to severe postoperative morbidity because the soft tissues around the major vessels had been removed in previous radical gastrectomy already. Therefore, a standard PD would be an appropriate surgical extent in patients who previously had radical gastrectomy. Last, the gastrointestinal anastomosis after PD is affected by the previous gastrointestinal anastomosis. In the present case, the previous gastroduodenostomy made this reconstruction easy. But in the case of a previous gastrojejunostomy, a different reconstruction strategy needs to be considered.</p><p>Gemcitabine is a first-line cancer drug widely used for the chemotherapy in the ductal adenocarcinoma.<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> However, a chemotherapy regimen for AFP-producing ACC has not been established yet because the number of affected patients is too small.<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> An in-vitro ATP-CRA (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>) was performed by us to evaluate the chemosensitivity of anticancer drugs for the potential application of chemotherapeutic agents in this rare pancreatic cancer case. In recent studies it was found that ATP-CRA results can predict the chemosensitivity in patients with ovarian cancer, gastrointestinal cancer or breast cancer.<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> Our result showed cyclophosphamide is the most desirable drug which was tested for AFP-producing ACC of the pancreas followed by cisplation and gemcitabine is less effective than cyclophosphamide or cisplatin for the AFP-producing ACCs. According to our institutional experience,<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> ACCs are very rare and show aggressive biologic behaviors such as regional or distant metastasis at the initial time of diagnosis. Currently the best treatment approach is the curative resection according to our institutional experience.<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> The reported patient received no postoperative adjuvant chemotherapy after the curative pancreatectomy because the tumor was reported as an early pancreatic cancer (T1N0M0, Stage I). However, the patient experienced aggressive carcinomatosis recurrence, cachexia and pulmonary complications, and deteriorated rapidly without application time for adjuvant or palliative chemotherapy. Based on the ATP-CRA, it might have been beneficial to apply adjuvant chemotherapy even if the tumor was on a relative early stage. To determine an effective chemotherapy regimen for AFP-producing ACCs, further experience and studies are necessary.</p><p>In summary, the AFP-producing ACC is a very rare malignant pathology in pancreas which requires curative pancreatectomy. Complex difficulties in the PD occurred due to the previous radical subtotal gastrectomy and the surgeon in particular needed to consider the anatomic relationships. Adjuvant postoperative chemotherapy based on the results of ATP-CRA test should be considered in this rare and unusual malignancy as well.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wisnoski</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Townsend</surname><given-names>CM</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Nealon</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>672 patients with acinar cell carcinoma of the pancreas: a population-based comparison to pancreatic adenocarcinoma</article-title><source>Surgery</source><year>2008</year><volume>144</volume><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>148</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18656619</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Baithun</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Morphological study of 391 cases of exocrine pancreatic tumours with special reference to the classification of exocrine pancreatic carcinoma</article-title><source>J Pathol</source><year>1985</year><volume>146</volume><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2989468</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ishizaki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Koito</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Namieno</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Acinar cell carcinoma of the pancreas: a rare case of an alpha-fetoprotein-producing cystic tumor</article-title><source>Eur J Radiol</source><year>1995</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>58</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8654461</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seregni</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Botti</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bombardieri</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biochemical characteristics and clinical applications of alpha-fetoprotein isoforms</article-title><source>Anticancer Res</source><year>1995</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>1491</fpage><lpage>1499</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7544570</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cingolani</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaco-Levy</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Farruggio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Alpha-fetoprotein production by pancreatic tumors exhibiting acinar cell differentiation: study of five cases, one arising in a mediastinal teratoma</article-title><source>Hum Pathol</source><year>2000</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>938</fpage><lpage>944</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10987254</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kolb-van Harten</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosien</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Kl&#x000f6;ppel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pancreatic acinar cell carcinoma with excessive alpha-fetoprotein expression</article-title><source>Pancreatology</source><year>2007</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>370</fpage><lpage>372</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17703084</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benassai</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Mastrorilli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Quarto</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Survival after pancreaticoduodenectomy for ductal adenocarcinoma of the head of the pancreas</article-title><source>Chir Ital</source><year>2000</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>263</fpage><lpage>270</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10932371</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Acinar cell carcinoma of the pancreas in Korea--clinicopathologic analysis of 27 patients from korean literature and 2 cases from our hospital--</article-title><source>Korean J Gastroenterol</source><year>2010</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>245</fpage><lpage>251</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20389178</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kawamoto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiraoka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanemitsu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Alpha-fetoprotein-producing pancreatic cancer--a case report and review of 28 cases</article-title><source>Hepatogastroenterology</source><year>1992</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>282</fpage><lpage>286</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1380476</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burris</surname><given-names>HA</given-names><suffix>3rd</suffix></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Improvements in survival and clinical benefit with gemcitabine as first-line therapy for patients with advanced pancreas cancer: a randomized trial</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>1997</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>2403</fpage><lpage>2413</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9196156</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kawamura</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikeda</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Takiyama</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The usefulness of the ATP assay with serum-free culture for chemosensitivity testing of gastrointestinal cancer</article-title><source>Eur J Cancer</source><year>1997</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>960</fpage><lpage>966</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9291821</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Yom</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>BI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The use of an in vitro adenosine triphosphate-based chemotherapy response assay to predict chemotherapeutic response in breast cancer</article-title><source>Breast</source><year>2008</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17659874</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name><name><surname>Ngan</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clinical applicability of the ATP cell viability assay as a predictor of chemoresponse in platinum-resistant epithelial ovarian cancer using nonsurgical tumor cell samples</article-title><source>Gynecol Oncol</source><year>2000</year><volume>76</volume><fpage>405</fpage><lpage>408</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10684718</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HU</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryu</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The clinical characteristics of acinar cell carcinoma in the Pancreas</article-title><source>Korean J Hepatobiliary Pancreat Surg</source><year>2009</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>54</fpage><lpage>59</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Preoperative image study findings. CT scan showed about a 2.5 cm-sized mass near the pancreatic neck portion without evidences of distant metastasis (A). No definitive hypermetabolic signal intensity was shown in FDG-PET scan (B). Filling defect and dilatation of the distal pancreatic duct was shown on magnetic resonance cholangiopancreatography (C).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="kjhbps-18-33-g001"/></fig><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Intraoperative findings. Severe adhesions were noted, especially around the common hepatic artery and the celiac axis. The pancreatic neck portion needed first to be dissected for the anatomic landmark identification. The round mass at the posterior aspect of the pancreatic neck portion (long, thick arrow) should be noted (A), an operative finding after pancreatoduodenectomy. The stump of the gastroduodenal artery is noted (short, thin arrow) (B). SMV, superior mesenteric vein; SV, splenic vein; PV, portal vein; S, remnant stomach; P, remnant pancreas; BD, common hepatic duct.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="kjhbps-18-33-g002"/></fig><fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Surgical pathology and postoperative course. An about 1.9 cm-sized pancreas-confining lobulated tumor was noted on the neck of the pancreas (A). The tumor cells are arranged in irregular solid sheets and acinar pattern (B, &#x000d7;100), The AFP immunohistochemical staining was diffuse positive in tumor cells (C, &#x000d7;100). The patient got no adjuvant chemotherapy in follow up. The serial follow up of serum AFP showed re-elevation after declining near the normal level following operation (D). H&#x00026;E, hematoxylin-eosin.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="kjhbps-18-33-g003"/></fig><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>APT-CRA chemosensitivity report (Tumor inhibition rates at serial concentrations of TDC)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="kjhbps-18-33-i001"/><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>TDC, test drug concentration</p><p><sup>*</sup><italic>p</italic>&#x0003c;0.05</p><p>Index=300-sum (of tumor inhibition rate 0.2x, 1x and 5x)</p><p><sup>&#x02020;</sup>Rank=more desirable in drug tested</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></floats-group></article>