<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="book-review"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Med Hist</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MEDICAL HISTORY</journal-id><journal-title>Medical History</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0025-7273</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Medical History</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">1369033</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">medhis5001-135</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Book Reviews</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Book Review</article-title><subtitle>Dangerous motherhood: insanity and childbirth in Victorian Britain</subtitle></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Marks</surname><given-names>Lara</given-names></name></contrib><aff><institution>Cambridge Group for the History of Population and Social Structure, Cambridge University</institution></aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>01</day><month>1</month><year>2006</year></pub-date><volume>50</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>135</fpage><lpage>136</lpage><product xlink:type="simple"><name><surname>Marland</surname><given-names>Hilary</given-names></name><x>. </x><break/><source>Dangerous motherhood: insanity and childbirth in Victorian Britain</source><x>. </x><break/><publisher-loc>Basingstoke and New York</publisher-loc><x>: </x><publisher-name>Palgrave Macmillan</publisher-name><x>. </x><year>2004</year><comment>, pp. xii, 303, illus., &#x000a3;50.00, US$69.95 (hardback </comment><x> </x><isbn>1-4039-2038-9</isbn><comment>).
</comment><x> </x></product><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; Lara Marks 2006</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2006</copyright-year></article-meta></front><body><p>Today psychiatrists estimate that between half and two-thirds of women experience some sort of post-natal depression shortly after childbirth. In the nineteenth century such sufferings were rarely remarked upon. Yet, severe mania or melancholia among pregnant women or those who had just given birth attracted a great deal of medical attention in the same period. Called &#x0201c;puerperal insanity&#x0201d; or &#x0201c;puerperal mania&#x0201d;, the disease was devastating to those it struck, causing once calm women to physically and verbally strike out at both themselves and those around them. At its most severe the disease could result in infanticide or suicide. Even at its less extreme a woman's behaviour could seem disturbing and bizarre, leading to the neglect of her child, home and her own body. Using a wealth of asylum records, case notes, diaries and medical texts, Hilary Marland's scholarly book, <italic>Dangerous motherhood</italic>, provides a rich window into some of the anguish puerperal insanity could inflict on women and their families, and the variety of ways medical practitioners explained its cause and sought to treat it.</p><p><italic>Dangerous motherhood</italic> begins by tracing the rising fascination of the medical profession with puerperal sepsis at the start of the nineteenth century and ends when many within the medical profession began to dispute the link between psychosis and childbearing at the end of same century. As Marland points out, puerperal insanity was a disease of its era, gripping lay people and the medical profession's attention at a time of heightened anxiety about the dangers of childbirth and social fears about the future sanctity of the bourgeois home. What stunned most contemporary observers was the intensity and violence of the condition and the degree to which it challenged the social norms and feminine behaviour expected of Victorian mothers. Moreover it could strike both rich and poor women, including Queen Victoria herself. So common was the disease believed to be that medical experts began to see it as an &#x0201c;almost anticipated accompaniment of the process of giving birth&#x0201d; (p. 5).</p><p>As Marland shows in her book, puerperal insanity became the subject of concern for a wide range of Victorian health professionals, including obstetricians, gynaecologists, asylum doctors, general practitioners and midwives. With many of these practitioners just beginning to forge their specialisms at this time, puerperal insanity provided a useful means of building reputations as well as obtaining clients. Given the disruption the disease could cause to households, health practitioners perceived themselves as healing the whole family as well as the woman herself.</p><p>Each type of practitioner attributed different causes to the disease, partly reflecting their specialism and clientele. Midwifery practitioners, who were more likely to deal with wealthier women, for example, commonly linked the condition with the risks and stresses associated with childbirth. By contrast, asylum doctors, whose clientele were poorer, frequently attributed the disorder to poverty and neglected health. Much of the debate around puerperal insanity, Marland points out, centred on the location of treatment. Many Victorian midwives and obstetricians believed the disease to be a special category of mental illness, which if caught early, lent itself, in less severe cases, to treatment at home. Asylum doctors, on the other hand, argued puerperal insanity was best treated within the confines of the asylum.</p><p><italic>Dangerous motherhood</italic> not only provides a vivid study of the specific Victorian conditions that led to the rise and fall in the fascination of puerperal insanity, but a powerful insight into the relationships between doctors, patients and their families in this period.</p></body></article>





