<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mol Ther Nucleic Acids</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Mol Ther Nucleic Acids</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Molecular Therapy. Nucleic Acids</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2162-2531</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5024509</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">mtna201643</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/mtna.2016.43</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A Glu-urea-Lys Ligand-conjugated Lipid Nanoparticle/siRNA System Inhibits
Androgen Receptor Expression <italic>In Vivo</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Justin B</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="aunote1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Kaixin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="aunote1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tam</surname><given-names>Yuen Yi C</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Quick</surname><given-names>Joslyn</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tam</surname><given-names>Ying K</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Paulo JC</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Sam</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Yan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nair</surname><given-names>Jayaprakash K</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zlatev</surname><given-names>Ivan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rajeev</surname><given-names>Kallanthottathil G</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Manoharan</surname><given-names>Muthiah</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rennie</surname><given-names>Paul S</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="aunote1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cullis</surname><given-names>Pieter R</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="caf1">*</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="aunote1">*</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Biochemistry and
Molecular Biology at the University of British Columbia, Vancouver</institution>,
British Columbia, <country>Canada</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution>Vancouver Prostate Centre,
Vancouver</institution>, British Columbia, <country>Canada</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution>Department of Drug Discovery, Alnylam
Pharmaceuticals</institution>, Cambridge, Massachusetts,
<country>USA</country>.</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="caf1"><label>*</label>Deaprtment of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, University
of British Columbia, 2350 Health Sciences Mall, Vancouver, British Columbia,
Canada V6T 1Z3. E-mail: <email>pieterc@mail.ubc.ca</email></corresp><fn fn-type="present-address" id="aunote1"><label/><p>The first two authors and the last two authors contributed equally to this
work.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>08</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>08</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>1</day><month>8</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>e348</fpage><lpage/><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>05</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>05</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2016 Official journal of the American Society of Gene &#x00026; Cell Therapy</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Official journal of the American Society of Gene &#x00026; Cell Therapy</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/"><!--author-paid--><license-p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons
Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License. The images or
other third party material in this article are included in the article's
Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in the credit line; if
the material is not included under the Creative Commons license, users will need
to obtain permission from the license holder to reproduce the material. To view
a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</ext-link></license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>The androgen receptor plays a critical role in the progression of prostate
cancer. Here, we describe targeting the prostate-specific membrane antigen using
a lipid nanoparticle formulation containing small interfering RNA designed to
silence expression of the messenger RNA encoding the androgen receptor.
Specifically, a Glu-urea-Lys PSMA-targeting ligand was incorporated into the
lipid nanoparticle system formulated with a long alkyl chain polyethylene
glycol-lipid to enhance accumulation at tumor sites and facilitate intracellular
uptake into tumor cells following systemic administration. Through these
features, and by using a structurally refined cationic lipid and an optimized
small interfering RNA payload, a lipid nanoparticle system with improved potency
and significant therapeutic potential against prostate cancer and potentially
other solid tumors was developed. Decreases in serum prostate-specific antigen,
tumor cellular proliferation, and androgen receptor levels were observed in a
mouse xenograft model following intravenous injection. These results support the
potential clinical utility of a prostate-specific membrane
antigen&#x02013;targeted lipid nanoparticle system to silence the androgen
receptor in advanced prostate cancer.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>androgen receptor</kwd><kwd>lipid nanoparticles</kwd><kwd>liposomes</kwd><kwd>prostate cancer</kwd><kwd>prostate specific membrane antigen</kwd><kwd>siRNA</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>We have previously shown that inhibition of androgen receptor (AR) expression and
reduction of prostate-specific antigen (PSA) serum levels in mouse models of
human prostate cancer (PCa) can be achieved by intravenous (i.v.) administration
of lipid nanoparticles (LNPs) containing small interfering RNA (siRNA) targeting
the gene encoding the AR (LNP-AR-siRNA).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">1</xref></sup> However, relatively high doses (six doses at 10&#x02009;mg
siRNA/kg body weight) were required to see appreciable effects. This is in
significant contrast to the potency of LNP-siRNA systems that have achieved 50%
silencing of a hepatic gene with a single dose of 0.005&#x02009;mg
siRNA/kg.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">4</xref></sup> This large-dose
disparity is attributed to the liver's favorable physiology and to
endogenous processes that result in targeting of LNPs to
hepatocytes.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">5</xref></sup> In particular, LNPs associate with apolipoprotein E
(ApoE)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">6</xref></sup> following i.v. administration and are taken into
hepatocytes through the LDL receptor, the scavenger receptor, and the
&#x0201c;LDL-like&#x0201d; receptor.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">7</xref></sup> Although it is unlikely that potencies
equivalent to those seen for gene silencing in hepatocytes can be achieved in
localized and disseminated PCa, reductions in current dose levels must be
achieved for this approach to become a viable clinical strategy.</p><p>The objective of this study was to improve the potency of the LNP-siRNA system
developed previously.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">1</xref></sup> The primary
techniques that we explored concerned using a different polyethylene glycol
(PEG)-lipid to achieve longer circulation lifetimes and facilitate higher levels
of LNP accumulation at tumor sites, as well as the use of targeting ligands
attached to the LNP-siRNA system to specifically enhance uptake into PCa cells
following arrival at the tumor site. However, in order to build the most potent
LNP system possible, two other LNP variables were investigated: first, the use
of a more potent cationic lipid and second, a more potent AR-siRNA than used
previously.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">1</xref></sup></p><p>The cationic lipid, DLin-KC2-DMA, used in our previous study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">1</xref></sup> was identified by screening a variety of
cationic lipids in LNP-siRNA systems.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">2</xref></sup>
Recent advances in cationic lipid design have resulted in a number of more
potent cationic lipids, including DMAP-BLP,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">8</xref></sup> which results in improved gene-silencing potency when
used in LNP-siRNA formulations compared to DLin-KC2-DMA.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">4</xref></sup> Furthermore, the AR-siRNA used
previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">1</xref></sup> was a 25-mer siRNA
complementary to nucleotides 3542-3563 in the AR mRNA region that encodes the
ligand-binding domain. Improvement in gene silencing can be expected with the
use of other sequence-optimized siRNAs as it has been shown that siRNAs against
different regions of an mRNA have drastically different silencing
activities.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">10</xref></sup></p><p>Additional factors that intrinsically influence the silencing activity of
LNP-siRNAs are their ability to accumulate at the target site and to be taken up
into the target cells. LNPs with long half-lives in circulation are likely to
accumulate at tumors due to the impaired lymphatic drainage and leaky
vasculature at these sites.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">12</xref></sup> The PEG-lipid used in the previous
studies was anchored into the LNP formulation by two C<sub>14</sub> alkyl
chains; these lipids rapidly exchange out of the LNP with half-times on the
order of minutes following i.v. injection.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">14</xref></sup> This loss of the
PEG-lipid results in short (&#x0003c; 1 hour) LNP circulation half-times with
substantial liver accumulation. In order to achieve longer circulation
lifetimes, we examined here the properties of LNP systems containing PEG-lipid
with long alkyl chains, which can reside in the LNP formulation for 24 hours or
longer.</p><p>The type of targeting ligand to actively target LNP-siRNA systems to PCa cells is
of interest. A small molecule-targeting approach has been previously
demonstrated for anisamide,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">17</xref></sup> as well
as the cardiac glycoside strophanthidin (STR).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">18</xref></sup> The prostate-specific membrane antigen (PSMA), a
plasma membrane glycoprotein that is overexpressed in PCa cells as well as the
neovasculature of many solid tumors (but not in healthy tissues),<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">19</xref></sup> represents an attractive target for LNP
systems. Binding to PSMA results in internalization through clathrin-mediated
endocytosis and thus can potentially carry LNP into the cell.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">20</xref></sup>
<italic>In silico</italic> screening studies have identified the small molecule
2-(3-(1,3-dicarboxypropyl)-ureido)pentanedioic acid (DUPA),<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">21</xref></sup> which binds specifically to PSMA with
high affinity.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">23</xref></sup> Urea-based analogs
of DUPA have served as the template for further development of various potent
PSMA-targeting ligands and have been studied by the Kozikowski,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">25</xref></sup>
Spiegel,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">28</xref></sup> and low
groups,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">23</xref></sup> resulting in
diagnostics and therapeutics that have considerable clinical
potential.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">29</xref></sup> In this
manuscript, we achieved improved potency in AR silencing by incorporating a DUPA
analog for PSMA-targeting in long-circulating LNP systems that contain optimized
cationic lipid and siRNA against AR.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>Optimized LNP-AR21-siRNA silences AR expression <italic>in
vitro</italic></title><p>Our first optimization of the LNP-AR-siRNA employed the ionizable cationic
lipid, DMAP-BLP,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">8</xref></sup> which is three
times more potent in hepatic gene silencing than the
DLin-KC2-DMA,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">4</xref></sup> the lipid
used in earlier LNP-AR-siRNA studies.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">1</xref></sup> Furthermore, the previously used AR siRNA
(AR25-siRNA) was a 25-mer derived from an shRNA sequence that was shown to
mediate silencing of AR and tumor growth delay <italic>in
vivo</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">30</xref></sup> In order to
improve gene-silencing activity, a 21-mer siRNA (AR21-siRNA) was identified
in a screen of siRNAs targeting the AR gene (data not shown). We
incorporated two phosphorothioate linkages in order to reduce degradation by
serum nucleases such as ribonuclease A (RNase A) and RNase A-like
enzymes,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">31</xref></sup> as well as
multiple 2&#x02032;-OMe modifications to enhance stability in the presence of
nucleases and to prevent undesired immune responses.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">32</xref></sup> To compare relative potencies of the
25-mer and 21-mer siRNAs, LNPs containing either AR21-siRNA or AR25-siRNA
were incubated with LNCaP cells <italic>in vitro</italic> at siRNA concentrations of
0.5, 1.0, or 5.0 &#x003bc;g/ml for 48 hours and AR protein levels were analyzed
by immunoblotting (<bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref></bold>).
Essentially, complete AR silencing was observed in cells treated with LNP
containing AR21-siRNA at all dose levels tested, whereas AR protein
knockdown was incomplete in cells treated with all doses of AR25-siRNA.
Untreated cells or cells treated with control siRNA (a scramble sequence or
siRNA against glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate dehydrogenase (GAPDH) showed no
reduction of AR levels (<bold>Supplementary Figures S3</bold> and <bold>S4</bold>).
Alternatively, another siRNA sequence against the AR also showed appreciable
AR knockdown (<bold>Supplementary Figure S4</bold>). These results indicate that
the AR21-siRNA is a more potent sequence than AR25-siRNA for silencing the
AR gene in LNCaP cells <italic>in vitro</italic>. In addition, an alternate siRNA
against The AR21-siRNA was used in all subsequent experiments.</p></sec><sec><title>LNPs containing PEG-DSG accumulate in distal tumors</title><p>Previously reported studies of AR siRNA utilized LNPs containing PEG-DMG, a
PEG-lipid with two C<sub>14</sub> alkyl chains.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">1</xref></sup> PEG-lipids are required to produce LNP systems
with defined sizes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">33</xref></sup> and to
prevent aggregation of the LNP after formation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">34</xref></sup> As noted elsewhere,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">14</xref></sup> PEG-lipids
with C<sub>14</sub> chains rapidly dissociate from the LNP (dissociation
halftimes of minutes or less) following <italic>in vivo</italic> administration and
result in short circulation lifetimes, enhancing liver accumulation but
reducing LNP accumulation at tumor sites. In order to improve tumor
accumulation, LNP systems used in this work incorporated PEG-DSG, a lipid
with C<sub>18</sub> alkyl chains. Previous work has shown that PEG-lipids
with C<sub>18</sub> alkyl chains remain associated with LNP for days or
longer,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">14</xref></sup> leading to
extended circulation lifetimes following i.v. administration relative to
those with shorter PEG chains.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">35</xref></sup> Consistent with these reports,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">35</xref></sup> we found that LNP-siRNA, produced by
microfluidic mixing incorporating 1.5% PEG-DSG, exhibited extended
circulation properties compared to LNP with equivalent amounts of
PEG-DMG.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">14</xref></sup> Increasing the
total PEG-DSG lipid in the LNP from 2.5 to 5% resulted in a marked increase
in circulation halftime from approximately 30 minutes to greater than 8
hours (<bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref></bold>). To show that increased
circulation lifetime translates to enhanced LNP accumulation in tumors,
fluorescently labeled LNP-AR21-siRNA containing either 2.5 or 5 mol% PEG-DSG
were prepared and administered intravenously once every day for 3 days at a
dose of 10&#x02009;mg siRNA/kg body weight in athymic nude mice bearing LNCaP
tumors. Tumors were harvested at 4 and 24 hours following the final
injection of LNP formulations, fixed in 10% formalin, cryo-sectioned, and
analyzed for LNP accumulation by confocal microscopy. Consistent with the
enhanced circulation lifetime, tumor tissues from mice treated with LNP
containing 5 mol% PEG-DSG showed significantly higher accumulation of
fluorescence than those from mice injected with LNP containing 2.5 mol%
PEG-DSG (<bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2b</xref></bold>). Fluorescent
micrographs showed that LNPs accumulated in tumor tissues over time, with
higher levels observed in tumors collected 24 hours postadministration than
at 4 hours. Approximately fourfold more LNP containing 5 mol% PEG-DSG was
observed in tumor tissues than LNP containing 2.5 mol% PEG-DSG (<bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2b</xref></bold>).</p></sec><sec><title>Incorporation of (Glu-urea-Lys)-PEG-DSG into LNP systems results in
increased cellular uptake and AR gene silencing in LNCaP cells and is
enhanced via a PSMA-dependent endocytic mechanism</title><p>A durable PEG coating enhances LNP accumulation at sites of tumors, but also
hinders uptake into cells and subsequent delivery of the siRNA payload to
the cytoplasm. A strategy to overcome this problem is to incorporate into
the LNP a small-molecule homing ligand that targets a cell surface
receptor.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">18</xref></sup> As indicated under Methods, we synthesized a
small-molecule PSMA-targeting ligand and chemically conjugated it to
PEG-DSG, as shown in <bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref></bold>.</p><p>Our PSMA-targeting analog is based on a Glu-urea-Lys scaffold and was
designed according to previously published data.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">23</xref></sup> The PSMA-targeting lipid (<bold>13</bold>, <bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref></bold>) is composed of a Glu-urea-Lys
moiety tethered to the PEG lipid through a phenyl ring. We first synthesized
the appropriately protected Glu-urea-Lys carboxylic acid <bold>5</bold>
(<bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref></bold>) from
2-[3-(5-amino-1-<italic>tert</italic>-butoxycarbonylpentyl)-ureido]pentanedioic
acid di-<italic>tert</italic>-butyl ester (<bold>4</bold>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">25</xref></sup> and from the carboxylic acid <bold>3</bold> under
peptide coupling conditions, followed by selective deprotection of the
benzyl ester as shown in Scheme 1. The carboxylic acid <bold>3</bold> was
synthesized from benzyl 5-hexynoate (<bold>1</bold>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">36</xref></sup> and (<italic>p</italic>-iodophenyl)acetic acid
(<bold>2</bold>) by standard Sonogashira coupling.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">37</xref></sup> Covalent attachment of the protected carboxylic
acid (<bold>5</bold>) under peptide coupling conditions with the amino-PEG-lipid
(<bold>11</bold>) followed by deprotection of functional groups afforded the
desired (Glu-urea-Lys)-PEG-DSG lipid (<bold>13</bold>), used for PSMA-targeting
LNP formulation of the siRNA. The experimental details and compound
characterization are included in the <bold>Supplementary Materials and
Methods</bold>.</p><p>To evaluate the effects of incorporating (Glu-urea-Lys)-PEG-DSG on cell
uptake, fluorescently-labeled LNP systems were utilized. A PSMA-targeted
LNP-AR-siRNA system containing 1&#x02009;mol % (Glu-urea-Lys)-PEG-DSG and
1.5% PEG-DSG was compared to an untargeted LNP system containing a total of
2.5% PEG-DSG lipid. Uptake into LNCaP cells was analyzed by fluorescence
microscopy. At 24 hours, fluorescence was approximately fourfold higher in
cells treated with the PSMA-targeted LNP-AR-siRNA compared to those treated
with the nontargeted LNP (<bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4a</xref></bold>).</p><p>To verify that uptake was via a PSMA-dependent mechanism, LNCaP cells were
treated with (Glu-urea-Lys)-LNP in the presence or absence of the
competitive reagent, 2-PMPA, at 100-fold molar excess to
(Glu-urea-Lys)-PEG-DSG. The addition of 2-PMPA caused a substantial
inhibition of (Glu-urea-Lys)-LNP uptake in LNCaP cells and little or no
effect on the uptake of nontargeted LNP (<bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure
4a</xref></bold>). Uptake of PSMA-targeted and untargeted LNPs was
also measured in the PSMA-negative PCa cell line PC-3 (ref. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">38</xref>); no enhancement in LNP uptake due to the
presence of the (Glu-urea-Lys) ligand in the LNP would be expected. In these
cells, significantly greater LNP uptake was observed for nontargeted LNP
compared to PSMA-targeted LNP (<bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure
4b</xref></bold>), possibly due to charge repulsion between the plasma
membrane and the negatively charged (Glu-urea-Lys) targeting ligand.</p><p>We next evaluated whether the presence of the (Glu-urea-Lys)-PEG-DSG would
lead to enhanced target gene silencing in LNCaP cells. In LNCaP cells
treated with PSMA-targeted LNP containing 0.5 or 1 mol%
(Glu-urea-Lys)-PEG-DSG, AR protein levels were significantly lower than in
cells incubated with nontargeted LNP (<bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure
4c</xref></bold>). In addition, a greater inhibition of AR expression
was observed with the formulation containing 1 mol% (Glu-urea-Lys)-PEG-DSG
than 0.5 mol% (Glu-urea-Lys)-PEG-DSG.</p></sec><sec><title>LNP-AR-siRNA systems containing the PSMA-targeting Glu-urea-Lys ligand
exhibit long circulation lifetimes</title><p>As described previously, LNP systems exhibiting long circulation
characteristics are essential to achieving enhanced accumulation at tumor
sites. In this context, it was important to establish that the presence of
the (Glu-urea-Lys)-PEG-DSG did not negatively impact the circulation
lifetime of the PEG-DSG LNP systems employed here. This is of potential
concern since (Glu-urea-Lys)-PEG-DSG contains three carboxylic acid chemical
groups at its hydrophilic terminal end (<bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure
3</xref></bold>). The p<italic>K</italic>a values of these carboxylic acid
groups are predicted to be 3.11, 3.69, and 3.99 (Marvin, ChemAxon, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.chemaxon.com/products/marvin/">http://www.chemaxon.com/products/marvin/</ext-link>), indicating that
this PSMA-targeting ligand will possess a strong negative charge at
physiological pH. Consistent with these estimates, the zeta-potential of LNP
containing 1 mol% of (Glu-urea-Lys)-PEG-DSG was determined to be
&#x02212;14.97&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;9.34 mV, whereas nontargeted LNP
exhibited a zeta-potential of &#x02212;4.91&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;11 mV. LNPs
exhibiting negative charges can be rapidly cleared from the bloodstream via
opsonization by serum proteins and subsequent accumulation in the
reticuloendothelial cells of the liver and spleen.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">40</xref></sup></p><p>The circulation lifetime of the PSMA-targeting LNP was determined following
i.v. administration of tritiated (<sup>3</sup>H) PSMA-targeted or
nontargeted LNP to mice at 1&#x02009;mg siRNA/kg body weight (see Materials
and Methods). Blood was collected via intracardiac sampling at 0.5, 2, 8, 24
hours postinjection and the percentage of the injected LNP remaining in the
circulation was determined (<bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref></bold>).
Importantly, the PSMA-targeted and nontargeted LNPs exhibited very similar
circulation properties; both formulations had <italic>t</italic><sub>1/2</sub>
values of approximately 10&#x02013;12 hours. Since it was previously shown
that LNP-siRNA systems incorporating PEG-DSG accumulate in tumors
(<bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref></bold>),<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">11</xref></sup> these data support the probability
that (Glu-urea-Lys)-LNP-siRNA will exhibit similar accumulation at distal
tumor sites.</p></sec><sec><title>PSMA-targeted (Glu-urea-Lys)-LNPs enhance AR knockdown in mice bearing
LNCaP tumors</title><p>The potency of long-circulating, PSMA-targeted (Glu-urea-Lys)-LNP systems was
evaluated in athymic nude mice bearing LNCaP tumors. When serum PSA levels
reached 50&#x02013;75&#x02009;ng/ml, mice were randomly assigned to three
experimental groups and treated i.v. with phosphate buffered saline (PBS) or
PSMA-targeted or nontargeted LNP at a dose of 5&#x02009;mg siRNA/kg body
weight. While serum PSA levels rose to 40% above the pretreatment levels by
Day 14 in the control group, PSA levels remained relatively unchanged
compared to baseline in mice treated with nontargeted LNP (<bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6a</xref></bold>). This represents a significant
improvement over previous studies, since similar effects on PSA levels were
observed at half the dose used for the first generation
LNP-AR-siRNA.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">1</xref></sup> The enhanced
potency can be attributed to the combined effects of a more potent cationic
lipid and a more active siRNA payload, as well as greater LNP accumulation
at the distal tumor site due to enhanced circulation characteristics. Even
more promising were the results from the PSMA-targeted (Glu-urea-Lys)-LNP
group; in these mice, a 45% reduction in the serum PSA levels was
observed at day 14 compared to the control group (<bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6a</xref></bold>). In mice treated with siRNA formulated in
the PSMA-targeted (Glu-urea-Lys)-LNP, a decrease in serum PSA levels
relative to pretreatment levels was observed. To directly verify AR gene
silencing, levels of AR and PSA mRNAs were assessed in samples from LNCaP
tumors at day 14 via quantitative real-time reverse-transcription polymerase
chain reaction (qRT-PCR). In the PSMA-targeting (Glu-urea-Lys)-LNP group,
there was a significant reduction in AR mRNA transcript levels compared to
mice treated with the nontargeted LNP or PBS (<bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure
6b</xref></bold>). The siRNA formulated in the nontargeted LNP did
not cause a significant reduction in mRNA transcript levels compared to the
PBS control (<bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6b</xref></bold>). These results
are consistent with AR protein levels (<bold>Supplementary Figure S1</bold>).
Similar results were obtained when levels of PSA mRNA transcript were
evaluated. There was a significant decrease in levels of PSA mRNA in the
PSMA-targeted LNP treatment group compared to mice treated with nontargeted
LNP-AR-siRNA (<bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6c</xref></bold>).</p></sec><sec><title>Intravenous administration of PSMA-targeted (Glu-urea-Lys)-LNP reduces
cellular proliferation, but does not enhance apoptosis</title><p>The ultimate goal in cancer treatment is to induce tumor regression; this
has never been observed in the LNCaP xenograft model using gene-silencing
strategies, even in conjunction with complete androgen ablation via
castration.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">30</xref></sup> LNCaP tumors were isolated from mice treated
with PBS as a control or AR21-siRNA formulated in PSMA-targeted or
nontargeted LNPs on day 14. Tumors were sectioned and analyzed by
immunohistochemistry for cellular proliferation as indicated by staining for
Ki67. Ki67 is a marker that is detected during all phases of the cell cycle,
but is absent in quiescent cells.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">41</xref></sup> Data indicated that treatment with AR21-siRNA
formulated in the PSMA-targeted (Glu-urea-Lys)-LNP caused an approximate 50%
decrease in Ki67-positive cells relative to levels in tumors from
PBS-treated mice (<bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7a</xref></bold>,<bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">b</xref></bold>). No effect on apoptosis was observed
based on TUNEL staining of LNCaP tumors from treated and untreated animals
(<bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7c</xref></bold>,<bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">d</xref></bold>). The lack of apoptotic cells may be due to the
short duration of this study (14 days).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>In previous work, we showed that AR25-siRNA formulated in LNP containing
DLin-KC2-DMA and PEG-DMG (a PEG-lipid that rapidly dissociates from the LNP
following i.v. injection) inhibited expression of the AR gene in an animal model
of PCa. The potential for translating this work into the clinic is limited by
the high doses necessary to achieve an appreciable pharmacological effect. Here,
we describe the optimization of properties of the LNP-AR-siRNA systems to
achieve improvements in the <italic>in vivo</italic> gene-silencing potency. An improved
cationic lipid, DMAP-BLP, was used and the siRNA sequence and chemistry were
optimized. In addition, a PEG-lipid (PEG-DSG) that does not readily dissociate
from LNP systems and a PSMA-targeting lipid were incorporated, resulting in a
longer lifetime in circulation, improved accumulation at distal tumor sites, and
PSMA-mediated uptake into prostate tumor cells.</p><p>Inclusion of 5 mol% PEG-DSG clearly resulted in improved LNP accumulation at the
tumor site compared to LNP with lower amounts of the PEG-lipid (<bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref></bold>). This had a minimal impact on
LNP-siRNA potency, as judged by PSA levels, compared to the previously reported
work.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">1</xref></sup> However, although the
more stable PEG coatings lead to improved tumor accumulation, the PEG coat can
impede cellular uptake, reducing the activity of the LNP payload. Ideally, the
PEG-lipid would remain associated with the LNP until arrival at the tumor site,
after which it would dissociate. For actively targeted systems such as those
containing the PSMA-targeted (Glu-urea-Lys)-PEG-lipid, it is possible that the
presence of the PEG-lipid may reduce the endosomolytic properties of the LNP
following ligand-dependent uptake.</p><p>The results presented demonstrate significantly greater reductions in AR (~40%)
and PSA (~50%) mRNA when the AR21-siRNA was formulated in the PSMA-targeted
(Glu-urea-Lys)-LNP system compared to the nontargeted LNP system (<bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6</xref></bold>). The use of the small molecule
targeting ligand has a number of advantages compared with use of larger entities
such as antibodies; most notably, the small molecule targeting ligands can
be incorporated at the time of LNP manufacture rather than after the LNP is
formed and well-defined, scalable systems are more readily achieved. It is
perhaps surprising that the highly negatively charged PSMA-targeting
Glu-urea-Lys ligand adopted a configuration when incorporated into the LNP in
which it is available on the external surface for ligand binding. A concern was
that the targeting ligand could become associated with the cationic lipid during
formulation and is buried in the interior of the LNP as a result. It is possible
that the PEG tether limits internal localization of the (Glu-urea-Lys)-PEG-DSG
due to polarity and/or steric effects.</p><p>The data presented here demonstrate that the potency of LNP siRNA systems to
silence the AR following i.v. administration can be improved from dose levels of
10&#x02009;mg/kg siRNA to 5&#x02009;mg/kg when more potent cationic lipids, higher
levels of tumor accumulation and the PSMA targeting ligand is employed. However,
the dose levels of 5&#x02009;mg siRNA/kg body weight required for AR silencing
are still approximately an order of magnitude too high for clinical applications
to be envisaged, and further work is required to improve potency. This is
especially important for achieving tumor growth regression, as we observed no
statistically significant difference in the tumor sizes between PSMA-targeted
LNP treatment mice and control groups, despite appreciable knockdown of the AR
and PSA in the treatment group (<bold>Supplementary Figure S2</bold>). Ways forward
include higher levels of external PSMA-targeting lipid or extending the
PSMA-targeting moieties beyond the PEG coat to improve targeting could be
envisioned. It has been noted that use of a PEG5000 tether to extend the
targeting ligand further from the LNP surface resulted in a 160-fold improvement
in targeting capability <italic>in vitro</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">42</xref></sup> Incorporation of an additional ligand that targets
another cell surface factor, such as the prostate stem cell
antigen,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">43</xref></sup> may synergistically
enhance the LNP uptake. Finally, nanoparticle systems smaller than 50&#x02009;nm
exhibit significantly improved delivery to tumor cells by virtue of their
ability to achieve improved tumor penetration.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">44</xref></sup> Of relevance to this approach, the microfluidic
mixing technique does offer the possibility of manufacturing LNP with sizes as
small as 20&#x02009;nm in diameter,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">33</xref></sup>
and efforts will be directed toward reductions in the size of the LNP-siRNA
system.</p><p>The potential of targeting ligands is demonstrated by recent highly encouraging
clinical data utilizing siRNAs directly conjugated to a
<italic>N</italic>-acetylgalactosamine (GalNAc) targeting ligand which have demonstrated
efficient systemic delivery allowing robust and durable mRNA knockdown of
various targets in hepatocytes.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">45</xref></sup> The
GalNAc ligand targets the highly expressed ASGPR receptor in
hepatocytes&#x02014;which presents the important advantages of exhibiting high
copy number and a quick turnover. In this aspect, the selection of efficient
receptors for targeting is a key parameter for the success of targeted siRNA
systems. In addition, recently developed biodegradable lipids enabling rapidly
eliminated LNPs that display improved tolerability and safety profiles can be
incorporated into potent and safe LNP-siRNA systems.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">46</xref></sup> It is therefore expected that this continuous
progress in the field of siRNA medicines will lead to LNP-AR-siRNAs targeting
PCas that have direct clinical utility.</p></sec><sec><title>Materials and Methods</title><p><italic>Materials.</italic> 1,2-Distearoyl-sn-glycero-3-phosphocholine (DSPC) was
purchased from Avanti Lipids (Alabaster, AL), cholesterol (Chol) was purchased
from Sigma (St. Louis, MO).
1,1&#x02032;-Dilinoleyl-3,3,3&#x02032;,3&#x02032;-tetramethylindocarbocyanine
perchlorate (DiI) was bought from Invitrogen (Burlington, ON, Canada). The
ionizable cationic lipid DMAP-BLP and PEG-lipids
(R)-2,3-bis(octadecyloxy)propyl-1-(methoxy poly(ethylene glycol)2000) carbamate
(PEG-DMG) and (R)-2,3-bis(stearyloxy)propyl-1-(methoxy poly(ethylene glycol)2000
carbamate (PEG-DSG) were synthesized at Alnylam Pharmaceuticals (Cambridge, MA).
The PSMA inhibitor 2-(phosphonomethyl)-pentanedioic acid (2-PMPA) was purchased
from Cedarlane (Burlington, ON, Canada).</p><p><italic>Cell culture, cell lines, and reagents.</italic> LNCaP and PC-3 human PCa cell
lines were used in all <italic>in vitro</italic> experiments.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">47</xref></sup> LNCaP and PC-3
cells were obtained from ATCC and were not passaged beyond 6 months after
receipt or resuscitation. LNCaP cells were maintained in RPMI 1640 (Life
Technologies, Burlington, ON, Canada), supplemented with 10% heat-inactivated
fetal bovine serum. PC-3 cells were maintained in DMEM (Life Technologies,
Burlington, ON, Canada) supplemented with 5% heat-inactivated fetal bovine
serum. Both cell lines were incubated at 37 &#x000b0;C with 5% CO<sub>2</sub>.</p><p><italic>siRNA sequences.</italic> The sequence of the human AR gene (GenBank accession
no. NM_000044) was extracted from the NCBI Entrez nucleotide database. The
AR21-siRNA was composed of two complementary RNA strands: sense strand (AR-S)
5&#x02032;-cuGGGAAAGucAAGcccAudTsdT -3&#x02032; and antisense strand (AR-AS):
5&#x02032;-AUGGGCUUGACUUUCCcAGdTsdT-3&#x02032;. The two strands of the AR21-siRNA
are modified 21-nt oligoribonucleotides that contain phosphorothioate linkages
(indicated as &#x0201c;s&#x0201d;) between the 3&#x02032;-deoxythymidine (dT)
overhangs and that include multiple 2&#x02032;-OMe modifications (indicated by
lower-case letters).</p><p><italic>Oligonucleotide synthesis.</italic> Oligonucleotides were synthesized using an
ABI-394 DNA/RNA synthesizer. Solvents/reagents, solid-supports and
phosphoramidites were all purchased from Glen Research or ChemGenes and used as
received. Oligonucleotides were synthesized using modified synthesis cycles
provided with the instrument. After solid phase synthesis, the oligonucleotides
were deprotected and released from the support. The crude oligonucleotides were
purified by anion-exchange high performance liquid chromatography (HPLC) to
&#x0003e;85% (260&#x02009;nm) purity and then desalted by size exclusion
chromatography. The isolated yields for the final oligonucleotides were
calculated based on the respective ratios of measured to theoretical
260&#x02009;nm optical density units (ODUs) and their identity was confirmed by
LC/MS. Hybridization to generate double-stranded siRNA duplexes was performed by
mixing equimolar amounts of purified complementary strands to a final
concentration of 20 &#x000b5;mol/l in 1&#x000d7; PBS buffer pH 7.4, and by heating
the solution over a water bath at 95 &#x000b0;C for 5 minutes and cooling it to room
temperature over a period of approximately 12 hours.</p><p><italic>Chemical synthesis.</italic> Detailed chemical synthesis procedures and
characterization data of all intermediates (according to <bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref></bold>) is given as <bold>Supplementary Materials and
Methods</bold> only.</p><p><italic>Preparation of tris-(t-Butyl) protected (Glu-urea-Lys)-PEG-DSG (12).</italic>
Compound <bold>5</bold> (see <bold>Supplementary Materials and Methods</bold>,
1.00&#x02009;g, 0.37 mmol) and compound <bold>11</bold> (see <bold>Supplementary Materials
and Methods</bold>, 0.35&#x02009;g, 0.48 mmol) were dissolved in DMF
(10&#x02009;ml) under argon atmosphere. HBTU (0.22&#x02009;g, 0.58 mmol) and DIEA
(0.250&#x02009;ml, 1.46 mmol) were added to the mixture, and the mixture was
stirred overnight. The solvents were removed under reduced pressure, and the
residue was purified by silica gel chromatography (5&#x02013;20% MeOH in DCM) to
yield compound <bold>12</bold> (0.53&#x02009;g, 43%) as a white solid. <sup>1</sup>H
NMR (400 MHz, DMSO-<italic>d</italic><sub>6</sub>): &#x003b4; 7.78 (t, <italic>J</italic> = 5.7
Hz, 2H), 7.14-7.05 (m, 3H), 6.26 (m, 2H), 4.11-3.83 (m, 5H), 3.75&#x02013;3.63 (m,
3H), 3.60&#x02013;3.30 (m, OC<italic>H</italic><sub>2</sub>- and O-C<italic>H</italic>-protons,
PEG, O-alkyl and glycerol), 3.27&#x02013;3.12 (m, 5H), 3.07&#x02013;2.85 (m, 4H),
2.30&#x02013;2.15 (m, 3H), 2.03 (t, <italic>J</italic> = 7.4, 2H), 1.59&#x02013;1.33 (m,
23H), 1.30&#x02013;1.18 (m, 60H), 0.84 (t, <italic>J</italic> = 6.7 Hz, 6H). MS calc. Av.
MW. ~ 3,343; MALDI Av. MW found: 3,342.</p><p><italic>Preparation of (Glu-urea-Lys)-PEG-DSG (13).</italic> Formic acid (20&#x02009;ml)
and anisole (0.5&#x02009;ml) were added to compound <bold>12</bold> (0.50&#x02009;g,
0.14 mmol), and the mixture was stirred at room temperature for 24 hours. The
solvents were removed under reduced pressure, and the residue was coevaporated
with toluene (2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;50&#x02009;ml). The crude compound was
purified by flash silica gel column chromatography using a gradient of
10&#x02013;50% MeOH in DCM followed by MeOH to yield compound <bold>13</bold> as a white
solid (230&#x02009;mg, 48%). <sup>1</sup>H NMR (400 MHz,
DMSO-<italic>d</italic><sub>6</sub>): &#x003b4; 7.96 (bs, 2H), 7.80&#x02013;7.77 (m,
3H), 7.22&#x02013;6.95 (m, 6H), 4.09&#x02013;3.80 (m, 6H), 3.68&#x02013;3.60 (m, 2H),
3.59&#x02013;3.40 (m, OC<italic>H</italic><sub>2</sub>- and O-C<italic>H</italic>-protons, PEG),
3.39&#x02013;3.08 (m, 33H), 3.05&#x02013;2.87 (m, 5H), 2.76&#x02013;2.57 (m, 4H),
2.36&#x02013;2.14 (m, 3H), 2.03 (t, <italic>J</italic> = 7.5 Hz, 5H), 1.78 (brs, 2H),
1.65&#x02013;1.60 (m, 2H), 1.55&#x02013;1.30 (m, 15H), 1.29&#x02013;1.13 (m, 61H),
1.10&#x02013;1.00 (m, <italic>J</italic> = 6.5 Hz, 19H), 0.84 (t, <italic>J</italic> = 6.7 Hz,
6H). MS calc. Av. MW. ~ 3,190; MALDI Av. MW found: ~3,193.</p><p><italic>Encapsulation of siRNA into LNP using microfluidic mixing.</italic> LNP
formulations were constructed using a microfluidic staggered herringbone
micromixer (SHM) provided by Precision Nanosystems (Vancouver, BC) as described
previously.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">33</xref></sup> The siRNA
solutions were prepared in 25 mmol/l acetate buffer at pH 4.0. For comparison
studies between AR21-siRNA and AR25-siRNA, lipid stocks were co-dissolved in
ethanol at molar ratio of 40% DMAP-BLP, 17.5% DSPC, 40% Chol, and 2.5% PEG-DMG.
For PEG-lipid comparison studies containing 2.5 mol% total PEG-lipid, lipid
stocks were codissolved in ethanol at appropriate molar ratios: 50 mol%
DMAP-BLP, 10 mol% DSPC, 37.3 mol% Chol, 0/0.5/1 mol% (Glu-urea-Lys)-PEG-DSG,
2.5/2/1.5 mol% PEG-DSG, and 0.2 mol% DiI. For cationic LNPs encapsulating
AR21-siRNA containing 5 mol% total PEG-lipid used for <italic>in vivo</italic> studies,
lipid stocks were codissolved in ethanol at the following molar ratios: 50 mol%
DMAP-BLP, 10 mol% DSPC, 34.8 mol% Chol, 0/1 mol% (Glu-urea-Lys)-PEG-DSG, 5/4
mol% PEG-DSG, and 0.2 mol% DiI. The siRNA to lipid ratio for all formulations
was kept at 0.067 (wt/wt). The siRNA and lipid ethanol solutions are mixed at a
1:3 ratio, respectively. Total formulation volume ranges from 4 to 40&#x02009;ml
depending on experiment size.</p><p><italic>Characterization of LNP.</italic> The mean diameter of the vesicles was
determined using a NICOMP370 particle sizer (Nicomp Particle Sizing, Santa
Barbara, CA). Intensity-weighted size and distribution data was used. LNPs
utilized for AR21-siRNA and AR25-siRNA comparisons were
56.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;17.6&#x02009;nm and 55.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;19.61
nm in size, respectively. The size of LNP containing a total of 2.5 mol%
PEG-lipid, (Glu-urea-Lys)-LNP-AR21-siRNA (1 mol% (Glu-urea-Lys)-PEG) was
84.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;32.5&#x02009;nm, (Glu-urea-Lys)-LNP-AR21-siRNA (0.5
mol% (Glu-urea-Lys)-PEG) was 77.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;23.6&#x02009;nm, and the
non-targeted LNP-AR21-siRNA (0 mol% (Glu-urea-Lys)-PEG) was
73.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;31.6&#x02009;nm. For LNPs containing a total of 5.0
mol% PEG-lipid: (Glu-urea-Lys)-LNP-AR21-siRNA (1 mol% (Glu-urea-Lys)-PEG-DSG)
the size was 55.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;22.5&#x02009;nm, and the non-targeted
LNP-AR21-siRNA (no targeting PEG-lipid) exhibited a size of
45.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;16.5&#x02009;nm. Zeta potentials of LNPs were
measured using the Malvern Nano ZS (Worcestershire, UK). Lipid concentrations
were determined based on total cholesterol content determined using the
Cholesterol E enzymatic assay from Wako Chemicals (Richmond, VA). Concentrations
of siRNA were measured using Quant-iT RiboGreen RNA Reagent and Kit (Life
Technologies) according to the manufacturer's protocol. Encapsulation
efficiency was determined by analysis of siRNA concentrations after addition of
1% Triton-X-100 (Sigma) to intact LNPs.</p><p><italic>Western blotting.</italic> LNCaP cells were plated in 12-well plates
(2.0&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup> cells per well). Cells were washed
with PBS and lysed with RIPA buffer (1% NP-40, 0.25% deoxycholic acid)
supplemented with protease inhibitors (Roche Diagnostics, Laval, Quebec,
Canada). Aliquots of 10 &#x003bc;g of total protein, as quantified by Bradford Assay,
were analyzed by immunoblotting. Antibodies to AR were purchased from Santa Cruz
Biotechnology (AR-441) (Santa Cruz, CA). Antibodies to &#x003b2;-Actin were
purchased from Abcam (Cambridge, MA). Antigen-antibody complexes were detected
using Millipore Immobilon Western Chemiluminescent HRP Substrate (Billerica,
MA).</p><p><italic>Confocal microscopy of tumor sections.</italic> Excised LNCaP tumors from groups
of three mice each were maintained in 10% buffered formalin and then
cryo-sectioned by Wax-IT Histology Services (Vancouver, BC). Tissue sections
were fixed onto glass cover slips and examined under an Olympus FV1000 (Center
Valley, PA) laser-scanning microscope. For each mouse xenograft, 5 tissue
sections and 20 fields of view were examined. LNP fluorescence was quantified
using Image J (v1.50b, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://imagej.nih.gov/">https://imagej.nih.gov/</ext-link>).</p><p><italic>Fluorescent microscopy.</italic> LNCaP cells were seeded at
2.0&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>4</sup> cells per well and PC-3 cells were
seeded at 1.5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>4</sup> cells per well in a 96-well
format. Cells were treated with 5 &#x003bc;g/ml (based on AR21-siRNA weight)
(Glu-urea-Lys)-LNP-AR21-siRNA (1 mol% (Glu-urea-Lys)-PEG-DSG) or LNP-AR21-siRNA
for 24 hours. 2-PMPA was added as a competitive reagent at 100-fold molar excess
to (Glu-urea-Lys)-PEG-DSG. Cells were fixed in 3% PFA with Hoechst's stain
and examined using a Cellomics ArrayScan VTI HCS Reader (Thermo Scientific,
Pittsburgh, PA).</p><p><italic>Pharmacokinetics of PSMA-targeted and nontargeted LNP-AR-siRNAs.</italic> Female
CD1 outbred mice (6 to 8 weeks old) were obtained from Charles River
Laboratories (Wilmington, MA) and acclimated for one week prior to use. Mice
were given 1&#x02009;mg/kg of either PSMA-targeted or nontargeted LNP-AR21-siRNA,
containing trace amounts of [<sup>3</sup>H]-cholesteryl hexadecylether (CHE),
via the lateral tail vein injection. At 0.5, 2, 8, and 24 hours postinjection,
mice were euthanized. Blood was collected via intracardiac sampling in
Vacutainer tubes containing EDTA (BD Biosciences, Canada) and was chemically
digested at room temperature using Solvable (Perkin-Elmer, Wellesley, MA)
followed by decolorization with hydrogen peroxide (30% w/w). The amount of LNP
in blood was determined by liquid scintillation counting in Pico-Fluor 40
(Perkin-Elmer). All procedures involving animals were approved by the Animal
Care Committee at the University of British Columbia and performed in accordance
with the guidelines established by the Canadian Council on Animal Care.</p><p><italic>Treatment of mice with PSMA-targeted and non-targeted LNP-AR21-siRNAs.</italic>
Xenograft prostate tumors were established as described.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">30</xref></sup> Briefly, LNCaP cells
(5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>6</sup>) in 0.1&#x02009;ml Matrigel (Becton
Dickinson Labware, Mississauga, Ontario, Canada) were inoculated subcutaneously
in two flank regions of 6- to 8-week-old male athymic nude mice (Harlan Sprague
Dawley, Indianapolis, IN) under halothane anesthesia using a 27-gauge needle.
When the tumors became palpable, volumes were measured, and blood was collected
from the tail vein to assess serum PSA by ELISA (ClinPro International, Union
City, CA). Once PSA values reached 50&#x02013;75&#x02009;ng/ml, animals were
randomized into three groups and were treated with
(Glu-urea-Lys)-LNP-AR21-siRNA, nontargeted LNP-AR21-siRNA, or aline (PBS) via
the tail vein. Animals treated with PBS were given one injection on day 1.
Animals given (Glu-urea-Lys)-LNP-AR21-siRNA and non-targeted LNP-AR21-siRNA were
treated on days 1, 2, 3, 7, 9, and 11 with 5&#x02009;mg siRNA/kg of mouse body
weight. Mice were sacrificed on day 14. Serum PSA levels and levels of mRNA
encoding AR and PSA were determined, and immunohistochemical analyses of
xenograft tumors were performed. All animal procedures were performed according
to the guidelines of the Canadian Council of Animal Care and with appropriate
institutional certification.</p><p><italic>qRT-PCR.</italic> Total RNA from mouse tissue was isolated using Trizol according
to the manufacturer's protocol (Life Technologies, Burlington, ON,
Canada). RNA extracts were reverse transcribed using random hexamers (Applied
Biosystems, Foster City, CA) and MMLV reverse transcriptase (Invitrogen).
Triplicates of the resulting cDNA were used as templates for quantitative
real-time PCR on the Applied Biosystems 7900HT Fast Real-Time PCR System
following the SYBR Green PCR Master Mix protocol as described
previously.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">48</xref></sup> 18S rRNA was
used as an endogenous control and relative quantitation was determined using the
comparative Ct (2<sup>-&#x00394;&#x00394;Ct</sup>) method. Primer sequences for AR
were: sense 5&#x02032;-GCAGGCAAGAGCACTGAAGATA-3&#x02032; and antisense
5&#x02032;-CCTTTGTGTAACCTCCCTTGA-3&#x02032;. Primers for PSA were: sense
5&#x02032;<bold><italic>-</italic></bold>TGTGCTTCAAGGTATCACGTCAT-3&#x02032; and antisense:
5&#x02032;- TGTACAGGGAAGGCCTTTCG-3&#x02032;. Primers for 18S rRNA were: sense
5&#x02032;-CGATGCTCTTAGCTGAGTGT-3&#x02032; and antisense
5&#x02032;-GGTCCAAGAATTTCACCTCT-3&#x02032;.</p><p><italic>Immunohistochemistry of tumor tissues.</italic> Immunohistochemistry (IHC)
staining was conducted using a Ventana autostainer model Discover XT (Ventana
Medical System Oro Valley, AZ) with an enzyme-labeled biotin streptavidin system
and solvent-resistant DAB Map kit. The antibody used for Ki67 was from Lab
Vision Corporation, and was diluted 1:500 in 1X PBS. The TUNEL, or apoptosis,
study was done using a TdT enzyme kit (Roche, Indianapolis, IN). IHC slides were
scanned on a Leica Digital Imaging System. Images were viewed using Digital
Image Hub, (SlidePath, Dublin, Ireland). The proliferation factor is defined as
the average number of Ki67 positive cells per core, or per section. The
apoptotic factor is the average number of apoptotic positive cells per core, or
per section.</p><p><italic>Statistical analyses.</italic> All statistical analyses were performed using
GraphPad. Initially, a one-way analysis of variance was used to statistically
evaluate the differences between treatment groups. In the case of statistically
significant results, the differences between treatment groups were assessed
through the use of the Tukey-Kramer multiple comparisons test, unless otherwise
stated. Probability (<italic>P</italic>) values less than 0.05 were considered
significant.</p><p><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1"><bold>SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIAL</bold></xref>&#x0000a;
<bold>Figure S1.</bold> Systemic administration of siRNA formulated in PSMA-targeted
(Glu-urea-Lys)-LNP enhances AR protein knockdown in vivo&#x0000a;
<bold>Figure S2.</bold> Effect of systemically administered LNP formulations on tumor growth.&#x0000a;
<bold>Figure S3.</bold> LNP encapsulating scramble (SC)-siRNA does not result in AR
knockdown in vitro.&#x0000a;
<bold>Figure S4.</bold> siRNA against GAPDH does not result in AR knockdown in
vitro&#x0000a; Materials and Methods</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors would like to acknowledge the Canadian Institutes of Health Research
grants (MOP-86587, FRN-111627, FRN-124295), Prostate Cancer Canada grant (D2013-5)
and Alnylam Pharmaceuticals for supporting this work.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Lee, JB, Zhang, K, Tam, YY, Tam, YK, Belliveau, NM, Sung, VY et al. (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Lipid nanoparticle siRNA systems for silencing the androgen receptor in
human prostate cancer in vivo</article-title>. <source>Int J Cancer</source>
<volume>131</volume>: <fpage>E781</fpage>&#x02013;E790.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22095615</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Semple, SC, Akinc, A, Chen, J, Sandhu, AP, Mui, BL, Cho, CK et al. (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Rational design of cationic lipids for siRNA delivery</article-title>. <source>Nat Biotechnol</source>
<volume>28</volume>: <fpage>172</fpage>&#x02013;176.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20081866</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Akinc, A, Querbes, W, De, S, Qin, J, Frank-Kamenetsky, M, Jayaprakash, KN et al. (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Targeted delivery of RNAi therapeutics with endogenous and exogenous
ligand-based mechanisms</article-title>. <source>Mol Ther</source>
<volume>18</volume>: <fpage>1357</fpage>&#x02013;1364.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20461061</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Jayaraman, M, Ansell, SM, Mui, BL, Tam, YK, Chen, J, Du, X et al. (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Maximizing the potency of siRNA lipid nanoparticles for hepatic gene
silencing in vivo</article-title>. <source>Angew Chem Int Ed Engl</source>
<volume>51</volume>: <fpage>8529</fpage>&#x02013;8533.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22782619</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Longmuir, KJ, Robertson, RT, Haynes, SM, Baratta, JL and Waring, AJ (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Effective targeting of liposomes to liver and hepatocytes <italic>in vivo</italic>
by incorporation of a Plasmodium amino acid sequence</article-title>. <source>Pharm Res</source>
<volume>23</volume>: <fpage>759</fpage>&#x02013;769.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16550476</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Cullis, PR, Chonn, A and Semple, SC (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Interactions of liposomes and lipid-based carrier systems with blood
proteins: Relation to clearance behaviour in vivo</article-title>. <source>Adv Drug Deliv Rev</source>
<volume>32</volume>: <fpage>3</fpage>&#x02013;17.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10837632</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Mahley, RW and Huang, Y (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Atherogenic remnant lipoproteins: role for proteoglycans in trapping,
transferring, and internalizing</article-title>. <source>J Clin Invest</source>
<volume>117</volume>: <fpage>94</fpage>&#x02013;98.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17200713</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Rungta, RL, Choi, HB, Lin, PJ, Ko, RW, Ashby, D, Nair, J et al. (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Lipid nanoparticle delivery of siRNA to silence neuronal gene expression in
the brain</article-title>. <source>Mol Ther Nucleic Acids</source>
<volume>2</volume>: <fpage>e136</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24301867</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Frank-Kamenetsky, M, Grefhorst, A, Anderson, NN, Racie, TS, Bramlage, B, Akinc, A et al. (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Therapeutic RNAi targeting PCSK9 acutely lowers plasma cholesterol in
rodents and LDL cholesterol in nonhuman primates</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
<volume>105</volume>: <fpage>11915</fpage>&#x02013;11920.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18695239</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Foster, DJ, Barros, S, Duncan, R, Shaikh, S, Cantley, W, Dell, A et al. (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Comprehensive evaluation of canonical versus Dicer-substrate siRNA <italic>in
vitro</italic> and in vivo</article-title>. <source>RNA</source>
<volume>18</volume>: <fpage>557</fpage>&#x02013;568.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22294662</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Maeda, H, Wu, J, Sawa, T, Matsumura, Y and Hori, K (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Tumor vascular permeability and the EPR effect in macromolecular
therapeutics: a review</article-title>. <source>J Control Release</source>
<volume>65</volume>: <fpage>271</fpage>&#x02013;284.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10699287</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Maeda, H (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>The enhanced permeability and retention (EPR) effect in tumor vasculature:
the key role of tumor-selective macromolecular drug targeting</article-title>. <source>Adv Enzyme Regul</source>
<volume>41</volume>: <fpage>189</fpage>&#x02013;207.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11384745</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Ambegia, E, Ansell, S, Cullis, P, Heyes, J, Palmer, L and MacLachlan, I (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Stabilized plasmid-lipid particles containing PEG-diacylglycerols exhibit
extended circulation lifetimes and tumor selective gene expression</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source>
<volume>1669</volume>: <fpage>155</fpage>&#x02013;163.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15893518</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Mui, BL, Tam, YK, Jayaraman, M, Ansell, SM, Du, X, Tam, YY et al. (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Influence of polyethylene glycol lipid desorption rates on pharmacokinetics
and pharmacodynamics of siRNA lipid nanoparticles</article-title>. <source>Mol Ther Nucleic Acids</source>
<volume>2</volume>: <fpage>e139</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24345865</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Banerjee, R, Tyagi, P, Li, S and Huang, L (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Anisamide-targeted stealth liposomes: a potent carrier for targeting
doxorubicin to human prostate cancer cells</article-title>. <source>Int J Cancer</source>
<volume>112</volume>: <fpage>693</fpage>&#x02013;700.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15382053</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Chono, S, Li, SD, Conwell, CC and Huang, L (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>An efficient and low immunostimulatory nanoparticle formulation for systemic
siRNA delivery to the tumor</article-title>. <source>J Control Release</source>
<volume>131</volume>: <fpage>64</fpage>&#x02013;69.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18674578</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Li, SD, Chono, S and Huang, L (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Efficient gene silencing in metastatic tumor by siRNA formulated in
surface-modified nanoparticles</article-title>. <source>J Control Release</source>
<volume>126</volume>: <fpage>77</fpage>&#x02013;84.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18083264</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Tam, YY, Chen, S, Zaifman, J, Tam, YK, Lin, PJ, Ansell, S et al. (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Small molecule ligands for enhanced intracellular delivery of lipid
nanoparticle formulations of siRNA</article-title>. <source>Nanomedicine</source>
<volume>9</volume>: <fpage>665</fpage>&#x02013;674.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23219877</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Holmes, EH, Greene, TG, Tino, WT, Boynton, AL, Aldape, HC, Misrock, SL et al. (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Analysis of glycosylation of prostate-specific membrane antigen derived from
LNCaP cells, prostatic carcinoma tumors, and serum from prostate cancer
patients</article-title>. <source>Prostate Suppl</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>25</fpage>&#x02013;29.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8950359</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Liu, H, Rajasekaran, AK, Moy, P, Xia, Y, Kim, S, Navarro, V et al. (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Constitutive and antibody-induced internalization of prostate-specific
membrane antigen</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source>
<volume>58</volume>: <fpage>4055</fpage>&#x02013;4060.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9751609</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Kularatne, SA, Wang, K, Santhapuram, HK and Low, PS (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Prostate-specific membrane antigen targeted imaging and therapy of prostate
cancer using a PSMA inhibitor as a homing ligand</article-title>. <source>Mol Pharm</source>
<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>780</fpage>&#x02013;789.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19361233</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Kularatne, SA, Venkatesh, C, Santhapuram, HK, Wang, K, Vaitilingam, B, Henne, WA et al. (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Synthesis and biological analysis of prostate-specific membrane
antigen-targeted anticancer prodrugs</article-title>. <source>J Med Chem</source>
<volume>53</volume>: <fpage>7767</fpage>&#x02013;7777.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20936874</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Thomas, M, Kularatne, SA, Qi, L, Kleindl, P, Leamon, CP, Hansen, MJ et al. (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Ligand-targeted delivery of small interfering RNAs to malignant cells and
tissues</article-title>. <source>Ann N Y Acad Sci</source>
<volume>1175</volume>: <fpage>32</fpage>&#x02013;39.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19796075</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Banerjee, SR, Foss, CA, Castanares, M, Mease, RC, Byun, Y, Fox, JJ et al. (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Synthesis and evaluation of technetium-99m- and rhenium-labeled inhibitors
of the prostate-specific membrane antigen (PSMA)</article-title>. <source>J Med Chem</source>
<volume>51</volume>: <fpage>4504</fpage>&#x02013;4517.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18637669</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Maresca, KP, Hillier, SM, Femia, FJ, Keith, D, Barone, C, Joyal, JL et al. (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>A series of halogenated heterodimeric inhibitors of prostate specific
membrane antigen (PSMA) as radiolabeled probes for targeting prostate
cancer</article-title>. <source>J Med Chem</source>
<volume>52</volume>: <fpage>347</fpage>&#x02013;357.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19111054</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">McEnaney, PJ, Parker, CG, Zhang, AX and Spiegel, DA (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Antibody-recruiting molecules: an emerging paradigm for engaging immune
function in treating human disease</article-title>. <source>ACS Chem Biol</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>1139</fpage>&#x02013;1151.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22758917</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Murelli, RP, Zhang, AX, Michel, J, Jorgensen, WL and Spiegel, DA (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Chemical control over immune recognition: a class of antibody-recruiting
small molecules that target prostate cancer</article-title>. <source>J Am Chem Soc</source>
<volume>131</volume>: <fpage>17090</fpage>&#x02013;17092.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19888723</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Zhang, AX, Murelli, RP, Barinka, C, Michel, J, Cocleaza, A, Jorgensen, WL et al. (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>A remote arene-binding site on prostate specific membrane antigen revealed
by antibody-recruiting small molecules</article-title>. <source>J Am Chem Soc</source>
<volume>132</volume>: <fpage>12711</fpage>&#x02013;12716.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20726553</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">He, W, Kularatne, SA, Kalli, KR, Prendergast, FG, Amato, RJ, Klee, GG et al. (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Quantitation of circulating tumor cells in blood samples from ovarian and
prostate cancer patients using tumor-specific fluorescent ligands</article-title>. <source>Int J Cancer</source>
<volume>123</volume>: <fpage>1968</fpage>&#x02013;1973.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18661519</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Cheng, H, Snoek, R, Ghaidi, F, Cox, ME and Rennie, PS (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Short hairpin RNA knockdown of the androgen receptor attenuates
ligand-independent activation and delays tumor progression</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source>
<volume>66</volume>: <fpage>10613</fpage>&#x02013;10620.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17079486</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Haupenthal, J, Baehr, C, Zeuzem, S and Piiper, A (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>RNAse A-like enzymes in serum inhibit the anti-neoplastic activity of siRNA
targeting polo-like kinase 1</article-title>. <source>Int J Cancer</source>
<volume>121</volume>: <fpage>206</fpage>&#x02013;210.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17351902</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Behlke, MA (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Chemical modification of siRNAs for <italic>in vivo</italic> use</article-title>. <source>Oligonucleotides</source>
<volume>18</volume>: <fpage>305</fpage>&#x02013;319.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19025401</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Belliveau, NM, Huft, J, Lin, PJ, Chen, S, Leung, AK, Leaver, TJ et al. (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Microfluidic synthesis of highly potent limit-size lipid nanoparticles for
<italic>in vivo</italic> delivery of siRNA</article-title>. <source>Mol Ther Nucleic Acids</source>
<volume>1</volume>: <fpage>e37</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23344179</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Yoshioka, H (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>Surface modification of haemoglobin-containing liposomes with polyethylene
glycol prevents liposome aggregation in blood plasma</article-title>. <source>Biomaterials</source>
<volume>12</volume>: <fpage>861</fpage>&#x02013;864.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1764558</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Chen, S, Tam, YYC,Lin, PJC,Sung, MMH, Tam, YK, Cullis, PRC (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Influence of particle size on the in vivo potency of lipid nanoparticle
formulations of siRNA.</article-title><source>J Control Release</source><volume>235</volume>:<fpage>236</fpage>&#x02013;244.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27238441</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Madani, H, Thompson, AS and Threadgill, MD (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>An expedient synthesis of 7-O-functionalised
pyrrolo[2,1-c][1,4]benzodiazepine-5,11-diones</article-title>. <source>Tetrahedron</source>
<volume>58</volume>: <fpage>8107</fpage>&#x02013;8111.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Sonogashira, K (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Development of Pd&#x02013;Cu catalyzed cross-coupling of terminal acetylenes
with sp2-carbon halides</article-title>. <source>J Organometallic Chem</source>
<volume>653</volume>:<fpage>46</fpage>&#x02013;49.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Kaighn, ME, Narayan, KS, Ohnuki, Y, Lechner, JF and Jones, LW (<year>1979</year>). <article-title>Establishment and characterization of a human prostatic carcinoma cell line
(PC-3)</article-title>. <source>Invest Urol</source>
<volume>17</volume>: <fpage>16</fpage>&#x02013;23.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">447482</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Chonn, A, Semple, SC and Cullis, PR (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Association of blood proteins with large unilamellar liposomes in vivo.
Relation to circulation lifetimes</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>267</volume>: <fpage>18759</fpage>&#x02013;18765.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1527006</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Park, YS, Maruyama, K and Huang, L (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Some negatively charged phospholipid derivatives prolong the liposome
circulation in vivo</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source>
<volume>1108</volume>: <fpage>257</fpage>&#x02013;260.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1637850</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Scholzen, T and Gerdes, J (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>The Ki-67 protein: from the known and the unknown</article-title>. <source>J Cell Physiol</source>
<volume>182</volume>: <fpage>311</fpage>&#x02013;322.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10653597</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Kawano, K and Maitani, Y (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Effects of polyethylene glycol spacer length and ligand density on folate
receptor targeting of liposomal Doxorubicin <italic>in vitro</italic></article-title>. <source>J Drug Deliv</source>
<volume>2011</volume>: <fpage>160967</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21490746</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Reiter, RE, Gu, Z, Watabe, T, Thomas, G, Szigeti, K, Davis, E et al. (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Prostate stem cell antigen: a cell surface marker overexpressed in prostate
cancer</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
<volume>95</volume>: <fpage>1735</fpage>&#x02013;1740.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9465086</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Cabral, H, Matsumoto, Y, Mizuno, K, Chen, Q, Murakami, M, Kimura, M et al. (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Accumulation of sub-100&#x02009;nm polymeric micelles in poorly permeable
tumours depends on size</article-title>. <source>Nat Nanotechnol</source>
<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>815</fpage>&#x02013;823.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22020122</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Nair, JK,Willoughby, JL,Chan, A,Charisse, K,Alam, MR,Wang, Qet al. (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Multivalent N-acetylgalactosamine-conjugated siRNA localizes in hepatocytes
and elicits robust RNAi-mediated gene silencing.</article-title><source>J Am Chem Soc</source><volume>136</volume>:<fpage>16958</fpage>&#x02013;16961.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25434769</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Maier, MA, Jayaraman, M, Matsuda, S, Liu, J, Barros, S, Querbes, W et al. (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Biodegradable lipids enabling rapidly eliminated lipid nanoparticles for
systemic delivery of RNAi therapeutics</article-title>. <source>Mol Ther</source>
<volume>21</volume>: <fpage>1570</fpage>&#x02013;1578.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23799535</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Horoszewicz, JS, Leong, SS, Kawinski, E, Karr, JP, Rosenthal, H, Chu, TM et al. (<year>1983</year>). <article-title>LNCaP model of human prostatic carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source>
<volume>43</volume>: <fpage>1809</fpage>&#x02013;1818.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6831420</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Snoek, R, Cheng, H, Margiotti, K, Wafa, LA, Wong, CA, Wong, EC et al. (<year>2009</year>). <article-title><italic>In vivo</italic> knockdown of the androgen receptor results in growth
inhibition and regression of well-established, castration-resistant prostate
tumors</article-title>. <source>Clin Cancer Res</source>
<volume>15</volume>: <fpage>39</fpage>&#x02013;47.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19118031</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sup1"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="xob1"><label>Supplementary Information</label><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mtna201643x1.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></back><floats-group><fig id="fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Lipid nanoparticle (LNP) encapsulating AR21-siRNA results in enhanced AR
knockdown <italic>in vitro</italic>.</bold> AR21-siRNA was composed of two
complementary RNA strands: sense strand (AR-S)
5&#x02032;-cuGGGAAAGucAAGcccAudTsdT-3&#x02032; and antisense strand (AR-AS):
5&#x02032;-AUGGGCUUGACUUUCCcAGdTsdT-3&#x02032;. LNCaP cells were incubated with
0.5, 1.0 or 5.0 &#x003bc;g/ml of LNP encapsulated with either AR25-siRNA or
AR21-siRNA for 48 hours. Equal portions of protein samples were analyzed by
immunoblotting to AR and &#x003b2;-actin, the latter serving as a loading
control.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mtna201643f1"/></fig><fig id="fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Systemic administration of lipid nanoparticle (LNP) containing 5 mol%
PEG-DSG results in greater accumulation in LNCaP tumors compared to LNP
containing 2.5 mol% PEG-DSG.</bold> (<bold>a</bold>) Mice were injected via the
tail vein with fluorescently labeled LNP containing 5 or 2.5 mol% PEG-DSG
(red) and were sacrificed 4 or 24 hours following the final i.v. injection.
LNCaP tumors were harvested, cryo-sectioned, and analyzed under a confocal
microscope. Representative images are shown. Nuclei were stained with
Hoescht (blue). (<bold>b</bold>) Quantitation of uptake of fluorescent label into
LNCaP tumor tissues was performed using ImageJ (<italic>n</italic> = 5) (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://rsb.info.nih.gov/ij/">http://rsb.info.nih.gov/ij/</ext-link>); <italic>*P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05;
<italic>**P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mtna201643f2"/></fig><fig id="fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>Reagents and conditions for synthesis of (Glu-urea-Lys)-PEG-DSG:</bold> (i)
(PPh<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>PdCl<sub>2</sub>, CuI,
triethylamine/acetonitrile, 80 &#x000b0;C, 3&#x02009;h, 95%; (ii) a.
<italic>N,N,N',N'</italic>-Tetramethyl-<italic>O-</italic>(1<italic>H</italic>-benzotriazol-1-yl)uronium
hexafluorophosphate (HBTU), <italic>N</italic>,<italic>N</italic>-diisopropylethylamine
(DIEA)/dichloromethane (DCM), rt, overnight 93% and b. H<sub>2</sub>, Pd-C/
methanol, rt, overnight, 92%; (iii) a.
<italic>N,N'</italic>-disuccinimidyl carbonate (DSC), triethylamine, DCM, 0
&#x000b0;C to room temperature, overnight and b. methyl 6-aminocaproate
hydrochloride, pyridine/DCM, 0 &#x000b0;C to rt, overnight, 88%; (iv) a.
LiOH, methanol/water/THF, 0 &#x000b0;C to rt, overnight, 96% and b.
<italic>N-</italic>hydroxysuccinimide,
<italic>N</italic>-(3-dimethylaminopropyl)-<italic>N'</italic>-ethylcarbodiimide
hydrochloride (EDAC), 4-(dimethylamino)pyridine DMAP)/DCM, rt, overnight; (v) Triethylamine (TEA)/DCM, rt, overnight,
66%; (vi) formic acid/DCM (2:1), rt, overnight, 91%; (vii) HBTU, DIEA / <italic>N,N</italic>-dimethylformamide (DMF), rt, overnight, 43%; (viii)
neat formic acid, 48%.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mtna201643f3"/></fig><fig id="fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><bold>Lipid nanoparticle (LNP) formulations containing (Glu-urea-Lys)-PEG-DSG
enhances cellular uptake and inhibition of AR expression in AR-positive
LNCaP cells <italic>in vitro</italic></bold>. (<bold>a</bold>) LNCaP cells were incubated
for 24 hours with fluorescently labeled AR-targeting LNP at an siRNA
concentration 5 &#x003bc;g/ml. Cellular uptake was quantified using Cellomics
ArrayScan and is expressed as mean fluorescent intensity per cell.
Approximately 400 cells were measured in four individual wells (<italic>n =</italic>
4). 2-PMPA was added to compete with AR-dependent uptake. Statistical
significance was determined for (Glu-urea-Lys)-LNP in comparison to all the
other groups; **<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01. (<bold>b</bold>) PC-3 (AR-negative) PCa
cells were incubated with 5 &#x003bc;g/ml of fluorescently labeled
(Glu-urea-Lys)-LNP for 24 hours. 2-PMPA was added as a competitor. Cellular
uptake was quantified using Cellomics ArrayScan and expressed as mean
fluorescent intensity per cell. Approximately 400 cells were measured in
four individual wells (<italic>n =</italic> 4). Statistical significance was
determined between non-targeted LNP versus PSMA-targeted (Glu-urea-Lys)-LNP
groups. **<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01. (<bold>c</bold>) LNCaP cells were incubated with
1, 5, 10, or 15 &#x003bc;g/ml siRNA formulated as indicated for 48 hours. Levels
of AR protein were analyzed by immunoblotting, with &#x003b2;-actin as the
loading control.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mtna201643f4"/></fig><fig id="fig5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><bold>PSMA-targeted (Glu-urea-Lys)-LNP and non-targeted LNP exhibit similar
pharmacokinetics.</bold> PSMA-targeted (Glu-urea-Lys)-LNP and nontargeted
lipid nanoparticle (LNP) were synthesized with trace amounts of
[<sup>3</sup>H] CHE. The LNP formulations contained
DMAP-BLP/DSPC/cholesterol/(Glu-urea-Lys)-PEG-DSG/PEG-DSG molar ratios of
50/10/35/1/4 or 50/10/35/0/5 or DMAP-BLP/DSPC/cholesterol/PEG-DSG at molar
ratios of 50/10/37.5/2.5. Mice treated by tail vein injection with
1&#x02009;mg/kg siRNA formulated in PSMA-targeted (Glu-urea-Lys)-LNP or
non-targeted LNP. Plots show percentage of the total injected dose remaining
as a function of time. Each data point represents the mean &#x000b1; SD
(<italic>n =</italic> 4). Circulation halftime (<italic>t</italic><sub>1/2</sub>) for
nontargeted 2.5% PEG-DSG LNP, nontargeted 5% PEG-DSG LNP and
(Glu-urea-Lys)-LNP was ~0.5, 8.7, and 11.6 hours, respectively. Area under
the curve (AUC) for nontargeted 2.5% PEG-DSG LNP, nontargeted 5% PEG-DSG LNP
and (Glu-urea-Lys)-LNP was
309.18&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;35.22%&#x000b7;hours,
1,066.57&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;57.21%&#x000b7;hours, and
1,095.90&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;45.65%&#x000b7;hours, respectively.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mtna201643f5"/></fig><fig id="fig6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><bold>Systemic administration of siRNA formulated in PSMA-targeted
(Glu-urea-Lys)-lipid nanoparticle (LNP) lowers serum PSA levels and
enhances AR gene silencing.</bold> Mice were treated via tail vein
injection with PBS as a control or with the 5&#x02009;mg/kg of siRNA
formulated in PSMA-targeted (Glu-urea-Lys)-LNP or nontargeted LNP.
(<bold>a</bold>) Percentages of serum PSA levels are relative to PSA levels one
day prior to treatment. Serum PSA levels were measured on days 7 and 14.
(<bold>b</bold>) Quantitative real-time PCR was used to assess AR mRNA levels
from tumor tissue on day 14. (<bold>c</bold>) Quantitative real-time PCR was used
to assess PSA mRNA levels from tumor tissue on day 14. Data points are the
means &#x000b1; SE (<italic>n =</italic> 6&#x02013;7); **<italic>P &#x0003c;</italic> 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mtna201643f6"/></fig><fig id="fig7"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p><bold>Systemic administration of PSMA-targeted (Glu-urea-Lys)-lipid nanoparticle
decreases cellular proliferation but does not induce apoptosis in tumor
cells.</bold> Tissues from the mice described in <bold>Figure 6</bold> were
analyzed. (<bold>a</bold>) Representative images of Ki67 (cell proliferation
marker) stained samples. (<bold>b</bold>) Quantitation of Ki67 stained tumor
sections plotted as means &#x000b1; SD (<italic>n =</italic> 6); **<italic>P</italic>
&#x0003c; 0.01. (<bold>c</bold>) Representative images of TUNEL (cell apoptosis marker)
stained samples, with red circles highlighting stained cells. (<bold>d</bold>)
Quantitation of TUNEL stained tumor sections plotted as the means &#x000b1;
SD (<italic>n</italic> = 6). No significant difference was observed for
TUNEL-stained tumor sections.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mtna201643f7"/></fig></floats-group></article>