<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nar</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">nar</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">20716518</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3001079</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkq709</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">gkq709</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Molecular Biology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Diversity and strength of internal outward-oriented promoters in group IIC-<italic>attC</italic> introns</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>L&#x000e9;on</surname><given-names>Gr&#x000e9;gory</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Quiroga</surname><given-names>Cecilia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Centr&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>Daniela</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>Paul H.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="AFF1"><sup>1</sup>Centre de Recherche en Infectiologie, Centre Hospitalier Universitaire de Qu&#x000e9;bec, <sup>2</sup>D&#x000e9;partement de Biochimie, de Microbiologie, et de Bio-informatique, Facult&#x000e9; des Sciences et de G&#x000e9;nie, Universit&#x000e9; Laval, Qu&#x000e9;bec, Canada and <sup>3</sup>Departamento de Microbiolog&#x000ed;a, Inmunolog&#x000ed;a y Parasitolog&#x000ed;a, Facultad de Medicina, Universidad de Buenos Aires, Buenos Aires, Argentina</aff><author-notes><corresp id="COR1">*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: <phone>+1 418 654 2705</phone>; Fax: <fax>+1 418 654 2715</fax>; Email: <email>paul.roy@crchul.ulaval.ca</email></corresp><fn><p>Present address: Cecilia Quiroga, Department of Microbiology and Immunology, McGill University, Montr&#x000e9;al, Qu&#x000e9;bec, Canada.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>12</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>8</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>14</day><month>8</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>38</volume><issue>22</issue><fpage>8196</fpage><lpage>8207</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>25</day><month>6</month><year>2010</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>26</day><month>7</month><year>2010</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>7</month><year>2010</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2010. Published by Oxford University Press.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2010</copyright-year><license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Integrons are genetic elements that incorporate mobile gene cassettes by site-specific recombination and express them as an operon from a promoter (Pc) located upstream of the cassette insertion site. Most gene cassettes found in integrons contain only one gene followed by an <italic>attC</italic> recombination site. We have recently shown that a specific lineage of group IIC introns, named group IIC-<italic>attC</italic> introns, inserts into the bottom strand sequence of <italic>attC</italic> sites. Here, we show that <italic>S.ma</italic>.I2, a group IIC-<italic>attC</italic> intron inserted in an integron cassette array of <italic>Serratia marcescens</italic>, impedes transcription from Pc while allowing expression of the following antibiotic resistance cassette using an internal outward-oriented promoter (P<sub>out</sub>). Bioinformatic analyses indicate that one or two putative P<sub>out</sub>, which have sequence similarities with the <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> consensus promoters, are conserved in most group IIC-<italic>attC</italic> intron sequences. We show that P<sub>out</sub> with different versions of the &#x02212;35 and &#x02212;10 sequences are functionally active in expressing a promoterless chloramphenicol acetyltransferase (<italic>cat</italic>) reporter gene in <italic>E. coli</italic>. P<sub>out</sub> in group IIC-<italic>attC</italic> introns may therefore play a role in the expression of one or more gene cassettes whose transcription from Pc would otherwise be impeded by insertion of the intron.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Integrons are genetic elements that capture gene cassettes using a site-specific tyrosine recombinase (called an integron integrase) and promote their co-expression by supplying a unique functional promoter, Pc, divergent to the integrase gene (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1 B2 B3">1&#x02013;3</xref>). Most gene cassettes are composed of a single structural gene followed by a short recombination site designated <italic>attC</italic> (or 59-base element), that is specifically recognized by integron integrases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>). Integrons are found on chromosomes and on diverse mobile elements, such as plasmids and transposons, and play a major role in lateral gene transfer in gram-negative bacteria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>). Distinct classes of mobile integrons, corresponding to their integrase genes, have been reported in the literature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>). Mobile class 1 integrons are the most widespread among multi-drug resistant bacteria and are often associated with transposons from the Tn<italic>21</italic> family (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>). The class 1 integron platform is composed of two conserved segments, the 5&#x02032;-conserved (5&#x02032;-CS) and 3&#x02032;-conserved (3&#x02032;-CS) regions, and one variable region (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>A). The 5&#x02032;-CS segment contains the integrase gene (<italic>intI1</italic>), two divergent promoter regions (called Pi for the integrase gene and Pc for gene cassettes), and a recombination site (<italic>attI1</italic>) into which cassettes are integrated. The 3&#x02032;-CS segment usually contains a partially functional intercalating dyes/quaternary ammonium compound resistance gene (<italic>qacE&#x00394;1</italic>) and most also contain a sulfonamide resistance gene (<italic>sul1</italic>), and an open reading frame (ORF5), whose product has some similarity to puromycin acetyltransferase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>). Between the two conserved segments, the variable region usually includes a short array of gene cassettes coding for various antibiotic resistance mechanisms or ORFs whose products have no known function (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10 B11 B12">10&#x02013;12</xref>). Almost all gene cassettes are promoterless structures that depend on the Pc promoter to express their genes. Among class 1 integrons, several Pc variants (the most prevalent being Pc<sub>weak</sub>, Pc<sub>hybrid 1</sub>, Pc<sub>strong</sub> and Pc<sub>hybrid 2</sub>, respectively) and a second cassette promoter region, P<sub>2</sub> (almost exclusively associated with the Pc<sub>weak</sub> variant), have been described in the literature with different versions of the &#x02212;35 and &#x02212;10 sequences for each promoter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13 B14 B15 B16">13&#x02013;16</xref>). Therefore, expression of gene cassettes is potentially influenced by the genomic localization of the integron (i.e. on a multicopy plasmid versus on the chromosome) and mutation of the transcription and translation initiation signals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>). Moreover, if several cassettes are inserted in the variable region, additional factors, such as premature transcription termination within <italic>attC</italic> sites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>), a cassette with its own promoter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>), or insertion of mobile genetic elements in <italic>attC</italic> sites (e.g. insertion sequences (IS) or group II introns) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>), may also influence expression of gene cassettes.
<fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Class 1 integron and cassette arrays. (<bold>A</bold>) Schematic diagrams of the general structure of a class 1 integron. P, promoters; <italic>intI1</italic>, integrase gene; <italic>qacE&#x00394;1</italic>, antiseptic resistance gene; <italic>sul1</italic>, sulfonamide resistance gene; orf5, gene of unknown function. (<bold>B</bold>) Schematic diagrams of the variable region (gene cassettes) of class 1 integrons found in <italic>S. marcescens</italic> SCH909, <italic>E. coli</italic> 702, <italic>K. pneumoniae</italic> and <italic>Acinetobacter</italic> genomospecies genomes. The gray arrows indicate cassette ORFs; the gray boxes indicate cassette <italic>attC</italic> sites; the white rectangles and arrows indicate group IIC-<italic>attC</italic> introns with their intron encoded proteins (IEP); and P<sub>out</sub> indicates a putative outward-oriented promoter within the intron.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkq709f1"/></fig></p><p>Group II introns, together with LINEs and SINEs, are mobile elements from among non-LTR retrotransposons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>). They are found in bacteria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>), Archaea (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>) and in organelle genes of plants, fungi and yeast (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>). Group II intron RNAs are characterized by a conserved secondary structure organized into six domains (DI&#x02013;DVI) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>). They fold into active ribozymes that catalyze their excision (from precursor RNAs) and invade new genomic locations, aided by the intron-encoded protein (IEP) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>). Eight lineages of group II introns, termed bacterial classes A-F, ML (mitochondrial-like) and CL (chloroplast-like), have been established according to phylogenetic analysis of their IEP sequences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28 B29 B30">28&#x02013;30</xref>). Group IIC introns are of special interest because they are found in intergenic regions, usually after palindromic sequences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31 B32 B33">31&#x02013;33</xref>), and have unique RNA structure and self-splicing properties (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>). Phylogenetic analyses of intron IEP sequences has shown that introns found in <italic>attC</italic> sites constitute a monophyletic subset of group IIC, named group IIC-<italic>attC</italic> introns (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>). Group IIC introns found in integrons are specifically inserted into the bottom strand sequence of gene cassettes and consequently are oriented opposite to the transcription of the adjacent genes. While most introns found in integrons are in the last cassettes of the variable region (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>), those found in the <italic>Serratia marcescens</italic> SCH909 (accession no. AF453998), <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> 702 (AY785243), and <italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> (AJ971342) integrons, are in the first cassette and potentially influence the expression of the following gene cassettes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>B).</p><p>In this study, we first show that <italic>S.ma</italic>.I2, a group IIC-<italic>attC</italic> intron inserted in an integron cassette array of <italic>S. marcescens</italic>, impedes transcription from Pc<sub>weak</sub>-P2 promoters located within the 5&#x02032;-CS region, while allowing expression of the following antibiotic resistance cassette using an internal outward-oriented promoter (P<sub>out</sub>). Then, we performed bioinformatic analyses of all group II-<italic>attC</italic> intron sequences available in databases in order to determine the prevalence of P<sub>out</sub>. We found that one or two putative P<sub>out</sub>, which have sequence similarities with the <italic>E. coli</italic> consensus promoters, are conserved in several group IIC-<italic>attC</italic> introns. We show that P<sub>out</sub> with different versions of the &#x02212;35 and &#x02212;10 sequences from various group IIC-<italic>attC</italic> introns are functionally active in expressing a promoterless chloramphenicol acetyltransferase (<italic>cat</italic>) reporter gene in <italic>E. coli</italic>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Recombinant plasmids, bacterial strains and growth conditions</title><p>Plasmids are described in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>. The pKK-In&#x00394;SmaI2 clone was obtained from pKK-In by PCR amplification using primer pair Sm909-3947.for and Sm909-1507.rev to remove the group II intron <italic>S.ma</italic>.I2. The PCR reaction mixture was digested with DpnI (in order to remove the methylated pKK-In template) and ethanol precipitated. Then, the recovered unmethylated 4396-bp PCR product (i.e. pKK-In&#x00394;SmaI2) was ligated with T4 DNA ligase (400 U; NEB) and transformed into <italic>E. coli</italic> DH5-&#x003b1; competent cells with ampicillin selection. <italic>Serratia marcescens</italic> SCH909, <italic>Shewanella baltica</italic> OS155 and <italic>E. coli</italic> DH5-&#x003b1; (<italic>supE44</italic> &#x00394;<italic>lacU169</italic> (&#x003d5;80<italic>lacZ&#x00394;M15</italic>) <italic>hsdR17 recA1 endA1 gyrA96 thi-1 relA1</italic>) were grown in Luria&#x02013;Bertani (LB) broth (5&#x02009;g NaCl, 10&#x02009;g tryptone, 5&#x02009;g yeast extract) supplemented with 1&#x02009;g glucose at 37&#x000b0;C. When necessary, antibiotics were used at the following concentrations: ampicillin (Ap), 100&#x02009;&#x000b5;g/ml; and chloramphenicol (Cm), 34&#x02009;&#x000b5;g/ml. <italic>Nitrosomonas europaea</italic> was cultured as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>). <italic>Geobacter sulfurreducens</italic> genomic DNA and the <italic>S. baltica</italic> OS155 strain were kindly provided by The Institute for Genomic Research and by the DOE Joint Genome Institute, respectively. Isopropyl-&#x003b2;-<sc>d</sc>-thiogalactopyranoside (IPTG) was added at 1&#x02009;mM final concentration for induction of the <italic>tac</italic> promoter in pLQ880. Total DNA was isolated using a phenol&#x02013;chloroform purification method as described by Sambrook and Russell (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>).
<table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Plasmids used in this study</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plasmids</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Description or relevant characteristics</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pKK232-8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cloning vector with a promoterless <italic>cat</italic> used for promoter selection.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">53</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pKK-IntI1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">349-bp SalI-HindIII PCR fragment amplified from <italic>S. marcescens</italic> SCH909 genomic DNA (primer pair IntI1-SalI and aadB-HindIII) containing part of <italic>intI1</italic> and the nucleotide sequence up to the initiation codon of the <italic>aadB</italic>::<italic>S.ma</italic>.I2 gene cassette and cloned into pKK232-8 digested by SalI-HindIII.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pKK-SmaI2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2095-bp SalI-HindIII PCR fragment amplified from <italic>S. marcescens</italic> SCH909 genomic DNA [primer pair SmaI2-SalI and ant(3&#x02033;)Ii-HindIII] containing the entire group II intron <italic>S.ma</italic>.I2 (1971&#x02009;bp) and the nucleotide sequence up to the initiation codon of the <italic>ant(3&#x02033;)-Ii-aac(6&#x02032;)-IId</italic> gene cassette and cloned into pKK232-8 digested by SalI-HindIII.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pKK-In</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2900-bp SalI-HindIII PCR fragment amplified from <italic>S. marcescens</italic> SCH909 genomic DNA [primer pair IntI1-SalI and ant(3&#x02033;)Ii-HindIII] containing part of <italic>intI1</italic>, the <italic>aadB</italic>::<italic>S.ma</italic>.I2 gene cassette and the nucleotide sequence up to the initiation codon of the <italic>ant(3&#x02033;)Ii-aac(6&#x02032;)-IId</italic> gene cassette and cloned into pKK232-8 digested by SalI-HindIII.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pKK-In&#x00394;SmaI2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clone derived from pKK-In by PCR (primer pair Sm909&#x02013;3947.for and Sm909&#x02013;1507.rev) to remove the group II intron <italic>S.ma</italic>.I2 (&#x02018;Materials and Methods&#x02019; section).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pKK-NeI1-P1out</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">200-bp PCR fragment amplified from <italic>N. europaea</italic> genomic DNA (primer pair NeI1-prom.for and NeI1-prom.rev) containing part of the group II intron <italic>N.e</italic>.I1 (base positions 1&#x02013;200 in <italic>N.e</italic>.I1) and cloned into pKK232-8 digested by SmaI.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pKK-GsI1-P1out</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">200-bp PCR fragment amplified from <italic>G. sulfurreducens</italic> genomic DNA (primer pair GsI1-prom.for and GsI1-prom.rev) containing part of the group II intron <italic>G.s</italic>.I1 (base positions 1&#x02013;200 in <italic>G.s</italic>.I1) and cloned into pKK232-8 digested by SmaI.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pKK-ShbaI2-P1out</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">200-bp PCR fragment amplified from <italic>S. baltica</italic> genomic DNA (primer pair ShbaI2-prom.for and ShbaI2-prom.rev) containing part of the group II intron <italic>Sh.ba</italic>.I2 (base positions 1&#x02013;200 in <italic>Sh.ba</italic>.I2) and cloned into pKK232-8 digested by SmaI.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pKK-SmaI2-P2out</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">383-bp SspI-BglII restriction fragment digested from the pUCSmI plasmid (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>) containing part of the group IIC intron <italic>S.ma</italic>.I2 (base positions 288&#x02013;675 in <italic>S.ma</italic>.I2) and cloned into pKK232-8 digested by SmaI by the TA-cloning method.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pLQ872</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weak Pc promoter from integron In0 (pVS1) cloned in pKK232-8.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pLQ876</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strong Pc promoter from integron In4 (Tn<italic>1696</italic>) cloned in pKK232-8.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pLQ880</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">96-bp HindIII-BamHI fragment of <italic>tac</italic> promoter cloned in pKK232-8.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec><title>Polymerase chain reaction procedures and primers</title><p>We used the Phusion DNA polymerase (Finnzymes) for plasmid assembly and the Biotools DNA polymerase (Biotools) for the 5&#x02032;-RACE, according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. PCR primers IntI-SalI (5&#x02032;-CGCACACCGTCGACACGGATGAAG), aadB-HindIII (5&#x02032;-CTGCCGCAGCTAGAAGCTTGTGTATCAATG), SmaI2-SalI (5&#x02032;-CCGCTTTCAGGTCGACATATGCGG), ant (3&#x02033;) Ii-HindIII (5&#x02032;-AGCTGTACCGAAGCTTCGGCGGGTAC), Sm909&#x02013;3497.for (5&#x02032;-ACAATTCATTCAAGCCGAACCC), Sm909&#x02013;1507.rev (5&#x02032;-TAGGCCGCATATCGCGACC), NeI1-prom.for (5&#x02032;-GTGCGCCCAGCATGGGCGCG), NeI1-prom.rev (5&#x02032;-AGCTCGCCTCGCCTGCCTCG), GsI1-prom.for (5&#x02032;-GTACGCCCGGCATGGGCGTG), GsI1-prom.rev (5&#x02032;-CTGACTTGCCCGGACACCCC), ShbaI2-prom.for (5&#x02032;-GTACGCCCAGCATGGGCATG), ShbaI2-prom.rev (5&#x02032;-ATGAACTTTCTTTGCACTGC), PKKL311 (5&#x02032;-TTCTTTACGATGCGATTG) and POLY(C) (5&#x02032;-CCCCCCCCCCCCCCC) were synthesized using an ABI-3900 DNA Synthesizer from Applied Biosystems Inc. (Foster City, CA, USA).</p></sec><sec><title>Genome project database searches for group IIC-<italic>attC</italic> introns</title><p>A protein&#x02013;protein Basic Local Alignment Search Tool (BLASTP) search was performed on the entire GenBank non redundant protein sequences (nr) using as a query the IEP peptide sequence of group IIC-<italic>attC</italic> intron <italic>S.ma</italic>.I2 from <italic>S. marcescens</italic> (accession no. AF453998).</p></sec><sec><title>Multiple sequence alignments and phylogenetic tree</title><p>Phylogenetic analysis was based on intron RT subdomains and X domains. Bacterial class C IEP sequences from <italic>Azotobacter vinelandii</italic> (accession no. CP001157), <italic>Bacillus halodurans</italic> (BA000004), <italic>Bacteroides thetaiotaomicron</italic> (AE015928), <italic>Burkholderia cenocepacia</italic> (CP000959), <italic>Clostridium acetobutylicum</italic> (AE001437), <italic>Lactobacillus reuteri</italic> (AY911856), <italic>Microscilla sp.</italic> (AF339846), <italic>Oceanobacillus iheyensis</italic> (BA000028), <italic>Pseudomonas alcaligenes</italic> (U77945), <italic>Pseudomonas syringae pv. tomato</italic> (AE016853), <italic>Streptococcus agalactiae</italic> (AJ292930), <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic> (AF030367) and <italic>Symbiobacterium thermophilum</italic> (AP006840) were retrieved from the Mobile group II intron web site (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>). The tree was rooted with IEP sequences from the <italic>Lactococcus lactis</italic> Ll.LtrB (mitochondrial-like; accession no. U50902) and <italic>Sinorhizobium meliloti</italic> RmInt1 (bacterial class D; accession no. Y11597) introns. The compiled IEP peptide sequences were aligned using CLUSTAL W (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>). The resulting multiple sequence alignments were subjected to analyses using the neighbor-joining algorithm, with the Poisson correction distance method, of the Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis (MEGA) package version 4.0 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>). One thousand bootstrap analyses were performed to estimate the robustness of the phylogenetic inference.</p></sec><sec><title>Bioinformatic predictions of internal outward-oriented promoters (P<sub>out</sub>) in group IIC-<italic>attC</italic> introns</title><p>We searched for P<sub>out</sub> in intron sequences, ranging from the 5&#x02032;-end of the intron to the nucleotide opposite the start codon of the ORF encoding the IEP on the bottom strand, using the Neural Network for Promoter Prediction (NNPP) version 2.2 (Berkeley Drosophila Genome Project, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fruitfly.org/index.html">http://www.fruitfly.org/index.html</ext-link>) and BPROM (SoftBerry, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://linux1.softberry.com/berry.phtml">http://linux1.softberry.com/berry.phtml</ext-link>) programs.</p></sec><sec><title>5&#x02032;-rapid amplification of cDNA end</title><p>Transcription initiation sites from the putative P<sub>out</sub> were determined using the 5&#x02032;-rapid amplification of cDNA ends (5&#x02032;-RACE) method as described by Sambrook and Russell (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>). <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> DH5-&#x003b1; competent cells were transformed with the indicated pKK232-8 clone and subjected to Ap selection. One colony of each transformant was cultured in LB medium containing both Ap and Cm at 37&#x000b0;C until the optical density at 600&#x02009;nm was 0.7. Total RNA was purified using the RNeasy Mini Kit (Qiagen). cDNA synthesis was done using the Superscript III reverse transcriptase (200&#x02009;U; Invitrogen) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions and the PKKL311 primer (10&#x02009;&#x000b5;M; reverse primer within <italic>cat</italic>) and incubated for 60&#x02009;min at 50&#x000b0;C. RNase H (5&#x02009;U; NEB) was added to the RT reactions and incubated for 30&#x02009;min at 37&#x000b0;C. cDNA transcripts were purified using the QIAquick PCR Purification Kit (Qiagen). A dG-tail was added to the purified cDNA transcripts using dGTP (100&#x02009;mM; Amersham Biosciences) and terminal transferase (20&#x02009;U; NEB) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. The tailed cDNA transcripts were purified using the QIAquick PCR Purification Kit. PCR amplification of the tailed cDNA was conducted with the PKKL311 and POLY(C) primer pair (10&#x02009;&#x000b5;M each) using Biotools DNA polymerase (2.5&#x02009;U; Biotools) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. In order to find transcription start sites, the PCR products were purified and sequenced using the PKKL311 primer.</p></sec><sec><title>CAT assay</title><p>CAT assays were performed as described by Levesque and collaborators (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>). CAT activity was assayed on crude cell extracts, from <italic>E. coli</italic> DH5-&#x003b1; cells carrying one of the pKK232-8 clones, prepared by sonication in Tris&#x02013;HCl (1&#x02009;mM [pH 7.6]). For each assay a 150&#x02009;&#x000b5;l reaction mix containing 9.6&#x02009;&#x000b5;l of [<sup>14</sup>C]Cm (0.05&#x02009;mCi/ml; PerkinElmer), 24&#x02009;&#x000b5;l of acetyl-coenzyme A (4&#x02009;mM, resuspended in 20&#x02009;mM sodium phosphate buffer [pH 7.0]), 39&#x02009;&#x000b5;l of Tris (1&#x02009;M [pH 7.5]) and 83.4&#x02009;&#x000b5;l of deionized water was prepared. The CAT assay was started by adding 20&#x02009;&#x000b5;l of total protein (1&#x02009;ng/&#x000b5;l) to 130&#x02009;&#x000b5;l of the reaction mix. After 60&#x02009;min incubation at 37&#x000b0;C, the reactions were stopped using 1&#x02009;ml of ethyl acetate and dried. The samples (resuspended in 20&#x02009;&#x000b5;l of ethyl acetate) were spotted onto thin-layer chromatography sheets of silica gel H (Analtech) and run in a chromatography chamber with chloroform:methanol (95:5 v/v) for 60&#x02009;min. Once dry, the silica plate was covered with plastic wrap and processed for phosphorimaging. CAT activity was calculated as the count of acetylated Cm (i.e. the total count of 1-acetoxy-Cm and 3-acetoxy-Cm divided by the sum of acetylated and non-acetylated Cm). We used as negative controls either 20&#x02009;&#x000b5;l of Tris&#x02013;HCl (1&#x02009;mM [pH 7.6]) or 20&#x02009;&#x000b5;l of crude cell extract of <italic>E. coli</italic> DH5-&#x003b1; competent cells transformed with the pKK232-8 plasmid.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>Insertion of <italic>S.ma</italic>.I2 into integron #2 of <italic>Serratia marcescens</italic> SCH909 affects the expression of the following gene cassette</title><p>The integron #2 of <italic>S. marcescens</italic> SCH909 (AF453998) is one of three class 1 multiresistance integrons located on a 60-kb conjugative plasmid (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>). The first cassette contains the <italic>aadB</italic> [also called <italic>ant(2&#x02033;)-Ia</italic>] aminoglycoside resistance gene, separated from its <italic>attC</italic> site by <italic>S.ma</italic>.I2 that inserted into the bottom strand sequence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>B). The <italic>attC</italic> site is followed by the <italic>ant(3&#x02033;)-Ii-aac(6&#x02032;)-IId</italic> aminoglycoside resistance gene cassette. This cassette is followed by an unknown ORF with an <italic>attC</italic> site and a partial gene composed of the beginning of the <italic>bla</italic><sub>OXA-10</sub> cassette interrupted by IS<italic>1</italic>. The sequence downstream of IS<italic>1</italic> revealed that the <italic>bla</italic><sub>OXA-10</sub> gene cassette is incomplete and that the 3&#x02032;-CS segment of this integron is absent. Sequencing of the 5&#x02032;-CS region showed that integron #2 harbors the Pc<sub>weak</sub>-P2 combination of promoters (data not shown). Previous studies showed that in the Pc<sub>weak</sub>-P2 combination, Pc<sub>weak</sub> does not contribute significantly to the expression of gene cassettes, which is mainly driven by P2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>). In order to estimate whether insertion of <italic>S.ma</italic>.I2 affects the expression of the following <italic>ant(3&#x02033;)-Ii-aac(6&#x02032;)-IId</italic> gene cassette, we cloned various DNA fragments from integron #2 into the pKK232-8 plasmid upstream of a <italic>cat</italic> reporter gene. The resulting plasmids pKK-IntI1, pKK-SmaI2, pKK-In and pKK-In&#x00394;SmaI2 (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref> for plasmid descriptions) were used in a quantitative CAT assay to examine expression of <italic>cat</italic> in <italic>E. coli</italic> DH5-&#x003b1; (&#x02018;Materials and Methods&#x02019; section). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref> shows the separation by thin-layer-chromatography of Cm from its derivatives, 1-acetoxy-Cm and 3-acetoxy-Cm, in a 60&#x02009;min assay at 37&#x000b0;C (1,3-diacetoxy-Cm was not detected). In our experimental conditions, we found that expression of <italic>cat</italic> from the clone pKK-In&#x00394;SmaI2 (i.e. in absence of <italic>S.ma</italic>.I2) was about 3.5-fold higher than with the clone pKK-In (27.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.6% and 7.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.5%, respectively) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>). We also found that expression of <italic>cat</italic> from the clone pKK-SmaI2 (i.e. cloned <italic>S.ma</italic>.I2 sequence only) was slightly lower than with the clone pKK-In (6.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.7% and 7.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.5%, respectively). Therefore, our data suggest that insertion of <italic>S.ma</italic>.I2 in integron #2 of <italic>S. marcescens</italic> potentially results in a 72% decrease of expression of the following <italic>ant(3&#x02033;)-Ii-aac(6&#x02032;)-IId</italic> gene cassette. Moreover, a 0.89 relative ratio of acetylated Cm between the pKK-SmaI2 and pKK-In clones suggests that most of <italic>ant(3&#x02033;)-Ii-aac(6&#x02032;)-IId</italic> transcripts comes from a putative outward-oriented promoter (P<sub>out</sub>) within <italic>S.ma</italic>.I2, and that <italic>S.ma</italic>.I2 disrupts transcripts from the Pc<sub>weak</sub>-P2 promoters. Nevertheless, a reverse trancriptase-(RT) assay showed that a small amount of transcription of <italic>cat</italic> from the Pc<sub>weak</sub>-P2 promoters occurs in the presence of <italic>S.ma</italic>.I2 (data not shown). On the other hand, a similar <italic>cat</italic> activity of the pKK-IntI1 and pKK-In&#x00394;SmaI2 clones (28.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.2% and 27.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.6%, respectively) suggests that, unlike <italic>S.ma</italic>.I2, the <italic>aadB</italic> gene cassette does not impede transcription from Pc<sub>weak</sub>-P2.
<fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Thin-layer chromatography of the [<sup>14</sup>C]chloramphenicol (Cm) CAT assay products in order to determine the effect of <italic>S.ma</italic>.I2 insertion in the integron #2 from <italic>S. marcescens</italic>. The pKK232 clones used for this assay are described in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>. The TLC plate was exposed to a Kodak BioMax MR film to obtain this image. CAT activity was assayed as described in &#x02018;Materials and Methods&#x02019; section. (<bold>a</bold>) indicates the origin; (<bold>b</bold>) indicates non-acetylated Cm; (<bold>c</bold>) indicates 1-acetoxy-Cm; (<bold>d</bold>) indicates 3-acetoxy-Cm.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkq709f2"/></fig>
<table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Expression of <italic>cat</italic> reporter gene in <italic>E. coli</italic> from promoter sequences within various cloned DNA fragments from <italic>S. marcescens</italic> SCH909 integron #2</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clone<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1"><sup>a</sup></xref></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA fragments from integron #2 cloned in pKK232-8</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Promoter</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cm acetylated (%)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF2"><sup>b</sup></xref></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ratio relative to pKK-In</th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">None<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF3"><sup>c</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pKK232-8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pKK-IntI1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Partial 5&#x02032;-CS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pc<sub>weak</sub>-P2 in 5&#x02032;-CS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.75</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pKK-In&#x00394;SmaI2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Partial 5&#x02032;-CS + <italic>aadB-attC</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pc<sub>weak</sub>-P2 in 5&#x02032;-CS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.64</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pKK-In</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Partial 5&#x02032;-CS + <italic>aadB</italic>::<italic>S.ma</italic>.I2-<italic>attC</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pc<sub>weak</sub>-P2 in 5&#x02032;-CS + putative P<sub>out</sub> in <italic>S.ma</italic>.I2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pKK-SmaI2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>S.ma</italic>.I2-<italic>attC</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative P<sub>out</sub> in <italic>S.ma</italic>.I2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TF1"><p><sup>a</sup>For detailed information about these clones see <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>.</p></fn><fn id="TF2"><p><sup>b</sup>Means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD of three independent experiments.</p></fn><fn id="TF3"><p><sup>c</sup>Tris&#x02013;HCl (1&#x02009;mM [pH 7.6]) was added to the reaction mix instead of crude cell extracts.</p></fn><fn id="TF4"><p>NA, not applicable</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec><title>Bioinformatic analyses indicate that putative outward-oriented promoters (P<sub>out</sub>) are found in several group IIC-<italic>attC</italic> introns</title><p>We wished to determine whether P<sub>out</sub> also occurs in the <italic>E.c</italic>.I7 (99.8% sequence identity with <italic>S.ma</italic>.I2) and <italic>Kl.pn</italic>.I1 introns that are inserted into the first <italic>attC</italic> site of integron cassette arrays (i.e. between the first cassette and the following cassettes, potentially affecting the expression of the latter) from <italic>E. coli</italic> (accession no. AY785243) and <italic>K. pneumoniae</italic> (AJ971342), respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1B</xref>). We were also interested in knowing whether or not P<sub>out</sub> is a conserved feature within the group IIC-<italic>attC</italic> intron lineage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>). Therefore, we first identified and analyzed several full length group IIC-<italic>attC</italic> introns distributed among 25 distinct bacterial genomes and two marine metagenome projects (&#x02018;Materials and Methods&#x02019; section and <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>). Phylogenetic analysis of intron IEPs confirmed that the introns belonged to bacterial class IIC (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>). Nodes of 100% bootstrap support define the bases of both bacterial IIC and IIC-<italic>attC</italic> lineages. Then, we used the BPROM and NNPP prediction programs for bacterial promoters in order to find putative P<sub>out</sub> (&#x02018;Materials and Methods&#x02019; section). <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref> shows a compilation of putative P<sub>out</sub> (&#x02212;35 region, &#x02212;10 region and the spacing between these regions) that obtained the highest scores from both programs. One or two putative promoters, designated P1<sub>out</sub> and P2<sub>out</sub>, were predicted for most introns, except for the <italic>Desulfurivibrio alkaliphilus</italic> (accession no. ACYL01000013) and <italic>Allochromatium vinosum</italic> (CP001896) introns, for which no promoter was predicted. The putative promoter sequences are generally similar to the <italic>E. coli</italic> consensus promoter, TTGACA-N<sub>16&#x02013;18</sub>-TATAAT (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>). <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref> also shows the positions of P1<sub>out</sub> and P2<sub>out</sub> among the introns. Interestingly, the putative P1<sub>out</sub> and P2<sub>out</sub> are precisely positioned within the ribozyme portion of the introns corresponding to domain I (DI) and domain II (DII), respectively. One exception was observed for the putative P2<sub>out</sub> from the <italic>Candidatus Accumulibacter phosphatis</italic> (accession no. CP001715) intron, which is positioned within domain III (DIII). These results suggest that outward-oriented promoters are general features of group IIC-<italic>attC</italic> introns, rather than being present only in <italic>S.ma</italic>.I2.
<fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Phylogenetic tree for group IIC-<italic>attC</italic> intron IEP amino acid sequences from various organisms. Evolutionary distances were computed using the neighbor-joining algorithm of the MEGA4 software (&#x02018;Materials and Methods&#x02019; section).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkq709f3"/></fig>
<table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Bioinformatic analysis for putative outward-oriented promoters (P<sub>out</sub>) in group IIC-<italic>attC</italic> introns</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Host organism<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF4"><sup>a</sup></xref></th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Accession no. - nucleotide</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">In<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF5"><sup>b</sup></xref></th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Accession no. - protein (IEP)</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">5&#x02032; exon gene<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF6"><sup>c</sup></xref></th><th colspan="5" align="center" rowspan="1">Putative P<sub>out</sub><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF7"><sup>d</sup></xref><hr/></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Name</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;35 region</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spacing</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;10 region</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positions</th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudomonas putida</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AY065966</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAL47550</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>qacE&#x00394;1</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P1<sub>out</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTGCCA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17&#x02009;nt</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TCTAAT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81&#x02013;109 (DI)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Serratia marcescens</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AY030343</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAK40354</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>qacE&#x00394;1</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P2<sub>out</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTGCCT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17&#x02009;nt</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTGCAT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">387&#x02013;415 (DII)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudomanas aeruginosa</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AY029772</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAK50439</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>qacE&#x00394;1</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Acinetobacter</italic> genomospecies</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AF369871</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAK54203</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>qacE&#x00394;1</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Serratia marcescens</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AY884051</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAX16009</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF8"><sup>e</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DQ153218</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAZ82494</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>qacE&#x00394;1</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudomanas aeruginosa</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EF207718</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABN10344</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>qacE&#x00394;1</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic>Salmonella enterica</italic></td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">AM932669</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Y</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">CAP69662</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic>qacE&#x00394;1</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P1<sub>out</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTGCCA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17&#x02009;nt</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TCTAAT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81&#x02013;109 (DI)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P2<sub>out</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTGCCT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17&#x02009;nt</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTGCAT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">387&#x02013;415 (DII)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Marine metagenome</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">EU686596</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Y</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">ND<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF8"><sup>e</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">orf (hypothetical prot.)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P1<sub>out</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTGCCA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17&#x02009;nt</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TCTAAT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80&#x02013;108 (DI)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P2<sub>out</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTACCC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17&#x02009;nt</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TCTCAT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">384&#x02013;412 (DII)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic></td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">AJ971342</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Y</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">CAJ29542</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic>arr2</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P1<sub>out</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTGCCA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17&#x02009;nt</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTGAAT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76&#x02013;104 (DI)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P2<sub>out</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTGCAT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17&#x02009;nt</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GATGAT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">359&#x02013;387 (DII)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Enterobacter cloacae</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GU944727</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADF59072</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF8"><sup>e</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P1<sub>out</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTGCCA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17&#x02009;nt</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTTAAT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76&#x02013;104 (DI)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FJ384365</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACJ76645</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>qacE&#x00394;1</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P2<sub>out</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTGCCC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17&#x02009;nt</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTTCAT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">381&#x02013;409 (DII)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FJ817422</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACO53361</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF8"><sup>e</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Marine metagenome</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">AACY020561240</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">N</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">ND<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF8"><sup>e</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">orf (hypothetical prot.)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P1<sub>out</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTGCCA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17&#x02009;nt</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTTAAT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76&#x02013;104 (DI)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P2<sub>out</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTGCCC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17&#x02009;nt</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTTCAT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">382&#x02013;410 (DII)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Salmonella enterica</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AY204504</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAO46869</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF8"><sup>e</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P1<sub>out</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTGCCA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17&#x02009;nt</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTTAAT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">91&#x02013;119 (DI)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic>Vibrio cholerae</italic></td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">EU116440</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Y</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">ABV21790</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">ND<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF8"><sup>e</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P1<sub>out</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTGCCA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17&#x02009;nt</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTTAAT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76&#x02013;104 (DI)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P2<sub>out</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTGCCC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17&#x02009;nt</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTTCAT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">381&#x02013;409 (DII)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Shewanella baltica</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CP000563</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">YP_001050216</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transcriptional regulator</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P1<sub>out</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTGCCA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17&#x02009;nt</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTTAAT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76&#x02013;104 (DI)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Shewanella putrefaciens</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAWY01000044</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZP_01707545</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Second group II intron</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P2<sub>out</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTACCC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17&#x02009;nt</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTTCAT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">382&#x02013;410 (DII)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Escherichia coli</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AY785243</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAV34200</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>aadA1</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P1<sub>out</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTGCCA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17&#x02009;nt</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTTAAT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77&#x02013;105 (DI)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Serratia marcescens</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AF453998</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAL51020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ant(3&#x02033;)-Ii- aac(6&#x02032;)-IId</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P2<sub>out</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTGAAC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17&#x02009;nt</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TAATCT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">322&#x02013;350 (DII)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Geobacter sulfurreducens</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AE017180</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NP_953517</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>vapC</italic> (NA)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P1<sub>out</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTGCCC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16&#x02009;nt</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TATGCT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">168&#x02013;195 (DI)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Geobacter sp.</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CP001390</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">YP_002536457</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">orf (hypothetical prot.)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P1<sub>out</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTGCCT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17&#x02009;nt</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TACGCT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74&#x02013;102 (DI)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Desulfurivibrio alkaliphilus</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACYL01000013</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZP_05710592</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NADH:flavin oxidoreductase/NADH oxidase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">none predicted</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic>Nitrosomonas europaea</italic></td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">AL954747</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Y</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">NP_842195</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic>ampG</italic> (NA)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P1<sub>out</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTGCCC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18&#x02009;nt</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TATACT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77&#x02013;106 (DI)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P2<sub>out</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTGCCA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16&#x02009;nt</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TCTGAT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">409&#x02013;435 (DII)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Candidatus Methylomirabilis oxyfera</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FP565575</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBE67152</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">orf (hypothetical prot.)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P1<sub>out</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTGCCT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17&#x02009;nt</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TCACAT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66&#x02013;94 (DI)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Allochromatium vinosum</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CP001896</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">YP_003442808</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">orf (hypothetical prot.)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">none predicted</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic>Candidatus Accumulibacter phosphatis</italic></td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">CP001715</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Y</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">ACV35120</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">orf (hypothetical prot.)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P1<sub>out</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTGCCC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18&#x02009;nt</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TATCAT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77&#x02013;106 (DI)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P2<sub>out</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTCGCG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17&#x02009;nt</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TACTAT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">468&#x02013;496 (DIII)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TF5"><p><sup>a</sup>Host organisms with identical introns were grouped together according to phylogenetic analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>).</p></fn><fn id="TF6"><p><sup>b</sup>This column indicates which introns are inserted (Y) or not inserted (N) into an integron cassette array.</p></fn><fn id="TF7"><p><sup>c</sup>Gene or gene cassette divergent with the intron IEP, and downstream of putative P<sub>out</sub>. NA, (not applicable) was indicated when the 5&#x02032;-exon ORF is convergent with the intron sequence.</p></fn><fn id="TF8"><p><sup>d</sup>Outward-oriented promoters predicted using the BPROM and NNPP programs. Positions of promoter extremities (beginning of the &#x02212;35 hexamer sequence&#x02014;end of the &#x02212;10 hexamer sequence) are indicated for the complementary strand. Domain I (DI), domain II (DII), or domain III (DIII) was indicated based on secondary structure analysis of intron RNA (data not shown) using the MFOLD program (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">54</xref>) and the consensus RNA secondary structure for group IIC introns (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>).</p></fn><fn id="TF9"><p><sup>e</sup>ND, not defined in databases.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p>In order to see whether putative P<sub>out</sub> with different versions of the &#x02212;35 and &#x02212;10 sequences are functionally active <italic>in vivo</italic>, the P1<sub>out</sub> sequences from the <italic>Nitrosomonas europaea</italic> intron <italic>N.e</italic>.I1 (accession no. AL954747), the <italic>Geobacter sulfurreducens</italic> intron <italic>G.s</italic>.I1 (AE017180) and the <italic>Shewanella baltica</italic> intron <italic>Sh.ba</italic>.I2 (CP000563) and the P2<sub>out</sub> sequence from <italic>S.ma</italic>.I2 were cloned upstream of a promoterless <italic>cat</italic> reporter gene in the pKK232-8 plasmid (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). For most introns, we cloned P1<sub>out</sub> rather than P2<sub>out</sub> because they are closer to exon 1 and are more similar to the consensus sequence. However, for <italic>S.ma</italic>.I2, we cloned P2<sub>out</sub> since it is closer to the consensus promoter and potentially involved in expression of the following gene cassettes. Transformation of any of the four pKK232-8 clones (i.e. pKK-NeI1-P1out, pKK-GsI1-P1out, pKK-ShbaI2-P1out or pKK-SmaI2-P2out) into competent <italic>E. coli</italic> DH5-&#x003b1; cells conferred resistance to Cm (32&#x02009;&#x000b5;g/ml) because of CAT activity, whereas <italic>E. coli</italic> DH5-&#x003b1; cells transformed with the original pKK232-8 plasmid were sensitive to the same concentration of Cm (data not shown). Therefore, transcription of <italic>cat</italic> occurred from a promoter within the cloned intron sequence that is functionally active in <italic>E. coli</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>Identification of promoter elements and transcription start sites of <italic>cat</italic> within the pKK232-8-based clones</title><p>In order to determine whether transcription of <italic>cat</italic> originated from the predicted P<sub>out</sub>, we used the 5&#x02032;-RACE method (&#x02018;Materials and Methods&#x02019; section). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref> shows an agarose gel containing specific 5&#x02032;-RACE&#x02013;PCR products for the identified clones using the PKKL311 (antisense primer in the <italic>cat</italic> gene) and POLY(C) primers. In order to find the transcription start sites, the four 5&#x02032;-RACE&#x02013;PCR products were sequenced using the PKKL311 primer. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref> shows an alignment of the sequenced 5&#x02032;-RACE&#x02013;PCR products (reversed and complemented) with the cloned intron sequences. Each alignment shows the &#x02212;35 and &#x02212;10 regions of a promoter in the intron bottom-strand sequence and the transcription start site. Comparison of the &#x02212;35 and &#x02212;10 regions from the 5&#x02032;-RACE data to those predicted using the BPROM and NNPP programs showed that both programs successfully identified either P1<sub>out</sub> or P2<sub>out</sub>, except for the <italic>G.s</italic>.I1 intron (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>). In fact, according to the 5&#x02032;-RACE data the functionally active P1<sub>out</sub> sequence in <italic>G.s</italic>.I1 is TTGCCG-N<sub>16</sub>-TACCCT (positions 73&#x02013;100 on the complementary strand). This sequence is located within the average range (i.e. 77&#x02013;105&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5) for putative P1<sub>out</sub> predicted in other intron sequences. We also show that P1<sub>out</sub> sequences found in both <italic>Sh.ba</italic>.I2 and <italic>S.ma</italic>.I2 introns (64% sequence identity) and the P2<sub>out</sub> found in <italic>S.ma</italic>.I2 (cloned in pKK-ShbaI2-P1out and pKK-SmaI2-P2out, respectively) are functionally active in <italic>E. coli</italic>. Therefore, in our experimental conditions, <italic>S.ma</italic>.I2 contains two functionally active P<sub>out</sub>.
<fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Agarose gel (2%) of the 5&#x02032;-RACE-PCR products. 5&#x02032;-RACE assays were performed as described in &#x02018;Materials and Methods&#x02019; section in order to find the transcription initiation site of <italic>cat</italic> in the indicated pKK232 clones (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref> for description).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkq709f4"/></fig>
<fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Alignments of the 5&#x02032;-RACE product sequences with their corresponding intron DNA sequences. ts and bs indicate the top strand and bottom strand sequences; &#x02212;35 and &#x02212;10, components of the promoter. +1, transcription initiation site. Reversed and complemented 5&#x02032;-RACE sequences are indicated (asterisks).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkq709f5"/></fig></p></sec><sec><title>Analysis of P<sub>out</sub> activity by comparison with that of the <italic>tac</italic> and integron promoters</title><p>In order to determine the relative strength of the four functionally active P<sub>out</sub> identified using the 5&#x02032;-RACE method, we used a quantitative CAT assay. We compared their relative efficiency to that of the <italic>tac</italic> promoter (TTGACA-N<sub>16</sub>-TATAAT) and the weak and strong versions of integron Pc promoter (Pc<sub>weak</sub> TGGACA-N<sub>17</sub>-TAAGCT and Pc<sub>strong</sub> TTGACA-N<sub>17</sub>-TAAACT, respectively) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref> shows the separation by thin-layer-chromatography of Cm from it derivatives, 1-acetoxy-Cm and 3-acetoxy-Cm, from a 60&#x02009;min assay at 37&#x000b0;C (1,3-diacetoxy-Cm was not detected). <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">Table 4</xref> shows the percentage of acetylated Cm for each version of P<sub>out</sub>. The most active intron promoters are <italic>S.ma.</italic>I2 P2<sub>out</sub> and <italic>N.e.</italic>I1 P1<sub>out</sub>. Transcription of <italic>cat</italic> using these promoters resulted in 6.65&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.68% and 6.15&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.88% of acetylated Cm, respectively (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>). The percentages of Cm acetylated using the Pc<sub>strong</sub> (36.83&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.42%) and <italic>tac</italic> (15.41&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.74%) promoters are respectively &#x0003e;5-fold and 2-fold higher than using either <italic>S.ma.</italic>I2 P2<sub>out</sub> or <italic>N.e.</italic>I1 P1<sub>out</sub>. However, expression of CAT using either <italic>S.ma.</italic>I2 P2<sub>out</sub> or <italic>N.e.</italic>I1 P1<sub>out</sub> was &#x0003e;5-fold higher than using the Pc<sub>weak</sub> (1.10&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.09%) promoter. In the same experimental conditions, expression of CAT using the <italic>Sh.ba</italic>.I2 P1<sub>out</sub> (identical to the <italic>S.ma</italic>.I2 P1<sub>out</sub>) is less than half that of <italic>S.ma</italic>.I2 P2<sub>out</sub>, but more than twice that of Pc<sub>weak</sub>. Finally, expression of CAT using the <italic>G.s</italic>.I1 P1<sub>out</sub> promoter resulted in the weakest level of acetylated Cm, 0.58&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.06%, which is less than half that of the Pc<sub>weak</sub> promoter.
<fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Thin-layer chromatography of the [<sup>14</sup>C]chloramphenicol (Cm) CAT assay products for determination of the relative strengths of group IIC-<italic>attC</italic> intron promoters (P<sub>out</sub>). The TLC plate was exposed to a Kodak BioMax MR film to obtain this image. CAT activity was assayed as described in &#x02018;Materials and Methods&#x02019; section. The pKK232 clones used for this assay are described in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>. pLQ872 and pLQ876 contain the weak and strong versions of integron Pc promoters (respectively) cloned into pKK232-8 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>). (<bold>a</bold>) indicates the origin; (<bold>b</bold>) indicates non-acetylated Cm; (<bold>c</bold>) indicates 1-acetoxy-Cm; (<bold>d</bold>) indicates 3-acetoxy-Cm.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkq709f6"/></fig>
<table-wrap id="T4" position="float"><label>Table 4.</label><caption><p>Relative strengths of group IIC-<italic>attC</italic> intron promoters (P<sub>out</sub>) compared with the <italic>tac</italic> and the weak and strong versions of integron Pc promoters</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clone<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF9"><italic><sup>a</sup></italic></xref></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Promoter</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cm acetylated (%)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF10"><sup>b</sup></xref></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ratio relative to <italic>tac</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><sub>&#x02013;</sub><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF11"><sup>c</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF12"><sup>d</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pKK232-8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pKK-SmaI2-P2out</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P2<sub>out</sub><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF13"><sup>e</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.65&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.68</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pKK-NeI1-P1out</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P1<sub>out</sub><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF13"><sup>e</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.15&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.88</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pKK-ShbaI2-P1out</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P1<sub>out</sub><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF13"><sup>e</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.99&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pKK-GsI1-P1out</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P1<sub>out</sub><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF13"><sup>e</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pLQ872</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pc<sub>weak</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pLQ876</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pc<sub>strong</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.83&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.40</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pLQ880</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>tac</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.41&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TF10"><p><sup>a</sup>For detailed information about these clones see <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>.</p></fn><fn id="TF11"><p><sup>b</sup>Means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD of three independent experiments.</p></fn><fn id="TF12"><p><sup>c</sup>Tris&#x02013;HCl (1&#x02009;mM [pH 7.6]) was added to the reaction mix instead of crude cell extracts.</p></fn><fn id="TF13"><p><sup>d</sup>NA, not applicable.</p></fn><fn id="TF14"><p><sup>e</sup>P<sub>out</sub> shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>In this study, we show that <italic>S.ma</italic>.I2, a group IIC-<italic>attC</italic> intron inserted in an integron cassette array of <italic>S. marcescens</italic>, impedes transcription from the Pc<sub>weak</sub>-P2 promoters located within the 5&#x02032;-CS region, while allowing expression of the following antibiotic resistance cassette using two internal outward-oriented promoters (P<sub>out</sub>). Despite these promoters, insertion of <italic>S.ma</italic>.I2 into integron #2 of <italic>S. marcescens</italic> potentially results in a 72% decrease of expression of the following <italic>ant(3&#x02033;)-Ii-aac(6&#x02032;)-IId</italic> gene cassette. Bioinformatic analyses of group IIC-<italic>attC</italic> introns from 25 distinct bacterial genomes and two marine metagenome projects indicate that one or two putative P<sub>out</sub> are also found in other introns. These promoters, designated P1<sub>out</sub> and P2<sub>out</sub>, are located at similar distances from their exon 1 in RNA domain I and domain II, respectively. Comparison of promoter sequences with the consensus RNA structure/sequence for group IIC introns (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>) showed that P<sub>out</sub> are located within the region of variable sequences (data not shown). Our data suggest that P<sub>out</sub> are conserved features of the group IIC-<italic>attC</italic> lineage. A distinct inward-directed internal promoter within the <italic>Lactococcus lactis</italic> intron, Ll.ltrB, was identified upstream of the gene for the IEP (LtrA) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>). Mutation of this promoter reduced the steady-state level of <italic>ltrA</italic> mRNA, LtrA, intron splicing and conjugation in <italic>L. lactis</italic>. A functional inward-directed promoter (tested in <italic>E. coli</italic>) was also found in <italic>S.ma</italic>.I2, CCTACA-N<sub>16</sub>-TAAACA (positions 375&#x02013;402 in <italic>S.ma</italic>.I2), upstream of the gene for the IEP (Smtr) (data not shown). We show that P<sub>out</sub> with different versions of the &#x02212;35 and &#x02212;10 sequences are functionally active in expressing a promoterless <italic>cat</italic> reporter gene in <italic>E. coli</italic>. These results are consistent considering that a consensus sequence of all the putative P<sub>out</sub> has a strong similarity with the <italic>E. coli</italic> consensus promoter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>). The quantitative data obtained for the tested P<sub>out</sub> sequences indicate that, despite their heterologous origins, these promoters work well in <italic>E. coli</italic>. On the other hand, GsI1-P1out and ShbaI2-P1out, which showed weak activity in <italic>E. coli</italic>, may have greater activities in their respective hosts, i.e. <italic>G. sulfurreducens</italic> (<italic>Delta</italic>-proteobacteria) and <italic>S. baltica</italic> (<italic>Gamma</italic>-proteobacteria), respectively.</p><p>Integrons can express multiple gene cassettes via read-through transcription from Pc to at least some extent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>). While the <italic>aadB</italic> gene cassette does not block transcription from Pc<sub>weak</sub>-P2, we showed that <italic>S.ma</italic>.I2 impedes transcription, most probably due to secondary structure within the intron. P<sub>out</sub> may therefore confer a selective advantage to inserted group IIC-<italic>attC</italic> introns by ensuring transcription of following gene cassettes. For instance, P<sub>out</sub> in the <italic>S.ma</italic>.I2 and <italic>E.c.</italic>I7 introns may play a role in the expression of the following <italic>ant(3&#x02033;)-Ii-aac(6&#x02032;)-IId</italic> and <italic>aadA1</italic> resistance genes whose transcription from Pc would be reduced by insertion of the intron (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>B). A P<sub>out</sub> in group IIC-<italic>attC</italic> introns may also ensure maintenance of the introns in integrons and their dissemination to other organisms.</p><p>Despite the potential selective advantages conferred by P<sub>out</sub> and specificity for <italic>attC</italic> site motifs, it is perplexing that only a few introns are found in either mobile or chromosomal integrons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>). We have previously demonstrated that the <italic>S.ma.</italic>I2 intron is not transcribed in the <italic>S. marcescens</italic> strain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>), suggesting that the insertion of group IIC-<italic>attC</italic> introns into the antisense strand relative to cassette transcription limits mobility of the intron to other <italic>attC</italic> sites.</p><p>The 3&#x02032;-CS segment of class 1 integrons usually contains a partially functional intercalating dyes/quaternary ammonium compound resistance gene (<italic>qacE&#x00394;1</italic>) and most also contain a sulfonamide resistance gene (<italic>sul1</italic>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>A). Although transcription of both genes, from either the Pc promoter or a promoter of their own, was shown (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>), we suggest that bacteria with class 1 integrons may use an additional source of transcription for the <italic>qacE&#x00394;1</italic> and <italic>sul1</italic> genes as a selective advantage in order to survive in the presence of intercalating dyes, low levels of quaternary ammonium compounds or sulfonamide. In this regard, the P<sub>out</sub> of group IIC-<italic>attC</italic> introns that are inserted into the last <italic>attC</italic> site of cassette arrays may contribute to the survival of the strain by potentially ensuring an enhanced transcription to <italic>qacE&#x00394;1</italic> and <italic>sul1</italic> genes. It has been shown that selection by quaternary ammonium compounds and sulfonamide in natural or clinical environments has the potential to coselect for multidrug resistance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48 B49 B50 B51">48&#x02013;51</xref>).</p><p>Mobile IS from the IS<italic>1111</italic> family, named ISPa21 and ISPst6, also target the <italic>attC</italic> sites of integron cassette arrays (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>). Phylogenetic analyses of transposase sequences has revealed that ISPa21, ISPst6 and ISPst6-related sequences constitute a monophyletic subset within the IS<italic>1111</italic> family, which is associated with <italic>attC</italic> sites (i.e. the IS<italic>1111-attC</italic> subgroup) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>). Interestingly, as with group IIC-<italic>attC</italic> introns, IS elements found in integrons are inserted near the 5&#x02032;-end of distinct <italic>attC</italic> site motifs and into the antisense strand with respect to the gene cassette array transcription. A putative P<sub>out</sub> was also suggested in both ISPa21 and ISPst6 elements. However, activity of such a promoter was either not reported (for ISPa21) or negative (for ISPst6) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>). Therefore, unlike IS elements, insertion of group IIC-<italic>attC</italic> into gene cassettes is more likely advantageous.</p><p>Analysis of the unique mobility pathway and distribution of group IIC-<italic>attC</italic> introns has shown that several factors potentially influence their presence and dissemination in bacterial genomes. The exact role of group IIC-<italic>attC</italic> introns in bacteria and especially in integrons remains undetermined. However, the unique features of integron cassettes suggest that these introns may play a role in cassette formation by recruiting and then joining genes and <italic>attC</italic> sites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>FUNDING</title><p>Fellowship from Canadian Institutes of Health Research (CIHR); Strategic Training Initiatives in Health Research (STIHR) grant STP-59324 (to G.L.); C.O.N.I.C.E.T. fellowship (to C.Q.); Canadian Institutes of Health Research grant MT-13564 (to P.H.R.). Funding for open access charges: Personal Funds.</p><p><italic>Conflict of interest statement</italic>. None declared.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title><p>D.C. is a member of the Carrera del Investigador Cient&#x000ed;fico, Consejo Nacional de Investigaciones Cient&#x000ed;ficas y T&#x000e9;cnicas (C.O.N.I.C.E.T.), Argentina.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>L&#x000e9;vesque</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Brassard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lapointe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diversity and relative strength of tandem promoters for the antibiotic-resistance genes of several integrons</article-title><source>Gene</source><year>1994</year><volume>142</volume><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8181756</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ouellette</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bissonnette</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Precise insertion of antibiotic resistance determinants into Tn<italic>21</italic>-like transposons: nucleotide sequence of the OXA-1 beta-lactamase gene</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>1987</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>7378</fpage><lpage>7382</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2823258</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stokes</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A novel family of potentially mobile DNA elements encoding site-specific gene-integration functions: integrons</article-title><source>Mol. Microbiol.</source><year>1989</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>1669</fpage><lpage>1683</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2560119</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Brookes</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Stokes</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Site-specific insertion of genes into integrons: role of the 59-base element and determination of the recombination cross-over point</article-title><source>Mol. Microbiol.</source><year>1991</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>1941</fpage><lpage>1959</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1662753</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boucher</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Labbate</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Koenig</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Stokes</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Integrons: mobilizable platforms that promote genetic diversity in bacteria</article-title><source>Trends Microbiol.</source><year>2007</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>301</fpage><lpage>309</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17566739</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mazel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Integrons: agents of bacterial evolution</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Microbiol.</source><year>2006</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>608</fpage><lpage>620</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16845431</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mobile gene cassettes and integrons: moving antibiotic resistance genes in gram-negative bacteria</article-title><source>Ciba Found. Symp.</source><year>1997</year><volume>207</volume><fpage>192</fpage><lpage>202</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9189642</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bissonnette</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of In0 of <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> plasmid pVS1, an ancestor of integrons of multiresistance plasmids and transposons of gram-negative bacteria</article-title><source>J. Bacteriol.</source><year>1992</year><volume>174</volume><fpage>1248</fpage><lpage>1257</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1310501</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paulsen</surname><given-names>IT</given-names></name><name><surname>Littlejohn</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><name><surname>R&#x000e5;dstr&#x000f6;m</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sundstr&#x000f6;m</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sk&#x000f6;ld</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Swedberg</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Skurray</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The 3&#x02032; conserved segment of integrons contains a gene associated with multidrug resistance to antiseptics and disinfectants</article-title><source>Antimicrob. Agents Chemother.</source><year>1993</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>761</fpage><lpage>768</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8494372</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fluit</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmitz</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Class 1 integrons, gene cassettes, mobility, and epidemiology</article-title><source>Eur. J. Clin. Microbiol. Infect. Dis.</source><year>1999</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>761</fpage><lpage>770</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10614949</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fluit</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmitz</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Resistance integrons and super-integrons</article-title><source>Clin. Microbiol. Infect.</source><year>2004</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>272</fpage><lpage>288</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15059115</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Partridge</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsafnat</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Coiera</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Iredell</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gene cassettes and cassette arrays in mobile resistance integrons</article-title><source>FEMS Microbiol. Rev.</source><year>2009</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>757</fpage><lpage>784</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19416365</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Collis</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression of antibiotic resistance genes in the integrated cassettes of integrons</article-title><source>Antimicrob. Agents Chemother.</source><year>1995</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>155</fpage><lpage>162</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7695299</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jov&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Da Re</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Denis</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ploy</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inverse correlation between promoter strength and excision activity in class 1 integrons</article-title><source>PLoS Genet.</source><year>2010</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>e1000793</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20066027</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><name><surname>N&#x000fc;cken</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Henschke</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nucleotide sequence analysis of 2&#x02032;&#x02032;-aminoglycoside nucleotidyl-transferase ANT(2&#x02032;&#x02032;) from Tn<italic>4000</italic>: its relationship with AAD(3&#x02032;&#x02032;) and impact on Tn<italic>21</italic> evolution</article-title><source>Mol. Microbiol.</source><year>1988</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>709</fpage><lpage>717</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2850441</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tenover</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name><name><surname>Filpula</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Plorde</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cloning and sequencing of a gene encoding an aminoglycoside 6&#x02032;-N-acetyltransferase from an R factor of <italic>Citrobacter diversus</italic></article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>1988</year><volume>170</volume><fpage>471</fpage><lpage>473</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2826403</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Papagiannitsis</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Tzouvelekis</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Miriagou</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relative strengths of the class 1 integron promoter hybrid 2 and the combinations of strong and hybrid 1 with an active P2 promoter</article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>2009</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>277</fpage><lpage>280</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19001114</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bissonnette</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Champetier</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Buisson</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of the nonenzymatic chloramphenicol resistance (<italic>cmlA</italic>) gene of the In<italic>4</italic> integron of Tn<italic>1696</italic>: similarity of the product to transmembrane transport proteins</article-title><source>J. Bacteriol.</source><year>1991</year><volume>173</volume><fpage>4493</fpage><lpage>4502</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1648560</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stokes</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sequence analysis of the inducible chloramphenicol resistance determinant in the Tn<italic>1696</italic> integron suggests regulation by translational attenuation</article-title><source>Plasmid</source><year>1991</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>10</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1658833</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Centr&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Presence of a group II intron in a multiresistant <italic>Serratia marcescens</italic> strain that harbors three integrons and a novel gene fusion</article-title><source>Antimicrob. Agents Chemother.</source><year>2002</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>1402</fpage><lpage>1409</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11959575</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Poirel</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Brinas</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Fortineau</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Nordmann</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Integron-encoded GES-type extended-spectrum beta-lactamase with increased activity toward aztreonam in <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic></article-title><source>Antimicrob. Agents Chemother.</source><year>2005</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>3593</fpage><lpage>3597</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16048994</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beauregard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Curcio</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Belfort</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The take and give between retrotransposable elements and their hosts</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Genet.</source><year>2008</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>587</fpage><lpage>617</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18680436</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimmerly</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Compilation and analysis of group II intron insertions in bacterial genomes: evidence for retroelement behavior</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2002</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>1091</fpage><lpage>1102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11861899</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Toro</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bacteria and Archaea group II introns: additional mobile genetic elements in the environment</article-title><source>Environ. Microbiol.</source><year>2003</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>143</fpage><lpage>151</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12588294</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bonen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The ins and outs of group II introns</article-title><source>Trends Genet.</source><year>2001</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>322</fpage><lpage>331</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11377794</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Michel</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferat</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure and activities of group II introns</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Biochem.</source><year>1995</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>435</fpage><lpage>461</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7574489</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pyle</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lambowitz</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Gesteland</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Cech</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Atkins</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Group II introns: ribozymes that splice RNA and invade DNA</article-title><source>The RNA World</source><year>2006</year><edition>3rd edn</edition><publisher-loc>Cold Spring Harbor, NY</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press</publisher-name><fpage>469</fpage><lpage>505</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>McNeil</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Pantuso</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Chai</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimmerly</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Group II introns in Eubacteria and Archaea: ORF-less introns and new varieties</article-title><source>RNA</source><year>2008</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>1704</fpage><lpage>1713</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18676618</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelchner</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimmerly</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A broadscale phylogenetic analysis of group II intron RNAs and intron-encoded reverse transcriptases</article-title><source>Mol. Biol. Evol.</source><year>2009</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>2795</fpage><lpage>2808</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19713327</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zimmerly</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hausner</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phylogenetic relationships among group II intron ORFs</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2001</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>1238</fpage><lpage>1250</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11222775</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Granlund</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Michel</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Norgren</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mutually exclusive distribution of IS<italic>1548</italic> and GBSi1, an active group II intron identified in human isolates of group B streptococci</article-title><source>J. Bacteriol.</source><year>2001</year><volume>183</volume><fpage>2560</fpage><lpage>2569</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11274116</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quiroga</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Centr&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Using genomic data to determine the diversity and distribution of target site motifs recognized by class C-<italic>attC</italic> group II introns</article-title><source>J. Mol. Evol.</source><year>2009</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>539</fpage><lpage>549</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19449055</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robart</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimmerly</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Insertion of group II intron retroelements after intrinsic transcriptional terminators</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2007</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>6620</fpage><lpage>6625</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17420455</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Podar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>VT</given-names></name><name><surname>Pyle</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Perlman</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Group II intron splicing <italic>in vivo</italic> by first-step hydrolysis</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1998</year><volume>391</volume><fpage>915</fpage><lpage>918</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9495347</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Toor</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hausner</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimmerly</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coevolution of group II intron RNA structures with their intron-encoded reverse transcriptases</article-title><source>RNA</source><year>2001</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1142</fpage><lpage>1152</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11497432</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quiroga</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Centr&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The <italic>S.ma.</italic>I2 class C group II intron inserts at integron <italic>attC</italic> sites</article-title><source>Microbiology</source><year>2008</year><volume>154</volume><fpage>1341</fpage><lpage>1353</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18451043</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>L&#x000e9;on</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Potential role of group IIC-<italic>attC</italic> introns in integron cassette formation</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>2009</year><volume>191</volume><fpage>6040</fpage><lpage>6051</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19633079</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>L&#x000e9;on</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Excision and integration of cassettes by an integron integrase of <italic>Nitrosomonas europaea</italic></article-title><source>J. Bacteriol.</source><year>2003</year><volume>185</volume><fpage>2036</fpage><lpage>2041</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12618471</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sambrook</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><source>Molecular Cloning: A Laboratory Manual</source><year>2001</year><edition>3rd edn</edition><publisher-loc>Cold Spring Harbor, NY</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Toor</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Keeping</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimmerly</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Database for mobile group II introns</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2003</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>424</fpage><lpage>426</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12520040</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CLUSTAL W: improving the sensitivity of progressive multiple sequence alignment through sequence weighting, position-specific gap penalties and weight matrix choice</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>1994</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>4673</fpage><lpage>4680</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7984417</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Dudley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MEGA4: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis (MEGA) software version 4.0</article-title><source>Mol. Biol. Evol.</source><year>2007</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>1596</fpage><lpage>1599</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17488738</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harley</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of <italic>E. coli</italic> promoter sequences</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>1987</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>2343</fpage><lpage>2361</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3550697</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Manias</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunny</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of intron function: efficient splicing <italic>in vivo</italic> of a bacterial group II intron requires a functional promoter within the intron</article-title><source>Mol. Microbiol.</source><year>2000</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>639</fpage><lpage>651</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10931357</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jacquier</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaoui</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanson-le Pors</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bercot</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Translation regulation of integrons gene cassette expression by the <italic>attC</italic> sites</article-title><source>Mol. Microbiol.</source><year>2009</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>1475</fpage><lpage>1486</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19486293</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sundstr&#x000f6;m</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>R&#x000e5;dstr&#x000f6;m</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Swedberg</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Sk&#x000f6;ld</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Site-specific recombination promotes linkage between trimethoprim- and sulfonamide resistance genes. Sequence characterization of <italic>dhfrV</italic> and <italic>sulI</italic> and a recombination active locus of Tn<italic>21</italic></article-title><source>Mol Gen Genet</source><year>1988</year><volume>213</volume><fpage>191</fpage><lpage>201</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3054482</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guerineau</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Mullineaux</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression of the sulfonamide resistance gene from plasmid R46</article-title><source>Plasmid</source><year>1990</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2190244</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Antunes</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Machado</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sousa</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Peixe</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dissemination of sulfonamide resistance genes (<italic>sul1</italic>, <italic>sul2</italic>, and <italic>sul3</italic>) in Portuguese <italic>Salmonella enterica</italic> strains and relation with integrons</article-title><source>Antimicrob. Agents Chemother.</source><year>2005</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>836</fpage><lpage>839</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15673783</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gaze</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdouslam</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawkey</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wellington</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Incidence of class 1 integrons in a quaternary ammonium compound-polluted environment</article-title><source>Antimicrob. Agents Chemother.</source><year>2005</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>1802</fpage><lpage>1807</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15855499</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kazama</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamashima</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasatsu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Arai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distribution of the antiseptic-resistance genes <italic>qacE</italic> and <italic>qacE</italic>&#x00394;<italic>1</italic> in gram-negative bacteria</article-title><source>FEMS Microbiol. Lett.</source><year>1998</year><volume>159</volume><fpage>173</fpage><lpage>178</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9503610</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>R&#x000e5;dstr&#x000f6;m</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Swedberg</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Sk&#x000f6;ld</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic analyses of sulfonamide resistance and its dissemination in gram-negative bacteria illustrate new aspects of R plasmid evolution</article-title><source>Antimicrob. Agents Chemother.</source><year>1991</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>1840</fpage><lpage>1848</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1952855</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tetu</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A family of insertion sequences that impacts integrons by specific targeting of gene cassette recombination sites, the IS<italic>1111</italic>-<italic>attC</italic> group</article-title><source>J. Bacteriol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>190</volume><fpage>4959</fpage><lpage>4970</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18487340</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brosius</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plasmid vectors for the selection of promoters</article-title><source>Gene</source><year>1984</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>151</fpage><lpage>160</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6327464</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zuker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mfold web server for nucleic acid folding and hybridization prediction</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2003</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>3406</fpage><lpage>3415</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12824337</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>