<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nar</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">nar</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">20702421</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2965260</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkq708</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">gkq708</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Methods Online</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Selection systems based on dominant-negative transcription factors for precise genetic engineering</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dutoit</surname><given-names>Rapha&#x000eb;l</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dubois</surname><given-names>Evelyne</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>Eric</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="AFF1"><sup>1</sup>Institut de Recherches Microbiologiques JM Wiame and <sup>2</sup>Laboratoire de Microbiologie de l&#x02019;Universit&#x000e9; Libre de Bruxelles, 1 avenue Emile Gryson, BE1070 Belgium</aff><author-notes><corresp id="COR1">*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: <phone>+ 322 526 7279</phone>; Fax: <fax>+322 526 7273</fax>; Email: <email>rdutoit@ulb.ac.be</email></corresp><corresp>Correspondence may also be addressed to Eric Jacobs. Tel: <phone>+33 681 53 43 88</phone>; Email: <email>eric.jacobs@ulb.ac.be</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>10</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>11</day><month>8</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>11</day><month>8</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>38</volume><issue>19</issue><fpage>e183</fpage><lpage>e183</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>5</day><month>1</month><year>2010</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>26</day><month>7</month><year>2010</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>7</month><year>2010</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2010. Published by Oxford University Press.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2010</copyright-year><license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Diverse tools are available for performing genetic modifications of microorganisms. However, new methods still need to be developed for performing precise genomic engineering without introducing any undesirable side-alteration. Indeed for functional analyses of genomic elements, as well as for some industrial applications, only the desired mutation should be introduced at the locus considered. This article describes a new approach fulfilling these requirements, based on the use of selection systems consisting in truncated genes encoding dominant-negative transcription factors. We have demonstrated dominant-negative effects mediated by truncated Gal4p and Arg81p proteins in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>, interfering with galactose and arginine metabolic pathways, respectively. These genes can be used as positive and negative markers, since they provoke both growth inhibition on substrates and resistance to specific drugs. These selection markers have been successfully used for precisely deleting <italic>HO</italic> and <italic>URA3</italic> in wild yeasts. This genetic engineering approach could be extended to other microorganisms.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>In the past decades, various systems have been established for genetic engineering of prototroph microorganisms, including wild yeasts. Powerful tools have been developed, in first instance using <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>, in the context of the collaborative genome sequencing and functional analysis projects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1 B2 B3">1&#x02013;3</xref>). Classically, the first step consists in selecting linear vector integration by homologous recombination at the target locus. Then, internal vector elements are removed by homologous recombination between appropriately designed, directly repeated, flanking sequences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>). To perform genomic modifications in prototroph yeasts dominant selective markers leading to drug resistance are available, such as <italic>neo</italic>, which confers resistance to G418 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>), but convenient negative selection systems for subsequent elimination of vector sequences remained to be developed. Indeed, excision of the selectable marker spontaneously occurs by recombination between short directly repeated flanking sequences, but its frequency is very low (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>). Therefore, genes encoding specific recombinases have been additionally used, together with specific pairs of target sequences included in the integrative vectors, which allowed increasing the homologous recombination frequency (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>). Then, only a short piece of foreign DNA including the recombinase recognition sequence remains at the modified locus. However, for genetic engineering of various functional elements, but also for several applications involving industrial strains, vector excision leading to the elimination of all foreign DNA sequences is desired. Such requirements exclude the use of systems involving specific recombinases. Some years ago, Akada <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>) and Olesen <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>) developed a counter-selection method for vector recycling in <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> based on conditioned over-expression of two particular genes (<italic>GIN11</italic> and <italic>PKA3</italic>) encoding proteins which cause lethality when overproduced (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>). These systems, combined with a positive marker, were successfully used in some industrial strains (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9 B10 B11">9&#x02013;11</xref>). However, they need to be adapted according to the behavior of a conditional promoter but also to the potency of the particular growth-inhibitory protein in the yeast host strain of interest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>). Considering these constraints and the diverse metabolic features of target hosts, it is obvious that new tools still need to be developed.</p><p>The approach described here is based on the use of expression cassettes encoding dominant-negative truncated transcription factors designed for interfering with specific regulatory pathways. Such defective transcription factors have been extensively used for fundamental research in higher eukaryotic cells, due to the difficulties of reverse genetics, or in view of therapeutic applications (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>). However, in yeast as well as in many other microorganisms, this tool has only been marginally used, for studying metabolic functions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13 B14 B15 B16">13&#x02013;16</xref>). For genetic engineering of prototroph microorganisms, dominant-negative transcription factors would provide ideal tools. Indeed, this approach should allow the design of both positive and negative selection systems that are very efficient and should be appropriate for performing any precise genomic modification. Using such strategy, we performed several precise genetic modifications in two wild strains isolated from banana leaves in Thailand (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>).</p><p>Two systems were established, respectively interfering with the catabolism of galactose and with the metabolism of arginine. In the absence of galactose, the transcriptional activator Gal4p is bound to specific sites (UAS) upstream the structural <italic>GAL</italic> genes, but is unable to activate their transcription, since the activation domain is masked by Gal80p (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>). In the presence of galactose, the Gal4p activation domain is liberated. Consequently, expression of <italic>GAL1</italic>, <italic>GAL2</italic>, <italic>GAL7</italic> and <italic>GAL10</italic> is induced (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>). To be efficient, the induction requires the relief of carbon catabolite repression.</p><p>A truncated transcription factor, Gal4p&#x00394; (aa 1&#x02013;147) is known to be localized in the nucleus and to bind to the UAS upstream the <italic>GAL</italic> genes, while being unable to activate their transcription in the presence of galactose (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20 B21 B22 B23">20&#x02013;23</xref>). Overproduction of Gal4p&#x00394; was expected to lead to competition with the endogenous Gal4p (which is produced at very low level) for binding to the DNA target sites, which should give rise to inhibition of induction in the presence of galactose, and to inhibition of growth on galactose as carbon source. We also expected that, when grown on a medium containing appropriate amounts of glucose and galactose, a yeast producing Gal4p&#x00394; should be less sensitive to 2-deoxy-galactose (2DG), a pro-drug whose toxicity was previously demonstrated to be increased in strains constitutively producing the enzymes of the pathway (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>). Therefore, a gene encoding Gal4p&#x00394; was placed under the control of a strong constitutive promoter, in view of designing both positive and negative selection systems.</p><p>The arginine biosynthetic pathway consists of five enzymes allowing conversion of glutamate to ornithine, which is then converted in arginine in three steps [ornithine carbamoyltransferase (<italic>ARG3</italic>), argininosuccinate synthetase (<italic>ARG1</italic>) and lyase (<italic>ARG4</italic>)] (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>). Arginine can be degraded by arginase (<italic>CAR1)</italic>, giving rise to urea and ornithine which is modified by a transaminase (<italic>CAR2</italic>) into glutamate semialdehyde, giving rise to glutamate and ammonium after several steps. Regulation of arginine anabolic and catabolic pathways is dependent on the availability of arginine or ornithine as nitrogen source. Several regulatory systems are involved, including a specific transcriptional control which regulates the production of both anabolic and catabolic enzymes and involves the &#x02018;ArgR&#x02013;Mcm1p&#x02019; complex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>). When arginine or ornithine is used as nitrogen source, this complex binds specific sequences and activates the catabolic pathway, the anabolic pathway being simultaneously downregulated. In the absence of arginine or ornithine, the complex is formed but does not bind to DNA. Deletion of <italic>ARG81</italic> leads to a growth defect on arginine or ornithine and to constitutive expression of genes encoding anabolic enzymes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>). In addition, such a mutant strain appeared to be resistant to canavanine (an arginine analog) toxicity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>), probably due to the accumulation of intracellular arginine. It has been shown that a truncated Arg81p (aa 1&#x02013;180) can be included in a functionally defective complex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>). The dominant-negative factor evaluated in this study was then constitutively overproduced, and was expected to compete with the endogenous Arg81p for complex formation.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Strains, culture media and chemicals</title><p><italic>Escherichia coli</italic> strain XL1blue (Stratagen) was used for all cloning steps and was cultivated on LB medium. For selective medium, ampicillin was added at 100&#x02009;&#x000b5;g/ml. <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> strains BY4709 (<italic>MAT&#x003b1; ura3&#x00394;0</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>), &#x003a3;1278b (<italic>MAT&#x003b1;</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>), TR2 and TR3 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>) were used as model strains through the development of dominant negative marker. DNA of FY1679 (<italic>MATa ura3-52 his3&#x00394;200/MAT&#x003b1; his3&#x00394;200 ura3-52</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>) has served as DNA template for cloning. These <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> strains were cultivated on YPD and on minimum medium YNB with 80&#x02009;mM ammonium and 20&#x02009;mg/ml glucose (except for selection media and growth conditions for transcriptional analysis, see below). 2-Deoxy-<sc>d</sc>-galactose was purchased from MP Biomedicals and <sc>l</sc>-canavanine from Sigma-Aldrich.</p></sec><sec><title>Plasmid construction</title><p>All plasmids are described in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>. Cloning procedures are largely described in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkq708/DC1">Supplementary Data</ext-link>.
<table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>List of plasmids used in this work</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plasmid name</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plasmid description</th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p0int</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>CYC1</italic>-integrative plasmid derived from pFL44&#x02009;L with an empty expression cassette (<italic>TDH3</italic> promoter and <italic>CYC1</italic> terminator). The restriction by MluI targets integration in genomic <italic>CYC1</italic>.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pGint</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p0int carrying <italic>GAL4</italic>&#x00394; encoding Gal4p (aa 1&#x02013;147).</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pGVint</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p0int carrying <italic>GAL4&#x00394;V5</italic> encoding Gal4p (aa 1&#x02013;147) with C-terminal V5 epitope.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pGVGint</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p0int carrying <italic>GAL4&#x00394;V5GFP</italic> encoding Gal4p (aa 1&#x02013;147) with C-terminal V5 epitope followed by eGFP.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pAint</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p0int carrying <italic>ARG81</italic>&#x00394; encoding Arg81p (aa 1&#x02013;180).</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pAVint</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p0int carrying <italic>ARG81</italic>&#x00394; encoding Arg81p (aa 1&#x02013;180) with C-terminal V5 epitope.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pGintL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pGint with a 613-bp sequence of <italic>LEU2</italic> (from nt 24 to 636). The restriction by KpnI targets integration in genomic <italic>LEU2.</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pGVintL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pGVint with a 613-bp sequence of <italic>LEU2.</italic> The restriction by KpnI targets integration in genomic <italic>LEU2.</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pGVdelHO</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pUC19 carrying the <italic>GAL4&#x00394;V5</italic> expression cassette flanked by two sequences homologous to upstream and downstream of <italic>HO</italic> ORF domains, with a short <italic>HO</italic> direct repeat for vector excision (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>).</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pGVdelURA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pUC19 carrying the <italic>GAL4&#x00394;V5</italic> expression cassette flanked by two sequences homologous to upstream and downstream of <italic>URA3</italic> ORF, with a short <italic>URA3</italic> direct repeat for vector excision (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>).</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pGVKdelHO</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pGVdelHO with <italic>KanMX</italic> cassette depending on a bidirectional <italic>TDH3</italic> promoter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>).</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pGVKdelURA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pGVdelURA with <italic>KanMX</italic> cassette depending on a bidirectional <italic>TDH3</italic> promoter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>).</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pAVdelHO</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pUC19 carrying the <italic>ARG81&#x00394;V5</italic> expression cassette flanked by two sequences homologous to upstream and downstream of <italic>HO</italic> ORF domains, with a short <italic>HO</italic> direct repeat for vector excision (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>).</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec><title>Transformation, positive and negative selection media</title><p><italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> strains were transformed using the lithium acetate procedure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>). For 10<sup>8</sup>&#x02013;10<sup>9</sup> harvested cells concentrated in 100&#x02009;&#x000b5;l, at least 5&#x02009;&#x000b5;g of integrative vector were added with 5&#x02009;&#x000b5;g of carrier DNA (10&#x02009;mg/ml fish sperm DNA solution, MB grade from Roche Diagnostics GmbH). For basic <italic>URA3</italic> selection, transformants were selected on YNB, 20&#x02009;mg/ml glucose. For <italic>GAL4</italic>&#x00394;, the positive selection medium was YNB, 30&#x02009;mg/ml glycerol, 20&#x02009;mg/ml 2-deoxygalatose, 5&#x02009;mg/ml casaminoacids, 1&#x02009;mg/ml galactose, 200&#x02009;&#x000b5;g/ml glucose, supplemented with 50&#x02009;mg/l leucine or 25&#x02009;mg/ml uracil if required. For <italic>ARG81</italic>&#x00394;, the positive selection medium was YNB, 20&#x02009;mg/ml glucose, 200&#x02009;&#x000b5;g/ml ornithine and 25&#x02009;&#x000b5;g/ml canavanine. Cells were not incubated in a non-selective growth medium before plating. Geneticin selection was performed as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>).</p><p>The loss of integrative plasmid or deletion cassette was selected depending on the negative marker. First, transformants were cultivated overnight at 30&#x000b0;C during 24&#x02009;h on YPD, diluted in fresh media to OD<sub>660&#x02009;nm</sub> 0.05 and then grown for 24&#x02009;h. Second, 10<sup>4</sup>, 10<sup>6</sup> and 3&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>8</sup> cfu were plated on selective media: YNB, 4&#x02009;mg/ml galactose for <italic>GAL4</italic>&#x00394; loss and YNB glucose, 1&#x02009;mg/ml ornithine for <italic>ARG81</italic>&#x00394; loss.</p></sec><sec><title>PCR characterization</title><p>All yeast transformants were characterized by PCR screening directly with colonies. First, cells were added to 10&#x02009;&#x000b5;l of 0.25% SDS and heated at 95&#x000b0;C during 15&#x02009;min. After this rapid DNA extraction, 90&#x02009;&#x000b5;l of water were added and, after 1&#x02009;min of centrifugation at 12&#x02009;000<italic>g</italic>, 1&#x02009;&#x000b5;l of supernatant was used as DNA template for PCR. The 25&#x02009;&#x000b5;l-reaction mixture contained 0.4&#x02009;&#x000b5;M of each primer, 0.8% Triton X100 and DreamTaq PCR MasterMix (Fermentas).</p></sec><sec><title>Sequencing of PCR fragments carrying genomic <italic>HO</italic> and <italic>URA3</italic> deletions</title><p>Fragments carrying genomic <italic>HO</italic> and <italic>URA3</italic> deletions were amplified by PCR with primer pairs ocej359/360 and ocej317/320, respectively (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkq708/DC1">Supplementary Table S1</ext-link> for primer sequences). Fragments were purified by using High Pure PCR Product Purification Kit (Roche Diagnostics GmbH) and sequenced using the same primers (DNAvision S.A.).</p></sec><sec><title>Immunodetection by Western blot</title><p>After separation by SDS&#x02013;PAGE, proteins were electroblotted onto a Hybond nitrocellulose membrane (GE Healthcare) with XcellII module (Invitrogen) and with NuPage Transfer Buffer (Invitrogen)/10% methanol. Tagged proteins were immunodetected with Anti-V5 antibodies (Invitrogen) and revealed by using Western-Breeze Chemiluminescent Kit Anti-Mouse (Invitrogen).</p></sec><sec><title>Quantitative qRT&#x02013;PCR</title><p>Quantification of mRNA was performed as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>). For inducing <italic>GAL</italic> genes expression, yeast strains were cultivated on YNB with 80&#x02009;mM ammonium, 20&#x02009;mg/ml raffinose until OD<sub>660&#x02009;nm</sub> 0.5 in which 2&#x02009;mg/ml galatose were added for a further 1-h growth. The anabolic and catabolic gene transcripts were quantified after growth on YNB with 80&#x02009;mM ammonium, 20&#x02009;mg/ml glucose in the presence or not of 1&#x02009;mg/ml arginine. Total RNA was extracted as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>). Primers amplified a 167-bp fragment of <italic>GAL1</italic> (ocej235, 5&#x02032;-CCGAAAAGTGCCCGAGCATA-3&#x02032;; ocej236, 5&#x02032;-GACGGCGCAAAGCATATCAA-3&#x02032;), a 145-bp fragment of <italic>GAL2</italic> (ocej237, 5&#x02032;-TGAATTGAAAGCCGGTGAGT-3&#x02032;; ocej238, 5&#x02032;-GGTATCCCAGCCAAACATGA-3&#x02032;), a 169-bp fragment of <italic>GAL10</italic> (GAL10-O1, 5&#x02032;-TGGGTTCCGGTAAAGGTTCT-3&#x02032;; GAL10-O2, 5&#x02032;-TGCAACTCGGTCTGCCATTT-3&#x02032;), a 149-bp fragment of <italic>CAR1</italic> (CAR1-O1, 5&#x02032;-AATACCCCGATGCTGGTCTT-3&#x02032;; CAR1-O2, 5&#x02032;-TTTGAGCGACTCGGGACAAT-3&#x02032;), a 100-bp fragment of <italic>ARG3</italic> (ARG3-O1, 5&#x02032;-GCCCGTGTGAACAAACATGA-3&#x02032;; ARG3-O2, 5&#x02032;-TTGCTTGCAAAGGGTGGAAT-3&#x02032;) and a 125-bp fragment of <italic>TBP1</italic> (TBP1-O1, 5&#x02032;-TATAACCCCAAGCGTTTTGC-3&#x02032;; TBP1-O2, 5&#x02032;-GCCAGCTTTGAGTCATCCTC-3&#x02032;).</p></sec><sec><title>Confocal imaging</title><p>Cells were imaged on LSM510-Axiovert 100&#x02009;M confocal microscope (Zeiss) by exciting eGFP fusion at 488&#x02009;nm.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>Dominant-negative effects resulting from overexpression of <italic>GAL4</italic>&#x00394; or <italic>ARG81</italic>&#x00394;</title><p>To ensure a constitutive overproduction of truncated protein, the <italic>S. cerevisiae GAL4</italic>&#x00394; sequence coding for Gal4p&#x00394; (aa 1&#x02013;147) was placed under the control of the strong <italic>TDH3</italic> promoter. The ORF was fused or not to the V5 epitope coding sequence allowing immunodetection with V5-specific antibodies. The expression cassette was cloned in integrative vectors. The <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> strain BY4709 was transformed with <italic>CYC1</italic> integrative plasmids (described in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>) by conventional <italic>URA3</italic> selection. Transformants harboring a single copy of the empty vector (p0int), plasmid with <italic>GAL4</italic>&#x00394; (pGint) or plasmid carrying <italic>GAL4</italic>&#x00394;<italic>:V5</italic> (pGVint) were chosen after PCR characterization of genomic DNA (data not shown). The production of the truncated Gal4p was verified by immunodetection with V5-specific antibodies (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkq708/DC1">Supplementary Figure S1</ext-link>). The phenotypes were determined by streaking the selected strains on minimal medium containing either glucose or galactose as sole carbon source. The growth of strains producing truncated Gal4p was significantly inhibited on galactose, indicating the occurrence of a dominant-negative effect (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). It should be noticed that this phenotype was slightly more pronounced with the <italic>GAL4</italic>&#x00394;:<italic>V5</italic> construct. This possibly results from a higher production level of Gal4p&#x00394;-V5 (expression or half-live) or from a functional benefit due to this particular C-terminal modification of the protein (conformation, interaction with other transcription factors, etc.). Another plasmid, pGVGint, was constructed in order to overproduce Gal4p&#x00394; as a fusion with GFP. The phenotype of a strain carrying such plasmid was similar to the one observed for pGVint. Observation by fluorescence microscopy revealed very efficient accumulation of the protein in the nucleus when <italic>GAL4</italic>&#x00394; is expressed under the control of the strong <italic>TDH</italic>3 promoter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). According to experiments described hereafter, the dominant-negative effect is due to interference of <italic>GAL4</italic>&#x00394; with the induction of genes belonging to the galactose pathway. Indeed, the transcriptional analysis by qRT&#x02013;PCR has shown a significant decrease of <italic>GAL1</italic>, <italic>GAL2</italic> and <italic>GAL10</italic> expression in raffinose grown strains carrying pGint or pGVint plasmids after 1-h pulse with galactose (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>A). Expression of genes encoding defective transcription factors unrelated to the galactose pathway did not significantly affect expression of <italic>GAL</italic> genes (transcriptional analysis of <italic>GAL1</italic>, <italic>GAL2</italic> and <italic>GAL10</italic> in <italic>ARG81&#x00394;:V5</italic> expressing strain, data not shown) and growth on galactose (see below <italic>ARG81</italic>&#x00394;).
<fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Phenotype determination of <italic>GAL4</italic>&#x00394; and <italic>ARG81</italic>&#x00394; expressing <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> strains. BY4709-derived strains carrying the various integrated vectors were streaked on diverse media for identifying phenotypes. P0int: negative control vector; pGint: <italic>GAL4</italic>&#x00394; expression vector; pGVint: <italic>GAL4</italic>&#x00394;<italic>:V5</italic> expression vector; pAVint: <italic>ARG81</italic>&#x00394;<italic>:V5</italic> expression vector; pAint: <italic>ARG81</italic>&#x00394; expression vector. First column: minimal medium (YNB) with 20&#x02009;mg/ml glucose as carbon source (no significant effect resulting from expression of <italic>GAL4</italic>&#x00394; or <italic>ARG81</italic>&#x00394;). <italic>GAL4</italic>&#x00394;-associated phenotypes were observed on YNB with 20&#x02009;mg/ml galactose (second column) and on 2DG selection medium (YNB with 30&#x02009;mg/ml glycerol, 20&#x02009;mg/ml 2DG, 5&#x02009;mg/ml casaminoacids, 1&#x02009;mg/ml galactose and 0.2&#x02009;mg/ml glucose, third column). <italic>ARG81</italic>&#x00394;-related phenotypes were highlighted on YNB with 1&#x02009;mg/ml ornithine as sole nitrogen source (fourth column) and on canavanine selection medium (YNB with 80&#x02009;mM ammonium, 20&#x02009;mg/ml glucose, 200&#x02009;&#x000b5;g/ml ornithine and 8&#x02009;&#x000b5;g/ml canavanine, (fifth column).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkq708f1"/></fig>
<fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Subcellular localization of truncated Gal4p-V5 fused to GFP.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkq708f2"/></fig>
<fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Transcriptional analysis of <italic>GAL1</italic>, <italic>GAL2</italic> and <italic>GAL10</italic> expression in wild-type (carrying empty <italic>CYC1</italic> integrative plasmid p0int) and truncated Gal4p overproducing <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> strains (harboring <italic>CYC1</italic> integrative pGint and pGVint vectors, enabling the expression of <italic>GAL4</italic>&#x00394; and <italic>GAL4</italic>&#x00394;<italic>:V5</italic> respectively). Strains were cultivated on YNB with 20&#x02009;mg/ml raffinose (glucose repression relieved, no galactose induction) and, for inducing <italic>GAL</italic> gene expression, 2&#x02009;mg/ml galactose was added for one hour. mRNA of <italic>GAL1</italic>, <italic>GAL2</italic> and <italic>GAL10</italic> were quantified by qRT&#x02013;PCR and the values were normalized with <italic>TBP1</italic> mRNA. (<bold>B</bold>) Transcriptional analysis of <italic>ARG3</italic> and <italic>CAR1</italic> expression in wild-type (carrying empty integrative plasmid p0int) and truncated Arg81p overproducing <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> strains (harboring <italic>CYC1</italic> integrative pAint and pAVint vectors, enabling the expression of <italic>ARG81</italic>&#x00394; and <italic>ARG81</italic>&#x00394;<italic>:V5</italic> respectively). Strains were cultivated either on YNB with 80&#x02009;mM ammonium, 20&#x02009;mg/ml glucose (expression of arginine biosynthesis genes, repression of arginine catabolic pathway genes) or on YNB with 80&#x02009;mM ammonium, 20&#x02009;mg/ml glucose and 1&#x02009;mg/ml arginine (repression of arginine anabolic pathway genes, induction of arginine degradation genes). By qRT&#x02013;PCR, mRNA of <italic>ARG3</italic> and <italic>CAR1</italic> were quantified and the values were normalized with <italic>TBP1</italic> mRNA.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkq708f3"/></fig></p><p>By a similar approach, the <italic>S. cerevisiae ARG81</italic> coding sequence spreading from ATG to codon 180 (<italic>ARG81</italic>&#x00394;), fused or not to the V5 epitope coding sequence, was placed under the control of <italic>TDH3</italic> promoter and cloned in an integrative plasmid. After transformation of BY4709 strain and selection of transformants harboring a single copy of these integrative plasmids, the production of Arg81p&#x00394; was also verified by immunodetection with V5-specific antibodies (data not shown). The phenotype was verified by streaking cells on a minimal medium containing ornithine as sole nitrogen source. Growth of strains expressing <italic>ARG81</italic>&#x00394; was inhibited in such medium (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>), indicating that the production of truncated Arg81p is sufficient to establish a dominant-negative effect. The transcriptional analysis by qRT&#x02013;PCR demonstrated a lower induction of catabolic <italic>CAR1</italic> expression and a reduced repression of anabolic <italic>ARG3</italic> expression in <italic>ARG81</italic>&#x00394;-expressing strain when cells were grown in the presence of arginine, as compared to the wild-type strain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>B). This dominant-negative effect was also highlighted through enzymatic assays of the arginase and the ornithine transcarbamylase (data not shown). We also verified that production of truncated Arg81p does not significantly affect growth on galactose and that production of truncated Gal4p does not interfere with growth on ornithine, confirming the specificity of the dominant-negative effects (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Drug resistance due to dominant-negative effect of <italic>GAL</italic>4&#x00394; and <italic>ARG</italic>81&#x00394;</title><p>Various enzymes are able to convert specific prodrugs to toxic compounds and such property has been exploited for developing negative selection systems using particular mutant host strains (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>). Such possibility was offered for the galactose pathway, and exploited in prototrophic host strains using <italic>GAL</italic>4&#x00394;.</p><p>Resistance to 2DG, a glycolysis inhibiting prodrug whose toxic effect is supposed to require a permease (presumably Gal2p) and the Gal1p galactokinase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>), was evaluated. This required modification of the growth medium, as previous assays involved a wild-type strain and mutants constitutively expressing the <italic>GAL</italic> genes. Various assays were performed to define a medium allowing a <italic>GAL4</italic> strain to be intoxicated by 2DG while <italic>GAL4</italic>&#x00394;-expressing strains being able to grow. A defined medium was optimized in view of selection of transformants carrying <italic>GAL4</italic>&#x00394; (data not shown). The optimal medium contains 1&#x02009;mg/ml galactose to induce the <italic>GAL</italic> genes (whose expression is required for 2DG catabolism), a low concentration of glucose (0.2&#x02009;mg/ml), 30&#x02009;mg/ml glycerol (carbon sources for transformants carrying <italic>GAL4</italic>&#x00394;) and 5&#x02009;mg/ml casaminoacids (improving growth of transformants carrying <italic>GAL4</italic>&#x00394;). The defined glucose concentration is apparently insufficient to impair the induction of <italic>GAL</italic> genes expression as well as galactose and deoxygalactose uptake. A reduced toxicity of this prodrug could be observed upon expression of <italic>GAL4</italic>&#x00394; (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>).</p><p>It was previously demonstrated that resistance to canavanine is encountered in <italic>can1</italic> and <italic>argR</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>). <italic>ARG81</italic>&#x00394;-expressing strains were streaked on a selection medium (YNB, 80&#x02009;mM ammonium, 20&#x02009;mg/ml glucose, 200&#x02009;&#x000b5;g/ml ornithine, 8&#x02009;&#x000b5;g/ml canavanine) rendering evident the canavanine resistance of <italic>argR</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>). As compared to the <italic>ARG81</italic> control strain, <italic>ARG81</italic>&#x00394;-expressing cells were resistant to the drug (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). <italic>ARG81</italic>&#x00394; was then also potentially usable as positive selection marker.</p></sec><sec><title>Genetic engineering vectors for prototrophic <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> strains</title><p>The selection through 2DG-resistance was assayed by transforming laboratory strains with a classical integrative plasmid carrying the <italic>GAL4</italic>&#x00394;:<italic>V5</italic> selective marker (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkq708/DC1">Supplementary Figure S2</ext-link>). After transformation of &#x003a3;1278b (haploid strain) and BY4700/9 (diploid strain), tiny colonies were obtained after 5&#x02013;7 days on 2DG medium, picked with the aid of a binocular and purified by streaking on a fresh 2DG selection plate. The small size of the transformants was probably due to the low glucose concentration in the 2DG medium (only 0.2&#x02009;mg/ml) and the residual metabolic activity of non-transformed cells. More than 50% of diploid colonies harbored the expected disruption of the targeted allele, as shown by PCR analysis of genomic DNA (data not shown) and expected 2:2 <italic>leu2</italic>:<italic>LEU</italic>2 segregation was observed after sporulation. For &#x003a3;1278b, &#x0223c;1% of 2DG-resistant clones appeared to carry the integrated vector. This lower efficiency probably results from a high frequency of spontaneous 2DG-resistant mutants (likely to be recessive, as not observed with the diploid). PCR-screening of the colonies should then be needed when transforming haploid strains. The efficiency of the negative selection system was demonstrated by selecting the vector excision event. Indeed, after growth on non-selective YPD medium and plating on minimal medium with galactose as sole carbon source, colonies showed a <italic>GAL4/LEU2</italic> phenotype.</p><p>To further evaluate the efficiency of the <italic>GAL4</italic>&#x00394; selection marker, gene deletions were performed in wild yeast strains (&#x02018;TR strains&#x02019;) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>). As most of the <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> wild strains, they are homothallic diploids, which implies that <italic>HO</italic> needs to be deleted for generating stable genetically modified recombinant strains (otherwise haploids of both mating types should appear after sporulation, giving rise spontaneously to a diploid cellular population by mating). For such purpose, a vector including a <italic>GAL4</italic>&#x00394; selective marker surrounded by upstream and downstream <italic>HO</italic> sequences and an appropriate small 30&#x02009;bp directly repeated <italic>HO</italic> sequence for subsequent vector excision was constructed (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>). BamHI restriction sites were created for allowing the generation of appropriate DNA fragments for gene-replacement by homologous recombination.
<fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Scheme of integrative cassettes for the deletion of <italic>HO</italic> and <italic>URA3</italic>. All cassettes are excised from pUC19 plasmid by a BamHI double digest. Up sequences are identical to a sequence upstream of targeted ORF and down sequences are identical to a sequence downstream of targeted ORF. Dashed yellow and blue boxes are small 30 repeats of upstream <italic>HO</italic> and <italic>URA3</italic> sequences, respectively.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkq708f4"/></fig></p><p>TR3, a <italic>GAL</italic> and 2DG-sensitive diploid strain, was first chosen for performing genetic modifications with the <italic>GAL4</italic>&#x00394; system. The pGVdelHO BamHI-digested vector was introduced into TR3 after transformation and selection on the 2DG medium. After 5 days, colonies were picked and purified by streaking on a fresh selection plate. PCR-characterization of genomic DNA has shown that &#x0003e;50% of the colonies exhibited the <italic>GAL4</italic>&#x00394;<italic>:V5</italic> cassette integrated in <italic>HO</italic> locus. After dissecting tetrads, stable <italic>ho</italic> haploids deriving from TR3 were obtained (2:2 <italic>HO</italic>:<italic>ho</italic> segregation). The integrated cassette in <italic>HO</italic> locus was then excised by spontaneous homologous recombination involving the small directly repeated <italic>HO</italic> sequences (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>), by selecting haploid <italic>GAL</italic> clones after growth on YPD medium as described in &#x02018;Materials and Methods&#x02019; section (PCR characterization, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkq708/DC1">Supplementary Figure S3</ext-link>). The cassette pop-out frequency was estimated at 3&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;5&#x02009;</sup>&#x000b1;&#x02009;6.5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;6</sup> from a set of three independent experiments. The expected accurate deletion of <italic>HO</italic> was confirmed by PCR-amplified genomic DNA sequencing. Among eight analyzed clones deriving from five independent transformants, seven carried the expected deletion (only one revertant showed an unexplained recombination event). Haploid strains of each mating type carrying the desired accurate <italic>HO</italic> deletion and devoid of any foreign DNA element were obtained and mated in order to generate a <italic>ho/ho</italic> diploid strain, TR3<italic>ho</italic>&#x00394;.
<fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Scheme of gene deletion by homologous recombination between linearized integrative vectors and targeted genomic sequences, and subsequent excision by homologous recombination between the designed short (30&#x02009;bp) directly repeated genomic sequences.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkq708f5"/></fig></p><p>Afterwards, <italic>URA3</italic> deletions were performed in TR3<italic>ho</italic>&#x00394; strain to generate modified hosts that could be transformed with classical expression vectors. For this purpose, a vector carrying the <italic>GAL4</italic>&#x00394;<italic>:V5</italic> cassette surrounded by appropriate <italic>URA3</italic> sequences was similarly constructed, pGVdelURA3 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>). Using the same approach, the deletion of <italic>URA3</italic> was successfully carried out starting from the diploid strain with a transformation efficiency of &#x0003e;50%. Haploids of both mating types carrying expected accurate deletions of <italic>URA3</italic>, as confirmed by genomic DNA sequencing, were obtained. Successive genetic modifications of strains could systematically be performed in the same way, by transforming diploids and performing classical genetics. Indeed, such procedure allows verifying expected segregation of the genetic modifications and selecting modified haploids of both mating types. In comparison, transformation of TR3<italic>ho</italic>&#x00394;-derived haploids was undertaken and, as mentioned above with &#x003a3;1278b, extensive PCR-screening was required (transformation efficiency of 7.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.3%), confirming that the diploid-transformation procedure is more convenient.</p><p>Surprisingly, some TR strains appeared to be naturally 2DG-resistant despite their <italic>GAL</italic> phenotype. One of these, the TR2 diploid, was transformed using a construct in which a <italic>neo</italic> marker was associated to <italic>GAL4</italic>&#x00394; (bidirectional <italic>TDH3</italic>-driven expression cassette), designed for the deletion of <italic>HO</italic> ORF (pGVKdelHO; <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>). After selection of G418-resistant transformants and PCR characterization, we observed a <italic>gal</italic> phenotype. Therefore, the dominant-negative effect of <italic>GAL4</italic>&#x00394; does occur in such 2DG-resistant wild strain. Using haploids derived from these TR2 transformants, stable <italic>ho</italic> haploids devoid of foreign DNA sequences were obtained after spontaneous vector excision at a frequency of 1.4&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;6&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;6</sup> (based on three independent experiments). The <italic>neo/GAL4</italic>&#x00394; expression cassette may then be convenient for modifying <italic>GAL</italic> strains that are not sensitive to 2DG (approach validated in BY4709 strain, data not shown). In addition, this vector provides an alternative for transformation of prototroph haploids (specifically in case only one mating type is available), as it avoids the PCR-screening of transformant candidates which was required with the 2DG selection due to the relatively high frequency of non-transformed 2DG-resistant haploid clones as mentioned above.</p><p>We also used the <italic>ARG81</italic>&#x00394; marker for modifying the 2DG-resistant TR2 strain, with an optimized selective medium with canavanine (25&#x02009;&#x000b5;g/ml). Using BamHI-digested pAVdelHO (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>), deletion of <italic>HO</italic> was successfully carried out (data not shown). After sporulation, <italic>ho</italic> haploids of both mating types were obtained. The growth of these <italic>ho</italic> haploids on ornithine as nitrogen source was inhibited, as expected, allowing selection of vector excision after growth on non-selective YPD medium, at a frequency of 5.5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.6&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup>. The expected accurate deletion of <italic>HO</italic> gene was confirmed by PCR-amplified genomic DNA sequencing. The <italic>ARG81</italic>&#x00394; marker may then provide a useful alternative for modifying 2DG-resistant strains.</p><p>In order to compare efficiencies of the 2DG and canavanine positive selection systems, a series of transformation experiments were performed with the <italic>HO</italic> and <italic>URA</italic>3 deletion vectors in TR2 and TR3 strains (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>). These results demonstrate that the two selection systems have similar efficiencies. A set of convenient vectors harboring <italic>GAL4</italic>&#x00394; and <italic>ARG81</italic>&#x00394; was developed (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref> and plasmid sequences in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkq708/DC1">Supplementary Data</ext-link>). With such plasmids, the introduction of homologous sequences to loci to be targeted can be easily carried out via two polylinkers flanking the selection cassette.
<table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Evaluation of transformation efficiencies for <italic>HO</italic> deletion in TR3 by pGVdelHO (2-deoxygalactose selection), <italic>URA3</italic> deletion in H2n1 (ho/ho diploid derived from TR3) by pGVdelURA (2DG selection) and <italic>HO</italic> deletion in TR2 by pAVdelHO (canavanine selection)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strain</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vector/selection</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean transformation efficiency (total screened colonies)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Standard deviation</th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TR3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pGVdelHO/2DG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.3% (66)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000b1;4.9%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TR3<italic>ho</italic>&#x00394;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pGVdelURA/2DG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.0% (79)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000b1;8.7%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TR2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pAVdelHO/canavanine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.7% (47)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000b1;0.8%</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TF1"><p>Transformation efficiency is defined as the percentage of PCR-characterized-colonies harboring the deletion cassette at the expected locus. The amount of screened colonies is given between brackets. The mean calculation and standard deviation are based on three independent experiments.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Plasmid maps of pCSC129, 130 and 131 containing <italic>GAL4</italic>&#x00394;, <italic>ARG81</italic>&#x00394; and <italic>GAL4</italic>&#x00394;/<italic>KanMX4</italic> selection markers respectively. These vectors are derived from pUC19 and contain two convenient polylinkers, BglII-AvrII-NotI and MluI-KpnI-BamHI, to introduce homologous sequences in view of genetic modification.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkq708f6"/></fig>
</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>CONCLUSION</title><p>The use of dominant-negative truncated transcription factors designed for interfering with specific regulatory pathways has been shown to allow performing precise genetic modification of wild strains of <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>. This method should be convenient for performing any site-directed modification [including point-mutations, as described in ref. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>)] in the genome, and avoids side-alterations in the locus, which is useful for a number of functional studies. The approach is based on the use of a single expression cassette leading to both resistance to a toxic compound and inhibition of growth on a specific substrate. It is particularly attractive for specific applications, such as building of genetically modified strains for the food industry, as only specific genes derived from the host strain should be used (avoiding the utilization of foreign genes). The described method is also more powerful than previously described systems such as 5-fluoroorotic acid resistance of <italic>ura3</italic> strains. Indeed, it does not require previous generation of a specific mutation or deletion. Moreover, in the specific case of the <italic>Saccharomyces</italic> wild strains, a preliminary deletion of <italic>HO</italic> is required for generating stable haploids, and the growth defect resulting from transcriptional interference appeared to be very convenient for subsequent vector recycling.</p><p>Resistance to a drug resulting from interference with a specific regulatory pathway is apparently not as systematically observed than metabolic alteration leading to growth inhibition. Indeed, not all the <italic>GAL</italic> wild strains appeared to be sensitive to 2DG in the various growth conditions assayed (data not shown). However, transformation of the 2DG-resistant diploid TR2 using a <italic>neo</italic> marker associated to the <italic>GAL4</italic>&#x00394; cassette gave rise to transformants that were deficient for growth on galactose. Therefore, the transcriptional interference occurred, and the counter-selection was adequate for selection of subsequent vector excision on the galactose medium. We could not explain such resistance behavior on 2DG, as the toxicity of this prodrug through inhibition of glycolysis is not fully understood (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>). Possibly, 2DG is not transported by the galactopermease or the derivative compound (2-deoxygalactose-1-phosphate and/or UDP-2-deoxygalactose) is not efficiently produced or else its toxic effect is not exerted in all <italic>GAL</italic> strains. In case of TR2, canavanine appeared to be toxic, and <italic>ARG81</italic>&#x00394; was successfully used as positive/negative selection marker, which offers an useful alternative to <italic>GAL4</italic>&#x00394;.</p><p>Based on the existing knowledge on metabolic pathways and regulatory genes, it should be possible to design a number of alternative dominant-positive/negative selection systems (see phenotypes database of <italic>Saccharomyces</italic> Genome Database)<italic>.</italic> Systematic studies could be designed which should allow generating both useful knowledge on known or predicted transcription factors as well as identifying new selective markers of interest, by searching for dominant-negative phenotypes upon transformation with appropriate constructs involving the <italic>neo</italic> positive marker, for example.</p><p>The approach could be extended to other yeasts, but also to other microorganisms. Data generated in the context of genomic sequencing projects allow identifying an increasing number of candidate genes for generating such modified transcription factors. For genetic modification of diploid wild strains of <italic>Saccharomyces</italic>, the use of modified transcription factors appeared to be particularly efficient. In this respect, it should be noticed that diploidy or polyploidy has been observed in the case of various wild microorganisms (various lower eukaryotes, but also bacteria and archaea) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39 B40 B41">39&#x02013;41</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA</title><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkq708/DC1">Supplementary Data</ext-link> are available at NAR Online.</p></sec><sec><title>FUNDING</title><p>Commission Communautaire Fran&#x000e7;aise. Funding for open access charge: a.s.b.l. Meurice Recherches &#x00026; D&#x000e9;veloppement.</p><p><italic>Conflict of interest statement</italic>. None declared.</p></sec>
<sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
<title>Supplementary Material</title>
<supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
<caption>
<title>Supplementary Data</title>
</caption>
<media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_38_19_e183__index.html"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"
xlink:href="supp_gkq708_Supplementary_Data.pdf"/>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title><p>The authors thank Christianne Legrain for her proofread of this article, Fabienne Vierendeels for technical support, Andr&#x000e9; Feller for technical advices and Magali Plas for her conscientious work during her student term.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Winzeler</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Shoemaker</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Astromoff</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Andre</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Bangham</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Benito</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Boeke</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Bussey</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Functional characterization of the S.cerevisiae genome by gene deletion and parallel analysis</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1999</year><volume>285</volume><fpage>901</fpage><lpage>906</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10436161</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giaver</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Connelly</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Riles</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>V&#x000e9;ronneau</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dow</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucau-Danila</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Andr&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Functional profiling of the <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> genome</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2002</year><volume>418</volume><fpage>387</fpage><lpage>391</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12140549</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scherens</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Goffeau</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The uses of genome-wide yeast mutant collections</article-title><source>Genome Biol.</source><year>2004</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>229</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15239820</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Riles</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hegemann</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gene disruption</article-title><source>Methods Enzymol.</source><year>2000</year><volume>350</volume><fpage>290</fpage><lpage>315</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12073319</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wach</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Brachat</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>P&#x000f6;hlmann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Philippsen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New heterologous modules for classical or PCR-based gene disruption in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic></article-title><source>Yeast</source><year>1994</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>1793</fpage><lpage>1808</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7747518</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>L&#x000e4;ngle-Rouault</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A method for performing precise alterations in the yeast genome using a recyclable selectable marker</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>1995</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>3079</fpage><lpage>3081</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7659536</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sauer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional Expression of the cre-lox Site-Specific Recombination System in the Yeast <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic></article-title><source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source><year>1987</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>2087</fpage><lpage>2096</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3037344</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>G&#x000fc;ldener</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Heck</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fielder</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Beinhauer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hegemann</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new efficient gene disruption cassette for repeated use in budding yeast</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>1996</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>2519</fpage><lpage>2524</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8692690</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akada</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Aritomi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishizawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>construction of recombinant sake yeast containing a dominant <italic>FAS2</italic> mutation without extraneous sequences by a two-step gene replacement protocol</article-title><source>J. Biosci. Bioeng.</source><year>1999</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>48</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16232423</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olesen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Johannesen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sorensen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gjerlansen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The pYC plasmids, a series of cassette-based yeast plasmid vectors providing means of counter-selection</article-title><source>Yeast</source><year>2000</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>1035</fpage><lpage>1043</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10923025</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hirosawa</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Aritomi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoshida</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kashiwagi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishizawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Akada</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Construction of a self-cloning sake yeast that overexpresses alcohol acetyltransferase gene by a two-step gene replacement protocol</article-title><source>Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol.</source><year>2004</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>68</fpage><lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14758521</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Urnov</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Rebar</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Reik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pandolfi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Designed transcription factors as structural, functional and therapeutic probes of chromatin in vivo</article-title><source>EMBO Rep.</source><year>2002</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>610</fpage><lpage>615</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12101091</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caponigro</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Abedi</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hurlburt</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Maxfield</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Judd</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamb</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transdominant genetic analysis of a growth control pathway</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>1998</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>750</fpage><lpage>7513</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>V&#x000e9;lot</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Srere</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reversible transdominant inhibition of a metabolic pathway</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2000</year><volume>275</volume><fpage>12926</fpage><lpage>12933</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10777592</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boyer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Badis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Fairhead</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Talla</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Hantraye</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Fabre</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hennequin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Koszul</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lafontaine</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Large-scale exploration of growth inhibition caused by overexpression of genomic fragments in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic></article-title><source>Genome Biol.</source><year>2004</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>R72</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15345056</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ortiz</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kinzy</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dominant-negative mutant phenotypes and the regulation of translation elongation factor 2 levels in yeast</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2005</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>5740</fpage><lpage>5748</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16214807</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koedrith</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubois</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Scherens</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Boonchird</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Messenguy</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification and characterization of a thermotolerant yeast strain isolated from banana leaves</article-title><source>Sci. Asia</source><year>2008</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>147</fpage><lpage>152</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nogi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukasawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional domains of a negative regulatory protein, <italic>GAL80</italic>, of <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic></article-title><source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source><year>1989</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>3009</fpage><lpage>3017</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2506435</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A model fungal gene regulatory mechanism: the <italic>GAL</italic> genes of <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic></article-title><source>Microbiol. Rev.</source><year>1987</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>458</fpage><lpage>476</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2830478</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silver</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Keegan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ptashne</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Amino terminus of the yeast <italic>GAL4</italic> gene product is sufficient for nuclear localization</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>1984</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>5951</fpage><lpage>5955</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6091123</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ptashne</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Negative effect of transcriptional activator <italic>GAL4</italic></article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1988</year><volume>334</volume><fpage>721</fpage><lpage>724</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3412449</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carey</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kakidani</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Leatherwood</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mostashari</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ptashne</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An amino-terminal fragment of <italic>GAL4</italic> binds DNA as a dimer</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol.</source><year>1989</year><volume>209</volume><fpage>423</fpage><lpage>432</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2511324</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chasman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kornberg</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>GAL4</italic> protein: purification, association with <italic>GAL80</italic> protein, and conserved domain structure</article-title><source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source><year>1990</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>2916</fpage><lpage>2923</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2188103</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Platt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Toxicity of 2-deoxygalactose to <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> cells constitutively synthesizing galactose-metabolizing enzymes</article-title><source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source><year>1984</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>994</fpage><lpage>996</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6328283</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Messenguy</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubois</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of arginine metabolism in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>: a network of specific and pleiotropic proteins in response to multiple environmental signals</article-title><source>Food Technol. Biotechnol.</source><year>2000</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>277</fpage><lpage>285</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Messenguy</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubois</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of MADS box proteins and their cofactors in combinatorial control of gene expression and cell development</article-title><source>Gene</source><year>2003</year><volume>316</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14563547</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubois</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Messenguy</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dissection of the bifunctional <italic>ARGRII</italic> protein involved in the regulation of arginine anabolic and catabolic pathways</article-title><source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source><year>1991</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>2169</fpage><lpage>2179</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2005903</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grenson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mousset</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiame</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x000e9;chet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiplicity of the amino acid permeases in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic></article-title><source>Biochim. Biophys. Acta</source><year>1966</year><volume>127</volume><fpage>325</fpage><lpage>338</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5964977</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Amar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Messenguy</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>El Bakkoury</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubois</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ArgRII, a component of the ArgR-Mcm1 complex involved in the control of arginine metabolism in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>, is the sensor of arginine</article-title><source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source><year>2000</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>2087</fpage><lpage>2097</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10688655</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brachmann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cost</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Caputo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hieter</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Boeke</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Designer deletion strains derived from <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> S288C: a useful set of strains and plasmids for PCR-mediated gene disruption and other applications</article-title><source>Yeast</source><year>1998</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>115</fpage><lpage>132</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9483801</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Winston</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Dollard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ricupero-Hovasse</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Construction of a set of convenient <italic>Saccharomyces</italic> strains that are Isogenic to S288C</article-title><source>Yeast</source><year>1995</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7762301</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukuda</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Murata</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transformation of intact yeast cells treated with alkali cations</article-title><source>J. Bacteriol.</source><year>1983</year><volume>153</volume><fpage>163</fpage><lpage>168</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6336730</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Georis</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Tate</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubois</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tor pathway control of the nitrogen-responsive <italic>DAL5</italic> gene bifurcates at the level of Gln3 and Gat1 regulation in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic></article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2008</year><volume>283</volume><fpage>8919</fpage><lpage>8929</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18245087</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmitt</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Trumpower</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A rapid and simple method for preparation of RNA from <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic></article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>1990</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>3091</fpage><lpage>3092</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2190191</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boeke</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Lacroute</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Fink</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A positive selection for mutants lacking orotidine-5&#x02032;-phosphate decarboxylase activity in yeast: 5-fluoro-orotic acid resistance</article-title><source>Mol. Gen. Genet.</source><year>1984</year><volume>197</volume><fpage>345</fpage><lpage>346</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6394957</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hartzog</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicholson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>McCusker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cytosine deaminase MX cassettes as positive/negative selectable markers in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic></article-title><source>Yeast</source><year>2005</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>789</fpage><lpage>798</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16088873</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lagunas</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibition of glycolysis by 2-deoxygalactose in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic></article-title><source>Yeast</source><year>1992</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>107</fpage><lpage>115</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1532877</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>B&#x000e9;chet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Grenson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiame</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mutations affecting repressibility of arginine biosynthetic enzymes in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic></article-title><source>Eur. J. Biochem.</source><year>1970</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>39</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5434281</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tobiason</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Seifert</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Obligate Human Pathogen, <italic>Neisseria gonorrhoeae</italic>, Is Polyploid</article-title><source>PLoS Biol.</source><year>2006</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1069</fpage><lpage>1078</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Michelsen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Albrechtsen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The MG1363 and IL1403 laboratory strains of <italic>Lactococcus lactis</italic> and several dairy strains are diploid</article-title><source>J. Bacteriol.</source><year>2010</year><volume>192</volume><fpage>1058</fpage><lpage>1065</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20023021</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Breuert</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Allers</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Spohn</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Soppa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulated polyploidy in halophilic archaea</article-title><source>PLos One</source><year>2006</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>e92</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17183724</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>