<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21750741</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3130059</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-11-06377</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0021929</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Biochemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Proteins</subject><subj-group><subject>Protein Chemistry</subject><subject>Protein Interactions</subject><subject>Recombinant Proteins</subject><subject>Regulatory Proteins</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Biomacromolecule-Ligand Interactions</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Biophysics</subject><subj-group><subject>Biomacromolecule-Ligand Interactions</subject><subject>Macromolecular Assemblies</subject><subject>Protein Chemistry</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Both the C-Terminal Polylysine Region and the Farnesylation of K-RasB Are Important for Its Specific Interaction with Calmodulin</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">CaM Binds to K-RasB</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Ling-Jia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Li-Rong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>Jun-Ming</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Jie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Yi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>&#x0002a;</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><addr-line>State Key Laboratory of Virology, College of Life Sciences, Wuhan University, Wuhan, Hubei, China</addr-line></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Kursula</surname><given-names>Petri</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">University of Oulu, Germany</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">&#x0002a; E-mail: <email>liangyi@whu.edu.cn</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: YL. Performed the experiments: L-JW L-RX J-ML. Analyzed the data: L-JW YL. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: JC. Wrote the paper: L-JW YL.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>5</day><month>7</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>7</issue><elocation-id>e21929</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>4</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>9</day><month>6</month><year>2011</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Wu et al. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Ras protein, as one of intracellular signal switches, plays various roles in several cell activities such as differentiation and proliferation. There is considerable evidence showing that calmodulin (CaM) binds to K-RasB and dissociates K-RasB from membrane and that the inactivation of CaM is able to induce K-RasB activation. However, the mechanism for the interaction of CaM with K-RasB is not well understood.</p></sec><sec><title>Methodology/Principal Findings</title><p>Here, by applying fluorescence spectroscopy and isothermal titration calorimetry, we have obtained thermodynamic parameters for the interaction between these two proteins and identified the important elements of K-RasB for its interaction with Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM. One K-RasB molecule interacts with one CaM molecule in a GTP dependent manner with moderate, micromolar affinity at physiological pH and physiologic ionic strength. Mutation in the polybasic domain of K-Ras decreases the binding affinity. By using a chimera in which the C-terminal polylysine region of K-RasB has been replaced with that of H-Ras and <italic>vice versa</italic>, we find that at physiological pH, H-Ras-(KKKKKK) and Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM formed a 1&#x02236;1 complex with an equilibrium association constant around 10<sup>5</sup> M<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, whereas no binding reaction of K-RasB-(DESGPC) with Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM is detected. Furthermore, the interaction of K-RasB with Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM is found to be enhanced by the farnesylation of K-RasB.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions/Significance</title><p>We demonstrate that the polylysine region of K-RasB not only contributes importantly to the interaction of K-RasB with Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM, but also defines its isoform specific interaction with Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM. The farnesylation of K-RasB is also important for its specific interaction with Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM. Information obtained here can enhance our understanding of how CaM interacts with K-RasB in physiological environments.</p></sec></abstract><counts><page-count count="10"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>In mammals, the three classical <italic>ras</italic> genes encode four highly homologous proteins, H-Ras, N-Ras, and two isoforms K-RasA and K-RasB, and <italic>ras</italic> genes with point mutations are found in approximately 30&#x00025; of human tumors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Barbacid1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Bos1">[2]</xref>. Ras proteins (21 kDa) are small GTPases, which cycle between inactive GDP-bound and active GTP-bound conformations at the plasma membrane, by interaction with a variety of guanine nucleotide exchange factors and GTPase activating proteins in response to stimulation. Following activation, Ras proteins bind and activate a plethora of downstream effector proteins and by this means control many cellular functions, including proliferation and differentiation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Downward1">[3]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Hancock1">[4]</xref>.</p><p>The Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>-binding protein calmodulin (CaM) is found in many eukaryotic cells. It is a small, heat- and acid-stable protein, whose amino acid sequence has been conserved almost perfectly throughout evolution. This protein mediates the control of a large number of enzymes by Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>. The control process occurs in two stages: binding of Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup> to CaM, accompanied by conformational changes, followed by the interaction of CaM with a variety of proteins <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Klee1">[5]</xref>. Some Ras-related small G proteins such as Rin are found bound to the Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM complex <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Wes1">[6]</xref>, and CaM may regulate Rin activation in the Rin-mediated signaling pathway <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Hoshino1">[7]</xref>. The Ras-related small G proteins Kir/Gem/Rad have also been found to bind to CaM <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Fischer1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Moyers1">[9]</xref>, and the binding of CaM to Kir and Gem significantly inhibits the binding of GTP to Kir/Gem <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Moyers1">[9]</xref>. Beguin <italic>et al.</italic> have addressed the mechanism of Kir/Gem regulation by CaM, and have indicated that the binding of Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM to Kir/Gem is required for inhibitory effect by promoting the cytoplasmic localization of Kir/Gem <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Bguin1">[10]</xref>. Furthermore, similar to Kir/Gem, CaM binding also regulates the subcellular distribution of Rad and Rem, both of which inhibit Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup> channel activity by preventing its expression on the cell surface <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Bguin2">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Bguin3">[12]</xref>. Wang and co-workers have shown that Ral-A is a CaM-binding protein, and Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM enhances the binding between GTP and Ral-A <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Wang1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Wang2">[14]</xref>. Park <italic>et al.</italic> have reported that Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM can dissociate RalA from synaptic membranes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Park1">[15]</xref>. It has been found that Ras-related small G protein Rab3A dissociates from synaptic membranes by forming a 1&#x02236;1 complex with Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM. CaM also plays a role in stimulating GTP binding to Rab3A that is complexed with GDP dissociation inhibitor, leading to the formation of an active GTP-bound form of the Rab3A/Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM complex <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Park2">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Park3">[17]</xref>.</p><p>Agell's group has first reported the interaction of K-RasB and CaM <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Villalonga1">[18]</xref>, and has indicated that the phosphorylation of K-RasB by protein kinase C is inhibited by CaM <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Villalonga2">[19]</xref>. CaM can cause dissociation of K-RasB from membranes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Sidhu1">[20]</xref>, and the polybasic farnesyl domain of K-RasB can act as a target for Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Ashery1">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Fivaz1">[22]</xref>. Three different regions in K-RasB are important for the interaction: the hypervariable region (HVR), the &#x003b1;-helix between amino acids 151 and 166, and the switch II <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-LpezAlcal1">[23]</xref>. A growing body of literature has demonstrated that the HVR of K-RasB is responsible for its specific interactions with CaM <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Fivaz1">[22]</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Abraham1">[24]</xref>, although interaction between K-RasB and CaM is not required for Golgi K-RasB translocation induced by Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup> influx in striatal neurons <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-LpezAlcal1">[23]</xref>.</p><p>In this study, we employed several biophysical approaches, such as fluorescence spectroscopy and isothermal titration calorimetry (ITC), to characterize the interaction between K-RasB and Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM. We demonstrated that K-RasB interacted with Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM in a GTP dependent manner. Furthermore, our data show that both the C-terminal polylysine region of K-RasB and the farnesylation of K-RasB are important for its specific interaction with Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Materials</title><p>GDP, GppNHp, farnesylpyrophosphate, and Ru(bpy)<sub>3</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub> were purchased from Sigma (Sigma-Aldrich Co, St. Louis, MO). Anti-CaM monoclonal antibody was obtained from Boster (Wuhan, China). Ni nitrilotriacetic acid agarose was obtained from Qiagen GmbH (Hilden, Germany), and SP Sepharose Fast Flow, Q Sepharose Fast Flow, and Phenyl Sepharose 6 Fast Flow were Amersham Biosciences products (Uppsala, Sweden). All other chemicals used were made in China and were of analytical grade.</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Plasmids and proteins</title><p>The coding sequence of full-length K-RasB was amplified from pEGFP-C3-K-RasB, a kind gift from Prof. Yoav Henis (Department of Neurobiochemistry, Tel Aviv University). The amplified fragment was digested with Nde1/Xho1 and inserted into pET28a vector to generate pET28a-K-RasB. K-RasB mutations were obtained from pET28a-K-RasB by single PCR but with reverse and forward oligonucleotides carrying the appropriate mutations. We exchanged the C-terminal polylysine region of K-RasB-(175&#x02013;180), KKKKKK, with the corresponding sequence of H-Ras-(175&#x02013;180), DESGPC, and <italic>vice versa</italic>, to create two chimeric Ras proteins, K-RasB-(DESGPC) and H-Ras-(KKKKKK). K-RasB-(DESGPC) and H-Ras-(KKKKKK) were obtained from pET28a-K-RasB and pET28a-H-Ras by three rounds of PCR reaction but with reverse and forward oligonucleotides carrying the appropriate mutations. All resultant constructs were confirmed by sequencing.</p><p>Plasmids containing target sequences were transformed into <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> BL21 (DE3) strain. The expression of recombinant Ras proteins was induced by adding isopropyl-&#x003b2;-D-thiogalactopyranoside in the culture medium to a final concentration of 0.1 mM. The induction was permitted for 10 h at 25&#x000b0;C and cells were harvested by centrifugation at 8000 <italic>g</italic> for 10 min at 4&#x000b0;C. H-Ras was expressed and purified as described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Liao1">[25]</xref>.</p><p>For K-RasB and its mutants, the harvested bacterial pellets from 2 liters of Luria Broth medium was resuspended and lysed in 100 ml of binding buffer (50 mM sodium phosphate buffer containing 500 mM NaCl, 1 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1 mM DTT, and 5 mM GDP, pH 7.8). The clarified supernatants were collected and applied to a Ni-nitrilotriacetic acid-agarose column equilibrated in the binding buffer. The proteins were eluted using elution buffer (50 mM sodium phosphate buffer containing 500 mM NaCl, 1 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1 mM DTT, and 5 mM GDP, pH 7.8) with a gradient of increasing imidazole concentration from 10 to 100 mM. Fractions containing K-RasB, as detected by SDS-PAGE and by UV absorbance, were pooled and diluted 10 times by 20 mM HEPES buffer containing 100 mM NaCl, 1 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1 mM dithiothreitol (DTT), and 5 mM GDP (pH 7.0), and applied to a SP-Sepharose column for K-RasB and its mutants. Proteins were eluted by 150&#x02013;800 mM linear NaCl gradient. His tags were removed by thrombin. K-RasB was loaded with GTP analogue GppNHp by incubation with a 5-fold molar excess of GppNHp prepared as described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-John1">[26]</xref> in the presence of 200 mM ammonium sulfate and 5 units of alkaline phosphatase per mg of protein at 30&#x000b0;C for 2 h. The concentrations of proteins were determined by the calculated extinction coefficient of 20 962 M<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> for K-RasB and K-RasB mutants, and 22 452 M<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> for H-Ras and H-Ras mutants, concerning the amino acid composition of each protein and the binding nucleotide.</p><p>CaM was purified from bovine brain (Hongxing, Wuhan, China) according to Gopalakrishna and Anderson <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Gopalakrishna1">[27]</xref>, using Phenyl Sepharose affinity chromatography as the main purification step. The primary structure of bovine brain CaM is the same as that of human brain CaM. The concentration of CaM was determined by the extinction coefficient of 3006 M<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> in its Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup> saturation state.</p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><italic>In vitro</italic> farnesylation of Ras proteins</title><p><italic>Escherichia coli</italic> DH5&#x003b1; strain containing yeast farnesyl transferase expressing plasmid PGP114-2/1/2 (a kind gift from Prof. Poulter, The University of Utah) was incubated in Super Broth (SB) medium to express farnesyl transferase <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Mayer1">[28]</xref>. The harvested bacterial pellets from 0.5 liter of SB medium was resuspended, lysed in 50 ml of lysis buffer (50 mM HEPES buffer containing 5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 40 mM NaCl, 10 &#x000b5;M ZnSO<sub>4</sub>, 1 mM phenylmethanesulfonyl fluoride, and 1 mM DTT, pH 7.5), and clarified by centrifuge. Purified <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> expressed Ras protein (5 mg), GDP (0.25 mg) and farnesylpyrophosphate (0.25 mg) were added to the clarified lysate and incubated overnight at room temperature. Ras proteins were re-purified from the lysate by the N-terminal hexahistidine tags and were separated from unprocessed Ras proteins by extraction with Triton X-114 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Bordier1">[29]</xref>, followed by the removal of the detergent with Q Sepharose column. About 2 mg of farnesylated Ras proteins were recovered from the original 5 mg of unprocessed starting material.</p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>Cross-linking reactions and Western blot analysis</title><p>Cross-linking reactions were carried out as described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Fancy1">[30]</xref>. Briefly, 50 &#x000b5;M CaM with or without 50 &#x000b5;M K-Ras in a total volume of 18 &#x000b5;l in 20 mM HEPES buffer (pH 7.4) containing 150 mM NaCl, 1 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 1 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 2.5 mM ammonium persulfate, and 0.125 mM Ru(bpy)<sub>3</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub> was placed in a 1.5-ml Eppendorf tube positioned for 1 min parallel to the beam of light from a 150-W common flashlight as the light source. Immediately after irradiation, samples were quenched with 6 &#x000b5;l of 4&#x000d7; loading buffer (250 mM Tris-HCl, pH 6.8, 8&#x00025; SDS, 10 mM EDTA, 2.88 M &#x003b2;-mercaptoethanol, 40&#x00025; glycerol, 2&#x00025; Coomassie brilliant blue G 250, and 2&#x00025; Phenol red), heated to 95&#x000b0;C for 5 min, and then applied to 13.5&#x00025; SDS polyacrylamide gel. CaM was detected by using anti-CaM monoclonal antibody on Western blot.</p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title>Isothermal titration calorimetry</title><p>ITC experiments on the interactions of CaM with K-RasB and its mutants in 20 mM HEPES buffer (pH 7.4) containing 150 mM NaCl, 1 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub> and 1 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub> were carried out at 25.0&#x000b0;C using an iTC<sub>200</sub> titration calorimetry (MicroCal, Northampton, MA). A solution of 20&#x02013;40 &#x000b5;M K-RasB protein was loaded into the sample cell (200 &#x000b5;l), and a solution of 0.3&#x02013;0.8 mM CaM was placed in the injection syringe (40 &#x000b5;l). The first injection (1 &#x000b5;l) was followed by 18 injections of 2 &#x000b5;l. Dilution heats of CaM were measured by injecting CaM solution into buffer alone and were subtracted from the experimental curves prior to data analysis. The stirring rate was 600 rpm. The resulting data were fitted to a single set of identical sites model using MicroCal ORIGIN software supplied with the instrument, and the standard molar enthalpy change for the binding, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0021929.e001.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, the dissociation constant, <italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub>, and the binding stoichiometry, <italic>n</italic>, were thus obtained. The standard molar free energy change, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0021929.e002.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, and the standard molar entropy change, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0021929.e003.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, for the binding reaction were calculated by the fundamental equations of thermodynamics <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-vanHolde1">[31]</xref>:<disp-formula><graphic xlink:href="pone.0021929.e004"/><label>(1)</label></disp-formula><disp-formula><graphic xlink:href="pone.0021929.e005"/><label>(2)</label></disp-formula></p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title>Fluorescence measurements</title><p>Dansyl-CaM was prepared according to the method of Johnson <italic>et al.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Johnson1">[32]</xref>. The bound dye concentration was determined by its absorbance at 335 nm using the molar extinction coefficient value of 3980 M<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Johnson1">[32]</xref>. Measurements of dansyl-CaM fluorescence were performed on an LS-55 luminescence spectrometer (PerkinElmer Life Sciences, Shelton, CT) at 25.0&#x000b0;C. A 0.5-ml solution containing 1 &#x000b5;M dansyl-CaM in 20 mM HEPES buffer (pH 7.4) containing 150 mM NaCl, 1 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub> and 1 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub> was titrated with 0.10&#x02013;10 &#x000b5;l aliquots of K-RasB solution (500&#x02013;100 &#x000b5;M) in the same buffer. Fluorescence spectra were recorded using an excitation wavelength of 335 nm and collecting the fluorescence emission between 420 and 560 nm. Slit widths were set at 5&#x02013;10 nm.</p><p>The dissociation constant (<italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub>) of a ligand to a protein can be calculated according to the following equation:<disp-formula><graphic xlink:href="pone.0021929.e006"/><label>(3)</label></disp-formula>where <italic>C</italic><sub>P,0</sub> is the total concentration of the protein (dansyl-CaM) being titrated, <italic>C</italic><sub>L,0</sub> is the total concentration of the ligand (K-RasB), and <italic>x</italic> represents the proportion of the protein bound by the ligand, which can be calculated according to the following equation:<disp-formula><graphic xlink:href="pone.0021929.e007"/><label>(4)</label></disp-formula>where &#x00394;<italic>F</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;<italic>F</italic>&#x02212;<italic>F</italic><sub>0</sub>, &#x00394;<italic>F</italic><sub>max</sub>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;<italic>F</italic><sub>max</sub>&#x02212;<italic>F</italic><sub>0</sub>, and <italic>F</italic><sub>0</sub>, <italic>F</italic> and <italic>F</italic><sub>max</sub> are the fluorescence intensities of dansylated CaM at 480 nm in the absence and in the presence of K-RasB and with saturating concentration of K-RasB.</p><p>Equations 3 and 4 are combined to deduce Equation 5:<disp-formula><graphic xlink:href="pone.0021929.e008"/><label>(5)</label></disp-formula></p><p>The dissociation constant, <italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub>, and the binding stoichiometry, <italic>n</italic>, were determined by fitting &#x00394;<italic>F</italic>/&#x00394;<italic>F</italic><sub>max</sub> <italic>versus C</italic><sub>L,0</sub> to Equation 5. In this study, the total volume increase during titration was less than 5&#x00025;, so the total concentration of dansyl-CaM was almost constant.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec id="s3a"><title>K-RasB and Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM form a 1&#x02236;1 complex in a GTP dependent manner</title><p>It has been reported that GTP-bound K-RasB interacts with CaM in a calcium dependent manner <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Villalonga1">[18]</xref>. The photolysis of the ruthenium(II) tris-bipyridyl dication ([Ru(II)bpy<sub>3</sub>]<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>) in the presence of ammonium persulfate was explored as a method to generate reactive intermediates that might bring about efficient cross-linking of associated proteins <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Fancy1">[30]</xref>. The bound of Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM to K-RasB was verified by chemical cross-linking using the photolysis of Ru(bpy)<sub>3</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub>. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0021929-g001">Fig. 1</xref>, photolysis resulted in the production of an extra band of about 45 kDa which was detected by anti-CaM antibody, corresponding to the covalently coupled 1&#x02236;1 complex of CaM with K-RasB-GppNHp (lane 5) whereas K-RasB-GDP not (lane 4).</p><fig id="pone-0021929-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0021929.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Photo-initiated cross-linking of the Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM with K-RasB-GDP and K-RasB-GppNHp.</title><p>Samples containing Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM alone (lane 1), Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM and K-RasB-GDP (lane 4), or Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM and K-RasB-GppNHp (lane 5), were irradiated for 1 minute with a 150-W common flashlight as described in &#x0201c;<xref ref-type="sec" rid="s2">Materials and Methods</xref>&#x0201d;. Samples containing Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM and K-RasB-GDP (lane 2), or Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM and K-RasB-GppNHp (lane 3) without Ru(bpy)<sub>3</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub> and irradiation were also conducted as controls. Shown is a Western blot using antibody raised against CaM.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0021929.g001"/></fig><p>The dansyl chomophore covalently bound to CaM is a sensitive probe for studying the interactions between CaM and its binding proteins <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Wu1">[33]</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Zhou2">[35]</xref>. To quantify the interaction between K-RasB and CaM, we carried out dansyl-CaM fluorescence titration experiments. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0021929-g002">Fig. 2A</xref>, the addition of K-RasB-GppNHp to Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>-saturated dansyl-CaM caused a significant increase in danysl fluorescence intensity and a pronounced blue shift of the fluorescence emission maximum from 504 to 479 nm, indicating that the dansyl group was located in a more hydrophobic environment in the complex than that in CaM alone. However no fluorescence change of dansyl-CaM was observed upon the addition of K-RasB-GppNHp in the absence of Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>, supporting the conclusion that the interaction between K-RasB and CaM was Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup> dependent (data not shown). As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0021929-g002">Fig. 2B</xref>, about 90&#x00025; of the saturation was reached when 8 &#x000b5;M K-RasB-GppNHp was added into Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM solution. The fluorescence titration data of Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM with K-RasB-GppNHp resulted in dissociation constants of 0.90&#x000b1;0.02 &#x000b5;M at physiological pH and physiologic ionic strength, as well as a 1&#x02236;1 CaM/K-RasB binding mode (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0021929-g002">Fig. 2B</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0021929-t001">Table 1</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0021929-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0021929.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Interaction of K-RasB with Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM at 25.0&#x000b0;C.</title><p>Fluorescence spectra (A) of 1.0 &#x000b5;M dansyl-CaM in the absence and in the presence of K-RasB-GppNHp at different concentrations. The arrow represents the concentration of K-RasB-GppNHp increases gradually from 0 (the bottom) to 8.0 &#x000b5;M (the top). &#x00394;<italic>F</italic>/&#x00394;<italic>F</italic><sub>max</sub> for the binding of K-RasB-GppNHp to Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM plotted as a function of the concentration of K-RasB-GppNHp (B). The solid squares were the experimental data and the solid line represented the best fit. The panel C represents typical calorimetric titration of K-RasB-GppNHp (20.0 &#x000b5;M) with CaM (300 &#x000b5;M) in the presence of 1 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>. The panel D shows the plots of the heat evolved (kcal) per mole of CaM added, corrected for the heat of CaM, against the molar ratio of CaM to K-RasB. The data (solid squares) were fitted to a single set of identical sites model and the solid line represented the best fit. The corresponding parameters from B and D are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0021929-t001">Table 1</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0021929.g002"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone-0021929-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0021929.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Thermodynamic parameters for the binding of Ras proteins to Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM as determined by ITC (<italic>A</italic>) and dansyl-CaM fluorescence titration (<italic>B</italic>) at 25.0&#x000b0;C.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0021929-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0021929.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ras Proteins</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub> by <italic>A</italic> (&#x000b5;M)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>n</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0021929.e009.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> (kcal mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0021929.e010.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> (kcal mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0021929.e011.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> (cal mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> K<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub> by <italic>B</italic> (&#x000b5;M)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K-RasB</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10&#x000b1;0.12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.924&#x000b1;0.013</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.63&#x000b1;0.72</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;8.12&#x000b1;0.07</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.4&#x000b1;0.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90&#x000b1;0.02</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K-RasB-farn</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39&#x000b1;0.16</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.13&#x000b1;0.01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.33&#x000b1;0.11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;8.73&#x000b1;0.10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.4&#x000b1;0.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17&#x000b1;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K-RasB-K175A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.54&#x000b1;0.84</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.995&#x000b1;0.032</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.48&#x000b1;0.11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;7.07&#x000b1;0.08</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.0&#x000b1;0.7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.26&#x000b1;0.07</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K-RasB-K175A-farn</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.60&#x000b1;0.23</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.972&#x000b1;0.039</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01&#x000b1;0.55</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;7.90&#x000b1;0.09</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.9&#x000b1;2.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02&#x000b1;0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H-Ras-(KKKKKK)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.89&#x000b1;0.45</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.903&#x000b1;0.022</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.16&#x000b1;0.21</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;7.38&#x000b1;0.07</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.4&#x000b1;1.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.53&#x000b1;0.18</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H-Ras</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NB</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NB</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K-RasB-(DESGPC)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NB</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NB</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p>The value of <italic>n</italic> was also determined as 1.0 for the binding of K-RasB to Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM by using Cross-linking.</p></fn><fn id="nt102"><label/><p>NB, no binding observed in the present conditions.</p></fn><fn id="nt103"><label/><p>Thermodynamic parameters, <italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0021929.e012.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, and <italic>n</italic>, were determined using a single set of identical sites model. The standard molar binding free energy (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0021929.e013.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>) and the standard molar binding entropy (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0021929.e014.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>) for the binding reaction were calculated using Equations 1 and 2 respectively. The buffer used was 20 mM HEPES buffer (pH 7.4) containing 150 mM NaCl, 1 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>, and 1 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>. Errors shown are standard errors of the mean.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>ITC is thought to be one of the most reliable and high-precision methods to quantitate noncovalent, equilibrium protein interactions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Liang1">[36]</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Zhu1">[38]</xref>. By using ITC, we obtained thermodynamic parameters for the interaction between Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>-saturated CaM and K-RasB proteins. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0021929-g002">Fig. 2C</xref> shows raw ITC curve resulting from the injections of Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>-saturated CaM into K-RasB-GppNHp solution. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0021929-g002">Fig. 2D</xref> shows the plots of the heat evolved per mole of CaM added, corrected for the heat of CaM dilution, against the molar ratio of CaM to K-RasB. The calorimetric data were best fit to a model assuming a single set of identical sites. The thermodynamic parameters for the binding of full-length K-RasB to Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0021929-t001">Table 1</xref>. As shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0021929-t001">Table 1</xref>, one K-RasB molecule interacted with one CaM molecule in a GTP dependent manner with moderate, micromolar affinity at physiological pH and physiologic ionic strength. The binding reactions were driven entirely by large favorable increases in entropy. Our ITC and fluorescence data (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0021929-t001">Table 1</xref>) clearly indicated that at physiological pH, the GTP bound form of full-length K-RasB and Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM formed a 1&#x02236;1 complex with an equilibrium association constant around 10<sup>6</sup> M<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>.</p></sec><sec id="s3b"><title>The polylysine region of K-RasB contributes importantly to the interaction of K-RasB with Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM</title><p>As a general rule, CaM binding regions in proteins are characterized by the presence of several hydrophobic residues interspersed with a number of positively charged residues (lysine and arginine) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-BofillCardona1">[39]</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Crivici1">[41]</xref>. To narrow down the key element of the interaction in the HVR of K-RasB, we evaluated the effects of lysine residues in the C-terminal polylysine region of K-RasB on the interaction between K-RasB and CaM by using dansyl-CaM fluorescence titration and ITC. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0021929-g003">Fig. 3, A and B</xref>, only 65&#x00025; of the saturation was reached when 8 &#x000b5;M K-RasB-K175A-GppNHp was added into Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>-saturated dansyl-CaM solution, indicating that single mutation of a lysine residue, Lys-175, to alanine in C-terminal polylysine region of K-RasB resulted in a 6-fold decrease in the binding affinity. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0021929-g003">Fig. 3C</xref> shows raw ITC curves resulting from the injections of Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>-saturated CaM into K-RasB-K175A-GppNHp solution. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0021929-g003">Fig. 3D</xref> displays the plots of the heat evolved per mole of CaM added, corrected for the heat of CaM dilution, against the molar ratio of CaM to K-RasB-K175A. The calorimetric data were best fit to a single set of identical sites model. The thermodynamic parameters for the binding of K-RasB-K175A to Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0021929-t001">Table 1</xref>. Clearly, at physiological pH, one K-RasB mutant molecule, interacted with one CaM molecule with markedly lower affinity than wild-type K-RasB (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0021929-t001">Table 1</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0021929-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0021929.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Interaction of K-RasB-K175A with Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM at 25.0&#x000b0;C.</title><p>Fluorescence spectra (A) of 1.0 &#x000b5;M dansyl-CaM in the absence and in the presence of K-RasB-K175A-GppNHp at different concentrations. The arrow represents the concentration of K-RasB-K175A increases gradually from 0 (the bottom) to 14.0 &#x000b5;M (the top). &#x00394;<italic>F</italic>/&#x00394;<italic>F</italic><sub>max</sub> for the binding of K-RasB-K175A to Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM plotted as a function of the concentration of K-RasB-K175A (B). The solid squares were the experimental data and the solid line represented the best fit. The panel C represents typical calorimetric titration of K-RasB-K175A (35.0 &#x000b5;M) with CaM (800 &#x000b5;M) in the presence of 1 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>. The panel D shows the plots of the heat evolved (kcal) per mole of CaM added, corrected for the heat of CaM, against the molar ratio of CaM to K-RasB-K175A. The data (solid squares) were fitted to a single set of identical sites model and the solid line represented the best fit. The corresponding parameters from B and D are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0021929-t001">Table 1</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0021929.g003"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3c"><title>The C-terminal polylysine region of K-RasB defines the specificity of the interaction of K-RasB with Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM</title><p>To better understand the role of the C-terminal polylysine region of K-RasB in the interaction between K-RasB and CaM, we exchanged the polylysine region of K-RasB-(175&#x02013;180), KKKKKK, with the corresponding sequence of H-Ras-(175&#x02013;180), DESGPC, and created two chimeric Ras proteins, K-RasB-(DESGPC) and H-Ras-(KKKKKK). The top panels in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0021929-g004">Fig. 4</xref> representatively show raw ITC curves resulting from the injections of Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>-saturated CaM into GppNHp form of H-Ras (Panel A), K-RasB-(DESGPC) (Panel B) and H-Ras-(KKKKKK) (Panel C) solutions. The bottom panels in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0021929-g004">Fig. 4</xref> show the plots of the heat evolved per mole of CaM added, corrected for the heat of CaM dilution, against the molar ratio of CaM to Ras proteins. The calorimetric data were best fit to a single set of identical sites model. The thermodynamic parameters for the binding of these two chimeric Ras proteins to Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0021929-t001">Table 1</xref>. As shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0021929-t001">Table 1</xref>, at physiological pH, H-Ras-(KKKKKK) and Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM formed a 1&#x02236;1 complex with an equilibrium association constant around 10<sup>5</sup> M<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. It has been reported that CaM binds to K-RasB, but not to H-Ras <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Villalonga1">[18]</xref>. In the present study, we designed a K-RasB mutant unable to bind to CaM and thus defined the molecular determinants of CaM-K-RasB interaction. Similar to wild-type H-Ras, no binding reaction of K-RasB-(DESGPC) with Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM was detected by ITC and dansyl-CaM fluorescence titration (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0021929-t001">Table 1</xref>), demonstrating that the C-terminal polylysine region of K-RasB and the corresponding sequence of H-Ras, DESGPC, are the key sequences for CaM binding to K-RasB but not to H-Ras. The C-terminal polylysine region of K-RasB defines the specificity of the interaction of K-RasB with Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM.</p><fig id="pone-0021929-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0021929.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Interaction of H-Ras, K-RasB-(DESGPC), and H-Ras-(KKKKKK) with Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM at 25.0&#x000b0;C.</title><p>The panels A, B, and C represent typical calorimetric titration of H-Ras-GppNHp (30.0 &#x000b5;M), K-RasB-(DESGPC)-GppNHp (25.0 &#x000b5;M) and H-Ras-(KKKKKK)-GppNHp (25.0 &#x000b5;M) with CaM (300 &#x000b5;M) respectively in the presence of 1 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>. The panels D, E, and F show the plots of the heat evolved (kcal) per mole of CaM added, corrected for the heat of CaM, against the molar ratio of CaM to Ras proteins. The data (solid squares) were fitted to a single set of identical sites model and the solid line represented the best fit.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0021929.g004"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3d"><title>The farnesylation of K-RasB is important for its specific interaction with Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM</title><p>Plasma membrane association of Ras proteins requires posttranslational modification by C-terminal farnesylation. Here, we prepared fanesylated K-RasB <italic>in vitro</italic> and investigated the role of farnesylation of K-RasB in its interaction with Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM by fluorescence titration and ITC. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0021929-g005">Figs. 5A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0021929-g006">6A</xref>, titration of K-RasB-farn or K-RasB-K175A-farn into Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>-saturated dansyl-CaM caused a significant increase in danysl fluorescence intensity and a pronounced blue shift of the fluorescence emission maximum from 498 (or 499) to 471 (or 474) nm. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0021929-g005">Figs. 5B</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0021929-g006">6B</xref>, the fluorescence titration data of Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM with K-RasB-farn and K-RasB-K175A-farn resulted in dissociation constants of 0.17&#x000b1;0.01 and 1.02&#x000b1;0.03 &#x000b5;M, respectively, 5- and 4-fold increases in the binding affinity compared with their unprocessed precursors (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0021929-g005">Figs. 5B</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0021929-g006">6B</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0021929-t001">Table 1</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0021929-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0021929.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Interaction of farnesylated K-RasB with Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM at 25.0&#x000b0;C.</title><p>Fluorescence spectra (A) of 1.0 &#x000b5;M dansyl-CaM in the absence and in the presence of GppNHp bound K-RasB-farn at different concentrations. The arrow represents the concentration of K-RasB-farn increases gradually from 0 (the bottom) to 3.3 &#x000b5;M (the top). &#x00394;<italic>F</italic>/&#x00394;<italic>F</italic><sub>max</sub> for the binding of K-RasB-farn to Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM plotted as a function of the concentration of K-RasB-farn (B). The solid squares were the experimental data and the solid line represented the best fit. The panel C represents typical calorimetric titration of K-RasB-farn (30.0 &#x000b5;M) with CaM (600 &#x000b5;M) in the presence of 1 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>. The panel D shows the plots of the heat evolved (kcal) per mole of CaM added, corrected for the heat of CaM, against the molar ratio of CaM to K-RasB. The data (solid squares) were fitted to a single set of identical sites model and the solid line represented the best fit. The corresponding parameters from B and D are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0021929-t001">Table 1</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0021929.g005"/></fig><fig id="pone-0021929-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0021929.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Interaction of farnesylated K-RasB-K175A with Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM at 25.0&#x000b0;C.</title><p>Fluorescence spectra (A) of 1.0 &#x000b5;M dansyl-CaM in the absence and in the presence of GppNHp bound K-RasB-K175A-farn at different concentrations. The arrow represents the concentration of K-RasB-K175A-farn increases gradually from 0 (the bottom) to 8.4 &#x000b5;M (the top). &#x00394;<italic>F</italic>/&#x00394;<italic>F</italic><sub>max</sub> for the binding of K-RasB-K175A-farn to Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM plotted as a function of the concentration of K-RasB-K175A-farn (B). The solid squares were the experimental data and the solid line represented the best fit. The panel C represents typical calorimetric titration of K-RasB-K175A-farn (25.0 &#x000b5;M) with CaM (600 &#x000b5;M) in the presence of 1 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>. The panel D shows the plots of the heat evolved (kcal) per mole of CaM added, corrected for the heat of CaM, against the molar ratio of CaM to K-RasB. The data (solid squares) were fitted to a single set of identical sites model and the solid line represented the best fit. The corresponding parameters from B and D are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0021929-t001">Table 1</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0021929.g006"/></fig><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0021929-g005">Figs. 5C</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0021929-g006">6C</xref> respectively show raw ITC curves resulting from the injections of Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>-saturated CaM into K-RasB-farn and K-RasB-K175A-farn solutions. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0021929-g005">Figs. 5D</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0021929-g006">6D</xref> show the plots of the heat evolved per mole of CaM added, corrected for the heat of CaM dilution, against the molar ratio of CaM to K-RasB. The calorimetric data were best fit to a model assuming a single set of identical sites. The thermodynamic parameters for the binding of K-RasB-farn and K-RasB-K175A-farn to Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM are also summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0021929-t001">Table 1</xref>. According to the ITC data, K-RasB-farn and K-RasB-K175A-farn bound to Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM with 3- and 4-fold increases in the binding affinity compared with their unprocessed precursors, which is consistent with the fluorescence titration data. Clearly, the farnesylation of K-RasB is important for its specific interaction with Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0021929-t001">Table 1</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>It has been reported that the binding of K-RasB to Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM is specific and only K-RasB but not other isoforms of Ras proteins interacts with Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Fivaz1">[22]</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Abraham1">[24]</xref>. Therefore, there may be sequences lying in HVR of H-Ras that inhibit the interaction with Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM, while the corresponding sequence of K-RasB not. In the present study, we demonstrated that the polylysine region of K-RasB not only contributed importantly to the interaction of K-RasB with Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM, but also defined its isoform specific interaction with Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM.</p><p>CaM is a ubiquitous protein that can regulate a number of different eukaryotic enzymes in a variety of cellular locations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Ikura1">[42]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Weinstein1">[43]</xref>. It is a dumb bell shaped protein molecule with two EF-hand motifs connected by a small antiparallel &#x003b2;-sheet between the two loops. Calcium binding results in the exposure of two hydrophobic pockets for target protein binding, surrounded by negatively charged residues <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Kuboniwa1">[44]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Zhang1">[45]</xref>. Although the sequence identity among the CaM target sequences is low, all of the consensus peptides for such sequences posses common features, including their ability to form amphipathic &#x003b1;-helices containing several positively charged residues <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Weinstein1">[43]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Kuboniwa1">[44]</xref>. In other words, CaM target sequences are characterized by the presence of several positively charged residues such as lysine. The present study demonstrated that the C-terminal polylysine region of K-RasB contributes importantly to the interaction of K-RasB with Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM and that H-Ras mutant containing such a polylysine region is able to bind to Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM. Therefore, this polylysine region could be a new CaM target sequence. Several studies have demonstrated that the positively charged residues in CaM binding proteins interact strongly with the negatively charged residues in CaM <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Hoeflich1">[40]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Crivici1">[41]</xref>. Our work continues the story of the possible role of electrostatic interactions in forming protein-CaM complexes. We found a strong salt concentration dependence of the dissociation constant of K-RasB binding to CaM as determined by dansyl-CaM fluorescence titration at 25.0&#x000b0;C (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0021929-t002">Table 2</xref>). At physiologic ionic strength (150 mM), the equilibrium association constant was determined to be around 10<sup>6</sup> M<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, and the data at 1.0 M NaCl afforded the nonionic contribution <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Hileman1">[46]</xref>. As shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0021929-t002">Table 2</xref>, the binding affinity of K-RasB for CaM was found to decrease significantly with increasing salt concentration, and the equilibrium association constant was smaller than 10<sup>5</sup> M<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> as detected by dansyl-CaM fluorescence titration when NaCl concentration increased up to 1.0 M, suggesting that long-range electrostatic interactions between the polylysine region of K-RasB and the negatively charged residues in CaM are important but not essential for the interaction between K-RasB and CaM.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0021929-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0021929.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Salt concentration dependence of the dissociation constants of K-Ras K-Ras-farn binding to CaM as determined by dansyl-CaM fluorescence titration at 25.0&#x000b0;C.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0021929-t002-2" xlink:href="pone.0021929.t002"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[NaCl] (M)</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"><italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub> (&#x000b5;M)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K-RasB</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K-RasB-farn</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52&#x000b1;0.02</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15&#x000b1;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90&#x000b1;0.02</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17&#x000b1;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.11&#x000b1;0.10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25&#x000b1;0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.80&#x000b1;0.22</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36&#x000b1;0.06</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.68&#x000b1;0.54</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78&#x000b1;0.08</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.4&#x000b1;2.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.47&#x000b1;0.16</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.5&#x000b1;3.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.05&#x000b1;0.19</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt104"><label/><p>The buffer used was 20 mM HEPES buffer (pH 7.4) containing 0.10&#x02013;1.0 M NaCl, 1 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>, and 1 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>. Errors shown are standard errors of the mean.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Plasma membrane association of Ras proteins requires posttranslational modification such as geranylgeranylation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Sidhu2">[47]</xref> and C-terminal farnesylation. Here we demonstrated that the farnesylation of K-RasB is important for its specific interaction with Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM. The contribution of the farnesylation of K-RasB to the interaction became big in the presence of high concentrations of salt. As shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0021929.s001">Table S1</xref>, with increasing salt concentration, the binding affinity of unprocessed K-RasB for CaM decreased significantly but that of farnesylated K-RasB for CaM decreased less significantly, once again demonstrated that the farnesylation of K-RasB is important for its specific interaction with Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM.</p><p>The fate of K-RasB is different from that of the other isoforms such as H-Ras because of the unique presence of a polybasic, lysine-rich region in its HVR. Such a region is responsible for the stable association of K-RasB to the inner plasma membrane <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Potenza1">[48]</xref>. Potenza <italic>et al.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Potenza1">[48]</xref> have indicated that the K-RasB-mediated signals required for the completion of embryonic development can also be transduced by H-Ras, whereas the physiology of the cardiovascular system seems to specifically require a K-RasB generated signal, highlighting a unique role for K-RasB in cardiovascular homeostasis. Because the first 85 amino acids of all of the Ras isoforms are identical and covers the site of interaction with all known Ras effectors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Omerovic1">[49]</xref>, the unique role of K-RasB could due to its localization and activity regulation different from the other isoforms. It has been reported that CaM binds to K-RasB, but not to H-Ras, modulating its downstream signaling <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Villalonga1">[18]</xref>, causing dissociation of only K-RasB from membranes in a Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>-dependent manner that could result in its translocation to distinct regions of the cell and activation of diverse signaling pathways <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-Sidhu1">[20]</xref>. CaM inhibits K-RasB phosphorylation at Ser 181 and consequently modulates the functionality of both the wild type and the oncogenic form of K-RasB <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021929-AlvarezMoya1">[50]</xref>. We demonstrated for the first time that the C-terminal polylysine region of K-RasB is the molecular determinant for CaM binding to K-RasB but not to H-Ras. Such a polylysine region could play an important role in the novel biological function of K-RasB to control cardiovascular homeostasis.</p><p>In conclusion we have shown that: (i) one K-RasB molecule interacts with one CaM molecule with moderate, micromolar affinity in physiological conditions, and the binding is GTP dependent; (ii) polylysine region of K-RasB contributes importantly to the interaction of K-RasB with Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM; (iii) the polylysine region of K-RasB defines the specificity of the interaction of K-RasB with Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM; (iv) the fanesylation of K-RasB increases the binding affinity of K-RasB for Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/CaM. Information obtained here can enhance our understanding of how CaM interacts with K-RasB in physiological environments.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0021929.s001"><label>Table S1</label><caption><p><bold>Salt concentration dependence of the dissociation constants of K-Ras K-Ras-farn binding to CaM as determined by dansyl-CaM fluorescence titration at 25.0&#x000b0;C.</bold> The buffer used was 20 mM HEPES buffer (pH 7.4) containing 0.10&#x02013;1.0 M NaCl, 1 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>, and 1 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>. Errors shown are standard errors of the mean.</p><p>(DOC)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0021929.s001.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors sincerely thank Prof. Yoav Henis (Department of Neurobiochemistry, Tel Aviv University) for kindly providing pEGFP-C3-K-RasB plasmids and Prof. Poulter (Department of Chemistry, University of Utah) for the gift of PGP-114-2/1/2 plasmid. The authors also thank Prof. Guang-Fu Yang (College of Chemistry, Central China Normal University) for his technical assistance on iTC<sub>200</sub>.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="conflict"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding: </bold>This study was supported by National Key Basic Research Foundation of China (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.most.gov.cn/">http://www.most.gov.cn/</ext-link>, Grant no. 2006CB910301, YL), National Natural Science Foundation of China (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nsfc.gov.cn/">http://www.nsfc.gov.cn/</ext-link>, Grant nos. 30970599 and 30770421, YL), and Fundamental Research Funds for the Central Universities (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.moe.edu.cn/">http://www.moe.edu.cn/</ext-link>, Grant no. 1104006, YL). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0021929-Barbacid1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barbacid</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1987</year>             <article-title>ras genes.</article-title>             <source>Annu Rev Biochem</source>             <volume>56</volume>             <fpage>779</fpage>             <lpage>827</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3304147</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0021929-Bos1"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bos</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1989</year>             <article-title>ras oncogenes in human cancer: a review.</article-title>             <source>Cancer Res</source>             <volume>49</volume>             <fpage>4682</fpage>             <lpage>4689</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2547513</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0021929-Downward1"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Downward</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Targeting Ras signalling pathways in cancer therapy.</article-title>             <source>Nat Rev Cancer</source>             <volume>3</volume>             <fpage>11</fpage>             <lpage>22</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12509763</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0021929-Hancock1"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hancock</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Ras proteins:different signals from different locations.</article-title>             <source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source>             <volume>4</volume>             <fpage>373</fpage>             <lpage>384</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12728271</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0021929-Klee1"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klee</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Crouch</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>Richman</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1980</year>             <article-title>Calmodulin.</article-title>             <source>Annu Rev Biochem</source>             <volume>49</volume>             <fpage>489</fpage>             <lpage>515</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6250447</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0021929-Wes1"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wes</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Montell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1996</year>             <article-title>RIC, a calmodulin-binding Ras-like GTPase.</article-title>             <source>EMBO J</source>             <volume>15</volume>             <fpage>5839</fpage>             <lpage>5848</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8918462</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0021929-Hoshino1"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoshino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Small GTPase Rin induces neurite outgrowth through Rac/Cdc42 and calmodulin in PC12 cells.</article-title>             <source>J Cell Biol</source>             <volume>163</volume>             <fpage>1067</fpage>             <lpage>1076</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14662747</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0021929-Fischer1"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Anagli</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Berchtold</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1996</year>             <article-title>Calmodulin binds to and inhibits GTP binding of the Ras-like GTPase Kir/Gem.</article-title>             <source>J Biol Chem</source>             <volume>271</volume>             <fpage>25067</fpage>             <lpage>25070</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8810259</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0021929-Moyers1"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moyers</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bilan</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kahn</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1997</year>             <article-title>Rad and Rad-related GTPases interact with calmodulin and calmodulin-dependent protein kinase II.</article-title>             <source>J Biol Chem</source>             <volume>272</volume>             <fpage>11832</fpage>             <lpage>11839</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9115241</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0021929-Bguin1"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>B&#x000e9;guin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagashima</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonoi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Shibasaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>Regulation of Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup> channel expression at the cell surface by the small G-protein Kir/Gem.</article-title>             <source>Nature</source>             <volume>411</volume>             <fpage>701</fpage>             <lpage>706</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11395774</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0021929-Bguin2"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>B&#x000e9;guin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahalakshmi</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagashima</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Cher</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuwamura</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Roles of 14-3-3and calmodulin binding in subcellular localization and function of the small G-protein Rem2.</article-title>             <source>Biochem J</source>             <volume>390</volume>             <fpage>67</fpage>             <lpage>75</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15862114</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0021929-Bguin3"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>B&#x000e9;guin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahalakshmi</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagashima</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Cher</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikeda</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Nuclear sequestration of &#x003b2;-subunits by Rad and Rem is controlled by 14-3-3 and calmodulin and reveals a novel mechanism for Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup> channel regulation.</article-title>             <source>J Mol Biol</source>             <volume>355</volume>             <fpage>34</fpage>             <lpage>46</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16298391</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0021929-Wang1"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Roufogalis</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1997</year>             <article-title>Identification and characterization of a calmodulin-binding domain in Ral-A, a Ras-related GTP-binding protein purified from human erythrocyte membrane.</article-title>             <source>J Biol Chem</source>             <volume>272</volume>             <fpage>16002</fpage>             <lpage>16009</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9188503</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0021929-Wang2"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Roufogalis</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/calmodulin stimulates GTP binding to the ras-related protein Ral-A.</article-title>             <source>J Biol Chem</source>             <volume>274</volume>             <fpage>14525</fpage>             <lpage>14528</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10329639</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0021929-Park1"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>Dissociation of RalA from synaptic membranes by Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/calmodulin.</article-title>             <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source>             <volume>263</volume>             <fpage>765</fpage>             <lpage>769</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10512754</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0021929-Park2"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Farnsworth</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Glomset</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1997</year>             <article-title>Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/calmodulin causes Rab3A to dissociate from synaptic membranes.</article-title>             <source>J Biol Chem</source>             <volume>272</volume>             <fpage>20857</fpage>             <lpage>20865</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9252412</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0021929-Park3"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>GTP binds to Rab3A in a complex with Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/calmodulin.</article-title>             <source>Biochem J</source>             <volume>362</volume>             <fpage>651</fpage>             <lpage>657</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11879192</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0021929-Villalonga1"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Villalonga</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopez-Alcal&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bosch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiloeches</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rocamora</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>Calmodulin binds to K-Ras, but not to H- or N-Ras, and modulates its downstream signaling.</article-title>             <source>Mol Cell Biol</source>             <volume>21</volume>             <fpage>7345</fpage>             <lpage>7354</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11585916</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0021929-Villalonga2"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Villalonga</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopez-Alcal&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiloeches</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gil</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Marais</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Calmodulin prevents activation of Ras by PKC in 3T3 fibroblasts.</article-title>             <source>J Biol Chem</source>             <volume>277</volume>             <fpage>37929</fpage>             <lpage>37935</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12151388</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0021929-Sidhu1"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sidhu</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Clough</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhullar</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/calmodulin binds and dissociates K-RasB from membrane.</article-title>             <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source>             <volume>304</volume>             <fpage>655</fpage>             <lpage>660</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12727204</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0021929-Ashery1"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ashery</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Yizhar</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Rotblat</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kloog</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Nonconventional trafficking of Ras associated with Ras signal organization.</article-title>             <source>Traffic</source>             <volume>7</volume>             <fpage>119</fpage>             <lpage>126</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16824054</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0021929-Fivaz1"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fivaz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Reversible intracellular translocation of KRas but not HRas in hippocampal neurons regulated by Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>/calmodulin.</article-title>             <source>J Cell Biol</source>             <volume>170</volume>             <fpage>429</fpage>             <lpage>441</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16043511</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0021929-LpezAlcal1"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>L&#x000f3;pez-Alcal&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Alvarez-Moya</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Villalonga</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Calvo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bachs</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Identification of essential interacting elements in K-Ras/calmodulin binding and its role in K-Ras localization.</article-title>             <source>J Biol Chem</source>             <volume>283</volume>             <fpage>10621</fpage>             <lpage>10631</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18182391</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0021929-Abraham1"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Nolet</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Calvert</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaponenko</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>The Hypervariable region of K-Ras4B is responsible for its specific interactions with calmodulin.</article-title>             <source>Biochemistry</source>             <volume>48</volume>             <fpage>7575</fpage>             <lpage>7583</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19583261</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0021929-Liao1"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mo</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Binding of calcium ions to Ras promotes Ras guanine nucleotide exchange under emulated physiological conditions.</article-title>             <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source>             <volume>1784</volume>             <fpage>1560</fpage>             <lpage>1569</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18790720</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0021929-John1"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>John</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sohmen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Feuerstein</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Linke</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wittinghofer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>1990</year>             <article-title>Kinetics of interaction of nucleotides with nucleotide-free H-ras p21.</article-title>             <source>Biochemistry</source>             <volume>29</volume>             <fpage>6058</fpage>             <lpage>6065</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2200519</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0021929-Gopalakrishna1"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gopalakrishna</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1982</year>             <article-title>Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>-induced hydrophobic site on calmodulin: application for purification of calmodulin by phenyl-sepharose affinity chromatography.</article-title>             <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source>             <volume>104</volume>             <fpage>830</fpage>             <lpage>836</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6803791</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0021929-Mayer1"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mayer</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Prestwich</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolence</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bond</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>1993</year>             <article-title>Protein farnesyltransferase: production in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> and immunoaffinity purification of the heterodimer from Saccharomyces cerevisiae.</article-title>             <source>Gene</source>             <volume>132</volume>             <fpage>41</fpage>             <lpage>47</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8406041</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0021929-Bordier1"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bordier</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1981</year>             <article-title>Phase separation of integral membrane proteins in Triton X-114 solution.</article-title>             <source>J Biol Chem</source>             <volume>256</volume>             <fpage>1604</fpage>             <lpage>1607</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6257680</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0021929-Fancy1"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fancy</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kodadek</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>Chemistry for the analysis of protein-protein interactions: Rapid and efficient cross-linking triggered by long wavelength light.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>             <volume>96</volume>             <fpage>6020</fpage>             <lpage>6024</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10339534</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0021929-vanHolde1"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="other">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Holde</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Principles of Physical Biochemistry</article-title>             <fpage>91</fpage>             <lpage>93</lpage>             <comment>Pearson Prentice Hall, Upper Saddle River, New Jersey</comment>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0021929-Johnson1"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Wittenauer</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1983</year>             <article-title>A fluorescent calmodulin that reports the binding of hydrophobic inhibitory ligands.</article-title>             <source>Biochem J</source>             <volume>211</volume>             <fpage>473</fpage>             <lpage>479</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6870843</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0021929-Wu1"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanson</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Francis</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Vishnivetskiy</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Thibonnier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Arrestin binding to calmodulin: A direct interaction between two ubiquitous signaling proteins.</article-title>             <source>J Mol Biol</source>             <volume>364</volume>             <fpage>955</fpage>             <lpage>963</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17054984</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0021929-Zhou1"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Lurtz</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Identification of the calmodulin binding domain of connexin.</article-title>             <source>J Biol Chem</source>             <volume>282</volume>             <fpage>35005</fpage>             <lpage>35017</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17901047</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0021929-Zhou2"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Lurtz</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Calmodulin mediates the Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>-dependent regulation of Cx44 gap junctions.</article-title>             <source>Biophys J</source>             <volume>96</volume>             <fpage>2832</fpage>             <lpage>2848</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19348766</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0021929-Liang1"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanglier</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Unfolding of rabbit muscle creatine kinase induced by acid A study using electrospray ionization mass spectrometry, isothermal titration calorimetry, and fluorescence spectroscopy.</article-title>             <source>J Biol Chem</source>             <volume>278</volume>             <fpage>30098</fpage>             <lpage>30105</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12771138</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0021929-Mo1"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mo</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>YZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Low micromolar zinc accelerates the fibrillization of human Tau via bridging of Cys-291 and Cys-322.</article-title>             <source>J Biol Chem</source>             <volume>284</volume>             <fpage>34648</fpage>             <lpage>34657</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19826005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0021929-Zhu1"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Shewmaker</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Quantitative characterization of heparin binding to Tau protein Implication for inducer-mediated Tau filament formation.</article-title>             <source>J Biol Chem</source>             <volume>285</volume>             <fpage>3592</fpage>             <lpage>3599</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19959468</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0021929-BofillCardona1"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bofill-Cardona</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kudlacek</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahorn</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Freissmuth</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>Binding of calmodulin to the D<sub>2</sub>-dopamine receptor reduces receptor signaling by arresting the G protein activation switch.</article-title>             <source>J Biol Chem</source>             <volume>275</volume>             <fpage>32672</fpage>             <lpage>32680</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10926927</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0021929-Hoeflich1"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoeflich</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Calmodulin in action: diversity in target recognition and activation mechanisms.</article-title>             <source>Cell</source>             <volume>108</volume>             <fpage>739</fpage>             <lpage>742</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11955428</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0021929-Crivici1"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crivici</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1995</year>             <article-title>Molecular and structural basis of target recognition by calmodulin.</article-title>             <source>Annu Rev Biophys Biomol Struct</source>             <volume>24</volume>             <fpage>85</fpage>             <lpage>116</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7663132</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0021929-Ikura1"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ikura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1996</year>             <article-title>Calcium binding and conformational response in EF-hand proteins.</article-title>             <source>Trends Biochem Sci</source>             <volume>21</volume>             <fpage>14</fpage>             <lpage>17</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8848832</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0021929-Weinstein1"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weinstein</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Mehler</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1994</year>             <article-title>Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>-binding and structural dynamics in the functions of calmodulin.</article-title>             <source>Annu Rev Physiol</source>             <volume>56</volume>             <fpage>213</fpage>             <lpage>236</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8010740</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0021929-Kuboniwa1"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuboniwa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tjandra</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Grzesiek</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Klee</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>1995</year>             <article-title>Solution structure of calcium-free calmodulin.</article-title>             <source>Nat Struct Biol</source>             <volume>9</volume>             <fpage>768</fpage>             <lpage>776</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7552748</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0021929-Zhang1"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1995</year>             <article-title>Calcium-induced conformational transition revealed by the solution structure of apo-calmodulin.</article-title>             <source>Nat Struct Biol</source>             <volume>2</volume>             <fpage>758</fpage>             <lpage>767</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7552747</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0021929-Hileman1"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hileman</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Jennings</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Linhardt</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1998</year>             <article-title>Thermodynamic analysis of the heparin interaction with a basic cyclic peptide using isothermal titration calorimetry.</article-title>             <source>Biochemistry</source>             <volume>37</volume>             <fpage>15231</fpage>             <lpage>15237</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9790687</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0021929-Sidhu2"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sidhu</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Elsaraj</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Grujic</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhullar</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Calmodulin binding to the small GTPase Ral requires isoprenylated Ral.</article-title>             <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source>             <volume>336</volume>             <fpage>105</fpage>             <lpage>109</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16125679</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0021929-Potenza1"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Potenza</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Vecchione</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Notte</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>De Rienzo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosica</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Replacement of K-Ras with H-Ras supports normal embryonic development despite inducing cardiovascular pathology in adult mice.</article-title>             <source>EMBO Rep</source>             <volume>6</volume>             <fpage>432</fpage>             <lpage>437</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15864294</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0021929-Omerovic1"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Omerovic</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Laude</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Prior</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Ras proteins: paradigms for compartmentalised and isoform-specific signalling.</article-title>             <source>Cell Mol Life Sci</source>             <volume>64</volume>             <fpage>2575</fpage>             <lpage>2589</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17628742</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0021929-AlvarezMoya1"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alvarez-Moya</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x000f3;pez-Alcal&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Drosten</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bachs</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Agell</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>K-Ras4B phosphorylation at Ser181 is inhibited by calmodulin and modulates K-Ras activity and function.</article-title>             <source>Oncogene</source>             <volume>29</volume>             <fpage>5911</fpage>             <lpage>22</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20802526</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>