<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22523552</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3327720</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-11-22782</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0034636</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Anatomy and Physiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cardiovascular System</subject><subj-group><subject>Circulatory Physiology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Cell Physiology</subject><subject>Electrophysiology</subject><subject>Neurological System</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Biophysics</subject><subj-group><subject>Biophysics Simulations</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Computational Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Biophysic Al Simulations</subject><subject>Computational Neuroscience</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Neuroscience</subject><subj-group><subject>Computational Neuroscience</subject><subject>Neural Networks</subject><subject>Neurophysiology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Anatomy and Physiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Electrophysiology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Cardiovascular</subject><subj-group><subject>Electrophysiology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Membranes with the Same Ion Channel Populations but Different Excitabilities</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Same Channels, Different Excitabilities</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Herrera-Valdez</surname><given-names>Marco Arieli</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>&#x0002a;</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Department of Mathematics, University of Arizona, Tucson, Arizona, United States of America</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Evelyn F. McKnight Brain Institute, University of Arizona, Tucson, Arizona, United States of America</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Department of Mathematics and Physics, University of Puerto Rico in Cayey, Cayey, Puerto Rico</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><addr-line>Institute for Interdisciplinary Research, University of Puerto Rico in Cayey, Cayey, Puerto Rico</addr-line></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Bondarenko</surname><given-names>Vladimir E.</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Georgia State University, United States of America</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">&#x0002a; E-mail: <email>marco.herrera@upr.edu</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: MH. Performed the experiments: MH. Analyzed the data: MH. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: MH. Wrote the paper: MH. Original idea behind the manuscript, performed the mathematical analysis, wrote the code for numerical simulations and wrote the paper: MH.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>4</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>4</issue><elocation-id>e34636</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>13</day><month>11</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>2</day><month>3</month><year>2012</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Marco Arieli Herrera-Valdez. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year></permissions><abstract><p>Electrical signaling allows communication within and between different tissues and is necessary for the survival of multicellular organisms. The ionic transport that underlies transmembrane currents in cells is mediated by transporters and channels. Fast ionic transport through channels is typically modeled with a conductance-based formulation that describes current in terms of electrical drift without diffusion. In contrast, currents written in terms of drift and diffusion are not as widely used in the literature in spite of being more realistic and capable of displaying experimentally observable phenomena that conductance-based models cannot reproduce (e.g. rectification). The two formulations are mathematically related: conductance-based currents are linear approximations of drift-diffusion currents. However, conductance-based models of membrane potential are not first-order approximations of drift-diffusion models. Bifurcation analysis and numerical simulations show that the two approaches predict <italic>qualitatively</italic> and <italic>quantitatively</italic> different behaviors in the dynamics of membrane potential. For instance, two neuronal membrane models with identical populations of ion channels, one written with conductance-based currents, the other with drift-diffusion currents, undergo transitions into and out of repetitive oscillations through different mechanisms and for different levels of stimulation. These differences in excitability are observed in response to excitatory synaptic input, and across different levels of ion channel expression. In general, the electrophysiological profiles of membranes modeled with drift-diffusion and conductance-based models having identical ion channel populations are different, potentially causing the input-output and computational properties of networks constructed with these models to be different as well. The drift-diffusion formulation is thus proposed as a theoretical improvement over conductance-based models that may lead to more accurate predictions and interpretations of experimental data at the single cell and network levels.</p></abstract><counts><page-count count="15"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Electrical signaling allows fast transfer of information within and between cells. Electrical signals are produced by ionic transport within tissues, and in particular, across the membranes of cells. Most transmembrane ionic transport is mediated by membrane-spanning proteins that may either mechanically translocate ions across the membrane (transporters), or facilitate ionic diffusion by forming pores <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Hille1">[1]</xref>. The dynamics of membrane potential can be modeled from a macroscopic perspective by assuming that the membrane, its channels and transporters, and the permeable ions on both sides of the membrane are equivalent to an electrical circuit <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Hodgkin1">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-DiFrancesco1">[3]</xref>. In this description, the total current through the membrane is the sum of the currents mediated by channels and transporters. Currents mediated by ion channels are typically modeled as the product of a conductance and a linear function of membrane potential <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Johnston1">[4]</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Ermentrout1">[7]</xref>. This approach will be referred to herein as <italic>conductance-based</italic> (CB). However, ionic transport through channels is driven by electrical drift, as assumed in CB models, but also by diffusion <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Stevens1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Weiss1">[9]</xref> which is not included in CB formulations.</p><p>Expressions for transmembrane ionic flux that take diffusion into account can be derived using the Nernst- Planck equation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Weiss2">[10]</xref>, and used to describe transmembrane currents as already done by Goldman <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Goldman1">[11]</xref> and others <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Eisenberg1">[12]</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Clay2">[15]</xref>. These currents will be herein called <italic>drift-diffusion</italic> (DD) and models of membrane potential constructed using CB, or alternatively, using DD currents will be referred to as CB or DD models. CB models are generally regarded as good descriptions of membrane potential, have been studied extensively <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Krinski1">[16]</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Kepler1">[20]</xref>, and are thus very popular and used along with experiments to study cellular excitability <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Hodgkin1">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-DiFrancesco1">[3]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Adrian1">[21]</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Ikeno1">[25]</xref>. On the other hand, DD models are more realistic <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Goldman1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Clay3">[26]</xref> but are not widely used in the literature. For instance, DD currents capture important nonlinear phenomena like rectification; a property that CB models cannot reproduce. In fact, as shown in the following paragraphs, the CB formulation for current is a <italic>linear approximation</italic> of its DD counterpart around the reversal potential of the current ( <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034636-g001">Fig. 1 a</xref>). DD and CB models reproduce basic features of the behavior of excitable cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Endresen1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-AvRon1">[19]</xref>. However, the nonlinearities contributed by DD formulations may result in very different dynamics in comparison to CB models. It is therefore important to ask to what extent the two approaches lead to qualitatively and quantitatively similar behaviors, everything else being equal. In other words, are CB and DD formulations computationally equivalent? If so, to what extent?</p><fig id="pone-0034636-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0034636.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>DD and CB currents and convergence to steady state.</title><p>(<bold>a</bold>) DD and CB currents in gray ( Eq. 1 ) and black ( Eq. 2 ) respectively. (<bold>b</bold>) Convergence to steady state in a model of membrane potential ( Eq. 14 ) with dynamics as in Eqs. 15&#x02013;16.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.g001"/></fig><p>Models of excitable cells are used to understand the role of ionic currents on cellular signaling, make testable quantitative predictions, and interpret experimental results. Therefore, it is crucial to understand more about how the dynamics of the membrane change with the DD or CB formulation. To start addressing this question, two low-dimensional versions of the same model of membrane potential, CB and DD respectively, are constructed. The two models are assumed to have identical ion channel populations mediating a leak current and two voltage-gated currents, namely, a transient sodium (Na<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e001.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>) current and a delayed rectifier potassium (K<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e002.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>) current <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-AvRon1">[19]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-HerreraValdez1">[27]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Mitchell1">[28]</xref>. The comparison is done by examining the bifurcation structure and behaviour of the two models in response to constant and time-dependent current stimulation, and synaptic input. In each case, different patterns of ion channel expression were taken into account. The qualitative features of the dynamics in the two models having identical ion channel populations are different, as predicted by their non-topologically equivalent phase spaces and bifurcation structures. For constant stimulation, the smallest sustained current amplitude that causes a transition between rest and repetitive oscillations in the membrane potential, or <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e003.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> for short, is shown to differ in the two models. In a more dynamical setting, the <italic>recruiting current</italic>, defined as the smallest amplitude in an up-going ramp stimulus that results in action potentials, is shown to be significantly smaller than <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e004.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> for both models, and smaller in the DD model than in the CB model. The excitatory synaptic current that causes repetitive spiking is also shown to be smaller than <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e005.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, and repetitive spiking in response to synaptic input requires a smaller number of synapses in the DD model in comparison to the CB model. In sum, repetitive spiking occurs for smaller stimulus currents, and within a smaller range in the DD model in comparison to the CB model. The results presented here can be modified and extended for the study of other excitable membranes.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Electrodiffusion currents and membrane potential</title><p>The formulation for transmembrane currents driven by drift and diffusion used here is a generalization of a derivation based on first principles of thermodynamics and electrochemistry previously reported in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Endresen1">[13]</xref> and expanded in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-HerreraValdez2">[29]</xref>. The derivation starts by considering the ionic flux through open pores across the membrane written as the sum of electrical drift and diffusion with the Nernst-Planck equation (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0034636.s007">Text S1</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Weiss1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Eisenberg1">[12]</xref>). In brief, the cross-sectional area of the pore region inside an ion channel and the electric field across the membrane are assumed to be smoothly varying functions of distance along the pore. Assuming the flow of charge is stationary and integrating the equation between the intra- and extra-cellular domains along the pore axis allows writing an expression for the transmembrane current as a function of the membrane potential <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e006.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>. As a result, the current carried by ions of type <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e007.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> as they electrodiffuse through an open pore can be written as<disp-formula><graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e008"/><label>(1)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e009.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> is the membrane potential, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e010.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e011.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e012.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e013.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> are the Nernst potential, valence, extracellular and intracellular concentrations of the ion <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e014.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Endresen1">[13]</xref>. The term <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e015.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> is a constant approximation to a function that depends on the properties of the pore, the electric field across the membrane, the mobility of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e016.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, and other factors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Nonner1">[30]</xref>. The Goldman constant field approximation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Goldman1">[11]</xref> can be obtained as a particular case of Eq. 1 if it is assumed that the electric potential inside a channel is a linear function of the distance along the channel pore, and that the pore has constant cross-sectional area <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Endresen1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-HerreraValdez1">[27]</xref>. The potential <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e017.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> is the quotient <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e018.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e019.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> is Boltzmann's constant, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e020.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> is the elementary charge, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e021.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> the absolute temperature. The current in Eq. 1 can be regarded as a macroscopic description of the transmembrane current produced by ions of type <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e022.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> as they diffuse through an open channel and will be herein referred to as a DD current. For contrast, the CB current through an open channel permeable to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e023.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> is a linear function of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e024.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034636-g001">Fig. 1 a</xref>) given by<disp-formula><graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e025"/><label>(2)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e026.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> represents the maximal conductance of the current carried by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e027.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>-ions. For K<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e028.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and Na<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e029.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> ions, but not for Ca<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e030.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, the concentrations <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e031.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e032.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> can be regarded as constants <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Johnston1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-HerreraValdez1">[27]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Whole-membrane currents</title><p>The formulation in Eq. 1 can be extended to consider the current mediated by several hundreds or thousands of gated channels. Let channel gating be represented by a number <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e033.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> between 0 and 1 that depends on the gating mechanism of the channel. The <italic>gated</italic> whole-membrane current can be written as:<disp-formula><graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e034"/><label>(3)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e035.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> is the number of channels in the membrane. Loosely speaking, the quantity <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e036.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> can be thought of as the average number of open channels permeable to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e037.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Aldrich1">[31]</xref> for an interesting perspective in this regard). If the absolute temperature and the transmembrane concentrations of Na<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e038.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and K<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e039.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> are assumed to be constant <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Johnston1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-HerreraValdez1">[27]</xref>, then<disp-formula><graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e040"/><label>(4)</label></disp-formula>can be thought of as a constant representing the maximum current through the membrane.</p><p>Voltage-dependent gating is described from a macroscopic perspective as a first-order process with steady states written explicitly in terms of the change in free energy caused by the conformational changes that underlie channel gating. Ligand-gated channels are modeled following previous work by Destexhe <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Destexhe1">[32]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Membrane potential</title><p>The comparison between the DD and CB models is done with a two-dimensional dynamical system defined in terms of a <italic>core</italic> set of currents: a leak current, two voltage-gated currents carried by Na<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e041.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and K<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e042.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, and a stimulus current representing either stimulation through an electrode, or fast excitatory synaptic input. Importantly, all the currents are written using the same gating functions and therefore, the only differences between the two models are in the driving force portion of the currents. An implicit assumption in this construction is that additional membrane channels and transporters fulfill a complementary, but not necessary, role in producing rest-to-spiking transitions, as explicitly illustrated, for instance in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-HerreraValdez1">[27]</xref>.</p><p>The membrane potential is represented by the variable <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e043.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> with dynamics defined by:<disp-formula><graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e044"/><label>(5)</label></disp-formula><disp-formula><graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e045"/><label>(6)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e046.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> is the membrane capacitance and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e047.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e048.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e049.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e050.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> represent, respectively, current from an external stimulus, voltage-gated Na<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e051.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and K<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e052.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> currents, and a non-gated leak current (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0034636-t001">Table 1</xref>). The variable <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e053.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> represents the dynamics of the K<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e054.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> channel activation. The gating charge and half-activation potential of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e055.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> are, respectively, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e056.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e057.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>. The basal rate of the gating reaction, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e058.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, is a function of temperature <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Ermentrout1">[7]</xref>. Since all the simulations presented here are assumed to occur at 22<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e059.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>C, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e060.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> becomes a constant. The peak and symmetry of the time constant as functions of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e061.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> are controlled by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e062.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e063.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, respectively <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-HerreraValdez2">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Willms1">[33]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Gerstner1">[34]</xref>. Na<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e064.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> channel inactivation and K<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e065.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> channel activation are linearly coupled <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Rinzel1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-AvRon1">[19]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-HerreraValdez1">[27]</xref>. Steady state activation for Na<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e066.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> channels is given by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e067.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>. Parameters for the simulations can be found in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0034636-t002">Table 2</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0034636-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0034636.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Functional forms of the different transmembrane currents.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0034636-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0034636.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Current</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DD</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CB</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e068.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e069.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e070.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e071.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e072.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e073.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e074.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e075.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e076.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e077.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e078.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e079.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p>Gating is the same in both formulations.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone-0034636-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0034636.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Parameters and Constants.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0034636-t002-2" xlink:href="pone.0034636.t002"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Name</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Value</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Units</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Description</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="4" align="left" rowspan="1">Physical constants</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e080.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.60217733<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e081.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>10<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e082.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elementary charge</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e083.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3806582<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e084.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>10<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e085.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mJ/K</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Boltzmann's constant</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="left" rowspan="1">Membrane properties</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e086.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e087.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>C</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Room Temperature <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e088.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>C</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e089.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">273.15&#x0002b;<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e090.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e091.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>K</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absolute temperature</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e092.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.43</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mV</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Boltzmann's potential</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e093.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mV</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reversal potential for Na<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e094.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e095.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;90</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mV</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reversal potential for K<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e096.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e097.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;60</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mV</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reversal potential for membrane leak <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e098.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e099.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e100.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Membrane resistance</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e101.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nF</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Membrane capacitance in adult <italic>Drosophila</italic> MN5 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Duch1">[84]</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="left" rowspan="1">Channel kinetics</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="left" rowspan="1">Transient Na from Adult <italic>Drosophila</italic> DmNav1 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Lin1">[42]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e102.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;29</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mV</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Half-activation</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e103.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gating charge of activation</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="left" rowspan="1">K-delayed rectifier from <italic>Drosophila</italic> Shab <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Tsunoda1">[38]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e104.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mV</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Half-activation</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e105.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gating charge of activation</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e106.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ms</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Max. activation time constant</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e107.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Symmetry of activation time constant</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="left" rowspan="1">Maximum current amplitudes and conductances</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e108.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NaT maximum current amplitude</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e109.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kd maximum current amplitude</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e110.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leak maximum current amplitude</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e111.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e112.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NaT maximum conductance</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e113.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e114.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kd maximum conductance</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e115.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e116.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leak maximum conductance</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="left" rowspan="1">Normalized model</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e117.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nA/nF</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.4 Scaling factor for physiologically relevant <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e118.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e119.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.96</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e120.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>S/nF</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e121.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximal current amplitude for potassium relative to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e122.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e123.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normalized maximal current amplitude for Kd</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e124.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normalized maximal current amplitude for Kd</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>The <italic>stimulus current</italic> is either a constant (used as a bifurcation parameter), a time-dependent function representing external stimulation, or a time- and voltage-dependent function representing synaptic input. The smallest <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e125.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> necessary to cause a transition between rest and sustained oscillations with a square pulse will be referred to as <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e126.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>. The <italic>time-dependent stimulation</italic> will consist of 5 epochs: (1) bottom, with stimulus amplitude 0 nA, (2) ramp up (<italic>Up</italic>), (3) constant stimulation with amplitude equal to the maximum reached by the ramp (<italic>Top</italic>), (4) ramp down (<italic>Down</italic>), and (5) bottom again. This stimulation protocol will be referred to as up-top-down (UTD). Unless otherwise specified, <italic>Up</italic>, <italic>Top</italic>, and <italic>Down</italic> epochs have the same duration with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e127.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> being continuous as a function of time. For <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e128.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> with a ramping stimulation, the minimum current amplitude required to start sustained oscillations during <italic>Up</italic> or <italic>Top</italic> will be called <italic>recruitment</italic> current, and the stimulus amplitude during <italic>Down</italic> at which a transition between sustained oscillations and rest occurs will be called <italic>de-recruitment</italic> current.</p><p><italic>Synaptic input.</italic> The activity of the presynaptic cells is simulated by generating <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e129.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> independent <italic>spike trains</italic> with gamma-distributed interspike intervals, each with a mean rate <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e130.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Gerstner1">[34]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-HerreraValdez3">[35]</xref>. For simplification purposes, it is assumed that an action potential in each of the input neurons activates, on average, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e131.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> synapses after a presynaptic action potential <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-HerreraValdez3">[35]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Jack1">[36]</xref>, each synapse having a maximum postsynaptic current amplitude <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e132.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>. Each synapse made by the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e133.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>th presynaptic cell is gated with a time-dependent probability of opening <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e134.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> with dynamics defined by<disp-formula><graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e135"/><label>(7)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e136.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> is the concentration of neurotransmitter for each of the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e137.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> synapses activated by the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e138.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>th presynaptic neuron at times <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e139.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Destexhe1">[32]</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0034636.s002">Fig. S2</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0034636-t003">Table 3</xref>). The time-course of neurotransmitter concentration in the cleft is given by<disp-formula><graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e140"/><label>(8)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e141.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> represents the maximum neurotransmitter concentration at synapses from the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e142.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>th presynaptic contact. The indicator function <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e143.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> is equal to 1 if <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e144.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and zero otherwise <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Koch1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Ermentrout1">[7]</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0034636-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0034636.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Parameters for simulations with time-dependent stimulation or synaptic input.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0034636-t003-3" xlink:href="pone.0034636.t003"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Name</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Value</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Units</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Description</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="4" align="left" rowspan="1">nAChRs from adult <italic>Drosophila</italic> central synapses <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Lee1">[44]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e145.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximum mEPSC amplitude</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e146.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e147.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximum conductance of mEPSCs</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e148.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normalized mEPSC amplitude relative to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e149.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e150.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mV</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reversal potential</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e151.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mM/ms</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward rate of postsynaptic activation</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e152.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/ms</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Backward rate of postsynaptic activation</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e153.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average number of activated synapses per spike</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e154.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0,10<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e155.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of excitatory synaptic axons</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e156.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hz</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Input rate of each excitatory axon</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>Reparametrization in terms of relative channel contributions</title><p>Recall that the CB approximation to the DD current is valid only for voltages near the reversal potential of the current. Therefore, for any given potential, the DD model (Eq. 5) cannot be written as a CB model by simply replacing the DD currents by their CB approximations. However, it is still possible to investigate whether the dynamics from the DD model are qualitatively different to those of the CB model by rewriting Eq. 5 so that the relative contributions of the channels to the change in membrane potential are the same. To do so, start by multiplying the right hand side of the DD model by a normalization current <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e157.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, and divide each of the currents by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e158.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>; do the same for the CB model using a normalization conductance <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e159.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>. As a consequence,<disp-formula><graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e160"/><label>(9)</label></disp-formula>with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e161.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e162.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>. The remaining coefficients leading each of the currents can then be set to be equal in both versions of the model:<disp-formula><graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e163"/><label>(10)</label></disp-formula>with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e164.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>. If <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e165.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> represents synaptic input, the amplitudes for the currents corresponding to each of the input axons can also be set as<disp-formula><graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e166"/></disp-formula></p><p>The normalization term for the DD model could be <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e167.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e168.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e169.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e170.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, or any other convenient current; the same applies for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e171.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> in CB models. The choice <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e172.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> allows, however, different interpretations for the model. For instance, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e173.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> could be the sum of all the amplitudes for DD and similarly for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e174.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, in which case the coefficients in front of each current can be thought of as weighted by a maximum total current (or conductance). Recall that the maximum amplitude of each of the DD currents (alternatively, maximum conductance for CB) can be thought of as multiple of the number of channels mediating the current, so these normalizations allow interpretations in terms of <italic>relative</italic> expression of ion channels. For instance, if all the currents in the DD model are divided by the maximum amplitude of the Na<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e175.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> channel (and their CB counterparts are divided by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e176.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>), then <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e177.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and the ratios <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e178.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e179.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e180.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> in the right hand side of Eq. 9 can be thought of as amplitudes relative to the number of Na<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e181.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> channels in the membrane. Then, as indicated by Eq. 4,<disp-formula><graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e182"/><label>(11)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e183.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e184.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> are the numbers of K<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e185.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and Na<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e186.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> channels and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e187.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> is a constant. Therefore, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e188.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> is proportional to the ratio of K<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e189.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> to Na<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e190.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> channels. In other words, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e191.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> can be thought of as an indicator of the <italic>relative expression</italic> of K<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e192.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> delayed rectifier channels in the membrane with respect to the expression of Na<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e193.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> channels.</p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title>Parameters and fits to experimental data</title><p>The channel kinetics used here are based on the biophysical properties of delayed-rectifier K<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e194.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> channels expressed in somato-dendritic compartments encoded by the <italic>Shab</italic> gene in central neurons of adult <italic>Drosophila</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Wei1">[37]</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Tsunoda2">[39]</xref>, or one of its vertebrate homologs (<italic>e.g.</italic> Kv2.1 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Islas1">[40]</xref>). The Na<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e195.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> channels can be thought of as one of the protein products of the <italic>para/DmNav</italic> gene also present in adult <italic>Drosophila</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-ODowd1">[41]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Lin1">[42]</xref> or one of its vertebrate homologs (<italic>e.g.</italic> Nav1.1&#x02013;1.9 in vertebrates <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-King1">[43]</xref>). Synaptic currents are assumed to be excitatory and mediated by fast cholinergic receptors, one of the main mechanisms of excitation in invertebrate central synapses <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Lee1">[44]</xref> also present in the central, peripheral, and enteric nervous systems of vertebrates <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Katz1">[45]</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Galligan1">[47]</xref>. In all the simulations presented here, each of the input axons is assumed to have an average firing rate of 7 Hz with gamma-distributed interspike intervals. Each action potential from an input cell is assumed to activate (on average) 10 synapses from its collateral terminals, each producing an excitatory post-synaptic current <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-HerreraValdez3">[35]</xref>. Data for the channel parameters was obtained by fitting digitized current traces recorded under voltage clamp mode and reported in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Tsunoda2">[39]</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Lin1">[42]</xref>. Digitalization was done with custom code (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0034636.s001">Fig. S1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0034636-t002">Table 2</xref>). Once the parameters for the channels are fixed, the only free parameters left in both CB and DD models are the maximum amplitudes and conductances, respectively. The differential contribution of the channels to the excitability of the membrane can then be directly assessed by considering the ratios of the maximum amplitudes (DD) or conductances (CB) of the different currents in the model. The parameters <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e196.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> can be determined by using the input resistance as illustrated in later paragraphs. <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e197.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and the maximum <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e198.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> are found directly from recordings.</p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title>Initial choices of parameters</title><p>The normalizing amplitude <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e199.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> can be found using <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e200.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e201.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e202.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> to fit the maximum rate of change in the model to the one obtained in recordings. This means one more parameter can be fixed if <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e203.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> is either <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e204.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> or <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e205.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>. A particularly convenient choice used here is <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e206.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, because the magnitude of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e207.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> matches the magnitude of the desired maximum <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e208.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>. The combined parameters <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e209.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e210.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> from Eq. 9 can then be used to constrain the model to represent different cell types because they control the maximum <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e211.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, which can be determined from recordings. As a rule of thumb, the maximum <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e212.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> should be less than 50 mV/ms for cardiac myocytes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Rasmusson1">[48]</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Wilders1">[50]</xref> and pancreatic beta cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Ribalet1">[51]</xref>. In neurons, the maximum <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e213.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> may reach <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e214.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>300 mV/ms (see for instance, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Fohlmeister2">[52]</xref>). For instance, for the model presented here, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e215.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> can be set to about 100 nA/nF (with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e216.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>). If the membrane capacitance is 0.1, then <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e217.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;10 nA. A starting value of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e218.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;3 (as rule of thumb between 2 and 10) leaves <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e219.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;30 nA. Notice that if <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e220.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, the rule of thumb can be applied by algebraically rearranging the terms, which yields <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e221.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;300 nA/nF (because <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e222.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>) and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e223.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.33.</p><p>The comparisons between DD and CB models shown subsequently are made assuming <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e224.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> with maximum potassium current amplitudes between 1 and 5 times larger than the maximal amplitude of the sodium current, corresponding to relative level of expression in the K<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e225.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> channels <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e226.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> within the interval <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e227.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>. The range was determined by a global exploration of the bifurcation structure of the models in codimension 1 using <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e228.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> as the bifurcation parameter. The analysis of the model will be focused on the transitions into and out of repetitive spiking as dictated by varying the relative contributions of the different currents to the change in membrane potential.</p></sec><sec id="s2g"><title>Bifurcation analysis and associated membrane potential behaviors</title><p>The <italic>steady state currents</italic> are obtained after excluding <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e229.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> from Eq. 5 and replacing <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e230.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> by its steady state <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e231.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> in the voltage-gated currents. The resulting curve, called <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e232.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> herein, is used to calculate the fixed points <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e233.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> of the system. If <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e234.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, then neither <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e235.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, nor <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e236.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> change. Trajectories that pass through focus points are <italic>spirals</italic>, which means the membrane potential oscillates when the system is near a focus point. In contrast, the membrane potential does not oscillate when the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e237.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> is near nodes. Trajectories near <italic>saddle node</italic> points initially move toward the saddle-node and eventually diverge from it, which means that if <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e238.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> is near a saddle-node, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e239.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> will eventually move away from the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e240.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>-value of the saddle-node. The <italic>cycles</italic> of the system represent sustained oscillations in the membrane potential. <italic>Limit cycles</italic> are asymptotically stable attractors. This means that the membrane potential will go into sustained oscillations if the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e241.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> is within the basin of attraction of a limit cycle. Sustained oscillations are regarded as repetitive spiking if their amplitude is <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e242.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>30 mV and their maximum <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e243.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>10 V/s. The system is <italic>bistable</italic> if it has two attractors (e.g. a fixed point and a limit cycle).</p><p>The system in Eqs. 5&#x02013;6 has at least one asymptotically stable attractor for parameters within the physiologically meaningful range. In other words, there should be either a fixed point or a limit cycle (sustained oscillation) that the system goes back to. If all the fixed points are unstable, there is no resting membrane potential and sustained oscillations are expected to occur (a limit cycle is expected to exist <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Izhikevich1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Ermentrout1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Rinzel2">[53]</xref>). The <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e244.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>-value of an asymptotically stable fixed point can be regarded as a <italic>resting potential</italic> (especially if near &#x02212;60 mV). Asymptotically stable <italic>focus</italic> points are such that the membrane potential oscillates toward the resting value. In contrast, the membrane potential converges to asymptotically stable <italic>node</italic> points monotonically (without oscillating). Recall that a <italic>bifurcation</italic> occurs when either the number, the type, or the stability of the fixed points or cycles of the system change <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Strogatz1">[54]</xref>. That is, a bifurcation indicates a qualitative change in the behavior of the system; for instance, a transition between rest and sustained spiking. Note therefore, that the analysis presented here links patterns of relative ion channel expression with bifurcation structure.</p></sec><sec id="s2h"><title>Bifurcations</title><p>The points shown in bifurcation diagrams are color-coded based on the characteristics of the eigenvalues of each fixed point. <italic>Asymptotically stable</italic> fixed points are represented with small solid dots. <italic>Unstable</italic> fixed points are represented with circles. <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e245.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> pairs corresponding to <italic>focus</italic> points are shown in black. The pairs <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e246.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> corresponding to <italic>node</italic> points are shown in blue. <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e247.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> from <italic>saddle-node</italic> points are shown in green.</p><p><italic>Andronov-Hopf</italic> (AH) bifurcations occur when a focus point changes in stability. Subcritical and supercritical AH bifurcations are associated to bistable and monostable systems, respectively. Systems like Eqs. 5&#x02013;6 that undergo a subcritical AH bifurcation, typically loose or gain an unstable limit cycle. In the former case, the membrane is typically bistable, with a limit cycle and a stable fixed point separated by an unstable cycle. At the bifurcation the unstable cycle closes into the fixed point and dissappears, leaving an unstable focus and the limit cycle around it. Prior to the bifurcation the system could go to rest or into repetitive spiking depending on its initial conditions. After the bifurcation, the system is monostable and its only asymptotic behavior is the sustained oscillation (repetitive spiking). In <italic>Saddle-node</italic> (SN) bifurcations the number of fixed points changes between 3 and 1 (or viceversa) and are associated with non-monotonic <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e248.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> curve. Repetitive spiking may emerge through a SN bifurcation if, for example, the remaining point is unstable and a limit cycle remains as the only attractor of the system. A <italic>fold limit-cycle</italic> (FLC) bifurcation is such that two cycles appear or disappear (similar to SN). One cycle is unstable and surrounds the stable fixed point. The other cycle is stable and surrounds the unstable cycle. The unstable cycle delimits the basins of attraction of the fixed point and the limit cycle. FLC bifurcations occur near subcritical Andronov-Hopf bifurcations.</p><p>The values used in the simulations presented here can be found in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0034636-t002">Table 2</xref>. Deviations from the parameter set used in the tables are noted in the figures.</p></sec><sec id="s2i"><title>Numerical solvers</title><p>Numerical simulations shown in this manuscript were performed using the solver integrate.odeint (lsoda from the FORTRAN library odepack) available from the Python module scipy (Python Software Foundation, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.python.org">http://www.python.org</ext-link>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec id="s3a"><title>Conductance-based currents are first-order local approximations of electrodiffusion currents</title><p>The CB and DD formulations are mathematically related. To see it, consider the Taylor series of the hyperbolic sine around 0 truncated to first-order: <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e249.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>. This means that Eq. 1 can be approximated around <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e250.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> as follows:<disp-formula><graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e251"/><label>(12)</label></disp-formula>The quotient in front of the voltage difference in Eq. 12 is a conductance (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e252.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>S), which can be rewritten as<disp-formula><graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e253"/><label>(13)</label></disp-formula>The CB expression for current from Eq. 2 is thus a first-order approximation of the DD current near the reversal potential <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e254.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>(see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034636-g001">Fig. 1 (a)</xref> and green trace for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e255.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034636-g002">Fig. 2</xref> ). If the membrane input resistance (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e256.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>) is known, the relationship between the maximum conductance and the maximum current in Eq. 13 allows calculation of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e257.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>. To do so, assume <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e258.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and calculate the amplitude of the leak current as <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e259.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> using the relationship between the DD and CB currents described in Eq. 13.</p><fig id="pone-0034636-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0034636.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Bifurcation diagrams and trajectories.</title><p>DD (solid) and CB (dashed). Panels (<bold>a</bold>) and (<bold>b</bold>) show the fixed points (by type) as a function <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e260.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, for relative expressions of K<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e261.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> channels <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e262.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;1,2,2.5,3,4,5. The fixed point curve for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e263.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;2.5 is shown in cyan. (<bold>c,d,e</bold>) Steady state currents, action potential, and its underlying currents, respectively, with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e264.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;(1,2.5,0.05). <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e265.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e266.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e267.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e268.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> are shown, respectively, in red, blue, green, and black. The time course of an action potential after a 35 mV shift from rest and its underlying currents are shown in (<bold>d</bold>) and (<bold>e</bold>), respectively. The black dot and the surrounding circle mark the resting potentials for the DD and CB models are illustrated.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.g002"/></fig><p>To obtain some intuition about the role of the leak current, and in particular <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e269.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> (or <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e270.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>), in shaping the asymptotic behavior of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e271.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, it is useful to consider a reduced version of Eq. 5 that only includes the leak current:<disp-formula><graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e272"/><label>(14)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e273.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> is the membrane capacitance ( <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034636-g001">Fig. 1 b</xref>). Assuming <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e274.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> as an initial condition, the first equality in Eq. 14 (DD) gives a membrane potential of the form<disp-formula><graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e275"/><label>(15)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e276.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e277.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>. The solution corresponding to the CB approximation on the right of Eq. 14 is<disp-formula><graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e278"/><label>(16)</label></disp-formula>It can be readily seen in both cases ( <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034636-g001">Fig. 1 b</xref>) that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e279.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> (or <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e280.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>) modulates the time constant that governs the return of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e281.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> in Eq. 14 to its resting value, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e282.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>. This explains why a larger leak current would lead to faster return to the resting potential. Larger values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e283.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> yield smaller membrane time constants, which results in faster convergence toward rest (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Rall1">[55]</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Kuhn1">[58]</xref>). Note the convergence to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e284.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> is slightly different for the two models.</p></sec><sec id="s3b"><title>Different behaviors for the same ion channel expression</title><p>As noted earlier, direct substitution of the DD or CB formulations into Eq. 5 may result in different excitability profiles. These differences can be examined from a macroscopic perspective using <italic>bifurcation analysis</italic> for different choices of the relative contribution of the K<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e285.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> current with respect to Na<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e286.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e287.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> (with fixed <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e288.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>). To do so, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e289.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> is fixed and the <italic>fixed points</italic> of the system and their types are found as a function of the external current <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e290.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034636-g002">Fig. 2 a&#x02013;b</xref>). In general, as <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e291.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> increases, the shape of the fixed point curve as a function of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e292.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> changes from non-monotonic to monotonic in both models, but monotonicity emerges in CB models for smaller <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e293.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>. The two models display, however, important differences in regard to the <italic>number</italic> and type of their fixed points depending on the relative levels of ion channel expression.</p><p>If the relative contribution of K<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e294.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and Na<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e295.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> channels is the same (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e296.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, first curve from left to right in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034636-g002">Fig. 2 a&#x02013;b</xref>), both DD and CB models have three fixed points when <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e297.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0. In the DD model, the two fixed points with lowest and highest <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e298.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>-values correspond to asymptotically stable focus points, the remaining one corresponds to a saddle point. The system is thus bistable: the smallest <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e299.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>-value corresponds to the resting membrane potential and the largest <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e300.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>-value corresponds to a depolarization block potential. In an experiment, this would mean that the membrane potential could be block-depolarized from its resting value by a brief but large enough pulse of current, or taken back to rest by down-shifting <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e301.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> with a negative short pulse of current. The number of fixed points decreases from 3 to 1 for larger stimulus amplitudes (SN bifurcation); the fixed point that remains is stable. Experimentally, this is a case in which square pulses of current injection would depolarize the membrane, perhaps generating a pulse that would end at a depolarized membrane potential. In this case no stimulus would result in repetitive spiking (see for instance <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034636-g001">Fig. 1</xref> in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Peng1">[59]</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0034636.s002">Fig. S2</xref>). In contrast, in the CB model has only one stable fixed point for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e302.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0. The only stable fixed point disappears in a SN bifurcation as <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e303.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> increases, leaving behind an unstable point and a limit cycle (not shown). As a consequence, the CB model predicts sustained spiking for large enough <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e304.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> if <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e305.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>.</p><p>If the maximum K<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e306.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> current amplitude is twice as large as the maximum Na<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e307.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> current amplitude (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e308.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;2), the DD model has three fixed points at <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e309.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0 and the CB model has only one (second curve from left to right in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034636-g002">Fig. 2 a&#x02013;b</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0034636.s003">Fig. S3</xref>). In this case, the fixed point curves of the two models are non-monotonic as a function of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e310.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>. Importantly, the transition into repetitive spiking with square pulses of current will occur in this case near a saddle node bifurcation in the DD model, and through a FLC bifurcation in the CB model (see inset in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034636-g002">Fig. 2 b</xref> inset, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0034636.s004">Fig. S4</xref>, and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0034636.s007">Text S1</xref>).</p><p>If the expression of potassium channels is higher, say <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e311.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> ( <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034636-g002">Fig. 2 a&#x02013;b</xref>, lower 3 curves), then both models have only one fixed point for all <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e312.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> considered here (the fixed point curves are monotonic as functions of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e313.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>). In all of these cases there are sustained oscillations that emerge through a FLC bifurcation (near Hopf points). These dynamics are like those observed in experiments where an up-going ramp current stimulus produces small subthreshold oscillations before repetitive spiking starts <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Yang1">[60]</xref>. A similar phenomenon occurs if a large enough stimulus amplitudes, when repetitive spiking disappears with an oscillation toward a depolarization block.</p><p>The DD and CB models also exhibit <italic>different sequences</italic> of fixed point bifurcations as <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e314.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> increases for each of the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e315.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>'s under consideration. For instance, for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e316.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;4 (second curve from right to left in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034636-g002">Fig. 2 a&#x02013;b</xref>), the sequence of fixed points in the DD model includes stable nodes (ca. <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e317.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0), then stable foci that become unstable and later turn into unstable nodes, then turn into unstable foci again that become stable (ca. <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e318.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;11), etc. In contrast, the CB model has stable nodes first (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e319.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0), then stable foci that become unstable and then stable again without turning into nodes (ca. <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e320.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;13), etc.</p><p>In sum, unstable nodes and foci appear earlier in the DD model (with respect toCB) as <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e321.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> increases (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034636-g002">Fig. 2 a&#x02013;b</xref>) and the minimal current stimulus that evokes repetitive spiking, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e322.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, is smaller for the DD model in comparison to the CB model, for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e323.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>. The <italic>range</italic> of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e324.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> for which repetititive spiking occurs is also smaller for DD models than for CB models for any given <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e325.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>. Experimentally, this means that the CB model requires larger depolarizations from rest in comparison with the DD model in order to show an action potential (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0034636.s004">Figs. S4</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0034636.s005">S5</xref>). In addition, the above observations highlight potentially different mechanisms underlying transitions into or out of repetitive spiking as a function of the relative expression of ion channels. Taken together, past paragraphs show that, in general, the dynamical systems that result from using DD and CB formulations in Eqs. 5&#x02013;6 are <italic>non-topologically equivalent</italic> despite having identical populations of voltage-gated channels. In other words, the DD and CB models yield membranes with <italic>different electrophysiological signatures</italic> despite of having <italic>identical channel expression</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="s3c"><title>Rest-to-spiking transitions</title><p>The choice of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e326.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;2.5 results in DD and CB models that are readily seen as not topologically equivalent because their <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e327.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> curves are non-monotonic and monotonic, respectively (cyan curves in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034636-g002">Fig. 2 a&#x02013;b</xref>, and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034636-g002">Fig. 2 c&#x02013;e</xref>). As a consequence, the dynamical behaviors of the two models are qualitatively different as well. For this reason, a more detailed comparison between DD and CB models is carried out from herein with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e328.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;2.5.</p><p>First, note that gating causes the divergence between the steady state <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e329.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> relationships of the CB and DD formulations to be more noticeable for K<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e330.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> currents than for Na<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e331.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> currents <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Clay1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Vandenberg1">[61]</xref>. To compare the dynamics in the two models, it is useful to consider the trajectory described by the system when an action potential occurs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034636-g002">Fig. 2 d</xref>). If the membrane potential is depolarized 35 mV from rest the action potentials in the two models are comparable in amplitude and duration, and they both go back to very similar resting potentials. However, the nonlinearities from the DD formulation can be observed in faster upstroke and initial downstroke, relative to the CB model. A closer inspection of the Na<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e332.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and K<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e333.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> currents shows an earlier activation in the DD model relative to the CB model ( <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034636-g002">Fig. 2 e</xref>). This time delay in the activation of the voltage-gated currents is accentuated for larger values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e334.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, especially for the Na<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e335.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> current (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0034636.s005">Fig. S5</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s3d"><title>Different behaviors for the same stimulus current</title><p>Qualitatively different behaviours can be observed in the CB and DD models as a function of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e336.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>. For instance, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e337.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;383 pA yields a bistable DD model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034636-g003">Fig. 3b</xref>), but its CB counterpart is monostable (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034636-g003">Fig. 3d</xref>). In contrast, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e338.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;675 pA yields monostability in the form of repetitive spiking for the DD model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034636-g003">Fig. 3c</xref>), but bistability for CB (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034636-g003">Fig. 3e</xref>). Both models display repetitive spiking for large enough values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e339.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and both models block-depolarize at some point. However, these sustained oscillations emerge and stop through different mechanisms in the two models for a given <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e340.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>.</p><fig id="pone-0034636-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0034636.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Bifurcation structure and dynamics of DD and CB models for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e341.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>. a.</title><p> Bifurcation profiles. <bold>b&#x02013;e.</bold> Dynamics of the DD (<bold>b,c</bold>) and CB model (<bold>d,e</bold>) for different initial conditions, for two values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e342.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> (vertical lines gray lines in <bold>a</bold>). The initial conditions are shown as empty dots near the left axis and the fixed points are shown on the right portion of each diagram.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.g003"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3e"><title>Ramp stimulation</title><p>Ramp stimulation (see UTD protocol and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034636-g004">Fig. 4a</xref>) has the advantage of not causing the artificial one-dimensional <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e343.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>-shift caused by square pulse stimulation, allowing the study of rest-to-spiking transitions while all the state variables of the system are changing. Importantly, the <italic>recruitment current</italic> in these conditions may be smaller than the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e344.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> predicted for constant <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e345.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> (this is called <italic>slow passage through Hopf</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Rinzel3">[<italic>62</italic>]</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034636-g004"><italic>Fig. 4b&#x02013;c</italic></xref><italic>)</italic>. Further, the mechanisms by which repetitive spiking starts when <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e346.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> is a constant (i.e. square pulse stimulation) are different in comparison to those predicted for ramp currents. For illustration, consider a case where a <italic>Top</italic> stimulus slightly larger than the recruitment current in the CB model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034636-g004">Fig. 4b&#x02013;c</xref>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e347.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>383 pA for DD and 608 pA for CB, <italic>Top</italic> amplitude&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;705 pA). In this case, repetitive spiking starts after a relatively long delay in the CB model. The reason is that the ramp allows both variables of the system to change, thereby moving the system toward one of its attractors. At the start of the ramp, the system moves toward its nearest stable fixed point, which is a focus. Shortly before the <italic>Top</italic> amplitude is reached, the fixed point undergoes an AH bifurcation in which the focus becomes unstable, leaving a limit cycle as the only attractor of the system (see also <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0034636.s006">Fig. S6</xref>). As a consequence, when the AH bifurcation occurs, the system starts oscillating away from the fixed point and toward the limit cycle. Note that repetitive spiking does not start through the FLC bifurcation as for constant <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e348.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> (compare to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034636-g003">Fig. 3a,e</xref>) because the system stays close to the stable fixed point during the ramp. When the bistability regime starts (FLC), the system remains within the basin of attraction of the fixed point. Sometimes the current during the up-ramp becomes large enough to induce a depolarization block, but decreasing <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e349.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> from there during <italic>Down</italic> may induce repetitive spiking. The amplitudes that result in block with a ramp current can also be different from the depolarization block stimulus predicted by the analysis in which <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e350.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> is constant.</p><fig id="pone-0034636-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0034636.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Dynamics of the model with DD currents and UTD stimulation.</title><p>Panels <bold>a&#x02013;c</bold> show, respectively, the current stimulus, membrane potentials of DD, and CB models as a function of time. Epochs last 250 milliseconds each (slope <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e351.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>2.82 nA/ms), <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e352.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, maximum stimulus amplitude 705 pA, and all other parameters as in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0034636-t002">Table 2</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.g004"/></fig><p>From comparing the <italic>response profiles</italic> to UTD stimulation with different maximal amplitudes and while keeping the same ramp durations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034636-g005">Fig. 5a&#x02013;b</xref>), it is possible to generalize the observation that sustained spiking in the DD model starts for smaller maximal current amplitudes in comparison to the CB model. The two models show two kinds of <italic>hysteresis</italic>: (1) with respect to the recruitment and de-recruitment current amplitudes, and (2) with respect to the recruitment and de-recruitment firing rates. As a rule of thumb for slow ramps, the recruitment current is more likely to be smaller than the de-recruitment current with a larger recruitment firing rate larger in comparison to the de-recruitment rate (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034636-g005">Fig. 5</xref> and also <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0034636.s006">Fig. S6c</xref>,f); the trend reverses for steep ramps (compare traces with low and high <italic>Top</italic> amplitudes in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034636-g005">Fig. 5a&#x02013;b</xref>). Also, the current at which spiking ceases during <italic>Up</italic> can be different than the current for which spiking starts during <italic>Down</italic> (upper traces of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034636-g005">Fig. 5a</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0034636-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0034636.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Response profiles of DD and CB models to UTD stimulation.</title><p>Panels <bold>a</bold> and <bold>b</bold> show, respectively, the responses displayed by the DD and CB versions of the system Eqs. 5 and 6. All simulations with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e353.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;2.5 with epochs lasting 250 ms and maximum stimulus amplitudes between 0.2 and 8 nA in increments of 0.5 nA.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.g005"/></fig><p>There is thus some qualitative agreement in the predictions of the behavior of the DD and CB models for constant <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e354.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and ramp stimulation. As predicted for constant <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e355.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, the recruitment current for the DD model is smaller relative to that of the CB model and within a smaller range (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034636-g004">Fig. 4b&#x02013;c</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034636-g005">Fig. 5a&#x02013;b</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s3f"><title>Different responses to the same synaptic input</title><p>The general differences in excitability described previously should also hold when <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e356.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> represents synaptic input. Two questions of particular importance for the study of motor neuron behavior, and for network models in general, are whether recruitment with excitatory synaptic input occurs for smaller synaptic drive in the DD model in comparison to the CB model.</p><p>To compare the response profiles of the two models, simulations were performed assuming <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e357.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> represents fast excitatory synaptic input ( Eqs. 7 and 8, and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0034636-t001">Table 1</xref>). The effects of synaptic drive on the two models are compared by increasing the number of synaptic contacts. The input axons, and hence their spiking activity, were assumed to be the same for the DD and CB models. On the postsynaptic end, the maximum amplitude, reversal potential, activation and inactivation constants, average number of active synapses, and the relative contributions of all channels, including the ones mediating synaptic input, are all identical in both models. The same excitatory synaptic input given to both models (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034636-g006">Fig. 6</xref>) produces similar fluctuations in their membrane potential (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034636-g006">Fig. 6a</xref>) with nearly identical synaptic currents except those around spike times (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034636-g006">Fig. 6b</xref>). Nevertheless, in agreement with the earlier recruitment of the DD model shown in the previous analysis, the DD model in the example illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034636-g006">Fig. 6</xref> fires more action potentials than the CB model for the same number of input synapses.</p><fig id="pone-0034636-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0034636.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>DD and CB action potentials in response to fast excitatory synaptic input.</title><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Membrane potential for the DD (black) and CB (blue) models, and presynaptic spike times (vertical dashed lines). (<bold>b</bold>) Post-synaptic current. Parameters: <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e358.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;150, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e359.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;10.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.g006"/></fig><p>To generate examples of the response profiles for the two models as a function of increasing excitatory input, the dynamics of the DD and CB membrane potentials were simulated for different numbers of excitatory axons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034636-g007">Fig. 7</xref>) assuming <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e360.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;2.5. Regular spiking responses (with relatively constant inter-spike intervals) occur when approximately 250 inputs excite the DD model. In contrast, the CB model starts producing regular spiking with approximately 450 inputs. In other words, the smallest number of activated excitatory synapses necessary to trigger sustained spiking in the DD model under consideration is smaller (by a factor close to 2) than the number of synapses needed to elicit repetitive spiking in the CB neuron. Therefore, the <italic>same synaptic input</italic> produced very different responses in these two model neurons having the same populations of ion channels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034636-g007">Fig. 7</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0034636-g007" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0034636.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>Profiles of DD and CB responses to excitatory synaptic input.</title><p>All simulations with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e361.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;2.5 with increasing numbers of excitatory synapses assuming the average number of activated synapses per input axon <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e362.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;10.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.g007"/></fig><p>The difference in the number of inputs required to recruit DD or CB neurons could have an important impact on the output properties and computations performed by small networks with a few thousand neurons.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="s4a"><title>Advantages of the drift-diffusion model</title><p>The formulation of currents based on DD from Eq. 3 represents a theoretical improvement over CB models. One consequence of taking diffusion into account is that currents in the DD model display rectification and other properties that cannot be observed in CB formulations without increasing the dimensionality of the system. Therefore, in comparison to CB models, DD formulations give more realistic representations of excitable membranes that do not require a large increase in computation. DD models could thus advance our current understanding of dynamical behavior in single cells and networks. For instance, the formulations shown here can be used to infer patterns of synaptic connectivity from knowledge about the input-output properties in cells or specific information about correlation patterns in their activity as done in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-HerreraValdez3">[35]</xref>. In addition, the normalizations used in this article allow estimations of relative patterns of channel expression.</p><p>As pointed out in the seminal work by Goldman <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Goldman1">[11]</xref>, by researchers in cardiophysiology (see for instance see Na<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e363.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, and K<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e364.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> currents in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Demir1">[63]</xref>) and neurophysiology <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Clay1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Clay2">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Clay4">[64]</xref>, the constant field approximation describes the voltage-dependence of currents better than the CB approach. Recall the Goldman constant field approximation is a particular case of the DD formulation used here. Evidence indicating that the DD approach is better in general can be found in several reports containing IV relationships with tails of hyperbolic sine shape. To mention a few instances, see recordings from photoreceptors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Hardie1">[65]</xref>, calcium channels <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Smith1">[66]</xref>, sodium channels <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Warmke1">[67]</xref> in <italic>Drosophila</italic>, snail neurons <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Neher1">[68]</xref>, in the mammalian cortex <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Baranauskas1">[69]</xref>, and even in glial cell recordings as reported in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Tang1">[70]</xref>. The DD models have the advantage that measurements can be made directly from the currents recorded without extra calculations of maximal conductances. Such conductances are obtained as slopes of the current-voltage relationship, assuming current is the product of a conductance and a voltage difference (electrical drift only). When using the DD formulation, the maximal currents from voltage-clamp experiments can be directly fit with the model because the leading coefficients in the DD formulation are already in units of current and no extra calculations are needed. This &#x0201c;out of the box&#x0201d; behavior is reassuring because it enables the direct translation from recordings to computational models.</p><p>A complementary comparison between the DD and CB models should be done, however, against experimental measurements. One way in which it would be possible to decide whether to use DD or CB models would be to compare the response profiles of a cell membrane having blocked as many currents as possible, except the transient Na<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e365.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and delayed-rectifier K<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e366.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> currents. Preparations like the squid giant axon might be ideal in this regard <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Clay1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Clay2">[15]</xref>. An alternative approach could be to use an exogenous expression system to construct an excitable cell and test the two models there. The idea in general is that the basic input-output properties of the recordings should be fit with the two models along with spike shapes and firing rates. The channel kinetics should be determined from voltage-clamp experiments. To determine the relative contribution of the channels, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e367.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> can be estimated from the maximum <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e368.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e369.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>. The relative contribution of the K<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e370.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> current <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e371.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> can then be found by matching the shape of the total steady state current. The resulting bifurcation profile (e.g. a fixed point curve like those from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034636-g002">Fig. 2 a&#x02013;b</xref>) would then be assigned to the recording. Once the bifurcation profile that matches the data has been determined, the stimulus currents giving repetitive spiking with both square pulses and with ramps should be better predicted by either the DD or CB model. In consideration of the more realistic representation of transmembrane current provided by the DD approach, the author hypothesizes that the DD model would yield more accurate predictions.</p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title>Mathematical relationship between the DD and CB models</title><p>The whole-membrane behavior of the DD model shares many of the properties of CB models in that it contains parameters that can be found experimentally and displays dynamics observable in excitable cells. As shown in previous paragraphs, the two models are mathematically related: the CB formulation for current is a linear approximation of the DD formulation around the reversal potential for the current. In agreement with previous reports <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Clay1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Clay2">[15]</xref>, the divergence between the CB and DD currents near typical resting potentials can be further decreased when channel gating is taken into account. As a result, the DD and CB versions of the system Eqs. 5&#x02013;6 display some qualitatively similar behaviors when observed macroscopically, but over different ranges of parameters. However, the two models with identical ion channel populations display qualitatively and quantitatively different transitions in their behaviors (i.e. the CB and DD models are <italic>not</italic> topologically equivalent).</p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title>Similar but not same excitabilities with the same channel populations</title><p>The DD and CB models are compared by setting the relative contributions of the channels to be identical in both models. One of the most obvious differences between the DD and CB models is their range for repetitive oscillations. In general, if the ratio between the maximum K<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e372.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and Na<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e373.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> current amplitudes is larger than <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e374.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1.2, then the DD model responds with action potentials for smaller external input currents found within a smaller range compared with the CB model. The number of input axons that causes sustained spiking is smaller, and within a narrower range in the DD model in comparison to the CB model. The DD membrane is thus more excitable, and responds within a smaller input range, than the CB membrane. Further, if the excitability type is defined as the kind of rest-to-spiking transition observed while the external current increases smoothly (e.g. ramp), the DD and CB models represent membranes with the same populations of channels and different types of excitability (see for instance <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034636-g003">Figs. 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034636-g004">4</xref>).</p><p>Interestingly, both models display two different hysteresis-related behaviors with ramping inputs. In very general terms, the recruitment current is larger than the de-recruitment current if the steepness of the ramps is shallow. In contrast, the recruitment current is smaller than the de-recruitment current when the ramps are very steep. For particular interest, the two models display what has been reported as a <italic>slow passage through Hopf</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Baer1">[71]</xref> in which a ramp current triggers sustained oscillations for current amplitudes smaller than <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e375.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, which can be predicted by bifurcation analysis using the stimulus current as the bifurcation parameter. A modified version of the slow passage through Hopf was also observed in simulations of excitatory synaptic input, as the total synaptic current that triggered spiking was also considerably smaller than the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e376.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> of the system.</p><sec id="s4c1"><title>An important remark related to firing rate hysteresis relevant for motor control</title><p>Note the only persistent current in the model is the delayed rectifier K<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e377.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> current. Therefore, the firing rate hysteresis and bistability regimes observed in the CB and DD models presented here are not the result of having persistent Na<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e378.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> or Ca<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e379.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> currents (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Hounsgaard1">[72]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Lee2">[73]</xref>), thus highlighting the importance of explicitly distinguishing firing rate hysteresis and bistability behaviors from the presence of persistent inward currents in a membrane.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s4d"><title>Model specificity and extensions</title><p>The models are constructed based on <italic>Drosophila</italic> data. The choice of the specific channels and animal model is based on the large availability of whole-cell patch clamp recordings, which provide measurements that can be directly used as model parameters. In addition, the use of <italic>Drosophila</italic> data allows interpretations in terms of specific channel genes. Since the parameters used here are representative of central neurons in <italic>Drosophila</italic> the post-synaptic currents are assumed to be mediated by fast cholinergic receptors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Lee1">[44]</xref>. It should be noted, however, that the biophysical properties of homologous channels in vertebrates have also been characterized (for sodium channels see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Caldwell1">[74]</xref>; potassium channels <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Wei1">[37]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Islas1">[40]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Pak1">[75]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Salkoff1">[76]</xref>; cholinergic neurotransmission <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Chu1">[77]</xref>; central synapses mediated with glutamate receptors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Destexhe1">[32]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Walmsley1">[78]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Destexhe2">[79]</xref>). Therefore, the approach taken here can easily extended to represent other channels so the formulations of membrane potential can be adjusted to model other systems.</p></sec><sec id="s4e"><title>Data fitting and modeling techniques</title><p>For theoretical interest, writing the model in terms of ratios using the normalizing amplitude <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e380.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> allows fixing one of the maximal current amplitudes in the model while fitting the maximum <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e381.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> to data. This way, the whole-membrane behavior can be tuned in terms of the relative contributions of the different channels guided by bifurcation theory, thus providing an alternative to brute-force fitting algorithms and other statistical approaches <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Prinz1">[80]</xref>. Furthermore, the conceptual improvement in the formulation for single channels is extended to facilitate quantitative agreement at the whole-membrane level.</p><p>The analysis and fitting procedures presented here can guide studies geared toward understanding cellular responses recorded in the laboratory under genetic and pharmacological manipulations. In this respect, it is worth remarking that this is one of only a few modeling efforts that incorporates data from an identified neuron in a single model system in which both the ion channel genes and their biophysics are known. Importantly, the results shown here in regard to the differences between the DD and CB models also hold if the models are adjusted to match the cellular dynamics in other model organisms. For instance, if the parameters are adjusted so that the membrane has the input resistance and capacitance measured from a vertebrate cell of interest, with fast-transient Na<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e382.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and K<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e383.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> delayed rectifier channels (e.g. Nav1.2 and Kv2.1) and fast AMPA synapses, the DD and CB models will display the same general qualitative differences in excitability presented here. If the specific genes are not known, the phenotypical behavior of currents can still be associated with specific families of proteins grouped by function (say, mediating fast-transient Na<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e384.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> currents), which can be modeled with the approach shown in this article. Another extension of this work could be made to incorporate neuronal structure and address issues related to the targeting of channels to specific submembrane domains. One further extension would involve the construction of networks formed with different cell types having realistic synaptic interactions to study the role played by synaptic efficacy, number of input synapses, and other variables on the input-output properties of networks.</p></sec><sec id="s4f"><title>Final remarks</title><p>The construction of the membrane models in this article rests on the hypothesis that the relative presence of channels in the membrane determines, to a large extent, what we could refer to as the <italic>electrophysiological profile</italic> of a cell <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-HerreraValdez1">[27]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Nowotny1">[81]</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Pedersen1">[83]</xref>. This theoretical principle was used here to compare and contrast responses to current injection and synaptic input of two membranes expressing identified ion channel genes with known biophysical properties. The non-topological equivalence between the DD and CB models predicts qualitatively different behaviors for the same patterns of channel expression. As shown here, the nonlinearities in the DD formulation for transmembrane currents can fundamentally change the spike-generating mechanisms and sensitivity to external stimulation in the whole DD model. Of particular importance, the two models generally display different spike-generating mechanisms as a function of the input current, synaptic or applied. As a consequence, the input and output firing rates of DD and CB cells within network models will be very different on any given architecture, potentially giving rise to very different results and interpretations. These differences are important because the intrinsic properties of neurons (and excitable cells in general) shape the activity of cellular networks to which they belong. Conversely, the network also influences the electrophysiological profile of single cells through the population of channels that mediate synaptic input and also through other modulatory influences. This is a subject that warrants a further and more careful examination currently underway.</p><p>The results presented here highlight the importance of exploring the different responses produced by two kinds of extensions of the DD models presented here: spatially detailed models and networks. These two extensions (and others) are likely to yield very different results and predictions in comparison to those from existing CB models, potentially prompting a reevaluation and possibly, a re-interpretation of accepted theories originated from network models of nervous function.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0034636.s001"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p><bold>Fitting of voltage clamp data from Shab channels </bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034636-Tsunoda2">[<bold>39</bold>]</xref><bold>.</bold> The data (black dots) were digitized from the original publication and fitting was done with a python script. The blue curves are fits to the data parameters <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e385.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>. Middle, steady state activation from the tail currents shown in the top panel (black dots), and average from all recordings (white dots). The lower panel shows the time constant fit.</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0034636.s001.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0034636.s002"><label>Figure S2</label><caption><p><bold>Cholinergic Synaptic input.</bold></p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0034636.s002.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0034636.s003"><label>Figure S3</label><caption><p><bold>Steady state currents for the DD and CB models for </bold><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e386.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula><bold>.</bold> The top curve in each panel of corresponds to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e387.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, the bottom curve corresponds to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e388.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, and the vertical gray line indicates the total current is zero.</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0034636.s003.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0034636.s004"><label>Figure S4</label><caption><p><bold>Trajectories of membrane potential with different levels of depolarization from rest (</bold><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e389.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula><bold>).</bold> DD (solid) and CB (dashed) for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e390.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> shown from left to right. The upper panels show the membrane potential and fixed points for the two models (DD solid lines and dots, CB dashed lines and circles). The lower panels show the corresponding currents (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e391.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e392.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e393.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e394.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> in red, blue, green, and black, respectively, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e395.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>). (<bold>a</bold>) <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e396.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> shifted 26 mV. (<bold>b</bold>) <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e397.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> shifted 34 mV.</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0034636.s004.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0034636.s005"><label>Figure S5</label><caption><p><bold>Profile of responses to square pulses of different amplitude.</bold> The pulses lasted 200 milliseconds with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e398.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;2. The minumum pulse amplitude was 0.025 nA, the steps where 0.5 nA.</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0034636.s005.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0034636.s006"><label>Figure S6</label><caption><p><bold>Comparison of phase trajectories and instantaneous firing rate during UTD stimulation.</bold> Panels <bold>a</bold> and <bold>c</bold> show, respectively, DD and CB trajectories in the phase plane <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e399.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>. The solid gray curves in panels represent the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e400.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e401.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>-nullclines in the absence of stimulation. The dashed gray line represents the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e402.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>-nullcline during <italic>Top</italic>. <bold>b</bold> and <bold>d</bold> Graphs of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e403.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> for DD and CB models, respectively. The horizontal line illustrates the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0034636.e404.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>-location of the fixed point. <bold>c</bold> and <bold>f</bold> Instantaneous firing rates as a function of time. The horizontal lines illustrate the recruitment and de-recruitment firing rates (blue and black, respectively).</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0034636.s006.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0034636.s007"><label>Text S1</label><caption><p>Overview of the derivation of the expressions for current driven by electrodiffusive transport and notes about bifurcation analysis.</p><p>(TEX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0034636.s007.tex" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="plain"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>The author thanks Joceline Lega for her guidance, criticism, and encouragement. Thanks also to Sandra Berger, Greg Buzzard, and Errol Montes-Pizarro for their comments and all the discussions we had related to this manuscript. Special thanks to Erin McKiernan and the two unknown reviewers for their encouragement and suggestions which helped to improve this manuscript. The author extends special thanks to Isar Godreau and other members of the BRIC team from the Institute of Interdisciplinary Research at the University of Puerto Rico in Cayey for their financial and logistic support, which made this publication possible.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="conflict"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding: </bold>Partial funding for this publication was provided by the University of Puerto Rico through its BRIC program from the National. No additional external funding was received for this study Center for Minority Health and Health Disparities (NCMHD), grant #1P20MD006144-01.The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0034636-Hille1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hille</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1992</year>
<article-title>Ionic Channels of Excitable Membranes.</article-title>
<comment>Sinauer Associates, Inc. Sunderland, Mass. 01375: Sinauer Associates</comment>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Hodgkin1"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hodgkin</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Huxley</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1952</year>
<article-title>A quantitative description of membrane current and its application to conduction and excitation in nerve.</article-title>
<source>Journal of Physiology</source>
<volume>117</volume>
<fpage>500</fpage>
<lpage>544</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12991237</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-DiFrancesco1"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>DiFrancesco</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Noble</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1985</year>
<article-title>A model of cardiac electrical activity incorporating ionic pumps and concentration changes.</article-title>
<source>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London Series B, Biological Sciences</source>
<volume>307</volume>
<fpage>353</fpage>
<lpage>398</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Johnston1"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>SMS</given-names></name><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1995</year>
<article-title>Foundations of cellular neurophysiology.</article-title>
<comment>MIT press Cambridge, MA</comment>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Koch1"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Segev</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1998</year>
<article-title>Methods in neuronal modeling: from ions to networks.</article-title>
<comment>MIT press Cambridge, MA</comment>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Izhikevich1"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Izhikevich</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Dynamical Systems in Neuroscience.</article-title>
<comment>MIT Press, 55 Hayward Street, Cambridge MA 02142: MIT</comment>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Ermentrout1"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ermentrout</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><name><surname>Terman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<source>Foundations of mathematical neuroscience (Interdisciplinary applied mathematics series, Vol. 35)</source>
<publisher-name>Springer Verlag</publisher-name>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Stevens1"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsien</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1979</year>
<source>Ion permeation through membrane channels, volume 3</source>
<publisher-name>Raven Press</publisher-name>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Weiss1"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1996</year>
<source>Cellular biophysics, volume 2: electrical properties</source>
<publisher-name>MIT Press</publisher-name>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Weiss2"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1996</year>
<source>Cellular Biophysics, Volume 1: Transport</source>
<publisher-name>MIT Press</publisher-name>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Goldman1"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goldman</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1943</year>
<article-title>Potential, impedance, and rectification in membranes.</article-title>
<source>Journal of general Physiology</source>
<volume>27</volume>
<fpage>37</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19873371</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Eisenberg1"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eisenberg</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1998</year>
<article-title>Ionic channels in biological membranes: natural nanotubes.</article-title>
<source>Accounts of chemical research</source>
<volume>31</volume>
<fpage>117</fpage>
<lpage>123</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Endresen1"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Endresen</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoye</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Myrheim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>A theory for the membrane potential of living cells.</article-title>
<source>European Journal of Biophysics</source>
<volume>29</volume>
<fpage>90</fpage>
<lpage>103</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Clay1"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clay</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Paydarfar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Forger</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>A simple modification of the hodgkin and huxley equations explains type 3 excitability in squid giant axons.</article-title>
<source>Journal of The Royal Society Interface</source>
<volume>5</volume>
<fpage>1421</fpage>
<lpage>1428</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Clay2"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clay</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Determining k&#x0002b; channel activation curves from k&#x0002b; channel currents often requires the goldman-hodgkin-katz equation.</article-title>
<source>Frontiers in Cellular Neuroscience</source>
<volume>3</volume>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Krinski1"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krinski&#x000e4;</surname><given-names>VI</given-names></name><name><surname>Kokoz</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1973</year>
<article-title>Analysis of the equations of excitable membranes. i. reduction of the hodgkins-huxley equations to a 2d order system].</article-title>
<source>Biofizika</source>
<volume>18</volume>
<fpage>506</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4717781</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Morris1"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lecar</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1981</year>
<article-title>Voltage oscillations in the barnacle giant muscle fiber.</article-title>
<source>Biophysical Journal</source>
<volume>35</volume>
<fpage>193</fpage>
<lpage>213</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7260316</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Rinzel1"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rinzel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1985</year>
<article-title>Excitation dynamics: insights from simplified membrane models.</article-title>
<comment>In: Fed. Proc. 44. volume 2944</comment>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-AvRon1"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Av-Ron</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Parnas</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Segel</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1991</year>
<article-title>A minimal biophysical model for an excitable and oscillatory neuron.</article-title>
<source>Biological Cybernetics</source>
<volume>65</volume>
<fpage>487</fpage>
<lpage>500</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1958734</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Kepler1"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kepler</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name><name><surname>Abbott</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name><name><surname>Marder</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1992</year>
<article-title>Reduction of conductance-based neuron models.</article-title>
<source>Biological Cybernetics</source>
<volume>66</volume>
<fpage>381</fpage>
<lpage>387</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1562643</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Adrian1"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adrian</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandler</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name><name><surname>Hodgkin</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1970</year>
<article-title>Voltage clamp experiments in striated muscle fibres.</article-title>
<source>The Journal of Physiology</source>
<volume>208</volume>
<fpage>607</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5499787</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Fohlmeister1"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fohlmeister</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1990</year>
<article-title>Modeling the repetitive firing of retinal ganglion cells.</article-title>
<source>Brain research</source>
<volume>510</volume>
<fpage>343</fpage>
<lpage>345</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2331606</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Buchholtz1"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buchholtz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Golowasch</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names>IR</given-names></name><name><surname>Marder</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1992</year>
<article-title>Mathematical model of an identified stomatogastric ganglion neuron.</article-title>
<source>Journal of neurophysiology</source>
<volume>67</volume>
<fpage>332</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1373763</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Traub1"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Traub</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Miles</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Michelson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1991</year>
<article-title>A model of a ca3 hippocampal pyramidal neuron incorporating voltage-clamp data on intrinsic conductances.</article-title>
<source>Journal of Neurophysiology</source>
<volume>66</volume>
<fpage>635</fpage>
<lpage>650</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1663538</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Ikeno1"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ikeno</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Usui</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>Mathematical description of ionic currents of the kenyon cell in the mushroom body of honeybee.</article-title>
<source>Neurocomputing</source>
<volume>26</volume>
<fpage>177</fpage>
<lpage>184</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Clay3"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clay</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1984</year>
<article-title>Potassium channel kinetics in squid axons with elevated levels of external potassium concentration.</article-title>
<source>Biophysical journal</source>
<volume>45</volume>
<fpage>481</fpage>
<lpage>485</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6320918</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-HerreraValdez1"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herrera-Valdez</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lega</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Reduced models for the pacemaker dynamics of cardiac cells.</article-title>
<source>Journal of Theoretical Biology</source>
<volume>270</volume>
<fpage>164</fpage>
<lpage>176</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20932980</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Mitchell1"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaeffer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>A two-current model for the dynamics of cardiac membrane.</article-title>
<source>Bulletin of mathematical biology</source>
<volume>65</volume>
<fpage>767</fpage>
<lpage>793</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12909250</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-HerreraValdez2"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herrera-Valdez</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Geometry and dynamics of minimal biophysical models of membrane excitability.</article-title>
<comment>Dissertation PhD in Mathematics University of Arizona</comment>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Nonner1"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nonner</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Eisenberg</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1998</year>
<article-title>Ion permeation and glutamate residues linked by poisson-nernstplanck theory in l-type calcium channels.</article-title>
<source>Biophysical Journal</source>
<volume>75</volume>
<fpage>1287</fpage>
<lpage>1305</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9726931</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Aldrich1"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aldrich</surname><given-names>RW, DPC</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1983</year>
<article-title>A reinterpretation of mammalian sodium channel gating based on single channel recording.</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<volume>306</volume>
<fpage>436</fpage>
<lpage>441</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6316158</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Destexhe1"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Destexhe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mainen</surname><given-names>ZF</given-names></name><name><surname>Sejnowski</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1994</year>
<article-title>An Efficient Method for Computing Synaptic Conductances Based on a Kinetic Model of Receptor Binding.</article-title>
<source>Neural Computation</source>
<volume>6</volume>
<fpage>14</fpage>
<lpage>18</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Willms1"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Willms</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Baro</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris-Warrick</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Guckenheimer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>An improved parameter estimation method for hodgkin-huxley models.</article-title>
<source>Journal of Computational Neuroscience</source>
<volume>6</volume>
<fpage>145</fpage>
<lpage>168</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10333160</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Gerstner1"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gerstner</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Kistler</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<source>Spiking neuron models</source>
<publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-HerreraValdez3"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herrera-Valdez</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Relationship between nearly coincident spiking and common excitatory synaptic input in motor neurons.</article-title>
<comment>Ph.D. thesis, The University of Arizona</comment>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Jack1"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jack</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Redman</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1981</year>
<article-title>The components of synaptic potentials evoked in cat spinal motoneurones by impulses in single group ia afferents.</article-title>
<source>Journal of Physiology</source>
<volume>321</volume>
<fpage>65</fpage>
<lpage>96</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6279826</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Wei1"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Covarrubias</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Pak</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>1990</year>
<article-title>K&#x0002b; current diversity is produced by an extended gene family conserved in Drosophila and mouse.</article-title>
<source>Science</source>
<volume>248</volume>
<fpage>599</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2333511</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Tsunoda1"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsunoda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Salkoff</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1995</year>
<article-title>Genetic Analysis of Drosophila Neurons: Shal, Shaw, and Shab Encode Most Embryonic Potassium Currents.</article-title>
<source>Journal of Neuroscience</source>
<volume>15</volume>
<fpage>1741</fpage>
<lpage>1754</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7891132</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Tsunoda2"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsunoda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Salkoff</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1995</year>
<article-title>The major delayed rectifier in both Drosophila neurons and muscle is encoded by Shab.</article-title>
<source>Journal of Neuroscience</source>
<volume>15</volume>
<fpage>5209</fpage>
<lpage>5221</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7623146</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Islas1"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Islas</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Sigworth</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>Voltage sensitivity and gating charge in Shaker and Shab family potassium channels.</article-title>
<source>Journal of General Physiology</source>
<volume>114</volume>
<fpage>723</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10539976</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-ODowd1"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O'Dowd</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Aldrich</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1988</year>
<article-title>Voltage-clamp analysis of sodium channels in wild-type and mutant Drosophila neurons.</article-title>
<source>Journal of Neuroscience</source>
<volume>8</volume>
<fpage>3633</fpage>
<lpage>3643</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2848103</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Lin1"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Muraro</surname><given-names>NI</given-names></name><name><surname>Baines</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Alternative Splicing in the Voltage-Gated Sodium Channel DmNav Regulates Activation, Inactivation, and Persistent Current.</article-title>
<source>Journal of Neurophysiology</source>
<volume>102</volume>
<fpage>1994</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19625535</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-King1"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name><name><surname>Escoubas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicholson</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Peptide toxins that selectively target insect na and ca channels.</article-title>
<source>Channels</source>
<volume>2</volume>
<fpage>100</fpage>
<lpage>116</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18849658</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Lee1"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Dowd</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>Fast Excitatory Synaptic Transmission Mediated by Nicotinic Acetylcholine Receptors in Drosophila Neurons.</article-title>
<source>Journal of Neuroscience</source>
<volume>19</volume>
<fpage>5311</fpage>
<lpage>5321</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10377342</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Katz1"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Miledi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1973</year>
<article-title>The binding of acetylcholine to receptors and its removal from the synaptic cleft.</article-title>
<source>The Journal of physiology</source>
<volume>231</volume>
<fpage>549</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4361216</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Roerig1"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roerig</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1997</year>
<article-title>Fast synaptic signaling by nicotinic acetylcholine and serotonin 5-ht3 receptors in developing visual cortex.</article-title>
<source>The Journal of neuroscience</source>
<volume>17</volume>
<fpage>8353</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9334409</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Galligan1"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Galligan</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>LePard</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Multiple mechanisms of fast excitatory synaptic transmission in the enteric nervous system.</article-title>
<source>Journal of the autonomic nervous system</source>
<volume>81</volume>
<fpage>97</fpage>
<lpage>103</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10869707</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Rasmusson1"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rasmusson</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Giles</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><name><surname>Shibata</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1990</year>
<article-title>A mathematical model of bullfrog cardiac pacemaker cell.</article-title>
<source>Am J Physiol</source>
<volume>259</volume>
<fpage>H352</fpage>
<lpage>H369</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2167020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Rasmusson2"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rasmusson</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Giles</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>1990</year>
<article-title>A mathematical model of electrophysiological activity in the bullfrog atrial cell.</article-title>
<source>Am J Physiol</source>
<volume>259</volume>
<fpage>H370</fpage>
<lpage>H389</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2386218</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Wilders1"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilders</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Computer modelling of the sinoatrial node.</article-title>
<source>Medical and Biological Engineering and Computing</source>
<volume>45</volume>
<fpage>189</fpage>
<lpage>207</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17115219</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Ribalet1"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ribalet</surname><given-names>B, PMB</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1982</year>
<article-title>Effects of sodium on beta-cell electrical activity.</article-title>
<source>American Journal of Physiology-Cell Physiology</source>
<volume>242</volume>
<fpage>C296</fpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Fohlmeister2"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fohlmeister</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1997</year>
<article-title>Impulse Encoding Mechanisms of Ganglion Cells in the Tiger Salamander Retina.</article-title>
<source>Journal of Neurophysiology</source>
<volume>78</volume>
<fpage>1935</fpage>
<lpage>1947</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9325362</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Rinzel2"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rinzel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ermentrout</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1989</year>
<article-title>Analysis of neural excitability and oscillations, Methods in neuronal modeling: From synapses to networks.</article-title>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Strogatz1"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Strogatz</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1994</year>
<article-title>Nonlinear dynamics and chaos: With applications to physics, biology, chemistry, and engineering.</article-title>
<source>Westview Pr</source>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Rall1"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rall</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1959</year>
<article-title>Branching dendritic trees and motoneuron membrane resistivity.</article-title>
<source>Experimental Neurology</source>
<volume>1</volume>
<fpage>491</fpage>
<lpage>527</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14435979</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Rall2"><label>56</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rall</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1962</year>
<article-title>Theory of physiological properties of dendrites.</article-title>
<source>Annals of the New York Academy of Sciences</source>
<volume>96</volume>
<fpage>1071</fpage>
<lpage>1092</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14490041</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Rall3"><label>57</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rall</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Rinzel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1973</year>
<article-title>Branch input resistance and steady attenuation for input to one branch of a dendritic neuron model.</article-title>
<source>Biophysical journal</source>
<volume>13</volume>
<fpage>648</fpage>
<lpage>688</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4715583</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Kuhn1"><label>58</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Aertsen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rotter</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Neuronal integration of synaptic input in the uctuationdriven regime.</article-title>
<source>Journal of Neuroscience</source>
<volume>24</volume>
<fpage>2345</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15014109</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Peng1"><label>59</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>IF</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Differential contributions of Shaker and Shab K&#x0002b; currents to neuronal firing patterns in Drosophila.</article-title>
<source>Journal of Neurophysiology</source>
<volume>97</volume>
<fpage>780</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17079336</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Yang1"><label>60</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>CZ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Membrane current-based mechanisms for excitability transitions in neurons of the rat mesencephalic trigeminal nuclei.</article-title>
<source>Neuroscience</source>
<volume>163</volume>
<fpage>799</fpage>
<lpage>810</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19591906</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Vandenberg1"><label>61</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vandenberg</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bezanilla</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1991</year>
<article-title>Single-channel, macroscopic, and gating currents from sodium channels in the squid giant axon.</article-title>
<source>Biophysical journal</source>
<volume>60</volume>
<fpage>1499</fpage>
<lpage>1510</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1663795</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Rinzel3"><label>62</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rinzel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Baer</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1988</year>
<article-title>Threshold for repetitive activity for a slow stimulus ramp: a memory effect and its dependence on uctuations.</article-title>
<source>Biophysical journal</source>
<volume>54</volume>
<fpage>551</fpage>
<lpage>555</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3207840</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Demir1"><label>63</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Demir</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphey</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Giles</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1994</year>
<article-title>A mathematical model of a rabbit sinoatrial node cell.</article-title>
<source>American Journal of Physiology-Cell Physiology</source>
<volume>266</volume>
<fpage>C832</fpage>
<lpage>C852</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Clay4"><label>64</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clay</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1991</year>
<article-title>A paradox concerning ion permeation of the delayed rectifier potassium ion channel in squid giant axons.</article-title>
<source>The Journal of Physiology</source>
<volume>444</volume>
<fpage>499</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1822560</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Hardie1"><label>65</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hardie</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Minke</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1994</year>
<article-title>Spontaneous activation of light-sensitive channels in drosophila photoreceptors.</article-title>
<source>The Journal of general physiology</source>
<volume>103</volume>
<fpage>389</fpage>
<lpage>407</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8195780</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Smith1"><label>66</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>XJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Peixoto</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Neumann</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>1996</year>
<article-title>A drosophila calcium channel <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>1 subunit gene maps to a genetic locus associated with behavioral and visual defects.</article-title>
<source>The Journal of neuroscience</source>
<volume>16</volume>
<fpage>7868</fpage>
<lpage>7879</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8987815</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Warmke1"><label>67</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Warmke</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Reenan</surname><given-names>RAG</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Arena</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>1997</year>
<article-title>Functional expression of drosophila para sodium channels.</article-title>
<source>The Journal of general physiology</source>
<volume>110</volume>
<fpage>119</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9236205</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Neher1"><label>68</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neher</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1971</year>
<article-title>Two fast transient current components during voltage clamp on snail neurons.</article-title>
<source>Journal of General Physiology</source>
<volume>58</volume>
<fpage>36</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5564761</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Baranauskas1"><label>69</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baranauskas</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Martina</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Sodium currents activate without a hodgkin and huxley-type delay in central mammalian neurons.</article-title>
<source>The Journal of Neuroscience</source>
<volume>26</volume>
<fpage>671</fpage>
<lpage>684</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16407565</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Tang1"><label>70</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Perez-Leighton</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Kofuji</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Inwardly rectifying potassium channel kir4. 1 is responsible for the native inward potassium conductance of satellite glial cells in sensory ganglia.</article-title>
<source>Neuroscience</source>
<volume>166</volume>
<fpage>397</fpage>
<lpage>407</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20074622</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Baer1"><label>71</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baer</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Erneux</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Rinzel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1989</year>
<article-title>The slow passage through a Hopf bifurcation: delay, memory effects, and resonance.</article-title>
<source>SIAM Journal on Applied mathematics</source>
<volume>49</volume>
<fpage>55</fpage>
<lpage>71</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Hounsgaard1"><label>72</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hounsgaard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hultborn</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Jespersen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiehn</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1984</year>
<article-title>Intrinsic membrane properties causing a bistable behaviour of <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-motoneurones.</article-title>
<source>Experimental brain research</source>
<volume>55</volume>
<fpage>391</fpage>
<lpage>394</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Lee2"><label>73</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Heckman</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1998</year>
<article-title>Bistability in spinal motoneurons in vivo: systematic variations in persistent inward currents.</article-title>
<source>Journal of neurophysiology</source>
<volume>80</volume>
<fpage>583</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9705452</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Caldwell1"><label>74</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caldwell</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaller</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lasher</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Peles</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Levinson</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Sodium channel Nav1. 6 is localized at nodes of Ranvier, dendrites, and synapses.</article-title>
<source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source>
<volume>97</volume>
<fpage>5616</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10779552</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Pak1"><label>75</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pak</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Covarrubias</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ratcliffe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Salkoff</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1991</year>
<article-title>A mouse brain homolog of the Drosophila Shab K&#x0002b; channel with conserved delayed-rectifier properties.</article-title>
<source>Journal of Neuroscience</source>
<volume>11</volume>
<fpage>869</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2002364</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Salkoff1"><label>76</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salkoff</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Covarrubias</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pak</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>1992</year>
<article-title>An essential set of K&#x0002b; channels conserved in ies, mice and humans.</article-title>
<source>Trends in Neurosciences</source>
<volume>15</volume>
<fpage>161</fpage>
<lpage>166</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1377421</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Chu1"><label>77</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>ZG</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Hablitz</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Nicotinic acetylcholine receptor-mediated synaptic potentials in rat neocortex.</article-title>
<source>Brain research</source>
<volume>887</volume>
<fpage>399</fpage>
<lpage>405</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11134630</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Walmsley1"><label>78</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walmsley</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><name><surname>Tracey</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1987</year>
<article-title>The probabilistic nature of synaptic transmission at a mammalian excitatory central synapse.</article-title>
<source>The Journal of neuroscience</source>
<volume>7</volume>
<fpage>1037</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3033165</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Destexhe2"><label>79</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Destexhe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mainen</surname><given-names>ZF</given-names></name><name><surname>Sejnowski</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1994</year>
<article-title>Synthesis of models for excitable membranes, synaptic transmission and neuromodulation using a common kinetic formalism.</article-title>
<source>Journal of Computational Neuroscience</source>
<volume>1</volume>
<fpage>195</fpage>
<lpage>230</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8792231</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Prinz1"><label>80</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prinz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Billimoria</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Marder</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Alternative to hand-tuning conductance-based models: construction and analysis of databases of model neurons.</article-title>
<source>Journal of Neurophysiology</source>
<volume>90</volume>
<fpage>3998</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12944532</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Nowotny1"><label>81</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nowotny</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sz&#x000fc;cs</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Levi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Selverston</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Models wagging the dog: are circuits constructed with disparate parameters?</article-title>
<source>Neural Computation</source>
<volume>19</volume>
<fpage>1985</fpage>
<lpage>2003</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17571936</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Schulz1"><label>82</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Goaillard</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Marder</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Quantitative expression profiling of identified neurons reveals cell-specific constraints on highly variable levels of gene expression.</article-title>
<source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source>
<volume>104</volume>
<fpage>13187</fpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Pedersen1"><label>83</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>A Biophysical Model of Electrical Activity in Human <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-Cells.</article-title>
<source>Biophysical journal</source>
<volume>99</volume>
<fpage>3200</fpage>
<lpage>3207</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21081067</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0034636-Duch1"><label>84</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Vonhoff</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryglewski</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Dendrite elongation and dendritic branching are affected separately by different forms of intrinsic motoneuron excitability.</article-title>
<source>Journal of Neurophysiology</source>
<volume>100</volume>
<fpage>2525</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18715893</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>