<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Negl Trop Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS Negl Trop Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosntds</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Neglected Tropical Diseases</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1935-2727</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1935-2735</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27280639</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4900637</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0004587</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PNTD-D-15-01959</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Toxicology</subject><subj-group><subject>Toxic Agents</subject><subj-group><subject>Toxins</subject><subj-group><subject>Venoms</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Pathology and Laboratory Medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Toxicology</subject><subj-group><subject>Toxic Agents</subject><subj-group><subject>Toxins</subject><subj-group><subject>Venoms</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Organisms</subject><subj-group><subject>Animals</subject><subj-group><subject>Vertebrates</subject><subj-group><subject>Amniotes</subject><subj-group><subject>Reptiles</subject><subj-group><subject>Squamates</subject><subj-group><subject>Snakes</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Toxicology</subject><subj-group><subject>Toxic Agents</subject><subj-group><subject>Toxins</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Pathology and Laboratory Medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Toxicology</subject><subj-group><subject>Toxic Agents</subject><subj-group><subject>Toxins</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Molecular Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Molecular Biology Techniques</subject><subj-group><subject>Sequencing Techniques</subject><subj-group><subject>Sequence Analysis</subject><subj-group><subject>Sequence Alignment</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Research and Analysis Methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Molecular Biology Techniques</subject><subj-group><subject>Sequencing Techniques</subject><subj-group><subject>Sequence Analysis</subject><subj-group><subject>Sequence Alignment</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>DNA</subject><subj-group><subject>Forms of DNA</subject><subj-group><subject>Complementary DNA</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Biochemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Nucleic acids</subject><subj-group><subject>DNA</subject><subj-group><subject>Forms of DNA</subject><subj-group><subject>Complementary DNA</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Molecular biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Molecular biology techniques</subject><subj-group><subject>Biomolecular isolation</subject><subj-group><subject>RNA isolation</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Research and analysis methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Molecular biology techniques</subject><subj-group><subject>Biomolecular isolation</subject><subj-group><subject>RNA isolation</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Organisms</subject><subj-group><subject>Animals</subject><subj-group><subject>Vertebrates</subject><subj-group><subject>Amniotes</subject><subj-group><subject>Reptiles</subject><subj-group><subject>Squamates</subject><subj-group><subject>Snakes</subject><subj-group><subject>Rattlesnakes</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Research and Analysis Methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Computational Techniques</subject><subj-group><subject>Split-Decomposition Method</subject><subj-group><subject>Multiple Alignment Calculation</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Full-Length Venom Protein cDNA Sequences from Venom-Derived mRNA: Exploring Compositional Variation and Adaptive Multigene Evolution</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Full-Length cDNAs from Snake Venoms</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Modahl</surname><given-names>Cassandra M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mackessy</surname><given-names>Stephen P.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor001">*</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff001"><addr-line>School of Biological Sciences, University of Northern Colorado, Greeley, Colorado, United States of America</addr-line></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Calvete</surname><given-names>Juan</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Instituto de Biomedicina de Valencia, UNITED STATES</addr-line></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: CMM SPM. Performed the experiments: CMM SPM. Analyzed the data: CMM SPM. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: CMM SPM. Wrote the paper: CMM SPM.</p></fn><corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>stephen.mackessy@unco.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>9</day><month>6</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>6</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue>6</issue><elocation-id>e0004587</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>11</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>8</day><month>3</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2016 Modahl, Mackessy</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Modahl, Mackessy</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="pntd.0004587.pdf"/><related-article id="d36e341" related-article-type="companion" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1371/journal.pntd.0004615">
<article-title>Stabilising the Integrity of Snake Venom mRNA Stored Under Tropical Field Conditions Expands Research Horizons</article-title>
</related-article><abstract><p>Envenomation of humans by snakes is a complex and continuously evolving medical emergency, and treatment is made that much more difficult by the diverse biochemical composition of many venoms. Venomous snakes and their venoms also provide models for the study of molecular evolutionary processes leading to adaptation and genotype-phenotype relationships. To compare venom complexity and protein sequences, venom gland transcriptomes are assembled, which usually requires the sacrifice of snakes for tissue. However, toxin transcripts are also present in venoms, offering the possibility of obtaining cDNA sequences directly from venom. This study provides evidence that unknown full-length venom protein transcripts can be obtained from the venoms of multiple species from all major venomous snake families. These unknown venom protein cDNAs are obtained by the use of primers designed from conserved signal peptide sequences within each venom protein superfamily. This technique was used to assemble a partial venom gland transcriptome for the Middle American Rattlesnake (<italic>Crotalus simus tzabcan</italic>) by amplifying sequences for phospholipases A<sub>2</sub>, serine proteases, C-lectins, and metalloproteinases from within venom. Phospholipase A<sub>2</sub> sequences were also recovered from the venoms of several rattlesnakes and an elapid snake (<italic>Pseudechis porphyriacus</italic>), and three-finger toxin sequences were recovered from multiple rear-fanged snake species, demonstrating that the three major clades of advanced snakes (Elapidae, Viperidae, Colubridae) have stable mRNA present in their venoms. These cDNA sequences from venom were then used to explore potential activities derived from protein sequence similarities and evolutionary histories within these large multigene superfamilies. Venom-derived sequences can also be used to aid in characterizing venoms that lack proteomic profiles and identify sequence characteristics indicating specific envenomation profiles. This approach, requiring only venom, provides access to cDNA sequences in the absence of living specimens, even from commercial venom sources, to evaluate important regional differences in venom composition and to study snake venom protein evolution.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="summary"><title>Author Summary</title><p>This work demonstrates that full-length venom protein messenger RNAs are present in secreted venoms and can be used to acquire full-length protein sequences of toxins from both front-fanged (Elapidae, Viperidae) and rear-fanged (Colubridae) snake venoms, eliminating the need to use venom glands. Full-length transcripts were obtained from venom samples that were fresh, newly lyophilized, old, field desiccated or commercially prepared, representing a significant advance over previous attempts which produced only partial sequence transcripts. Transcripts for all major venom protein families (metalloproteinases, serine proteases, C-type lectins, phospholipases A<sub>2</sub> and three-finger toxins) responsible for clinically significant snakebite symptoms were obtained from venoms. These sequences aid in the identification and characterization of venom proteome profiles, allowing for the identification of peptide sequences, specific isoforms, and novel venom proteins. The application of this technique will help to provide venom protein sequences for many snake species, including understudied rear-fanged snakes. Venom protein transcripts offer important insights into potential snakebite envenomation profiles and the molecular evolution of venom protein multigene families. By requiring only venom to obtain venom protein cDNAs, the approach detailed here will provide access to cDNA-based protein sequences from commercial and other venom sources, facilitating study of snake venom protein composition and evolution.</p></abstract><funding-group><award-group id="award001"><funding-source><institution>UNC Provost Fund</institution></funding-source><award-id>n/a</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Mackessy</surname><given-names>Stephen P.</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="award002"><funding-source><institution>UNC Graduate Student Association</institution></funding-source><award-id>n/a</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Modahl</surname><given-names>Cassandra M.</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><funding-statement>The authors received no specific funding for this work.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="8"/><table-count count="4"/><page-count count="24"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><title>Data Availability</title><p>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</p></notes></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001"><title>Introduction</title><p>The evolution of venoms among the advanced colubroid snakes has had tremendous adaptive significance and has allowed this clade to diversify rapidly and occupy a diversity of niches globally [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Snake venoms are complex glandular secretions that may contain 2&#x02013;100+ protein/peptide components with a myriad of biological activities, ranging from potent neurotoxins to rapid-acting myotoxins to hydrolytic enzymes [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. These toxins are synthesized and stored in a cephalic venom gland which allows immediate deployment as a chemical weapon, also necessitating intricate storage and protective mechanisms [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Venoms likely allowed a transition from mechanical capture and processing of prey to one dependent on chemical means [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], and during the approximately 100 million year history of snakes [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], a diversity of biochemical compositional &#x0201c;strategies&#x0201d; have evolved [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Resulting venom phenotypes can therefore be significantly different, even among closely related species [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>], and these different phenotypes are often correlated with dietary variables or foraging strategies [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Determining detailed venom composition among differing lineages of snakes can provide important connections linking phenotypic variation to specific selective pressures, and linking venom composition to snakebite envenomation effects.</p><p>The application of transcriptomic methods has provided insight into venom protein post-transcriptional regulation, as well as documenting isoform diversity and molecular evolutionary trends within large multigene venom protein superfamilies [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Venom gland transcriptomics has evolved from the generation of ESTs (expressed sequence tags) [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] to more comprehensive next generation sequencing (454 pyrosequencing or Illumina) of total venom gland cDNA (complementary DNA) [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. However, these methods both currently rely on venom gland tissue to obtain venom protein cDNAs, requiring access to venomous snake tissues and animal euthanasia. The ability to acquire venom protein cDNA sequences from venom has been documented [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], but this source has not been fully exploited because mRNA yields have been highly variable and very low, and cDNA amplification has previously focused only on known venom protein transcripts and only partial transcripts were amplified. Extracellular messenger RNA has been demonstrated to be unusually stable, for at least several years within lyophilized venom [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. This alternative source to obtain venom protein cDNAs is a less destructive method because sacrifice of animals is avoided. It also increases the availability of venom protein cDNA sequences to researchers that have limited access to venom gland tissues, as in the case of rare or difficult to acquire snake species, or due to limitations on animal euthanasia protocols. Further, this approach provides the opportunity to generate both venom transcriptomic and proteomic profiles, essentially a genotype-phenotype map, using only the same venom sample from one individual.</p><p>The standardized venomics approach of characterizing venoms by separating venom components by HPLC (high performance liquid chromatography), followed by trypsin digestion and tandem mass spectrometry, primarily relies on protein identification from databases such as MASCOT [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Mass spectral matching to determine peptide sequences is an efficient and less expensive alternative to N-terminal sequencing (Edman degradation). An advantage to this venomic approach is that it is at least semi-quantitative, allowing inter- and intrapopulational variation in amounts of specific proteins to be estimated. However, many venom proteins, in particular those from rear-fanged venomous snakes, are not present within current databases or are poorly represented, making it difficult to use this methodology to characterize these venoms [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. The incorporation of transcriptomics into venom proteomics has resulted in venom protein-locus resolution and has been labeled next generation snake venomics [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Species-specific venom gland transcriptomes aid in the identification and characterization of venom profiles by providing custom databases for tandem mass spectrometry (MS/MS) spectra matching, allowing for the identification of additional peptide sequences, specific isoforms, and novel venom proteins [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, <xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. This study provides support for an approach to obtain species-specific venom protein transcript sequences, including those from rear-fanged venomous snakes, using relatively little starting material (2 mg of lyophilized venom or 100 &#x003bc;l of fresh venom) that does not require venom gland tissue. cDNA derived from this method has great potential to fill gaps within databases and to aid in the characterization of understudied snake venoms.</p><p>Acquiring full-length venom protein sequences can also help to identify protein characteristics indicative of serious envenomation profiles, because venom toxins commonly utilize conserved structural folds but produce diverse pharmacological activities. For example, many venoms contain enzymatic phospholipase A<sub>2</sub>s (PLA<sub>2</sub>s) of low toxicity [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, <xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]; some contain PLA<sub>2</sub>s with potent myotoxic activity, and a limited number contain neurotoxic PLA<sub>2</sub>s (crotoxin-like complexes or other asparagine-6 containing PLA<sub>2</sub> sequences). Current methods for examining venom protein pharmacological activity can be labor intensive, requiring multiple protein purification steps and functional assays. Phospholipase A<sub>2</sub> functionality based on clustering with other PLA<sub>2</sub>s sharing similar sequence has been demonstrated to be a potential <italic>in silico</italic> alternative for predicting specific PLA<sub>2</sub> activity [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Knowledge of sequences and sequence similarities to others with noted activity and that are currently promising drug leads can help guide new drug exploration or even help to identify unique characteristics of prey-specific toxins that allow them to specifically target selected prey receptors, as in the case of rear-fanged snake venom three-finger toxins (3FTxs).</p><p>Rear-fanged snake venoms have not been as well-studied as front-fanged snake venoms, largely due to the difficulties extracting venoms from these snakes and the fact that the large majority of envenomations from these snakes are not life threatening [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. However, rear-fanged snake venoms potentially contain proteins that could serve as novel pharmaceutical drug leads or in other applications, such as proteolytic enzymes for protein fragmentation for mass spectrometry [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, <xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Rear-fanged snake venoms have also demonstrated unique evolutionary trajectories, including the presence of the only prey-specific toxins yet identified within snake venoms [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, <xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>].</p><p>The aim of this study was to obtain cDNA sequences of abundant venom proteins to predict protein activities or envenomation symptomology. From the rattlesnake PLA<sub>2</sub> transcripts identified, sequences characteristic of known viper neurotoxic PLA<sub>2</sub>s were observed, demonstrating the utility of using these methods to obtain predictive venom activities and envenomation profiles. In addition, this technique could be used to screen for novel sequences that could be of potential biomedical development based on predicted activities, and to explore the evolutionary trajectories in complex multigene superfamilies.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec002"><title>Methods</title><sec id="sec003"><title>Snake Venoms and Reagents</title><p>Venom was collected from front-fanged vipers <italic>Crotalus scutulatus scutulatus</italic> (Mohave Rattlesnake; SE Arizona), <italic>Crotalus cerastes</italic> (Sidewinder; S Arizona), <italic>Crotalus oreganus cerberus</italic> (Arizona Black Rattlesnake; E Arizona), <italic>Crotalus oreganus concolor</italic> (Midget Faded Rattlesnake; S. Wyoming), and <italic>Sistrurus miliarius barbouri</italic> (Florida Pigmy Rattlesnake; central Florida) by placing an RNase Away (Thermo Fisher Scientific Inc., U.S.A.)-treated 100 &#x003bc;l capillary tube over each fang and gently massaging the gland; 100 &#x003bc;l of venom was then immediately added to 1 mL of TRIzol (Life Technologies, CA, U.S.A.). Venom from <italic>Crotalus simus tzabcan</italic> (Middle American Rattlesnake; Yucat&#x000e1;n Peninsula, M&#x000e9;xico) was extracted into a sterile beaker and 10 &#x003bc;l, 25 &#x003bc;l, 50 &#x003bc;l and 100 &#x003bc;l of venom were each immediately added to 1 mL of TRIzol; the remaining venom was then centrifuged (9500 x g for 5 minutes), lyophilized and stored at -20&#x000b0;C until used. Venom from <italic>Crotalus molossus nigrescens</italic> (Mexican Black-tailed Rattlesnake; Morelia, M&#x000e9;xico) was collected in the field, desiccated, and stored at -20&#x000b0;C until used. Lyophilized venom from <italic>Crotalus pricei</italic> (Twin-spotted Rattlesnake; SE Arizona) was collected from a captive snake and stored frozen (-20&#x000b0;C) with desiccant for approximately 20 years; lyophilized <italic>Crotalus basiliscus</italic> (Mexican West Coast Rattlesnake; W. M&#x000e9;xico) venom was purchased from the Miami Serpentarium (Lot#CB15SZ) and lyophilized venom from an elapid snake, <italic>Pseudechis porphyriacus</italic> (Red-bellied Black Snake; E Australia), was a gift from Venom Supplies Pty Ltd (Tanunda, South Australia).</p><p>Venoms from the rear-fanged snakes <italic>Boiga irregularis</italic> (Brown Treesnake, Guam), <italic>Boiga dendrophila</italic> (Mangrove Snake; Indonesia), <italic>Boiga nigriceps</italic> (Black-headed Catsnake; Indonesia), <italic>Trimorphodon biscutatus lambda</italic> (Sonoran Lyre Snake; Portal, AZ), and <italic>Alsophis portoricensis</italic> (Puerto Rican Racer; Guana Island, British Virgin Islands) were extracted using the method of Hill and Mackessy (1997) with subcutaneous injections of ketamine-HCl (20&#x02013;30 mg/kg) followed by pilocarpine-HCl (6 mg/kg). Venom was collected by placing RNase Away-treated 100 &#x003bc;l capillary tubes over each enlarged rear maxillary tooth [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>], and venom (100 &#x003bc;l) was then added to 1 mL of TRIzol. For the rear-fanged snakes <italic>Boiga cynodon</italic> (Dog-toothed Catsnake; Indonesia), <italic>Oxybelis fulgidus</italic> (Green Vine Snake; Central America), and <italic>Ahaetulla prasina</italic> (Asian Vine Snake; Indonesia), venom was collected using the same protocol without RNase Away treated capillary tubes, centrifuged (9500 x g for 5 minutes), lyophilized, and stored at -20&#x000b0;C until used.</p><p>The 3&#x02019; RACE System kit, PCR SuperMix High Fidelity polymerase, custom oligonucleotides, DNase I, and <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> DH5 &#x003b1; competent cells were purchased from Life Technologies, CA, U.S.A. The plasmid Quick Clean 5M Miniprep Kit was from GenScript, Inc (Piscataway Township, NJ, U.S.A), and the pGEM-T Easy Vector System and Wizard SV gel and PCR clean-up system from Promega, Inc. (Madison, WI, U.S.A.) All other reagents were purchased from Sigma (St. Louis, MO, U.S.A).</p></sec><sec id="sec004"><title>Ethics Statement</title><p>Many of the snake venoms were collected manually from venomous snakes maintained in the University of Northern Colorado Animal Resource Facility in accordance with protocols #9204 and 1302D-SM-S-16 (evaluated and approved by the UNC IACUC) and collecting permits from state and federal agencies (Arizona Game and Fish Department #MCKSY000221 and #SP727017; Colorado Parks and Wildlife #15HP974; U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service #MA022452-0). Snakes are maintained for venoms in accordance with guidelines published by the American Society of Ichthyologists and Herpetologists [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec005"><title>Venom RNA Isolation and cDNA Synthesis</title><p>RNA was purified from 2 mg of lyophilized venom or 100 &#x003bc;l of freshly collected venom that had been added to 1 mL of TRIzol following the recommended TRIzol RNA protocol: after incubation for 5 minutes, 200 &#x003bc;L of chloroform was added to each tube, tubes were centrifuged at 12,000 x g for 15 minutes, aqueous upper phases were transferred to new RNase-free tubes, and 500 &#x003bc;L 100% isopropanol added to each aqueous phase to precipitate RNA. Tubes were incubated at room temperature for 10 minutes and centrifuged at 12,000 x g for 10 minutes. Supernatant was removed and the resulting RNA pellet (not visible) washed with 1 mL 75% ethanol. Another centrifuge step at 7,500 x g for 5 minutes was performed and supernatant poured off. A -20&#x000b0;C overnight incubation in 300 &#x003bc;L 100% ethanol with 40 &#x003bc;L 3 M sodium acetate was then performed to increased RNA yields, and the following day tubes were centrifuged at 10,000 x g for 15 minutes, supernatant removed, and total RNA resuspended in 16 &#x003bc;L nuclease-free H<sub>2</sub>O. To evaluate the effect of different amounts of lyophilized and fresh venom on cDNA yields, 5 mg, 10 mg, and 20 mg of lyophilized venom or 10, 25, 50 or 100 &#x003bc;L of crude fresh venom from <italic>C</italic>. <italic>s</italic>. <italic>tzabcan</italic> was added to TRIzol reagent and processed as above. For rear-fanged snake venoms, extraction methods resulted in retention of significant amounts of contaminating DNA; therefore, an Amplification Grade DNase I digestion after RNA isolation was performed at room temperature for 15 minutes, followed by the addition of 1 &#x003bc;l 25 mM EDTA (pH 8.0) and a 15 minute 65&#x000b0;C incubation. cDNA synthesis from total RNA was accomplished using the 3&#x02019; RACE System following the manufacturer&#x02019;s protocols. The oligo(dT) adaptor primer provided with the kit initiated reverse transcriptase cDNA synthesis and effectively selected for polyadenylated mRNAs.</p></sec><sec id="sec006"><title>3&#x02019;RACE (Rapid Amplification of cDNA Ends)</title><p>Sense primer sequences were designed from conserved signal peptide regions for each venom protein superfamily (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd.0004587.t001">Table 1</xref>). To identify conserved signal peptide sequences, multiple sequence alignments within MEGA v6.06 [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>] using MUSCLE [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>] were performed for each venom protein superfamily, with representative sequences obtained from the NCBI (National Center for Biotechnology Information) nucleotide database. Each sense primer was used in a reaction with the 3&#x02019;RACE system AUAP antisense primer 5&#x02019;-GGCCACGCGTCGACTAGTAC-3&#x02019;. For Mojave toxin, published sense and antisense primers were used for both acidic and basic subunits [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Twenty-three &#x003bc;L of PCR SuperMix High Fidelity polymerase was used with 1&#x02013;2 &#x003bc;L of cDNA template and 0.5 &#x003bc;L of each primer (sense and antisense). PCR was performed with seven touchdown cycles of 94&#x000b0;C for 25 seconds, 52&#x000b0;C for 30 seconds, and 68&#x000b0;C for two minutes. Thirty additional cycles followed with 94&#x000b0;C for 25 seconds, 48&#x000b0;C for 30 seconds, and 68&#x000b0;C for two minutes with a final 68&#x000b0;C extension for five minutes. The amplified products were observed on a 1% agarose gel, and bands of the estimated transcript sizes (based on previous published transcripts) were excised and then purified using the Wizard SV gel and PCR clean-up system.</p><table-wrap id="pntd.0004587.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0004587.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>List of primers used for amplification of transcripts within specific venom protein families.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pntd.0004587.t001g" xlink:href="pntd.0004587.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Venom Protein</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primer sequence</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rattlesnake phospholipase A<sub>2</sub></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5&#x02019;-GTCTGGATTCRGGAGGATGAGG-3&#x02019;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Current study</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elapid phospholipase A<sub>2</sub></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5&#x02019;-CTGYTGBTGANBKTG-3&#x02019;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Current study</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rattlesnake metalloproteinase (PII and PIII)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5&#x02019;-AATCYAGSCTCCAAAATGATC-3&#x02019;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Current study</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rear-fanged snake metalloproteinase</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5&#x02019;-ATGATCCAAGYTCTCTTGRTWACTATATRCTTAG-3&#x02019;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Current study</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rattlesnake serine protease</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5&#x02019;-ATGGTGCTGATCAGAGTGCTAGCAAACCTTCT-3&#x02019;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Current study</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rattlesnake C-type lectin</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5&#x02019;-ATGKGGCRATTSAYC-3&#x02019;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Current study</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mojave toxin subunit A</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sense: 5&#x02019;-GGTATTTCGTACTACAGCTCTTACGGA-3&#x02019;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wooldridge et al., 2001</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antisense: 5&#x02019;-TGATTCCCCCTGGCAATT-3&#x02019;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mojave toxin subunit B</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sense: 5&#x02019;-AACGCTATTCCCTTCTATGCCTTTTAC-3&#x02019;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wooldridge et al., 2001</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antisense: 5&#x02019;-CCTGTCGCACTCACAAATCTGTTCC-3&#x02019;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t001fn001"><p>R = purine (A or G)</p></fn><fn id="t001fn002"><p>Y = pyrimidine (C or T)</p></fn><fn id="t001fn003"><p>B = not A (C, G, or T)</p></fn><fn id="t001fn004"><p>K = keto (G or T)</p></fn><fn id="t001fn005"><p>S = strong (C or G)</p></fn><fn id="t001fn006"><p>W = weak (A or T)</p></fn><fn id="t001fn007"><p>N = any base (A, C, G, or T).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec007"><title>Cloning and Sequencing of Venom cDNA</title><p>Amplified and purified cDNA was ligated into the pGEM-T Easy Vector System and transformed into <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> DH5 &#x003b1; competent cells following the manufacture&#x02019;s recommended protocol. Transformed <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic> were grown on nutrient rich agar plates overnight at 37&#x000b0;C with ampicillin, IPTG and &#x003b2;-galactosidase for white/blue colony selection. Recombinant plasmids were selected from agar plates, and <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic> colonies picked for viper PLA<sub>2</sub> sequences were as follows: three colonies were picked for <italic>Crotalus cerastes</italic>, three for <italic>S</italic>. <italic>m</italic>. <italic>barbouri</italic>, four for <italic>C</italic>. <italic>m</italic>. <italic>nigrescens</italic>, six for <italic>C</italic>. <italic>o</italic>. <italic>cerberus</italic>, six for <italic>C</italic>. <italic>basiliscus</italic>, eight for <italic>C</italic>. <italic>pricei</italic>, twelve for <italic>C</italic>. <italic>o</italic>. <italic>concolor</italic>, and fifteen were picked for <italic>C</italic>. <italic>s</italic>. <italic>tzabcan</italic>. In addition to the PLA<sub>2</sub> sequences, eight colonies for serine proteases, ten colonies for C-type lectins, and eighteen colonies for metalloproteinases were chosen from <italic>C</italic>. <italic>s</italic>. <italic>tzabcan</italic> venom to obtain transcripts for all major venom protein families. For rear-fanged colubrid snake 3FTxs, the following number of <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic> colonies were selected: three were picked for <italic>T</italic>. <italic>b</italic>. <italic>lambda</italic>, three for <italic>A</italic>. <italic>prasina</italic>, six for <italic>O</italic>. <italic>fulgidus</italic>, four for <italic>B</italic>. <italic>nigriceps</italic>, ten for <italic>B</italic>. <italic>cynodon</italic>, twenty for <italic>B</italic>. <italic>dendrophila</italic>, and nineteen were picked for <italic>B</italic>. <italic>irregularis</italic>. A sampling of 3FTxs from <italic>Boiga sp</italic>. was chosen because of the three currently identified prey-specific 3FTxs, two have been found in <italic>Boiga</italic> species [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Three-finger toxin sequences from rear-fanged snakes, especially those from <italic>Boiga sp</italic>. and <italic>O</italic>. <italic>fulgidus</italic>, can provide insight into the evolution of 3FTx prey-specific binding affinities. Three colonies were also picked for metalloproteinase transcripts in <italic>A</italic>. <italic>portoricensis</italic> venom. For the elapid snake <italic>P</italic>. <italic>porphyriacus</italic>, five colonies from amplified PLA<sub>2</sub>s were picked. The numbers of colonies picked varied depending on the number of expected isoforms within each snake venom protein family and also because some primers were still being evaluated for specificity (only a few colonies were selected in these cases). Each <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic> colony was placed into 2 mL LB broth with 1 &#x003bc;L/mL ampicillin, and shaken overnight at 37&#x000b0;C. Plasmid copies for each <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic> colony were than purified using the Quick Clean 5M Miniprep Kit and were sequenced at the DNASU facility (Arizona State University, AZ, U.S.A) using Big Dye V3.1 chemistry with samples processed on an Applied Biosystems 3730XL Sequence Analysis Instrument.</p></sec><sec id="sec008"><title>Sequence Analysis</title><p>Sequences were viewed with 4Peaks software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nucleobytes.com/index.php/4peaks">http://nucleobytes.com/index.php/4peaks</ext-link>) and base pairs with acceptable quality scores (Phred score &#x0003e;20) were retained for analysis. Redundant sequences were removed. Sequences were identified with BLASTx (Basic Local Alignment Search Tool) on the NCBI server, limiting the search to &#x0201c;Serpentes (taxid: 8570)&#x0201d; proteins. Protein identities were considered significant if they fell below an e-value threshold of e<sup>-4</sup> and shared sequence similarity to other known snake venom proteins. Sequences were translated to their corresponding amino acid sequence and trimmed in MEGA v6.06 [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>], then aligned with MUSCLE [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>] and manually checked. Sequence alignment figures were generated using BoxShade 3.3.1 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mobyle.pasteur.fr/cgi-bin/portal.py?#forms::boxshade">http://mobyle.pasteur.fr/cgi-bin/portal.py?#forms::boxshade</ext-link>). All full-length CDS sequences, including all rattlesnake PLA<sub>2</sub>s, <italic>C</italic>. <italic>s</italic>. <italic>tzabcan</italic> serine proteases, <italic>C</italic>. <italic>s</italic>. <italic>tzabcan</italic> C-type lectins, and rear-fanged snake three-finger toxin sequences, were submitted to GenBank (accessions KU666900-KU666937).</p><p>Phylogenetic analysis was completed with MrBayes v3.2.4 [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>] using models selected by PartitionFinder v1.1 [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. PartitionFinder v.1.1 models selected were favored using Akaike Information Criterion. These datasets were then run in duplicate using MrBayes v3.2.4 with the default of three heated and one cold chain for 1x10<sup>7</sup> generations, sampling every 1,000 generations, and with the first 10% discarded as burn-in. Tracer v1.6 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://tree.bio.ed.ac.uk/software/tracer/">http://tree.bio.ed.ac.uk/software/tracer/</ext-link>) was used to check for run convergences. Consensus tree figures were prepared with FigTree v1.4.0 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://tree.bio.ed.ac.uk/software/figtree/">http://tree.bio.ed.ac.uk/software/figtree/</ext-link>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec009"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec010"><title>Venom RNA Isolation</title><p>Venom RNA concentrations were determined using both a Nanodrop 2000 (Thermo Fisher Scientific, NY, U.S.A) and a Qubit 2.0 Fluorometer (Life Technologies, CA, U.S.A) with a high sensitivity RNA assay kit. Various RNA isolation kits and reagents were used to determine which method produced the greatest RNA yields and amplification success (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd.0004587.t002">Table 2</xref>). The TRIzol RNA isolation protocol described in the methods was found to produce the most consistent results when isolating venom RNA and amplifying transcripts; however, the Direct-zol RNA kit (Zymo Research, CA, U.S.A) and <italic>mir</italic>Vana miRNA isolation kit (Life Technologies, CA, U.S.A) were also successful. Dynabeads from Life Technologies, CA, U.S.A were tried using a previously published technique for isolating extracellular mRNA within venom [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], as well as a FastTrack MAG mRNA isolation kit (Life Technologies, CA, U.S.A) and a RNeasy mini kit (QIAGEN, CA, U.S.A), but cDNA amplification did not produce visible PCR products (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd.0004587.t002">Table 2</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="pntd.0004587.t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0004587.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>RNA and mRNA isolation protocols used to obtain extracellular RNA within venom, and the resulting yields and cDNA amplification success.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pntd.0004587.t002g" xlink:href="pntd.0004587.t002"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RNA or mRNA isolation procedure</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Total RNA or mRNA yields (Nanodrop)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total RNA or mRNA yields (Qubit)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Successful cDNA amplification</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRIzol</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10&#x02013;13.60 &#x003bc;g (RNA)</td><td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x0003c; 20 ng/&#x003bc;l (RNA)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>mir</italic>Vana miRNA isolation kit</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33&#x02013;1 &#x003bc;g (RNA)</td><td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x0003c; 20 ng/&#x003bc;l (RNA)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Direct-zol RNA kit</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08&#x02013;0.13 &#x003bc;g (RNA)</td><td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">nd</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RNeasy mini kit</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08&#x02013;0.30 &#x003bc;g (RNA)</td><td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">nd</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dynabeads</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20&#x02013;1.19 &#x003bc;g (mRNA)</td><td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">nd</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FastTrack MAG mRNA isolation kit</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01&#x02013;0.03 &#x003bc;g (mRNA)</td><td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">nd</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t002fn001"><p>nd = not determined</p></fn><fn id="t002fn002"><p>+ = successful amplification</p></fn><fn id="t002fn003"><p>- = unsuccessful.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The TRIzol reagent Nanodrop readings for RNA yields of different rattlesnake venoms varied from 69 ng/&#x003bc;l (1.1 &#x003bc;g of total RNA isolated from 2 mg of lyophilized rattlesnake venom) to 683.3 ng/&#x003bc;l (10.9 &#x003bc;g of total RNA isolated from 100 &#x003bc;l of fresh rattlesnake venom) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd.0004587.t002">Table 2</xref>). Rear-fanged snake venoms consistently showed slightly higher yields (10.3 &#x003bc;g&#x02013; 13.6 &#x003bc;g of total RNA) as determined by Nanodrop; however, this appeared to be mostly due to the 260 nm readings of contaminating DNA from saliva during venom collection, and all RNA isolated from rear-fanged snakes required a DNase I digestion before PCR to prevent nonspecific amplification. When fresh venom was used, 100 &#x003bc;l of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>s</italic>. <italic>tzabcan</italic> venom yielded a total RNA amount (Nanodrop) of 6.1 &#x003bc;g, 50 &#x003bc;l yielded 8 &#x003bc;g, and 25 &#x003bc;l yielded 10.4 &#x003bc;g. However, when the same volume amounts were used for cDNA synthesis and amplification, successful amplification of PLA<sub>2</sub> transcripts tended to decrease with decreasing venom input (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0004587.g001">Fig 1A</xref>). When different lyophilized venom amounts were used, 20 mg yielded 6.1 &#x003bc;g, 10 mg yielded 5.2 &#x003bc;g, 5 mg yielded 6.5 &#x003bc;g, 2 mg yielded 5.3 &#x003bc;g, and 1 mg yielded 8.4 &#x003bc;g of total RNA (Nanodrop). As seen with the total RNA amounts from fresh venom, the Nanodrop amount of total RNA from lyophilized venom did not demonstrate a clear relationship to PLA<sub>2</sub> transcript amplification success, and 2 mg produced the highest concentration of PLA<sub>2</sub> amplicons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0004587.g001">Fig 1B</xref>). All Nanodrop readings showed low 260/280 and 260/230 ratios, indicating low purity. The typical 260/280 ratio observed was 1.5 and 1.6 for 260/230. Qubit results revealed values &#x0003c; 20 ng/&#x003bc;l, below instrument detection, for all measured samples (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd.0004587.t002">Table 2</xref>).</p><fig id="pntd.0004587.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0004587.g001</object-id><label>Fig 1</label><caption><title>Agarose gel electrophoresis showing cDNA transcripts amplified from mRNA in venomous snake venoms.</title><p>Various amounts of fresh venom (A) and lyophilized venom (B) from <italic>Crotalus simus tzabcan</italic> were used to determine optimal amplification conditions for phospholipase A<sub>2</sub> transcripts. Regions of phospholipase A<sub>2</sub> Mojave toxin subunit A (sA) and subunit B (sB) cDNAs were amplified to demonstrate transcript detectability in <italic>Crotalus scutulatus scutulatus</italic> venom (C). Three-finger toxin cDNA sequences were also amplified from mRNA derived from venoms of rear-fanged snakes (D).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pntd.0004587.g001"/></fig><p>It was possible to isolate RNA from both fresh venom and from lyophilized venom that had been stored at -20&#x000b0;C (including after 20 years of storage), as well as from venom desiccated in the field and venom purchased from a commercial venom supply source. Both front-fanged and rear-fanged venomous snakes were found to have extracellular RNA within their venoms; this is the first report of mRNA in the venom of rear-fanged venomous snakes, and RNA was isolated from both freshly collected and lyophilized rear-fanged snake venoms.</p></sec><sec id="sec011"><title>Venom Protein cDNA Sequences within Venom</title><p>As proof of concept, cDNA amplicons from <italic>C</italic>. <italic>s</italic>. <italic>scutulatus</italic> venom, obtained using published primer sequences [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>], were used to confirm presence of the two Mojave toxin subunits (acidic and basic chains; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0004587.g001">Fig 1C</xref>). These basic and acidic subunits were both sequenced and found to be 100% identical to the published sequences for <italic>C</italic>. <italic>s</italic>. <italic>scutulatus</italic> (PA2A_CROSS and PA2Ba_CROSS) [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>, <xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>], demonstrating that cDNAs of mRNA within venom can be used to detect the presence of specific expressed venom protein transcripts. In this case, the presence and abundance of crotoxin/Mojave toxin-like acidic and basic subunits is strongly indicative of neurotoxic envenomation symptoms characteristic of human envenomations by these rattlesnakes.</p><p>3&#x02019;RACE with sense primers designed from conserved sequences of the signal peptide or the 5&#x02019;UTR (untranslated region) of transcripts (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd.0004587.t001">Table 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pntd.0004587.s002">S1 Fig</xref>) were used to amplify cDNAs for a diversity of PLA<sub>2</sub>s, metalloproteinases, serine proteases, C-type lectins, and 3FTxs from viperid, elapid and rear-fanged snake venoms. This is the first time that cDNA derived from venom transcripts has been used to obtain unknown sequences for such a diversity of venom protein families. For Middle American Rattlesnake venom (<italic>C</italic>. <italic>s</italic>. <italic>tzabcan)</italic>, full-length cDNA sequences were successfully amplified for the major venom proteins present within this rattlesnake&#x02019;s venom [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>] in spite of limited colony sampling (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd.0004587.t003">Table 3</xref>). A partial venom gland transcriptome was assembled, focusing on venom protein transcripts that significantly contribute to envenomation symptomology, including metalloproteinases, serine proteases, and C-type lectins. There are likely many more unique C-type lectins, serine proteases, and metalloproteinase transcripts within <italic>C</italic>. <italic>s</italic>. <italic>tzabcan</italic> venom, but the intent here was to demonstrate the presence of diverse, intact venom protein transcripts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0004587.g002">Fig 2</xref>). Greater diversity of C-type lectins has been identified within other rattlesnake venom gland transcriptome assemblies using next generation sequencing [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], but the vast majority of these C-type lectins transcripts were found to be present in very low abundance.</p><fig id="pntd.0004587.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0004587.g002</object-id><label>Fig 2</label><caption><p><bold>Aligned Middle American Rattlesnake (<italic>Crotalus simus tzabcan</italic>) C-type lectins (A) and serine proteases (B).</bold> A) Four unique venom-based C-type lectin transcripts (asterisks) were identified for <italic>C</italic>. <italic>s</italic>. <italic>tzabcan</italic> and aligned to other crotaline species. Identical nucleotide sequences are shaded and corresponding GenBank accession numbers are as follows: Crotalus_adamanteus (AEJ31974.1), Deinagkistrodon_acutus (AAM22790.1), Crotalus_d_terrificus (Q719L8.1), and Crotalus_o_helleri (AEU60004.1). B) Venom-based serine proteases cDNA sequences (asterisks) were also obtained from <italic>C</italic>. <italic>s</italic>. <italic>tzabcan</italic> and were aligned with toxins from several other species; identical nucleotide sequences are shaded, and the catalytic triad composed of Ser195, Asp102, and His57 associated with thrombin-like activity in snake venom serine proteases are identified (arrowheads). Isoform 3 from <italic>C</italic>. <italic>s</italic>. <italic>tzabcan</italic> is a partial sequence. GenBank accession numbers are as follows: Agkistrodon_p_leucostoma (HQ270466.1), Bothrops_asper (DQ247724.1), Crotalus_d_terrificus7 (EU360954.1), Crotalus_d_terrificus4 (EU360952.1), Crotalus_d_terrificus3 (EU360951.1), Crotalus_d_durissus (DQ164401.1), Sistrurus_c_edwardsi (DQ464239.1), Trimeresurus_mucrosquamatus (X83225.1), Crotalus_adamanteus (HQ414118.1), Calloselasma_rhodostoma (L07308.1), Deinagkistrodon_acutus (AY861382.1), Trimeresurus_stejnegeri (AF545575.1), and Crotalus_atrox (AF227153.1).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pntd.0004587.g002"/></fig><table-wrap id="pntd.0004587.t003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0004587.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Venom protein transcripts amplified from the venom of the Middle American Rattlesnake (<italic>Crotalus simus tzabcan</italic>) for the four dominant protein families present.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pntd.0004587.t003g" xlink:href="pntd.0004587.t003"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Venom Protein Family</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"># Colony Picks</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"># Unique Isoforms</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metalloproteinase (PII and PIII)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phospholipase A<sub>2</sub></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C-type Lectin</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Serine Protease</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>The diversity of PLA<sub>2</sub> isoforms appeared to vary for each rattlesnake species (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd.0004587.t004">Table 4</xref>). For <italic>C</italic>. <italic>pricei</italic>, only one unique PLA<sub>2</sub> sequence was discovered in eight selected clones, while <italic>C</italic>. <italic>m</italic>. <italic>nigrescens</italic> had three unique sequences found in the selection of only four clones. There was no clear positive trend between the number of colonies sequenced and the number of unique sequences (Pearson&#x02019;s correlation test; df = 6, r = 0.6684, p = 0.0699); instead, isoform diversity appeared to be dependent on the species (and likely on the abundance of the most prominent isoform). The number of clones sampled in this study was relatively low, and an increase in the number of clones sequenced should increase the chance of observing less abundant isoforms and determining the total number of isoforms present in each venom [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>].</p><table-wrap id="pntd.0004587.t004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0004587.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Relationship between the number of colony picks and the number of observed unique phospholipase A<sub>2</sub> isoforms.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pntd.0004587.t004g" xlink:href="pntd.0004587.t004"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Species</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"># Colony Picks</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"># Unique PLA<sub>2</sub> Isoforms</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Crotalus simus tzabcan</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Crotalus oreganus concolor</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Crotalus pricei pricei</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Crotalus oreganus cerberus</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Crotalus basiliscus</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Crotalus molossus nigrescens</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Crotalus cerastes cercobombus</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Sistrurus miliarius barbouri</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudechis porphyriacus</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>Of the fifteen PLA<sub>2</sub> clones selected from <italic>C</italic>. <italic>s</italic>. <italic>tzabcan</italic>, two unique sequences were similar to sequences from crotoxin or Mojave toxin-like acidic A chain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0004587.g003">Fig 3</xref>). One sequence (C_s_tzabcan1) was the most abundant, with six identical clones, and it was 99% identical in amino acid sequence to crotoxin acidic A chain (PAIA_CRODU) from the South American Rattlesnake (<italic>Crotalus durissus terrificus</italic>), while the second sequence (C_s_tzabcan4) had only one clone and was 88% identical to the Mojave toxin acidic (A) chain (PA2A_CROSS) from the Mojave Rattlesnake (<italic>C</italic>. <italic>s</italic>. <italic>scutulatus</italic>). This less abundant acidic chain sequence revealed that isoform variation within the acidic (A) chains of the toxin also exists for <italic>C</italic>. <italic>s</italic>. <italic>tzabcan</italic>.</p><fig id="pntd.0004587.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0004587.g003</object-id><label>Fig 3</label><caption><p><bold>Aligned Group IIA phospholipase A<sub>2</sub> acidic (A) and basic (B) subunit isoforms.</bold> The neurotoxic, heterodimeric PLA<sub>2</sub> complex of crotoxin/Mojave toxin homologs consists of both an acidic A subunit and basic B subunit. A) Sequence alignments of the acidic (A) subunit of crotoxin or Mojave toxin homologs with identical residues shaded; the conserved signal peptide region is indicated by the red bar, and the Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding loop is indicated by the blue bar. Regions of the A subunit which are post-translationally cleaved in the mature protein are indicated by red brackets below sequences. Sequences similar to crotoxin/Mojave toxin acidic subunit A derived from from venom (asterisks) were discovered in <italic>Crotalus oreganus concolor</italic> and <italic>C</italic>. <italic>simus tzabcan</italic> venoms. GenBank accession numbers of known toxins are as follows: Crotalus_s_scutulatus_MojaveTX (U01026.1), Crotalus_d_terrificus_CrotoxinA (X12606.1), Sistrurus_c_tergeminus_SistruxinA (Q6EAN6.1), and Gloydius_intermedius_GintexinA (AID56658.1). B) Sequence alignments of the basic (B) subunit of crotoxin/Mojave toxin homologs with identical residues shaded; the conserved signal peptide region is indicated by the red bar, and the Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding loop is indicated by the blue bar. The asparagine-6 (N6) associated with neurotoxic PLA<sub>2</sub> functionality is indicated by arrowheads. Sequences similar to the crotoxin or Mojave toxin basic B subunits derived from venom (asterisks) were discovered in <italic>Crotalus oreganus concolor</italic>, <italic>C</italic>. <italic>simus tzabcan</italic>, and <italic>C</italic>. <italic>basiliscus</italic> venoms, with N6 sequences also found in <italic>C</italic>. <italic>m</italic>. <italic>nigrescens</italic> and <italic>C</italic>. <italic>o</italic>. <italic>cerberus</italic> venoms. GenBank accession numbers of known toxins are as follows: Crotalus_s_scutulatus_MojaveTX (U01027.1), Crotalus_d_terrificus_CrotoxinB (X12603.1), Crotalus_v_viridis_N6 (AF403138.1), Sistrurus_c_tergeminus_N6 (AY355169.1), Sistrurus_c_tergeminus_SistruxinB (Q6EER2.1), Bothriechis_schlegelii_N6 (AY355168.1), Protobothrops_mucrosquamatus (AF408409.1), and Deinagkistrodon_acutus (X77649.1).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pntd.0004587.g003"/></fig><p>A crotoxin-like basic (B) chain was also sequenced from <italic>C</italic>. <italic>s</italic>. <italic>tzabcan</italic> venom, with three clones that were 100% identical in amino acid sequence to crotoxin subunit CBc from <italic>C</italic>. <italic>d</italic>. <italic>terrificus</italic> (PA2BC_CRODU), providing molecular evidence that <italic>C</italic>. <italic>s</italic>. <italic>tzabcan</italic> from this study has an abundance of available PLA<sub>2</sub> transcripts to form a neurotoxic complex similar to that of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>d</italic>. <italic>terrificus</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0004587.g003">Fig 3</xref>). The PLA<sub>2</sub> cDNAs obtained from <italic>C</italic>. <italic>basiliscus</italic> also had multiple clones containing crotoxin-like basic B chain sequences (C_basiliscus3), which were 100% identical in amino acid sequence to crotoxin basic subunit CBc of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>d</italic>. <italic>terrificus</italic> (PA2BC_CRODU) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0004587.g003">Fig 3B</xref>). However, crotoxin-like acidic subunit sequences were not discovered, either due to a lack of sufficient sampling or absence from this venom sample. Crotoxin-like protein complexes have been previously observed in <italic>C</italic>. <italic>basiliscus</italic> venom [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>].</p><p>Mojave toxin-like PLA<sub>2</sub> sequences were obtained from <italic>C</italic>. <italic>o</italic>. <italic>concolor</italic> venom (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0004587.g003">Fig 3</xref>), which has been previously recognized as containing a neurotoxic PLA<sub>2</sub> complex (concolor toxin) similar to Mojave toxin, identified from Ouchterlony immunodiffusion, immunoelectrophoresis, ELISA, and Western blot analyses [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>, <xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]; however, the full sequence has not been published. Concolor toxin acidic (A) chain was found to share 100% sequence identity with Mojave toxin acidic (A) subunit (PA2A_CROSS) from <italic>C</italic>. <italic>s</italic>. <italic>scutulatus;</italic> however, the concolor basic (B) subunit was found to be more similar to crotoxin subunit CBc (PA2BC_CRODU) from <italic>C</italic>. <italic>d</italic>. <italic>terrificus</italic>, sharing 99% amino acid sequence identify with this crotoxin basic (B) chain.</p><p>Interestingly, <italic>C</italic>. <italic>o</italic>. <italic>cerberus</italic> and <italic>C</italic>. <italic>m</italic>. <italic>nigrescens</italic> venoms also had PLA<sub>2</sub> sequences that contained the asparagine-6 (N6) substitutions associated with myotoxic/neurotoxic activity, also a feature of the basic (B) subunits of crotoxin and Mojave toxin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0004587.g003">Fig 3</xref>). All other PLA<sub>2</sub> sequences were similar in sequence to acidic PLA<sub>2</sub>s that show edema-inducing activity and myotoxicity, corresponding to the envenomation symptomology seen in bites from these species. The <italic>S</italic>. <italic>m</italic>. <italic>barbouri</italic> PLA<sub>2</sub> sequence reported here was found to be 100% identical to the amino acid sequence of a previously reported PLA<sub>2</sub> from <italic>S</italic>. <italic>m</italic>. <italic>barbouri</italic> venom (ABY77929.1 [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]).</p><p>There were only two unique PLA<sub>2</sub> transcripts identified in five colonies selected from an elapid (<italic>P</italic>. <italic>porphyriacus</italic>) venom (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd.0004587.t003">Table 3</xref>). However, of the identified PLA<sub>2</sub> sequences, 4/5 clones were 100% identical in mature protein sequence (P. porphyriacus1) to a previously identified PLA-1 precursor (AAZ22667.1) from <italic>P</italic>. <italic>porphyriacus</italic> venom gland [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>], and the other unique isoform (P. porphyriacus2) was 99% identical to PLA<sub>2</sub> pseudexin B chain (PA2BB_PSEPO), also from <italic>P</italic>. <italic>porphyriacus</italic> [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. Again, sequences determined from venom-derived mRNAs are identical to previously reported venom protein sequences (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0004587.g004">Fig 4</xref>), validating this method.</p><fig id="pntd.0004587.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0004587.g004</object-id><label>Fig 4</label><caption><title>Aligned <italic>Pseudechis</italic> Group IA phospholipase A<sub>2</sub> (PLA<sub>2</sub>) mature protein sequences.</title><p>Amplified PLA<sub>2</sub> sequences from <italic>Pseudechis porphyriacus</italic> venom (asterisks) were aligned to known PLA<sub>2</sub> sequences from the same species and known PLA<sub>2</sub> sequences from two other <italic>Pseudechis</italic> species. Sequences from <italic>P</italic>. <italic>porphyriacus</italic> venom showed 99% and 100% identity to <italic>P</italic>. <italic>porphyriacus</italic> mature PLA<sub>2</sub> protein sequences that had been obtained from venom gland tissue or via Edman degradation.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pntd.0004587.g004"/></fig><p>Full-length venom protein transcripts were also identified from rear-fanged snake venoms. Thirty full-length 3FTx sequences were obtained using a degenerate sense primer designed from multiple sequence alignments with published non-conventional 3FTx sequences (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0004587.g001">Fig 1D</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pntd.0004587.s002">S1B Fig</xref>). Three-finger toxin transcripts were found in the venoms of <italic>T</italic>. <italic>b</italic>. <italic>lambda</italic>, <italic>A</italic>. <italic>prasina</italic>, <italic>O</italic>. <italic>fulgidus</italic>, <italic>B</italic>. <italic>nigriceps</italic>, <italic>B</italic>. <italic>cynodon</italic>, <italic>B</italic>. <italic>dendrophila</italic>, and <italic>B</italic>. <italic>irregularis</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0004587.g005">Fig 5</xref>).</p><fig id="pntd.0004587.g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0004587.g005</object-id><label>Fig 5</label><caption><title>Aligned sequences of non-conventional three-finger toxins (3FTxs) from venoms of rear-fanged and elapid snakes.</title><p>Venom-derived 3FTx sequences (asterisks) obtained from <italic>Boiga irregularis</italic>, <italic>B</italic>. <italic>dendrophila</italic>, <italic>B</italic>. <italic>nigriceps</italic>, <italic>B</italic>. <italic>cynodon</italic>, <italic>Oxybelis fulgidus</italic>, <italic>Ahaetulla prasina</italic>, and <italic>Trimorphodon biscutatus lambda</italic> were aligned with various other rear-fanged and Elapidae species; identical nucleotide sequences are shaded. GenBank accession numbers are as follows: Trimorphodon_biscutatus_Tri3 (EU029678.1), Trimorphodon_biscutatus_Tri2 (EU029677.1), Telescopus_dhara_Tel4 (EU029686.1), Boiga_dendrophila_denmo (DQ366293.1), Boiga_irregularis_irditoxinB (DQ304539.1), Boiga_irregularis_irditoxinA (DQ304538.1), Boiga_irregularis_1f (GBSH01000015.1), Thrasops_jacksoni_Thr3 (EU029685.1), Dispholidus_typus_Dis1 (EU029674.1), Telescopus_dhara_Tel1 (EU029675.1), Thrasops_jacksoni_Thr5 (EU036635.1), Trimorphodon_biscutatus_Tri1 (EU029675.1), Naja_atra (AF031472.1), Bungarus_multicinctus (AF056400.1), Ophiophagus_hannah (FJ952515.1), Psammophis_mossambicus_Psa1 (EU029669.1), Leioheterodon_madagascariensis (EU029676.1), Bungarus_candidus (AY057878.1), and Dendroaspis_angusticeps (AF241871.1).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pntd.0004587.g005"/></fig><p>Although none of the three 3FTx sequences from <italic>T</italic>. <italic>b</italic>. <italic>lambda</italic> venom were 100% identical to previously published 3FTx sequences from this species [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>], they did cluster with the previous <italic>T</italic>. <italic>b</italic>. <italic>lambda</italic> sequences within a well-supported clade also containing other 3FTx sequences from New World rear-fanged venomous snakes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0004587.g006">Fig 6</xref>). A greater diversity of 3FTxs within <italic>T</italic>. <italic>b</italic>. <italic>lambda</italic> venom is possible considering that only three clones were picked for this study and all were unique 3FTx sequences; differences observed could also be due to locality-specific transcript variation. Two unique 3FTx sequences were found in <italic>A</italic>. <italic>prasina</italic> venom and only one unique 3FTx sequence in <italic>O</italic>. <italic>fulgidus</italic>. The sequence from <italic>O</italic>. <italic>fulgidus</italic> venom was not identical to the previously characterized fulgimotoxin, which was based on N-terminal Edman degradation sequencing [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]; however, it did show 95% amino acid sequence identity.</p><fig id="pntd.0004587.g006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0004587.g006</object-id><label>Fig 6</label><caption><title>Bayesian sequence similarity tree depicting non-conventional three-finger toxin (3FTx) relationships.</title><p>3FTx cDNA sequences derived from venom (asterisks) were obtained from <italic>Boiga irregularis</italic>, <italic>B</italic>. <italic>dendrophila</italic>, <italic>B</italic>. <italic>nigriceps</italic>, <italic>B</italic>. <italic>cynodon</italic>, <italic>Oxybelis fulgidus</italic>, <italic>Ahaetulla prasina</italic> and <italic>Trimorphodon biscutatus lambda</italic>, and sequence relationships with various known rear-fanged and Elapidae 3FTxs are shown. Posterior probabilities are shown for each node, and GenBank accession numbers correspond to sequences in Fig 6.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pntd.0004587.g006"/></fig><p>Only two unique 3FTx sequences were found in the venom of <italic>B</italic>. <italic>cynodon</italic> (from ten selected colonies) and one in <italic>B</italic>. <italic>nigriceps</italic> venom (from four selected colonies). Many of the clones sequenced from rear-fanged snake venoms were of poor quality and were culled, so more sequences are likely present. Fifteen unique 3FTx sequences were revealed in <italic>B</italic>. <italic>dendrophila</italic> venom, but the majority were missing complete signal peptide sequences and therefore were omitted from further analysis because it is unknown if these transcripts produce proteins that are secreted in the venom gland and are active components of <italic>B</italic>. <italic>dendrophila</italic> venom. Six unique 3FTx sequences were found in <italic>B</italic>. <italic>irregularis</italic> venom, but none were 100% identical to either irditoxin subunits [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], although one sequence was 96% identical to irditoxin subunit B. One of the 3FTx <italic>B</italic>. <italic>cynodon</italic> clones was 97% identical (amino acid sequence) to irditoxin subunit B and another sequence had 83% amino acid sequence identity with irditoxin subunit A; these toxins also clustered together with irditoxin in the 3FTx phylogenetic tree (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0004587.g006">Fig 6</xref>). These results suggest that <italic>B</italic>. <italic>cynodon</italic> venom likely contains a prey-specific heterodimeric 3FTx complex similar to irditoxin.</p><p>One unique metalloproteinase sequence was amplified, cloned and sequenced from the venom of the Puerto Rican Racer (<italic>Alsophis portoricensis</italic>). Although this sequence was not similar to alsophinase, a previously characterized metalloproteinase in <italic>A</italic>. <italic>portoricensis</italic> venom [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], it was similar in sequence to other rear-fanged and elapid P-III metalloproteinase cDNA sequences (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0004587.g007">Fig 7</xref>). The complete metalloproteinase sequence was amplified, based on the observed amplified product size, but longer venom protein transcripts (&#x0003e;2,000bp) required multiple sequencing reactions that were not performed for this analysis, and therefore only the partial sequence is shown in the alignment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0004587.g007">Fig 7</xref>).</p><fig id="pntd.0004587.g007" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0004587.g007</object-id><label>Fig 7</label><caption><title><italic>Alsophis portoricensis</italic> venom PIII metalloproteinase sequence aligned with amino acid sequences from rear-fanged and elapid snake species.</title><p>Identical residues are shaded, demonstrating PIII metalloproteinase sequence conservation in these diverse species. Only a partial sequence of the complete transcript from <italic>A</italic>. <italic>portoricensis</italic> (asterisks) was used for the alignment. Genbank accession numbers are as follows: Philodryas_chamissonis (AJB84503.1), Philodryas_olfersii (ACS74987.1), Cerberus_rynchops (ADJ51055.1), Pseudechis_porphyriacus (ABQ01133.1), and Demansia_vestigiata (ABK63559.1).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pntd.0004587.g007"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec012"><title>Other cDNA Sequences within Venom</title><p>While optimizing primers, other sequences were incidentally amplified from both rattlesnake and rear-fanged snake venom, including complete 60S ribosomal sequences. These sequences, from <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cerastes</italic> and <italic>A</italic>. <italic>portoricensis</italic> venom, were 99% identical to the predicted Burmese Python (<italic>Python bivittatus</italic>) 60S ribosomal protein L7a (XP_007420634.1) and L15 isoform X1 (XP_007421748.1), respectively. There were also 40S ribosomal protein sequences amplified from <italic>C</italic>. <italic>s</italic>. <italic>scutulatus</italic> which showed 100% sequence identity with the 40S ribosomal protein S9-like isoform X1 from <italic>P</italic>. <italic>bivittatus</italic> (XP_007439934.1). Cathelicidin-OH antimicrobial peptides (XP_007442672.1) were identified from <italic>C</italic>. <italic>o</italic>. <italic>cerberus</italic> and <italic>B</italic>. <italic>irregularis</italic> venom. These sequences were observed in both rattlesnake and rear-fanged snake venoms, demonstrating that other complete transcripts, in addition to venom protein transcripts, exist within venoms (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pntd.0004587.s003">S2 Fig</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec013"><title>Relationship of Sequence Similarities to Empirical and Predictive Protein Activities</title><p>Sequences that were similar to crotoxin/Mojave toxin acidic (A) subunits in <italic>C</italic>. <italic>o</italic>. <italic>concolor</italic> and <italic>C</italic>. <italic>simus tzabcan</italic> venoms formed one well-supported clade (1.0 posterior probability), and sequences that were similar to crotoxin/Mojave toxin basic (B) subunits discovered in <italic>C</italic>. <italic>o</italic>. <italic>concolor</italic>, <italic>C</italic>. <italic>simus tzabcan</italic>, and <italic>C</italic>. <italic>basiliscus</italic> clustered with other known neurotoxic N6 PLA<sub>2</sub> homologs (1.0 posterior probability; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0004587.g008">Fig 8</xref>). Other PLA<sub>2</sub>s from <italic>C</italic>. <italic>o</italic>. <italic>concolor</italic>, <italic>C</italic>. <italic>simus tzabcan</italic>, and <italic>C</italic>. <italic>basiliscus</italic> venoms, and also from <italic>C</italic>. <italic>pricei</italic>, <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cerastes</italic>, <italic>C</italic>. <italic>m</italic>. <italic>nigrescens</italic>, <italic>C</italic>. <italic>o</italic>. <italic>cerberus</italic>, and <italic>S</italic>. <italic>m</italic>. <italic>barbouri</italic> venoms, clustered within an acidic hemolytic PLA<sub>2</sub> clade shared with other rattlesnakes (0.96 posterior probability; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0004587.g008">Fig 8</xref>). It has been experimentally determined that even neurotoxic PLA<sub>2</sub>s can also exhibit anticoagulant activity, and this appears to be a common characteristic of many venom PLA<sub>2</sub> enzymes.</p><fig id="pntd.0004587.g008" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0004587.g008</object-id><label>Fig 8</label><caption><title>Bayesian sequence similarity tree depicting viper Group II phospholipase A<sub>2</sub> (PLA<sub>2</sub>) relationships.</title><p>PLA<sub>2</sub> cDNA sequences were obtained from <italic>Crotalus simus tzabcan</italic>, <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cerastes</italic>, <italic>C</italic>. <italic>molossus nigrescens</italic>, <italic>C</italic>. <italic>oreganus concolor</italic>, <italic>C</italic>. <italic>oreganus cerberus</italic>, <italic>C</italic>. <italic>pricei</italic>, <italic>C</italic>. <italic>basiliscus</italic>, <italic>and Sistrurus miliarius barbouri</italic> venoms (asterisks), and their relationships with various published Old and New World viperid venom PLA<sub>2</sub>s are shown. Newly sequenced crotoxin homologs are indicated by double asterisks (crotoxin A&#x02014;left side; crotoxin B&#x02013;right side). GenBank accession numbers are listed within the tree. Published PLA<sub>2</sub> sequences are colored corresponding to empirically determined biological activity. Whole clades are highlighted where at least two of the published sequences within the clade have the same experimentally determined activity. Red, neurotoxic; blue, hemolytic; green, edematous; pink, myotoxic.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pntd.0004587.g008"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec014"><title>Discussion</title><p>Concentrations of total extracellular RNA within snake venom were observed to be moderate but variable using Nanodrop. Using a Qubit instrument, RNA concentrations were all below the instrument detection limit (&#x0003c; 20 ng/&#x003bc;l) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd.0004587.t002">Table 2</xref>). Qubit readings provide better accuracy because the fluorescent dye is highly selective for RNA and not DNA, which has also been detected in venom [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. In addition, common contaminants do not affect Qubit readings. The more accurate Qubit readings revealed a much lower concentration of extracellular RNA within venom, lower than Nanodrop concentrations reported in this and in a previous study [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. However, in spite of low RNA concentrations, venom protein cDNAs could still be amplified successfully from both front and rear-fanged venomous snakes. By using extracellular messenger RNA from venom to obtain full-length venom protein transcripts, this method can be used without the need to sacrifice living animals to obtain venom gland tissue. It was also possible to successfully amplify full-length venom protein transcripts from venom that was fresh, lyophilized or stored at -20&#x000b0;C for 20+ years, desiccated over silica gel in the field, or obtained from a commercial venom supplier. This represents a significant advance over previous attempts to amplify venom-derived mRNAs, which typically produced only partial sequence transcripts [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>].</p><p>Venom protein genes experience an accelerated rate of nucleotide substitution [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>, <xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>], making it difficult to design sense and antisense pairs of primers to amplify unknown venom proteins sequences, which is why complete venom gland transcriptomes from gland tissue are usually assembled. However, venom proteins demonstrate high conservation of nucleotide signal peptide sequence and/or 5&#x02019;UTRs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0004587.g002">Fig 2</xref>). By designing degenerate sense primers from these conserved nucleotide sequences and performing 3&#x02019;RACE, the successful amplification of a diversity of transcript sequences for the major venom protein families (metalloproteinases, serine proteases, C-type lectins, phospholipase A<sub>2</sub>s, and three-finger toxins) responsible for clinically significant snakebite were obtained from venom. This approach also allowed determination of unique, currently unknown full-length toxin sequences for many front-fanged and rear-fanged species in all of the major clades of venomous snakes (Viperidae, Elapidae, Colubridae). This use of degenerate primers to amplify unknown full-length venom protein sequences within a superfamily from snake venom can be employed to screen sequences within each species for toxins of interest, to examine novel mutations within a venom protein superfamily, or to provide an inexpensive method to obtain complete amino acid sequence for a protein under investigation.</p><p>Venom gland transcriptomes generated from next-generation sequencing (Roche 454 or Illumina) provide more comprehensive transcriptome profiles and identify the complete repertoire of transcripts within each venom protein superfamily [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. An abundance of unique 3FTx transcripts identified in rear-fanged snake venom gland transcriptomes generated by next-generation sequencing has been reported, with over fifty 3FTxs transcripts in the case of <italic>Boiga irregularis</italic> [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. The number of unique venom protein PLA<sub>2</sub> sequences discovered in viper venom gland transcriptomes completed with next-generation sequencing ranges from 4&#x02013;9 [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]; therefore, the number of unique sequences obtained in this study was by no means a comprehensive evaluation of all transcripts within these protein superfamilies. However, using established procedures that are readily accessible to many researchers, such as 3&#x02019;RACE and the selection/sequencing of <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic> clones, it was possible to identify the major transcripts present for each venom protein superfamily explored in this study. The approach used here allows for researchers interested in a single venom protein superfamily to obtain selectively all highly abundant transcripts for that protein superfamily. This approach is cost-effective and does not require the computing resources/bioinformatics needed for next generation sequencing transcriptome assemblies. Because venom protein cDNA sequences are obtained from venoms, this method also allows for the assembly of a genotype-phenotype map, using only venom as source material.</p><p>Phospholipase A<sub>2</sub> enzymes and 3FTxs were chosen as the main focus of this study because they constitute very large venom protein superfamilies that exhibit a diversity of activities, including neurotoxic, myotoxic, cardiotoxic, anticoagulant and hemolytic activities [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>, <xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. These venom proteins are ideal for structure/function studies as well as protein engineering studies, because a variety of activities and functional sites are possible using the same conserved protein structural scaffold. Also, 3FTxs and PLA<sub>2</sub>s are venom proteins that are observed in abundance in snake venoms, and both are toxins that contribute significantly to serious snake envenomation symptomology. Presence of crotoxin or Mojave toxin PLA<sub>2</sub> heterodimeric complexes result in phenotypically neurotoxic venoms, and the absence or presence of these complexes result in distinctive venom types that have been labeled type I and type II. Type I venoms have higher metalloproteinase activity and lower toxicity, and type II venoms have low metalloproteinase activity and high toxicity/neurotoxicity [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>].</p><p>There can be variation in the occurrence of crotoxin/Mojave toxin complexes within a species, as is seen among different populations of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>horridus</italic>, <italic>C</italic>. <italic>scutulatus</italic> and <italic>C</italic>. <italic>simus</italic> throughout their range [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>, <xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>, <xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. This study shows that it is possible to detect the acidic and basic subunit transcripts of these neurotoxic PLA<sub>2</sub> complexes within venom. In the case of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>s</italic>. <italic>tzabcan</italic> utilized in this study, several isoforms of acidic and basic crotoxin-like subunits were observed. The neurotoxicity of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>s</italic>. <italic>tzabcan</italic> venom varies with snake locality [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]; because the specific locality of the <italic>C</italic>. <italic>s</italic>. <italic>tzabcan</italic> used in this study was unknown, sequencing venom protein transcripts present within venom was a successful approach to evaluating venom phenotype.</p><p>This technique can also be used to analyze the amino acid sequences of toxins in unexplored venoms, and this study is the first to report the complete sequence for both subunits of concolor toxin from venom of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>o</italic>. <italic>concolor</italic>. Although it has been known for some time that this neurotoxic complex is present in <italic>C</italic>. <italic>o</italic>. <italic>concolor</italic> venom [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>, <xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>], the presence of acidic and basic crotoxin/Mojave toxin homologs confirmed that a PLA<sub>2</sub>-based neurotoxin was present in this type II venom. The viper PLA<sub>2</sub> Bayesian sequence similarity tree revealed some distinctive clusters that corresponded with experimentally characterized PLA<sub>2</sub> protein activities. For example, analysis of PLA<sub>2</sub> sequences from <italic>C</italic>. <italic>o</italic>. <italic>cerberus</italic>, a subspecies with type I venom, demonstrated that its PLA<sub>2</sub> clustered within the acidic hemolytic PLA<sub>2</sub> clade, as is typical of many low toxicity rattlesnake PLA<sub>2</sub>s. Mojave and crotoxin-like PLA<sub>2</sub> clusters for acidic and basic subunits were also separate from the clades that contained Old World viper neurotoxic PLA<sub>2</sub> complexes (basic and acidic subunits of a heterodimer PLA<sub>2</sub> from <italic>Vipera nikolskii</italic> and vaspin subunits from <italic>Vipera aspis aspis</italic>), suggesting the possibility of a separate evolutionary origin for Old World and New World neurotoxic heterodimeric PLA<sub>2</sub> complexes.</p><p>Venom 3FTxs and PLA<sub>2</sub>s can have multiple different, active sites, and individual toxins are rarely tested for all possible activities or substrates, so it is difficult to predict protein activities or to determine if misclassifications are occurring with predictive methods based solely on sequences similarities [<xref rid="pntd.0004587.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Nevertheless, sequence similarity clustering did successfully identify crotoxin and Mojave toxin homologs, PLA<sub>2</sub>s that are associated with serious neurotoxic envenomation symptomology, in known and previously uninvestigated venoms. Two 3FTx transcripts were discovered in <italic>Boiga cynodon</italic> venom that were very similar in sequence to the two subunits of the heterodimeric, prey-specific iriditoxin from <italic>B</italic>. <italic>irregularis</italic> venom, indicating the presence of another lizard and bird-specific neurotoxin within the venom of a closely related species. Full-length venom protein transcripts obtained from venom can therefore be used to screen for particular toxins or venom phenotypes.</p><p>As more full-length transcripts become available, high throughput methods such as next-generation proteomic (and transcriptomic) characterization of venoms that lack profiles, including most rear-fanged snake species and many understudied front-fanged snake species, will be greatly facilitated. The methods described here provided full-length venom protein transcripts from venoms representing the three major families of venomous snakes, making it is possible to determine snake venom genotype-phenotype relationships without the need to sacrifice living snakes. By requiring only venom to obtain venom protein cDNAs, the approaches detailed here will provide access to cDNA-based protein sequences in the absence of living specimens, from commercial and other venom sources, and will facilitate study of snake venom protein composition and evolution, and in turn, provide greater predictability of the development of regionally-specific reactions following snakebite envenomation.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec015"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pntd.0004587.s001"><label>S1 Text</label><caption><title>Accession numbers.</title><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pntd.0004587.s001.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pntd.0004587.s002"><label>S1 Fig</label><caption><p><bold>Multiple sequence alignments of the first 75 nucleotides of various Group IIA viperid phospholipase A<sub>2</sub>s (A) and non-conventional three-finger toxins (B).</bold> A) Venom-based PLA<sub>2</sub> cDNA sequences (asterisks) were obtained from <italic>Crotalus p</italic>. <italic>pricei</italic>, <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cerastes cercobombus</italic>, <italic>C</italic>. <italic>molossus nigrescens</italic>, <italic>C</italic>. <italic>oreganus concolor</italic>, <italic>C</italic>. <italic>oreganus cerberus</italic>, <italic>C</italic>. <italic>basiliscus</italic>, <italic>C</italic>. <italic>simus tzabcan</italic>, and <italic>Sistrurus miliarius barbouri</italic> and were aligned with toxins from several other crotaline species; identical nucleotide sequences are shaded, and regions utilized for a specifically-designed sense primer are indicated by the red bar. This primer sequence includes the end of the 5&#x02019;UTR and beginning of the signal peptide. GenBank accession numbers for known toxins are as follows: Crotalus_atrox (AF269131), Crotalus_h_horridus (GQ168368.1), Sistrurus_c_tergeminus (AY508692.1), Agkistrodon_contortrix (ACU21335), Lachesis_muta (KM459520.1), Bothriechis_schlegelii (AY764137.1), Vipera_b_berus (AJ580215.1), Echis_carinatus (AY268946.2), Daboia_russellii (DQ090661.1), Gloydius_intermedius (KJ654336.1), Deinagkistrodon_acutus (X77649.1), and Protobothrops_mucrosquamatus (AF408409). B) Venom based 3FTx cDNA sequences (asterisks) were obtained from <italic>Boiga irregularis</italic>, <italic>B</italic>. <italic>dendrophila</italic>, <italic>B</italic>. <italic>nigriceps</italic>, <italic>B</italic>. <italic>cynodon</italic>, <italic>Oxybelis fulgidus</italic>, <italic>Ahaetulla prasina</italic>, and <italic>Trimorphodon biscutatus lambda</italic> and were aligned with toxins from several other rear-fanged and Elapidae species; identical nucleotide sequences are shaded and regions utilized for a specifically-designed sense primer are indicated by the red bar. This primer sequence includes the beginning of the signal peptide. GenBank accession numbers are as follows: Trimorphodon_biscutatus_Tri3 (EU029678.1), Trimorphodon_biscutatus_Tri2 (EU029677.1), Telescopus_dhara_Tel4 (EU029686.1), Boiga_dendrophila_denmo (DQ366293.1), Boiga_irregularis_irditoxinB (DQ304539.1), Boiga_irregularis_irditoxinA (DQ304538.1), Boiga_irregularis_1f (GBSH01000015.1), Thrasop_jacksoni_Thr3 (EU029685.1), Dispholidus_typus_Dis1 (EU029674.1), Telescopus_dhara_Tel1 (EU029675.1), Thrasops_jacksoni_Thr5 (EU036635.1), Trimorphodon_biscutatus_Tri1 (EU029675.1), Naja_atra (AF031472.1), Bungarus_multicinctus (AF056400.1), Ophiophagus_hannah (FJ952515.1), Psammophis_mossambicus_Psa1 (EU029669.1), Leioheterodon_madagascariensis (EU029676.1), Bungarus_candidus (AY057878.1), and Dendroaspis_angusticeps (AF241871.1).</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pntd.0004587.s002.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pntd.0004587.s003"><label>S2 Fig</label><caption><title>Additional amplified non-toxin transcripts within venom found during primer optimization.</title><p>Transcript sequences for non-toxin proteins (ribosomal and cathelicidin proteins) were found within both rattlesnake and rear-fanged snake venoms demonstrating that other complete transcripts are found in venoms.</p><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pntd.0004587.s003.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors thank Peter Mirtschin (Venom Supplies Pty. LTD) for the donation of <italic>Pseudechis</italic> venom, and University of Northern Colorado (UNC) undergraduates Katelyn Currier and Jessica Rogers for lab assistance. We also thank Dr. Steven D. Aird for his thoughtful suggestions which greatly improved the manuscript.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Greene</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name>. <article-title>Dietary correlates of the origin and radiation of snakes</article-title>. <source>American Zoologist</source>. <year>1983</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>431</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>41</lpage>. .</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Mackessy</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>The field of reptile toxinology: snakes, lizards and their venoms</chapter-title> In: <name><surname>Mackessy</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, editor. <source>Handbook of Venoms and Toxins of Reptiles</source>. <publisher-loc>Boca Raton, FL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>CRC Press/Taylor &#x00026; Francis Group</publisher-name>; <year>2010</year> p. <fpage>2</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>23</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mackessy</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baxter</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>Bioweapons synthesis and storage: The venom gland of front-fanged snakes</article-title>. <source>Zoologischer Anzeiger</source>
<year>2006</year>;<volume>245</volume>(<issue>3&#x02013;4</issue>):<fpage>147</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>59</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kardong</surname><given-names>KV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lavin-Murcio</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Venom delivery of snakes as high-pressure and low-pressure systems</article-title>. <source>Copeia</source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>1993</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>644</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>50</lpage>. .</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Martill</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tischlinger</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Longrich</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name>. <article-title>A four-legged snake from the Early Cretaceous of Gondwana</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>349</volume>:<fpage>416</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.aaa9208">10.1126/science.aaa9208</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26206932</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kardong</surname><given-names>KV</given-names></name>. <article-title>Snake toxins and venoms: An evolutionary perspective</article-title>. <source>Herpetologica</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>52</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>36</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>46</lpage>. .</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>The evolution of venom-delivery systems in snakes</article-title>. <source>Zoological Journal of the Linnean Society</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>137</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>337</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>54</lpage>. .</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pawlak</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mackessy</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sixberry</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stura</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Le Du</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Menez</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Irditoxin, a novel covalently linked heterodimeric three-finger toxin with high taxon-specific neurotoxicity</article-title>. <source>Faseb Journal</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>534</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>45</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1096/fj.08-113555">10.1096/fj.08-113555</ext-link></comment> .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18952712</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Calvete</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ghezellou</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Paiva</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Matainaho</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ghassempour</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goudarzi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Snake venomics of two poorly known Hydrophiinae: Comparative proteomics of the venoms of terrestrial <italic>Toxicocalamus longissimus</italic> and marine <italic>Hydrophis cyanocinctus</italic></article-title>. <source>J ournal of Proteomics</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>75</volume>(<issue>13</issue>):<fpage>4091</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>101</lpage>. Epub 2012/05/31. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jprot.2012.05.026">10.1016/j.jprot.2012.05.026</ext-link></comment> .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22643073</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fry</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kini</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Eggs-only diet: Its implications for the toxin profile changes and ecology of the marbled sea snake (<italic>Aipysurus eydouxii</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Journal of Molecular Evolution</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>60</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>81</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00239-004-0138-0">10.1007/s00239-004-0138-0</ext-link></comment> .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15696370</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Casewell</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wagstaff</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>W&#x000fc;ster</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>DAN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bolton</surname><given-names>FMS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>King</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Medically important differences in snake venom composition are dictated by distinct postgenomic mechanisms</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>111</volume>(<issue>25</issue>):<fpage>9205</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1405484111">10.1073/pnas.1405484111</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Doley</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pahari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mackessy</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kini</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Accelerated exchange of exon segments in Viperid three-finger toxin genes (<italic>Sistrurus catenatus edwardsii</italic>; Desert Massasauga)</article-title>. <source>BMC Evolutionary Biology</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>196</issue>). 196 <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2148-8-196">10.1186/1471-2148-8-196</ext-link></comment> .</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ibison</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wilbraham</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wagstaff</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Identification of cDNAs encoding viper venom hyaluronidases: Cross-generic sequence conservation of full-length and unusually short variant transcripts</article-title>. <source>Gene</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>392</volume>(<issue>1&#x02013;2</issue>):<fpage>22</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>33</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.gene.2006.10.026">10.1016/j.gene.2006.10.026</ext-link></comment> .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17210232</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Durban</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Perez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sanz</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gomez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bonilla</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Integrated "omics" profiling indicates that miRNAs are modulators of the ontogenetic venom composition shift in the Central American rattlesnake, <italic>Crotalus simus simus</italic></article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>234</issue>). <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2164-14-234">10.1186/1471-2164-14-234</ext-link></comment> .</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vonk</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Casewell</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Henkel</surname><given-names>CV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Heimberg</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McCleary</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>The king cobra genome reveals dynamic gene evolution and adaptation in the snake venom system</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>110</volume>(<issue>51</issue>):<fpage>20651</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>. Epub 2013/12/04. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1314702110">10.1073/pnas.1314702110</ext-link></comment> .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24297900</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ching</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Paes Leme</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zelanis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rocha</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Furtado Mde</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Venomics profiling of <italic>Thamnodynastes strigatus</italic> unveils matrix metalloproteinases and other novel proteins recruited to the toxin arsenal of rear-fanged snakes</article-title>. <source>Journal of Proteome Research</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>1152</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>62</lpage>. Epub 2011/12/16. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1021/pr200876c">10.1021/pr200876c</ext-link></comment> .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22168127</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chatrath</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chapeaurouge</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>QS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dunstan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mirtschin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Identification of Novel Proteins from the Venom of a Cryptic Snake <italic>Drysdalia coronoides</italic> by a Combined Transcriptomics and Proteomics Approach</article-title>. <source>Journal of Proteome Research</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>739</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>50</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1021/pr1008916">10.1021/pr1008916</ext-link></comment> .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21133350</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wagstaff</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sanz</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Juarez</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Calvete</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Combined snake venomics and venom gland transcriptomic analysis of the ocellated carpet viper, <italic>Echis ocellatus</italic></article-title>. <source>Journal of Proteomics</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>71</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>609</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>23</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jprot.2008.10.003">10.1016/j.jprot.2008.10.003</ext-link></comment> .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19026773</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pahari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mackessy</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kini</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>. <article-title>The venom gland transcriptome of the Desert Massasauga Rattlesnake (<italic>Sistrurus catenatus edwardsii</italic>): towards an understanding of venom composition among advanced snakes (Superfamily Colubroidea)</article-title>. <source>BMC Molecular Biology</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>115</issue>). <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2199-8-115">10.1186/1471-2199-8-115</ext-link></comment> .</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>QH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>XW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Transcriptome analysis of <italic>Deinagkistrodon acutus</italic> venomous gland focusing on cellular structure and functional aspects using expressed sequence tags</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>152</issue>). 152 <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2164-7-152">10.1186/1471-2164-7-152</ext-link></comment> .</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Francischetti</surname><given-names>IMB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>My-Pham</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Garfield</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>JMC</given-names></name>. <article-title><italic>Bitis gabonica</italic> (Gaboon viper) snake venom gland: toward a catalog for the full-length transcripts (cDNA) and proteins</article-title>. <source>Gene</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>337</volume>:<fpage>55</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>69</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.gene.2004.03.024">10.1016/j.gene.2004.03.024</ext-link></comment> .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15276202</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Junqueira-de-Azevedo</surname><given-names>ILM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ching</surname><given-names>ATC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Faria</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nishiyama</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title><italic>Lachesis muta</italic> (Viperidae) cDNAs reveal diverging pit viper molecules and scaffolds typical of cobra (Elapidae) venoms: Implications for snake toxin repertoire evolution</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>173</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>877</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>89</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1534/genetics.106.056515">10.1534/genetics.106.056515</ext-link></comment> .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16582429</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Aird</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Villar-Briones</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Terada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mikheyev</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Quantitative high-throughput profiling of snake venom gland transcriptomes and proteomes (<italic>Ovophis okinavensis</italic> and <italic>Protobothrops flavoviridis</italic>)</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>790</issue>). <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2164-14-790">10.1186/1471-2164-14-790</ext-link></comment> .</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Margres</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McGivern</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wray</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Seavy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Calvin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rokyta</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Linking the transcriptome and proteome to characterize the venom of the eastern diamondback rattlesnake (<italic>Crotalus adamanteus</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Journal of Proteomics</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>96</volume>(<issue>0</issue>):<fpage>145</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>58</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jprot.2013.11.001">10.1016/j.jprot.2013.11.001</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24231107</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rokyta</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wray</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Margres</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>The genesis of an exceptionally lethal venom in the timber rattlesnake (<italic>Crotalus horridus</italic>) revealed through comparative venom-gland transcriptomics</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>394</issue>). Epub 2013/06/14. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2164-14-394">10.1186/1471-2164-14-394</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMCPmc3701607.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23758969</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Durban</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ju&#x000e1;rez</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Angulo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lomonte</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Flores-Diaz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alape-Gir&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Profiling the venom gland transcriptomes of Costa Rican snakes by 454 pyrosequencing</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>259</fpage>&#x02013;. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2164-12-259">10.1186/1471-2164-12-259</ext-link></comment> .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21605378</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rokyta</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wray</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lemmon</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lemmon</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Caudle</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>. <article-title>A high-throughput venom-gland transcriptome for the Eastern Diamondback Rattlesnake (<italic>Crotalus adamanteus</italic>) and evidence for pervasive positive selection across toxin classes</article-title>. <source>Toxicon</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>57</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>657</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>71</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.toxicon.2011.01.008">10.1016/j.toxicon.2011.01.008</ext-link></comment> .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21255598</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>McGivern</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wray</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Margres</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Couch</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mackessy</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rokyta</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>. <article-title>RNA-seq and high-definition mass spectrometry reveal the complex and divergent venoms of two rear-fanged colubrid snakes</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>1061</issue>). Epub 2014/12/06. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2164-15-1061">10.1186/1471-2164-15-1061</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMCPmc4289226.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25476704</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bjourson</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Orr</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kwok</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ivanyi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Unmasking venom gland transcriptomes in reptile venoms</article-title>. <source>Analytical Biochemistry</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>311</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>152</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>. Pii s0003-2697(02)00404-9 <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/s0003-2697(02)00404-9">10.1016/s0003-2697(02)00404-9</ext-link></comment> .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12470674</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Currier</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Calvete</surname><given-names>Juan</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sanz</surname><given-names>Libia</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>Robert</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rowley</surname><given-names>Paul</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wagstaff</surname><given-names>Simon</given-names></name>. <article-title>Unusual stability of messenger RNA in snake venom reveals gene expression dynamics of venom replenishment</article-title>. <source>Plos One</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fagundes</surname><given-names>FHR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huancahuire-Vega</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Romero-Vargas</surname><given-names>FF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ponce-Soto</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Marangoni</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>cDNA and deduced primary structure of basic phospholipase A2 with neurotoxic activity from the venom secretion of the <italic>Crotalus durissus collilineatus</italic> rattlesnake</article-title>. <source>Brazilian Journal of Medical and Biological Research</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>43</volume>:<fpage>262</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>70</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20401434</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Cloning and characterisation of three novel disintegrin precursors from the venoms of three <italic>Atheris</italic> species: <italic>Atheris chlorechis</italic>, <italic>Atheris nitschei</italic> and <italic>Atheris squamigera</italic></article-title>. <source>Toxicon</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>71</volume>:<fpage>31</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>40</lpage>. Epub 2013/06/05. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.toxicon.2013.05.012">10.1016/j.toxicon.2013.05.012</ext-link></comment> .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23732124</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Calvete</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Snake venomics: From the inventory of toxins to biology</article-title>. <source>Toxicon</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>75</volume>:<fpage>44</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>62</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.toxicon.2013.03.020">10.1016/j.toxicon.2013.03.020</ext-link></comment> .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23578513</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Calvete</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Next-generation snake venomics: protein-locus resolution through venom proteome decomplexation</article-title>. <source>Expert Review of Proteomics</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>315</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>29</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1586/14789450.2014.900447">10.1586/14789450.2014.900447</ext-link></comment> .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24678852</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chapeaurouge</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reza</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mackessy</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Valente</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Teixeira-Ferreira</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Interrogating the venom of the viperid Snake <italic>Sistrurus catenatus edwardsii</italic> by a combined approach of electrospray and MALDI mass spectrometry</article-title>. <source>Plos One</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>5</issue>). <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0092091">10.1371/journal.pone.0092091</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Montecucco</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guti&#x000e9;rrez</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lomonte</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>. <article-title>Cellular pathology induced by snake venom phospholipase A2 myotoxins and neurotoxins: common aspects of their mechanisms of action</article-title>. <source>Cell Mol Life Sci</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>65</volume>(<issue>18</issue>):<fpage>2897</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>912</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00018-008-8113-3">10.1007/s00018-008-8113-3</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18563294</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Malhotra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Creer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>St&#x000f6;cklin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Favreau</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thorpe</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Predicting function from sequence in a large multifunctional toxin family</article-title>. <source>Toxicon</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>72</volume>(<issue>0</issue>):<fpage>113</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>25</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.toxicon.2013.06.019">10.1016/j.toxicon.2013.06.019</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23831284</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mackessy</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Biochemistry and pharmacology of colubrid snake venoms</article-title>. <source>Journal of Toxicology-Toxin Reviews</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>1&#x02013;2</issue>):<fpage>43</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>83</lpage>. .</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Peichoto</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tavares</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Santoro</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mackessy</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Venom proteomes of South and North American opisthoglyphous (Colubridae and Dipsadidae) snake species: A preliminary approach to understanding their biological roles</article-title>. <source>Comparative Biochemistry and Physiology Part D: Genomics and Proteomics</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>361</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.cbd.2012.08.001">10.1016/j.cbd.2012.08.001</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Weinstein</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Warrell</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>White</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Keyler</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>"Venomous" bites from non-venomous snakes</chapter-title>: <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>; <year>2011</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chiszar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Colubrid envenomations in the United States</article-title>. <source>Journal of Toxicology-Toxin Reviews</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>1&#x02013;2</issue>):<fpage>85</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>104</lpage>. .</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Saviola</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peichoto</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mackessy</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Rear-fanged snake venoms: an untapped source of novel compounds and potential drug leads</article-title>. <source>Toxin Reviews</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>0</volume>(<issue>0</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>17</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3109/15569543.2014.942040">10.3109/15569543.2014.942040</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Weldon</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mackessy</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Alsophinase, a new P-III metalloproteinase with alpha-fibrinogenolytic and hemorrhagic activity from the venom of the rear-fanged Puerto Rican Racer <italic>Alsophis portoricensis</italic> (Serpentes: Dipsadidae)</article-title>. <source>Biochimie</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>94</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1189</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>98</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.biochi.2012.02.006">10.1016/j.biochi.2012.02.006</ext-link></comment> .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22349739</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pawlak</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mackessy</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fry</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bhatia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mourier</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fruchart-Gaillard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Denmotoxin, a three-finger toxin from the colubrid snake <italic>Boiga dendrophila</italic> (mangrove catsnake) with bird-specific activity</article-title>. <source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>281</volume>(<issue>39</issue>):<fpage>29030</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>41</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1074/jbc.M605850200">10.1074/jbc.M605850200</ext-link></comment> .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16864572</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Heyborne</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mackessy</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Identification and characterization of a taxon-specific three-finger toxin from the venom of the Green Vinesnake (<italic>Oxybelis fulgidus</italic>; family Colubridae)</article-title>. <source>Biochimie</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>95</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1923</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>32</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.biochi.2013.06.025">10.1016/j.biochi.2013.06.025</ext-link></comment> .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23851011</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref046"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mackessy</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Venom yields from several species of colubrid snakes and differential effects of ketamine</article-title>. <source>Toxicon</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>671</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9203291</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref047"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>American Society of Ichthyologists and Herpetologists</collab>. <chapter-title>Guidelines for use of live amphibians and reptiles in field and laboratory research</chapter-title>, <edition>2nd ed.</edition>
<year>2004</year>
<publisher-name>Herpetological Animal Care and Use Committee</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref048"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stecher</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Filipski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>MEGA6: Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis version 6.0</article-title>. <source>Molecular Biology and Evolution</source>. <year>2013</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref049"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Edgar</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>. <article-title>MUSCLE: multiple sequence alignment with high accuracy and high throughput</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Research</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1792</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkh340">10.1093/nar/gkh340</ext-link></comment> .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15034147</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref050"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wooldridge</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pineda</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Banuelas-Ornelas</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dagda</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gasanov</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rael</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Mojave rattlesnakes (<italic>Crotalus scutulatus scutulatus</italic>) lacking the acidic subunit DNA sequence lack Mojave toxin in their venom</article-title>. <source>Comparative biochemistry and physiology Part B, Biochemistry &#x00026; molecular biology</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>130</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>169</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>79</lpage>. Epub 2001/09/07. .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11544087</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref051"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Huelsenbeck</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ronquist</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>. <article-title>MRBAYES: Bayesian inference of phylogenetic trees</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics (Oxford, England)</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>754</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>. Epub 2001/08/29. .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11524383</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref052"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lanfear</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Calcott</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>SYW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guindon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>PartitionFinder: Combined Selection of Partitioning Schemes and Substitution Models for Phylogenetic Analyses</article-title>. <source>Molecular Biology and Evolution</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1695</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>701</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/molbev/mss020">10.1093/molbev/mss020</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22319168</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref053"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Aird</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kruggel</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kaiser</surname><given-names>II</given-names></name>. <article-title>Amino acid sequence of the basic subunit of Mojave toxin from the venom of the Mojave rattlesnake (<italic>Crotalus s</italic>. <italic>scutulatus</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Toxicon</source>. <year>1990</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>669</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>73</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0041-0101(90)90255-6">10.1016/0041-0101(90)90255-6</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2402763</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref054"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bieber</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McParland</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shabanowitz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yates Iii</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>The complete sequence of the acidic subunit from Mojave toxin determined by Edman degradation and mass spectrometry</article-title>. <source>Biochimica et Biophysica Acta (BBA)&#x02014;Protein Structure and Molecular Enzymology</source>. <year>1990</year>;<volume>1037</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>413</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>21</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0167-4838(90)90045-H">10.1016/0167-4838(90)90045-H</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2310754</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref055"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Castro</surname><given-names>EN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lomonte</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Del Carmen Guti&#x000e9;rrez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alag&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guti&#x000e9;rrez</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Intraspecies variation in the venom of the rattlesnake <italic>Crotalus simus</italic> from Mexico: Different expression of crotoxin results in highly variable toxicity in the venoms of three subspecies</article-title>. <source>Journal of Proteomics</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>87</volume>:<fpage>103</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>21</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jprot.2013.05.024">10.1016/j.jprot.2013.05.024</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23727490</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref056"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cardoso</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Da Silva</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>GGL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Torres</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Del Bem</surname><given-names>LEV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vidal</surname><given-names>RO</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>A transcriptomic analysis of gene expression in the venom gland of the snake <italic>Bothrops alternatus</italic> (urutu)</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>605</issue>). <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2164-11-605">10.1186/1471-2164-11-605</ext-link></comment> .</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref057"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y-H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y-M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hseu</surname><given-names>M-J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>I-H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Molecular evolution and structure&#x02013;function relationships of crotoxin-like and asparagine-6-containing phospholipases A(2) in pit viper venoms</article-title>. <source>Biochemical Journal</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>381</volume>(<issue>Pt 1</issue>):<fpage>25</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>34</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1042/BJ20040125">10.1042/BJ20040125</ext-link></comment> .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15032748</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref058"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Glenn</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Straight</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>The midget faded rattlesnake (<italic>Crotalus viridis concolor</italic>) venom: Lethal toxicity and individual variability</article-title>. <source>Toxicon</source>. <year>1977</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>129</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>32</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0041-0101(77)90031-9">10.1016/0041-0101(77)90031-9</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">854933</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref059"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Weinstein</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Minton</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wilde</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>. <article-title>The distribution among ophidian venoms of a toxin isolated from the venom of the Mojave rattlesnake (<italic>Crotalus scutulatus scutulatus</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Toxicon</source>. <year>1985</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>825</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>44</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0041-0101(85)90014-5">10.1016/0041-0101(85)90014-5</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3937297</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref060"><label>60</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gibbs</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rossiter</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>. <article-title>Rapid evolution by positive selection and gene gain and loss: PLA(2) venom genes in closely related <italic>Sistrurus</italic> rattlesnakes with divergent diets</article-title>. <source>Journal of Molecular Evolution</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>66</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>151</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>66</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00239-008-9067-7">10.1007/s00239-008-9067-7</ext-link></comment> .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18253686</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref061"><label>61</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pierre</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Earl</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Masci</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lavin</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>. <article-title>Identification and analysis of venom gland-specific genes from the coastal taipan (<italic>Oxyuranus scutellatus</italic>) and related species</article-title>. <source>Cell Mol Life Sci</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>62</volume>(<issue>22</issue>):<fpage>2679</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>93</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00018-005-5384-9">10.1007/s00018-005-5384-9</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16261251</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref062"><label>62</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Middlebrook</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Purification, sequencing and characterization of pseudexin phospholipases A2 from <italic>Pseudechis porphyriacus</italic> (Australian red-bellied black snake)</article-title>. <source>Toxicon</source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>805</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>18</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2675391</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref063"><label>63</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fry</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Scheib</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Junqueira de Azevedo</surname><given-names>IdLM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Casewell</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Novel transcripts in the maxillary venom glands of advanced snakes</article-title>. <source>Toxicon</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>59</volume>(<issue>7&#x02013;8</issue>):<fpage>696</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>708</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.toxicon.2012.03.005">10.1016/j.toxicon.2012.03.005</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22465490</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref064"><label>64</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pook</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McEwing</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Mitochondrial DNA sequences from dried snake venom: a DNA barcoding approach to the identification of venom samples</article-title>. <source>Toxicon</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>711</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>. Epub 2005/09/15. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.toxicon.2005.07.005">10.1016/j.toxicon.2005.07.005</ext-link></comment> .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16157361</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref065"><label>65</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nobuhisa</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nakashima</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Deshimaru</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ogawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shimohigashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fukumaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Accelerated evolution of <italic>Trimeresurus okinavensis</italic> venom gland phospholipase A(2) isozyme-encoding genes</article-title>. <source>Gene</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>172</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>267</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>72</lpage>. .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8682315</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref066"><label>66</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ogawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oda</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nakashima</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hattori</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sakaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Unusually high conservation of untranslated sequence in cDNA for <italic>Trimeresurus flavoviridis</italic> phospholipase A2 isozymes</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>89</volume>(<issue>18</issue>):<fpage>8557</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>61</lpage>. .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1528861</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref067"><label>67</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kini</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Doley</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><article-title>. Structure, function and evolution of three-finger toxins: Mini proteins with multiple targets</article-title>. <source>Toxicon</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>56</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>855</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>67</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.toxicon.2010.07.010">10.1016/j.toxicon.2010.07.010</ext-link></comment> .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20670641</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref068"><label>68</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kini</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Excitement ahead: structure, function and mechanism of snake venom phospholipase A2 enzymes</article-title>. <source>Toxicon</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>827</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>40</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.toxicon.2003.11.002">10.1016/j.toxicon.2003.11.002</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15019485</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref069"><label>69</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mackessy</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Evolutionary trends in venom composition in the Western Rattlesnakes (<italic>Crotalus viridis sensu lato</italic>): Toxicity vs. tenderizers</article-title>. <source>Toxicon</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>55</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1463</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>74</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.toxicon.2010.02.028">10.1016/j.toxicon.2010.02.028</ext-link></comment> .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20227433</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref070"><label>70</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Glenn</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Straight</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wolt</surname></name>. <article-title>Regional variation in the presence of canebrake toxin in <italic>Crotalus horridus</italic> venom</article-title>. <source>Comparative Biochemistry and Physiology Part C: Pharmacology, Toxicology and Endocrinology</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>107</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>337</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>46</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/1367-8280(94)90059-0">10.1016/1367-8280(94)90059-0</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pntd.0004587.ref071"><label>71</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Massey</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Calvete</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>S&#x000e1;nchez</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sanz</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Curtis</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Venom variability and envenoming severity outcomes of the <italic>Crotalus scutulatus scutulatus</italic> (Mojave rattlesnake) from Southern Arizona</article-title>. <source>Journal of Proteomics</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>75</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>2576</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>87</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jprot.2012.02.035">10.1016/j.jprot.2012.02.035</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22446891</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>