<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Pathog</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plospath</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Pathogens</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1553-7366</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1553-7374</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19543378</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2691606</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">08-PLPA-RA-1593R3</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000483</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Cell Biology/Cell Adhesion</subject><subject>Cell Biology/Cell Signaling</subject><subject>Cell Biology/Gene Expression</subject><subject>Cell Biology/Microbial Growth and Development</subject><subject>Genetics and Genomics/Gene Discovery</subject><subject>Genetics and Genomics/Gene Expression</subject><subject>Genetics and Genomics/Gene Function</subject><subject>Infectious Diseases/Bacterial Infections</subject><subject>Microbiology/Microbial Growth and Development</subject><subject>Molecular Biology/Post-Translational Regulation of Gene Expression</subject><subject>Cell Biology/Extra-Cellular Matrix</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Connecting Quorum Sensing, c-di-GMP, Pel Polysaccharide, and Biofilm Formation in <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> through Tyrosine Phosphatase TpbA (PA3885)</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">TpbA Reduces Biofilm via c-di-GMP</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ueda</surname><given-names>Akihiro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>Thomas K.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>&#x0002a;</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Artie McFerrin Department of Chemical Engineering, Texas A &#x00026; M University, College Station, Texas, United States of America</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Department of Biology, Texas A &#x00026; M University, College Station, Texas, United States of America</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Zachry Department of Civil Engineering, Texas A &#x00026; M University, College Station, Texas, United States of America</addr-line></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Ausubel</surname><given-names>Frederick M.</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Massachusetts General Hospital, United States of America</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">&#x0002a; E-mail: <email>Thomas.Wood@chemail.tamu.edu</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: AU TKW. Performed the experiments: AU. Analyzed the data: AU TKW. Wrote the paper: AU TKW.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>6</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><!-- Fake ppub added to accomodate plos workflow change from 03/2008 and 03/2009 --><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>6</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>6</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue>6</issue><elocation-id>e1000483</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>12</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>5</month><year>2009</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Ueda, Wood. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</copyright-statement></permissions><abstract><p>With the opportunistic pathogen <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>, quorum sensing based on homoserine lactones was found to influence biofilm formation. Here we discern a mechanism by which quorum sensing controls biofilm formation by screening 5850 transposon mutants of <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> PA14 for altered biofilm formation. This screen identified the PA3885 mutant, which had 147-fold more biofilm than the wild-type strain. Loss of PA3885 decreased swimming, abolished swarming, and increased attachment, although this did not affect production of rhamnolipids. The PA3885 mutant also had a wrinkly colony phenotype, formed pronounced pellicles, had substantially more aggregation, and had 28-fold more exopolysaccharide production. Expression of PA3885 in <italic>trans</italic> reduced biofilm formation and abolished aggregation. Whole transcriptome analysis showed that loss of PA3885 activated expression of the <italic>pel</italic> locus, an operon that encodes for the synthesis of extracellular matrix polysaccharide. Genetic screening identified that loss of PelABDEG and the PA1120 protein (which contains a GGDEF-motif) suppressed the phenotypes of the PA3885 mutant, suggesting that the function of the PA3885 protein is to regulate 3,5-cyclic diguanylic acid (c-di-GMP) concentrations as a phosphatase since c-di-GMP enhances biofilm formation by activating PelD, and c-di-GMP inhibits swarming. Loss of PA3885 protein increased cellular c-di-GMP concentrations; hence, PA3885 protein is a negative regulator of c-di-GMP production. Purified PA3885 protein has phosphatase activity against phosphotyrosine peptides and is translocated to the periplasm. Las-mediated quorum sensing positively regulates expression of the PA3885 gene. These results show that the PA3885 protein responds to AHL signals and likely dephosphorylates PA1120, which leads to reduced c-di-GMP production. This inhibits matrix exopolysaccharide formation, which leads to reduced biofilm formation; hence, we provide a mechanism for quorum sensing control of biofilm formation through the <italic>pel</italic> locus and suggest PA3885 should be named TpbA for <underline>t</underline>yrosine <underline>p</underline>hosphatase related to <underline>b</underline>iofilm formation and PA1120 should be TpbB.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="summary"><title>Author Summary</title><p>Most bacteria live in biofilms, which are complex communities of microorganisms attached to a surface via polysaccharides; these biofilms are responsible for most human bacterial diseases. The pathogen <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> is best-studied for biofilm formation. Currently, it is recognized that cell communication or quorum sensing is important for biofilm formation, but how these external signals are converted into internal signals to regulate the networks of genes that result in biofilm formation is not well understood. Here, by studying 5850 bacterial strains, each of which lacks a single protein, we identify a new enzyme of <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>, a tyrosine phosphatase (TpbA), that links extracellular quorum sensing signals to polysaccharide production and biofilm formation. We find that TpbA is subject to control by quorum sensing signals, that it is in the periplasm, and that it controls the level of the intracellular secondary messenger 3,5-cyclic diguanylic acid (c-di-GMP). By controlling c-di-GMP concentrations, TpbA serves to regulate biofilm formation, rapid cell movement on the surface, colony morphology, cell aggregation, and polysaccharide production. The importance of our study is that it shows the secondary messenger c-di-GMP may be regulated by tyrosine phosphorylation; hence, it provides a new target for controlling bacterial social behavior.</p></abstract><counts><page-count count="15"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p><italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>, an opportunistic pathogen, is often used to elucidate how biofilms form because persistence of this bacterium is linked to its ability to form biofilms <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Ryder1">&#x0005b;1&#x0005d;</xref>. Biofilms are formed by the attachment of bacteria to submerged surfaces in aquatic environments through their production of microbial products including polysaccharides, proteins, and nucleic acids <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Ryder1">&#x0005b;1&#x0005d;</xref>. In <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> PA14, the glucose-rich extracellular polysaccharide (EPS) of the biofilm matrix is formed by proteins encoded by the <italic>pel</italic> operon; note the related strain <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> PAO1 has two EPS production loci, <italic>pel</italic> and <italic>psl</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Jackson1">&#x0005b;2&#x0005d;</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Friedman1">&#x0005b;3&#x0005d;</xref>. Mutations in the <italic>pel</italic> locus of <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> PA14 dramatically decrease biofilm formation as well as pellicle formation; pellicles are formed at the interface between the air and liquid medium <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Friedman1">&#x0005b;3&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><p>Regulation of Pel polysaccharide involves 3,5-cyclic diguanylic acid (c-di-GMP) which is formed by diguanylate cyclases with GGDEF motifs that synthesize this second messenger; phosphodiesterases with EAL motifs catabolize c-di-GMP. Many proteins with GGDEF motifs enhance biofilm formation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Kulasakara1">&#x0005b;4&#x0005d;</xref>; for example, c-di-GMP increases cellulose biosynthesis in <italic>Acetobacter xylinus</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Ross1">&#x0005b;5&#x0005d;</xref>, and c-di-GMP enhances EPS production by binding the PelD protein that is a c-di-GMP receptor in <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> PA14 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Lee1">&#x0005b;6&#x0005d;</xref>. Thus, biofilm formation is controlled by a signal cascade mediated by a complex of c-di-GMP and PelD in <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> PA14; however, the upstream portions of this cascade have not been elucidated <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Sakuragi1">&#x0005b;7&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><p>Quorum sensing (QS) is bacterial communication using diffusible molecules known as autoinducers to regulate population behavior and is related to both polysaccharide production and biofilm formation. To date, three QS systems have been identified in <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>. Las-based QS is regulated by <italic>N</italic>-(3-oxododecanoyl)-L-homoserine lactone, produced by LasRI <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Passador1">&#x0005b;8&#x0005d;</xref>, and Rhl-based QS is regulated by <italic>N</italic>-butyryl homoserine lactone, produced by RhlRI <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Ochsner1">&#x0005b;9&#x0005d;</xref>. The third QS molecule, 2-heptyl-3-hydroxy-4-quinolone (PQS), was identified as a regulator for both Las- and Rhl-QS <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Diggle1">&#x0005b;10&#x0005d;</xref>. These cell communication signals regulate several phenotypes including virulence and antibiotic resistance <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Wagner1">&#x0005b;11&#x0005d;</xref>. Although the relationship between QS and biofilm formation has not been fully elucidated, some lines of evidence show the importance of QS for biofilm formation. Cells lacking Las-QS in <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> form flat biofilms, and this structural abnormality makes bacteria in biofilms more sensitive to antibiotic treatment <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Davies1">&#x0005b;12&#x0005d;</xref>. Biofilm architecture is regulated by rhamnolipids whose synthesis is controlled by Rhl-QS <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Davey1">&#x0005b;13&#x0005d;</xref>. Thus, <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> QS seems to participate in the development of biofilm architecture rather than initiation of biofilm formation. In addition, LasR- and RhlR-QS have been shown to influence the <italic>pel</italic> operons indirectly and another transcriptional regulator that controls <italic>pel</italic> has been predicted <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Sakuragi1">&#x0005b;7&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><p>Protein phosphorylation and dephosphorylation are well-conserved posttranslational modifications in both prokaryotes and eukaryotes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Deutscher1">&#x0005b;14&#x0005d;</xref>. Protein kinases and phosphatases modulate cellular activity by adding and removing phosphate groups at Ser, Thr, or Tyr residues. Phosphorylation also occurs at His and Asp residues by histidine kinases and response regulators in two-component regulatory systems. Although the discovery of protein phosphorylation was delayed in prokaryotes compared to eukaryotes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Deutscher1">&#x0005b;14&#x0005d;</xref>, many genome sequences predict the existence of phosphorylation/dephosphorylation systems in prokaryotes. The <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> genome encodes an extraordinary number of the genes for two-component regulatory systems <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Stover1">&#x0005b;15&#x0005d;</xref>, and diverse cellular functions are regulated by His-Asp phosphorylation including chemotaxis, iron acquisition, alginate production, and virulence factors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Rodrigue1">&#x0005b;16&#x0005d;</xref>. In contrast, phosphorylation at Ser, Thr, and Tyr residues has not been studied well in <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>; although, Fha1 of the Type VI secretion system is posttranslationally regulated through Thr phosphorylation by the protein kinase PpkA and dephosphorylated by the phosphatase PppA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Mougous1">&#x0005b;17&#x0005d;</xref>. In <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic>, mutations in <italic>prkC</italic>, a Ser/Thr kinase, and <italic>prpC</italic>, a phosphatase, decrease sporulation and biofilm formation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Madec1">&#x0005b;18&#x0005d;</xref>. Mutations in <italic>stk1</italic>, a Ser/Thr kinase, and <italic>stp1</italic>, a phosphatase of Stk1, decrease virulence in <italic>Streptococcus agalactiae</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Rajagopal1">&#x0005b;19&#x0005d;</xref>. These findings show that posttranslational modification via protein phosphorylation at Ser, Thr, and Tyr residues regulates various cellular functions.</p><p>In this study, our goal was to explore the complex regulatory cascade that includes detection of QS signals, Pel polysaccharide production, and biofilm formation. By screening 5850 transposon mutants for altered biofilm formation, we identified and characterized a novel protein tyrosine phosphatase, TpbA (<underline>t</underline>yrosine <underline>p</underline>hosphatase related to <underline>b</underline>iofilm formation), that represses biofilm formation through the <italic>pel</italic> locus. The <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant displays pleiotropic phenotypes such as hyperbiofilm formation, enhanced EPS production, altered colony morphology, increased aggregation, elevated c-di-GMP, and abolished swarming. Loss of an uncharacterized GGDEF protein, PA1120 (TpbB), suppressed these phenotypes, indicating that TpbA controls c-di-GMP production through TpbB. Therefore, the mechanism for QS-control of biofilm formation has been extended to include a novel phosphatase (TpbA), a diguanylate cyclase (TpbB), and c-di-GMP; hence, the predicted additional level of control of the <italic>pel</italic> polysaccharide locus has been identified and involves c-di-GMP as controlled by a tyrosine phosphatase.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2a"><title>TpbA negatively regulates biofilm formation and positively regulates swimming and swarming</title><p>Previously, by screening 5850 transposon mutants for altered biofilm formation, we identified 137 transposon mutants of <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> PA14 with over 3-fold enhanced biofilm formation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Ueda1">&#x0005b;20&#x0005d;</xref>. Among these mutants, the <italic>tpbA</italic> (PA3885) mutant increased biofilm formation by 147-fold after 8 h in LB medium at 37&#x000b0;C (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000483-g001">Fig. 1A</xref>). This significant increase in biofilm formation upon inactivating <italic>tpbA</italic> is partially due to enhanced attachment to the polystyrene surface because biofilm formation at the bottom of the plates (solid/liquid interface) increased gradually with the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant while PA14 did not form biofilm on the bottom of the plate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000483-g001">Fig. 1B</xref>).</p><fig id="ppat-1000483-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000483.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Inactivation of <italic>tpbA</italic> increases biofilm formation.</title><p>Total biofilm formation (at the liquid/solid and air/liquid interfaces) (A), and biofilm formation on the bottom of polystyrene plates (B) by <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> PA14 and the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant at 37&#x000b0;C in LB after 50 h. Six to ten wells were used for each culture. Data show the average of the two independent experiments&#x000b1;s.d.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ppat.1000483.g001"/></fig><p>Motility often influences biofilm formation in <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>; biofilm formation is inversely influenced by swarming motility <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Caiazza1">&#x0005b;21&#x0005d;</xref>, and swimming motility increases initial attachment to surfaces during biofilm development <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-OToole1">&#x0005b;22&#x0005d;</xref>. To examine the relationship between enhanced biofilm formation and motility in the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant, we examined swimming and swarming motility for this mutant; <italic>rhlR</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Khler1">&#x0005b;23&#x0005d;</xref> and <italic>flgK</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-OToole1">&#x0005b;22&#x0005d;</xref> mutants were used as negative controls for swarming and swimming motility, respectively. Although PA14 swarmed on the surface of plates at 24 h, the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutations abolished swarming like the <italic>rhlR</italic> mutation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000483-g002">Fig. 2A</xref>). The <italic>tpbA</italic> mutation also decreased swimming motility by 40&#x00025; (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000483-g002">Fig. 2B</xref>). Swarming is positively influenced by production of the biosurfactant putisolvins in <italic>P. putida</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Lindum1">&#x0005b;24&#x0005d;</xref> and rhamnolipids in <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Khler1">&#x0005b;23&#x0005d;</xref>. However, no significant difference was found in the production of rhamnolipids between PA14 and the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000483-g002">Fig. 2C</xref>). This shows the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutation abolishes swarming in a manner distinct from the production of rhamnolipids.</p><fig id="ppat-1000483-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000483.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>TpbA regulates swarming, swimming motility, and production of rhamnolipids.</title><p>Swarming motility (A), swimming motility (B), and production of rhamnolipids (C) of <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> PA14 and the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant at 37&#x000b0;C after 24 h. Five plates were used for each swarming and swimming culture, and data show the average of two independent experiments. For the production of rhamnolipids, data show the average of the two independent experiments&#x000b1;s.d.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ppat.1000483.g002"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>TpbA affects colony morphology, decreases EPS, and decreases pellicle production</title><p>Congo-red is often used to observe colony morphology because it detects EPS production and this impacts biofilm formation; for example, the <italic>wspF</italic> mutant shows wrinkly colony morphology on Congo-red plates and has increased biofilm formation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Hickman1">&#x0005b;25&#x0005d;</xref>, while smooth colonies like the <italic>pelA</italic> mutant <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Friedman1">&#x0005b;3&#x0005d;</xref> form less biofilm. We found that the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant formed a red, wrinkly colony when it was grown on Congo-red plates at 37&#x000b0;C, although PA14 and the <italic>pelA</italic> mutant formed white smooth colonies (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000483-g003">Fig. 3A</xref>). When the bacteria were grown at 25&#x000b0;C, both PA14 and the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant formed red wrinkly colonies, but the <italic>pelA</italic> mutant still formed a white smooth colony (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000483-g003">Fig. 3A</xref>). These observations with the <italic>pelA</italic> mutant and wild-type PA14 are identical to the previous report that expression of the <italic>pel</italic> genes is induced at room temperature and repressed at 37&#x000b0;C <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Sakuragi1">&#x0005b;7&#x0005d;</xref>. Therefore, the red wrinkly colony formed by the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant at 37&#x000b0;C implies increased production of EPS via Pel.</p><fig id="ppat-1000483-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000483.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Inactivation of <italic>tpbA</italic> increases colony roughness and enhances EPS production.</title><p>Colony morphology of <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> PA14, the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant, and the <italic>pelA</italic> mutant on Congo-red plates after 6 days at 25&#x000b0;C or 37&#x000b0;C (A). EPS production of each strain after 24 h at 37&#x000b0;C or after 48 h at 25&#x000b0;C (B). Data show the average of the two independent experiments&#x000b1;s.d.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ppat.1000483.g003"/></fig><p>We also quantified the amount of EPS bound to cells of PA14 and the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant at both 37&#x000b0;C and 25&#x000b0;C. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000483-g003">Fig. 3B</xref>, the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant produced 28-fold more EPS than PA14 at 37&#x000b0;C. The <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant also produced 4.3-fold more EPS than PA14 at room temperature. The <italic>pelA</italic> mutant (negative control) did not form EPS at both temperatures tested. We also found that the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant formed a pronounced pellicle at 37&#x000b0;C after 1 day, but PA14 and the <italic>pelA</italic> mutant did not form a pellicle (data not shown). At 25&#x000b0;C, both the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant and PA14 formed pellicles after 5 days. Taken together with the EPS production data, TpbA reduces pellicle formation by decreasing Pel activity.</p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Differentially regulated genes in biofilm cells of the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant</title><p>To confirm the impact of the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutation on <italic>pel</italic> expression and to investigate its impact on the whole genome, a whole-transcriptome analysis was performed with biofilm cells of the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant at 37&#x000b0;C at 7 h; planktonic cells were not assayed since we were primarily interested in how TpbA controls biofilm formation. Inactivation of <italic>tpbA</italic> altered diverse loci including genes related to EPS production (<italic>pelACDF</italic> induced approximately 4-fold), transport (PA2204 repressed approximately 5-fold, PA4142&#x02013;PA4143 induced approximately 3-fold), type IV pili (PA4302 to PA4306 repressed approximately 4-fold), and a putative adhesin and its regulator (PA4624&#x02013;PA4625 induced approximately 4-fold) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1000483.s006">Tables S1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1000483.s007">S2</xref>). Expression of <italic>tpbA</italic> was induced as much as 120-fold in the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant, suggesting that TpbA negatively regulates its transcription. The whole-transcriptome experiments were performed twice using independent cultures of PA14 and the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant at 7 h, and most of the differentially regulated genes were consistently altered except <italic>pel</italic> genes which were induced the most in the samples containing an RNase inhibitor. A whole-transcriptome analysis was also conducted using biofilm cells at 4 h since the mode of growth switched from planktonic to biofilm for the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant at this time (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000483-g001">Fig. 1A</xref>). Similar to the 7 h results, several loci were induced including <italic>pelAEF</italic> (1.5- to 1.7-fold), <italic>tpbA</italic> (42-fold), PA1168&#x02013;PA1169 (1.4- to 2.1-fold), PA3886 (3.5-fold), and PA4624&#x02013;PA4625 (2- to 3.7-fold) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1000483.s006">Table S1</xref>).</p><p>To verify induction of the <italic>pel</italic> locus, expression of <italic>pelA</italic> was determined by quantitative real time-PCR (qRT-PCR). Using two independent RNA samples extracted from biofilm cells at 7 h, <italic>pelA</italic> was induced 112&#x000b1;100-fold in the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant vs. PA14. These results showed EPS production is induced significantly in the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant due to overexpression of <italic>pel</italic> genes. qRT-PCR also confirmed induction of PA4625 (7&#x000b1;7-fold) as well as PA4139 (38&#x000b1;30-fold) that encodes a hypothetical protein.</p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>TpbA represses adhesin expression and reduces aggregation</title><p>Cell aggregative behavior is also related to biofilm formation so we investigated the role of TpbA on cell aggregation and found the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant causes cell aggregation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000483-g004">Fig. 4A</xref>). Autoaggregation of the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant was also observed in 96-well polystyrene plates during biofilm formation (data not shown). Our whole-transcriptome analysis showed that inactivating <italic>tpbA</italic> induced both PA4624 (encodes for a putative hemolysin activator) and PA4625 (encodes for an adhesin/hemagglutinin) by 2.1- to 4.9-fold. In <italic>E. coli</italic>, adhesin regulates cell aggregation as well as attachment <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Sherlock1">&#x0005b;26&#x0005d;</xref>. To examine whether PA4624&#x02013;PA4625 control adhesive activity in <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>, we investigated biofilm formation with these mutants. Both mutants showed decreased initial biofilm formation; i.e., initial attachment, to polystyrene plates at 1 h and 2 h (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000483-g004">Fig. 4B</xref>), and final biofilm formation at 24 h was also decreased for both the PA4624 and PA4625 mutants, which suggests that both gene products control attachment to the surface. Therefore, TpbA decreases cell aggregation probably by repressing the PA4624 and PA4625 genes.</p><fig id="ppat-1000483-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000483.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Inactivation of <italic>tpbA</italic> increases cell aggregation.</title><p>Aggregation of PA14 and the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant after diluting with fresh LB medium (percentages indicate volume &#x00025; of the starting overnight culture and fresh medium) (A). Biofilm formation of mutants lacking adhesin (PA4625) and its regulator (PA4624) at 37&#x000b0;C after 1, 2, and 24 h (B). Ten wells were used for each culture. Data show the average of the two independent experiments&#x000b1;s.d.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ppat.1000483.g004"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2e"><title>Complementation of the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutation</title><p>To verify whether the phenotypes observed in the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant were caused by loss of function of TpbA, we confirmed transposon insertion in <italic>tpbA</italic> by PCR at residue 25. Furthermore, biofilm formation for both PA14 and the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant were examined with <italic>tpbA</italic> expressed in <italic>trans</italic> under the control of an arabinose-inducible promoter. <italic>tpbA</italic> expression reduced biofilm formation of the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant by 33&#x00025; (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1000483.s001">Fig. S1A</xref>) and abolished biofilm formation on the bottom of the plates (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1000483.s001">Fig. S1B</xref>). Similar results were found upon expressing <italic>tpbA</italic> in wild-type PA14 (OD<sub>540</sub> value was 0.22&#x000b1;0.02 for PA14/pMQ70 and 0.02&#x000b1;0.01 for PA14/pMQ70-<italic>tpbA</italic>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1000483.s001">Fig. S1A</xref>). In addition, the aggregative phenotype of the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant was also complemented by expression of <italic>tpbA</italic> in <italic>trans</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1000483.s001">Fig. S1C</xref>). Taken together, TpbA functions as a negative regulator of biofilm formation and aggregation in PA14.</p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title>Genetic screening identified Pel and GGDEF-proteins downstream of TpbA</title><p>To investigate how TpbA regulates biofilm formation, EPS production, wrinkly colony morphology, and cell aggregation, genetic screening was conducted using Tn<italic>5-luxAB</italic> transposon mutagenesis to find suppressive loci for the phenotypes of the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutation. The double mutant library (<italic>tpbA</italic> plus random gene inactivations) was screened first for a reduction in aggregation; this step eliminated most cells with unaltered phenotypes by allowing them to aggregate and precipitate at the bottom of the tube. The cells remaining in the supernatant that failed to aggregate like the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant were grown on Congo-red plates, incubated at 37&#x000b0;C for 3&#x02013;4 days, and colonies displaying a white and smooth shape like the wild-type strain were chosen. After that, a third screen was performed by assaying biofilm formation using 96-well polystyrene plates to identify double mutants that had biofilm formation like the wild-type strain. Twenty-six mutants were identified that showed reduced aggregation, a white smooth colony, and reduced biofilm formation like the wild-type strain, and 19 of these mutations were in the <italic>pel</italic> locus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000483-g005">Fig. 5A</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="ppat-1000483-t001">Table 1</xref>). Four of the other mutants have the Tn<italic>5-luxAB</italic> insertion in the TpbB gene (encodes a GGDEF-motif protein) and in the PA1121 gene (encodes a hypothetical protein). In addition, insertions were found in the PA1678 gene (encodes a putative DNA methylase) and in the promoter of the PA5132 gene (encodes a putative protease) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="ppat-1000483-t001">Table 1</xref>). Like the double mutants, all of the single mutants lacking the gene identified by genetic screening were tested for biofilm formation, and all of these mutants formed less biofilm as reported previously (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000483-g005">Fig. 5</xref>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Friedman1">&#x0005b;3&#x0005d;</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Kulasakara1">&#x0005b;4&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><fig id="ppat-1000483-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000483.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Reduction in biofilm formation by <italic>tpbA</italic> phenotype reversal mutations.</title><p>Biofilm formation of double mutants (A) and single mutants (B) identified by genetic screening for the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutation at 37&#x000b0;C in LB after 24 h. Six to ten wells were used for each culture. Representative data are shown in (A). Biofilm formation of each mutant was calculated relative to that of PA14 (OD<sub>540</sub> mutant/OD<sub>540</sub> wild-type). Data show the average of the two independent experiments&#x000b1;s.d.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ppat.1000483.g005"/></fig><table-wrap id="ppat-1000483-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000483.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Phenotype reversal loci for the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutation.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="ppat-1000483-t001-1" xlink:href="ppat.1000483.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strain</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PAO1 ID</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14 ID</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene Name</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene function</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Relative biofilm formation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Colony morphology</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aggregation</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">white smooth</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>tpbA</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA3885</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_13660</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>tpbA</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tyrosine phosphatase (this study)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">red wrinkly</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0002b;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mutant 1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA1120</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_49890</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>tpbB</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c-di-GMP cyclase, GGDEF motif</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">white smooth</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mutant 19</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA1120</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_49890</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>tpbB</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c-di-GMP cyclase, GGDEF motif</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">white smooth</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mutant 4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA1121</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_49880</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">white smooth</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mutant 11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA1121</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_49880</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">white smooth</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mutant 2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA1678</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_42790</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative DNA methylase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">white smooth</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mutant 6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA1678</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_42790</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative DNA methylase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">white smooth</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mutant 5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA3058</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_24560</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>pelG</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Predicted membrane protein related to EPS production, PelG</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">white smooth</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mutant 7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA3058</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_24560</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>pelG</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Predicted membrane protein related to EPS production, PelG</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">white smooth</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mutant 9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA3058</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_24560</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>pelG</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Predicted membrane protein related to EPS production, PelG</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">white smooth</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mutant 12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA3058</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_24560</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>pelG</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Predicted membrane protein related to EPS production, PelG</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">white smooth</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mutant 18</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA3058</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_24560</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>pelG</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Predicted membrane protein related to EPS production, PelG</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">white smooth</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mutant 10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA3060</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_24530</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>pelE</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sucrose synthase related to EPS production, PelE</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.41</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">white smooth</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mutant 15</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA3060</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_24530</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>pelE</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sucrose synthase related to EPS production, PelE</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">white smooth</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mutant 3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA3061</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_24510</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>pelD</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-lactate permease related to EPS production, PelD</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">white smooth</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mutant 16</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA3063</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_24490</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>pelB</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Conserved hypothetical protein related to EPS production, PelB</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">white smooth</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mutant 21</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA3063</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_24490</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>pelB</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Conserved hypothetical protein related to EPS production, PelB</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">white smooth</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mutant 22</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA3063</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_24490</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>pelB</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Conserved hypothetical protein related to EPS production, PelB</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">white smooth</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mutant 23</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA3063</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_24490</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>pelB</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Conserved hypothetical protein related to EPS production, PelB</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">white smooth</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mutant 25</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA3063</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_24490</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>pelB</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Conserved hypothetical protein related to EPS production, PelB</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">white smooth</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mutant 27</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA3063</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_24490</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>pelB</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Conserved hypothetical protein related to EPS production, PelB</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">white smooth</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mutant 8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA3064</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_24480</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>pelA</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oligogalacturonide lyase related to EPS production, PelA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">white smooth</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mutant 14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA3064</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_24480</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>pelA</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oligogalacturonide lyase related to EPS production, PelA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">white smooth</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mutant 17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA3064</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_24480</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>pelA</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oligogalacturonide lyase related to EPS production, PelA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">white smooth</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mutant 20</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA3064</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pro-PA14_24480</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>pelA</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oligogalacturonide lyase related to EPS production, PelA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">white smooth</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mutant 24</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA3064</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_24480</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>pelA</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oligogalacturonide lyase related to EPS production, PelA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">white smooth</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mutant 13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA5132</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pro-PA14_67780</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative protease</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">white smooth</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><p>Genetic screening identified additional mutations that mask the phenotypes of the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant (enhanced biofilm formation, EPS production, wrinkly colony morphology, and aggregation). Relative biofilm formation is shown as a ratio of that of the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2g"><title>TpbA negatively controls cellular c-di-GMP concentrations</title><p>Results of genetic screening and the whole-transcriptome analysis implied TpbA regulates c-di-GMP concentrations since loss of one of the GGDEF proteins (TpbB) masked the phenotypes of the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant. <italic>tpbB</italic> encodes a functional GGDEF protein whose activity was confirmed by overexpressing this gene in <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Kulasakara1">&#x0005b;4&#x0005d;</xref>. We also confirmed that expression of <italic>tpbB</italic> increases cell aggregation and attachment to tubes so the <italic>tpbB</italic> mutation may be complemented (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1000483.s002">Fig. S2</xref>). In addition, we measured the cellular c-di-GMP concentrations of PA14 and the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant using high performance liquid chromatography (HPLC) as reported previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Kulasakara1">&#x0005b;4&#x0005d;</xref>. The peaks corresponding to c-di-GMP were observed with the extracts of the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant, but not with those of PA14, and the peak was confirmed by comparing the spectrum to purified c-di-GMP as well as by spiking the samples with purified c-di-GMP (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1000483.s003">Fig. S3</xref>). We estimated the cellular c-di-GMP concentration was 10&#x000b1;2 pmol/mg cells in the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant. This is comparable to the c-di-GMP concentration found for a small colony variant that showed aggregation (around 2.0 pmol/mg cells) and a mutant with wrinkly colony morphology <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Meissner1">&#x0005b;27&#x0005d;</xref>. Overexpression of <italic>tpbB</italic> results in c-di-GMP concentrations of 134 pmol/mg cells in PA14 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Kulasakara1">&#x0005b;4&#x0005d;</xref>. Therefore, TpbA reduces c-di-GMP concentrations in the cell and probably does so via TpbB.</p></sec><sec id="s2h"><title>TpbA is a tyrosine phosphatase</title><p><italic>tpbA</italic> encodes a 218 aa protein that has the conserved domain for a protein tyrosine phosphatase <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Denu1">&#x0005b;28&#x0005d;</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Lubben1">&#x0005b;29&#x0005d;</xref> since it has the C(X)<sub>5</sub>R(S/T) motif beginning at aa 132 (<named-content content-type="gene"><underline>C</underline>KHGNN<underline>RT</underline></named-content>). To confirm it is a tyrosine phosphatase, we purified TpbA by adding a polyhistidine tag at either the N-terminus (TpbA-nHis) or the C-terminus (TpbA-cHis) (note only the C-terminus fusion protein was active). Expression of recombinant TpbA was confirmed in <italic>E. coli</italic> by clear expression of a band at 24 kD (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000483-g006">Fig. 6A</xref>). The purified TpbA protein had phosphatase activity with <italic>p</italic>-nitrophenyl phosphate (pNPP) that is often used as a general phosphatase substrate <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Lubben1">&#x0005b;29&#x0005d;</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000483-g006">Fig. 6B</xref>). Further proof that TpbA is a tyrosine phosphatase was found using a tyrosine phosphatase specific inhibitor, trisodium orthovanadate <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Gordon1">&#x0005b;30&#x0005d;</xref>, that completely inhibited the phosphatase activity of TpbA-cHis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000483-g006">Fig. 6B</xref>). The third and fourth lines of evidence that TpbA is a tyrosine phosphatase were found using tyrosine specific substrates; TpbA-cHis dephosphorylated both phosphotyrosine peptides, END(pY)INASL (peptide type I) and DADE(pY)LIPQQG (peptide type II) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000483-g006">Fig. 6C</xref>), and this activity was inhibited by trisodium orthovanadate. These results show conclusively that TpbA encodes a tyrosine phosphatase.</p><fig id="ppat-1000483-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000483.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>TpbA has phosphatase activity against tyrosine residues.</title><p>Purification of TpbA-cHis (lane 1: protein marker, lane 2: whole cell lysate from <italic>E. coli</italic> BL21(DE3)/pET28b-13660c after 3 h of IPTG induction, lane 3: purified TpbA-cHis) (A). <italic>p</italic>-Nitrophenyl phosphate phosphatase assay with TpbA-cHis protein (B). Phosphatase reaction was performed at 37&#x000b0;C for 1 h with the indicated amount of protein. Na<sub>3</sub>VO<sub>4</sub> (10 mM) was used as an inhibitor specific for tyrosine phosphatases. Protein tyrosine phosphatase assay with TpbA-cHis (C). Phosphatase reaction was performed with synthetic phosphotyrosine peptides (type I: END(pY)INASL and type II: DADE(pY)LIPQQG) at 37&#x000b0;C for 3 h. Na<sub>3</sub>VO<sub>4</sub> (50 mM) was used as an inhibitor.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ppat.1000483.g006"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2i"><title>Tyrosine phosphorylation enhances biofilm formation in PA14</title><p>To see the effect of tyrosine phosphorylation on biofilm formation, biofilm formation was examined in PA14 with trisodium orthovanadate at 37&#x000b0;C for 4 h which should reduce dephosphorylation by TpbA. Trisodium orthovanadate increased PA14 biofilm formation 3.6-fold (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1000483.s004">Fig. S4</xref>), showing that cellular tyrosine phosphorylation increases biofilm formation.</p></sec><sec id="s2j"><title>TpbA is found in the periplasm</title><p>The N-terminal region of TpbA protein has a putative signal peptide, predicted by pSORT <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Nakai1">&#x0005b;31&#x0005d;</xref>, that appears necessary for secretion of this protein (28 aa, MHRSPLAWLRLLLAAVLGAFLLGGPLHA). This implied that processing of N-terminal region of TpbA protein may be essential for full phosphatase activity. To prove that TpbA has an active signal sequence, we expressed TpbA in <italic>E. coli</italic> and collected the proteins from cytosolic, periplasmic, and membrane fractions. All fractioned proteins were analyzed by SDS-PAGE, and we found that TpbA exclusively localized in the periplasm (data not shown). Hence, TpbA probably dephosphorylates its substrate in the periplasm which explains why phosphatase activity was seen only with the fusion protein with the His tag at the C-terminus.</p></sec><sec id="s2k"><title>Y48 and Y62 are responsible for TpbB activity</title><p>Since TpbA is a tyrosine phosphatase that is found in the periplasm and since TpbB has three likely periplasmic tyrosines (Y48, Y62, and Y95) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Hirokawa1">&#x0005b;32&#x0005d;</xref>, we mutated the periplasmic tyrosine residues by converting them to phenylalanine and checked for TpbB activity in the <italic>tpbB</italic> mutant. Active TpbB, from overexpression of <italic>tpbB</italic> using the <italic>tpbB</italic> mutant and pMQ70-<italic>tpbB</italic>, always leads to aggregation whereas the empty plasmid does not cause aggregation (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1000483.s005">Fig. S5</xref>); hence, if a necessary tyrosine is mutated, there should be a reduction in aggregation. Aggregation was always observed with TpbB-Y95F in nine cultures; hence TpbB-Y95F remains active even though it lacks tyrosine 95 so this tyrosine is not phosphorylated/dephosphorylated. In contrast, the Y48F mutation of TpbB decreased aggregation for 43&#x00025; of the cultures (20 of 46 cultures did not aggregate), and the Y62F mutation decreased aggregation for 24&#x00025; of the cultures (9 of 37 cultures did not aggregation). Hence, both Y48 and Y62 are likely targets for tyrosine phosphorylation/dephosphorylation of TpbB with Y48 preferred. We confirmed that these mutations did not affect expression level of TpbB protein (data not shown).</p></sec><sec id="s2l"><title>TpbA tyrosine phosphatase is unique among bacteria and eukaryotes</title><p>Tyrosine phosphorylation and dephosphorylation have crucial roles in cellular signaling and are well-conserved among many organisms <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Barford1">&#x0005b;33&#x0005d;</xref>. Some bacterial tyrosine phosphorylations have been identified and these regulatory systems control divergent cellular functions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Cozzone1">&#x0005b;34&#x0005d;</xref>. In order to predict whether TpbA function is conserved among other species, we conducted a BLASTP search and found the TpbA protein is highly conserved among <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> (PAO1, PA14, C3719, and PA7 with an E value less than 3<sup>e-98</sup>) and is well-conserved among <italic>P. fluorescens</italic> Pf-5, <italic>P. fluorescens</italic> Pf0-1, <italic>P. mendocina</italic>, <italic>Burkholderia cepacia</italic>, <italic>Pelobacter carbinolicus</italic>, <italic>Desulfatibacillum alkenivorans</italic>, <italic>Bacteroides thetaiotaomicron</italic>, <italic>B. ovatus</italic>, <italic>B. caccae</italic>, <italic>Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>, <italic>Desulfococcus oleovorans</italic>, and <italic>Geobacter metallireducens</italic> (E values less than 3<sup>e-11</sup>). All of these conserved tyrosine phosphatases have the C(X)<sub>5</sub>R(S/T) signature and most are uncharacterized. Even though protein similarity is not very high, some eukaryotes, such as <italic>Homo sapiens</italic> and <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>, have TpbA homologs with a C(X)<sub>5</sub>R(S/T) signature. Therefore, TpbA and TpbA homologs may share important functions in procaryotes and eucaryotes.</p></sec><sec id="s2m"><title>Las-QS regulates expression of <italic>tpbA</italic></title><p>QS regulates many genes in <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> via a conserved <italic>cis</italic>-element in the promoter of each gene. <italic>N</italic>-(3-oxododecanoyl)-L-homoserine lactone binds to the LasR transcriptional regulator <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Seed1">&#x0005b;35&#x0005d;</xref>, and this complex interacts with the <italic>las-</italic>box, defined as CT-(N)<sub>12</sub>-AG sequence <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Whiteley1">&#x0005b;36&#x0005d;</xref>. The Las-box is conserved among the promoters of the Las-QS regulated genes including <italic>lasB</italic>, <italic>rhlAB</italic>, and <italic>rhlI</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Whiteley1">&#x0005b;36&#x0005d;</xref>. Another class of transcriptional regulation is governed by the <italic>lys</italic>-box, that is defined as a palindromic sequence, T-(N)<sub>11</sub>-A <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Schell1">&#x0005b;37&#x0005d;</xref>, and MvfR is a LysR-type transcription factor that binds to the <italic>lys</italic>-box <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Xiao1">&#x0005b;38&#x0005d;</xref>. We found that the promoter of <italic>tpbA</italic> (p<italic>tpbA</italic>) has a putative <italic>las-</italic>box 220 bp upstream of the start codon (<named-content content-type="gene"><underline>CT</underline>CGCCTCGCTGAA<underline>AG</underline></named-content>) and a putative <italic>lys</italic>-box 90 bp upstream of the start codon (<named-content content-type="gene"><underline>T</underline>GAAGCTGCCTC<underline>A</underline></named-content>). In order to examine if expression of <italic>tpbA</italic> is regulated by QS, we constructed a p<italic>tpbA</italic>::lacZ fusion plasmid (pLP-p<italic>tpbA</italic>) and transformed this into QS-related PA14 mutants (<italic>lasI</italic>, <italic>rhlI</italic>, and <italic>lasR rhlR</italic>). Expression of <italic>tpbA</italic> gene in biofilm cells was reduced by 42&#x00025; in the <italic>lasI</italic> mutant, but not in the <italic>rhlI</italic> mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000483-g007">Fig. 7</xref>). Corroborating these results, inactivation of both <italic>lasR</italic> and <italic>rhlR</italic> also decreased expression of <italic>tpbA</italic> gene by 39&#x00025; (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000483-g007">Fig. 7</xref>). Similar results were obtained when the activity of p<italic>tpbA</italic>::<italic>lacZ</italic> was examined in planktonic cells (50&#x00025; reduction in transcription for the <italic>lasI</italic> mutant and 37&#x00025; reduction for the <italic>lasR rhlR</italic> mutant). Since loss of QS only affected expression of <italic>tpbA</italic> by 50&#x00025;, other factors may also participate in the regulation of <italic>tpbA</italic>. These results suggest that Las-QS, rather than Rhl-QS, is an activator of <italic>tpbA</italic> expression with other unknown regulators.</p><fig id="ppat-1000483-g007" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000483.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>Las QS activates transcription of <italic>tpbA</italic>.</title><p>&#x003b2;-galactosidase activity of p<italic>tpbA</italic> was measured with biofilm cells of PA14 and the mutants <italic>lasI</italic>, <italic>rhlI</italic>, and <italic>lasR rhlR</italic> using pLP-p<italic>tpbA</italic>. Data show the average of the two independent experiments&#x000b1;s.d.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ppat.1000483.g007"/></fig><p>We also investigated whether the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutation influences the regulation of Las- and Rhl-QS using p<italic>lasR</italic>::<italic>lacZ</italic> and p<italic>rhlR</italic>::<italic>lacZ</italic> plasmids. Expression of <italic>lasR</italic> was slightly increased (1.3-fold) with the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutation. This indicated that Las-QS has more impact on expression of <italic>tpbA</italic> than <italic>tpbA</italic> does on that of Las-QS. In addition, expression of <italic>rhlR</italic> was decreased by 2-fold in the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant. Hence, LasR appears to enhance <italic>tpbA</italic> transcription and TpbA leads to increased <italic>rhl</italic> transcription.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Discussion</title><p>In this study, we demonstrate that TpbA is a tyrosine phosphatase that regulates diverse phenotypes in <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> including the concentration of cellular c-di-GMP. As a second messenger, c-di-GMP is a positive regulator of biofilm formation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Kulasakara1">&#x0005b;4&#x0005d;</xref>, EPS production <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Lee1">&#x0005b;6&#x0005d;</xref>, and pellicle formation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Kulasakara1">&#x0005b;4&#x0005d;</xref>, and a negative regulator of swarming motility <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Merritt1">&#x0005b;39&#x0005d;</xref>. The lines of evidence that show TpbA represses c-di-GMP production in <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> that we found are (i) inactivating <italic>tpbA</italic> increases c-di-GMP (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1000483.s003">Fig. S3</xref>); (ii) inactivating <italic>tpbA</italic> increases biofilm formation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000483-g001">Fig. 1</xref>), EPS production (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000483-g003">Fig. 3B</xref>), and pellicle formation, and c-di-GMP stimulates biofilm formation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Kulasakara1">&#x0005b;4&#x0005d;</xref>, EPS production <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Lee1">&#x0005b;6&#x0005d;</xref>, and pellicle formation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Kulasakara1">&#x0005b;4&#x0005d;</xref>; (iii) inactivating <italic>tpbA</italic> increases expression of the <italic>pel</italic> locus (seen via the whole-transcriptome analysis and RT-PCR), and c-di-GMP activates expression of <italic>pelA</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Lee1">&#x0005b;6&#x0005d;</xref>; (iv) inactivating <italic>tpbA</italic> increases aggregation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000483-g004">Fig. 4</xref>) and expression of adhesins (PA4625), and c-di-GMP stimulates adhesion <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Rmling1">&#x0005b;40&#x0005d;</xref>; (v) inactivating <italic>tpbA</italic> decreases motility (abolishing swarming and decreasing swimming in the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000483-g002">Fig. 2AB</xref>), and c-di-GMP decreases swarming <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Rmling1">&#x0005b;40&#x0005d;</xref>; (vi) inactivating <italic>tpbB</italic> (encodes a GGDEF-motif protein that produces c-di-GMP <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Kulasakara1">&#x0005b;4&#x0005d;</xref>) suppresses the phenotypes observed in the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant, and (vii) expression of <italic>tpbA</italic> and <italic>tpbB</italic> in <italic>trans</italic> complements aggregation/biofilm formation and aggregation, respectively. Thus, TpbA represses these phenotypes by decreasing c-di-GMP. A proposed regulatory mechanism for biofilm formation by TpbA is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000483-g008">Fig. 8</xref>.</p><fig id="ppat-1000483-g008" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000483.g008</object-id><label>Figure 8</label><caption><title>Schematic of TpbA regulation of biofilm formation in <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> PA14.</title><p>The QS molecule, <italic>N</italic>-(3-oxododecanoyl)-L-homoserine lactone (3-oxoC12-HSL), binds to the LasR transcription factor, and this complex activates expression of <italic>tpbA</italic>. TpbA has a N-terminal signal sequence and is translocated into the periplasm. Periplasmic TpbA dephosphorylates the membrane-anchored GGDEF protein TpbB at a tyrosine reside which deactivates GGDEF protein activity. The reduced cellular c-di-GMP concentration decreases expression of the <italic>pel</italic> operon as well as adhesin genes. This leads to reduced EPS production, biofilm formation, and pellicle formation, as well as enhanced swarming motility. Production of rhamnolipids is not regulated by TpbA.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ppat.1000483.g008"/></fig><p>EPS production in <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> PA14 is regulated by PelA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Friedman1">&#x0005b;3&#x0005d;</xref>. Transcription of <italic>pelA</italic> is higher at temperatures lower than 37&#x000b0;C, and PA14 forms more biofilm at lower temperatures <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Sakuragi1">&#x0005b;7&#x0005d;</xref>. However, the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutation seems to constitutively enhance <italic>pel</italic> expression independently from this temperature regulation as seen in the enhanced EPS production at 37&#x000b0;C (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000483-g003">Fig. 3</xref>) and the whole-transcriptome analysis that was conducted at 37&#x000b0;C (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1000483.s007">Table S2</xref>). In addition to increased expression of <italic>pelA</italic>, additional activation of Pel proteins might be caused by the increased c-di-GMP concentration by the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutation since c-di-GMP binds PelD and increases EPS production <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Lee1">&#x0005b;6&#x0005d;</xref>. In addition to the enhanced EPS production (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000483-g003">Fig. 3B</xref>) and increased <italic>pel</italic> expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000483-g003">Fig. 3A</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1000483.s006">Table S1</xref>, and qRT-PCR) seen in the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant, another reason why inactivating <italic>tpbA</italic> increased biofilm formation is the elevated adhesin activity as seen via enhanced biofilm formation on the bottom of polystyrene plates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000483-g001">Fig. 1B</xref>). Cell surface adhesins affect bacterial adhesive activity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Dunne1">&#x0005b;41&#x0005d;</xref>, and we have discovered a novel adhesin (PA4625) that is related to TpbA (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1000483.s006">Table S1</xref>) and to initial biofilm formation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000483-g004">Fig. 4B</xref>). Since expression of adhesion factors is also positively regulated by c-di-GMP <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Rmling1">&#x0005b;40&#x0005d;</xref>, elevated c-di-GMP level enhances adhesion of the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant.</p><p>c-di-GMP seems to control the switch of motility-sessility of the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant since inactivation of TpbA abolished swarming motility (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000483-g002">Fig. 2A</xref>) and decreased swimming motility by 40&#x00025; (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000483-g002">Fig. 2B</xref>), although regulation of swarming motility is very complex as its activity is controlled by QS, flagellar synthesis, and production of rhamnolipids <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Verstraeten1">&#x0005b;42&#x0005d;</xref>. In addition, our whole-transcriptome results showed weak repression of some of flagellar biosynthesis genes (<italic>flg</italic>, <italic>fle</italic>, and <italic>fli</italic> loci) due to the elevated c-di-GMP, and activity of FleQ, a transcriptional activator of flagellar biosynthesis, is repressed upon binding c-di-GMP <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Hickman2">&#x0005b;43&#x0005d;</xref>. Hence, the increased c-di-GMP concentrations may repress motility of the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant via the FleQ pathway that affects expression of flagellar synthesis genes.</p><p>Many genes are expected to be differentially regulated by changing c-di-GMP concentrations since it plays a role as a second messenger in <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>. Similar regulation of gene expression was observed between the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant and the other strains related to c-di-GMP production. For example, production of PA1107, TpbB, and PA3702 proteins that have a GGDEF-domain leads to activation of <italic>pelA</italic> expression <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Lee1">&#x0005b;6&#x0005d;</xref>. Mutation in <italic>wspF</italic>, encoding a CheB-like methylesterase, increases both biofilm formation and c-di-GMP production <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Hickman1">&#x0005b;25&#x0005d;</xref>. <italic>wspF</italic> mutation altered expression of genes such as <italic>pelABCDEFG</italic>, PA4624, PA4625, PA2440, and PA2441 whose expression are induced in the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1000483.s007">Table S2</xref>). Common regulation of these genes may be partially controlled by the elevated cellular c-di-GMP concentrations. In contrast, expression of <italic>pelA</italic> was not induced in the <italic>bifA</italic> mutant that produces more c-di-GMP <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Kuchma1">&#x0005b;44&#x0005d;</xref>. This may be because regulation of c-di-GMP signaling is complex in that the <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> genome encodes 17 diguanylate cyclases, 5 phosphodiesterases, and 16 diguanylate cyclase-phosphodiesterase proteins <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Kulasakara1">&#x0005b;4&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><p>Relevance of c-di-GMP to regulation of diverse cellular functions is now an emerging topic in bacteriology. This second messenger is an activator of cellulose synthase in <italic>Acetobactor xylinum</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Ross1">&#x0005b;5&#x0005d;</xref> and controls many phenotypes in <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Kulasakara1">&#x0005b;4&#x0005d;</xref>. Several GGDEF proteins for synthesis and EAL proteins for degradation of c-di-GMP have been identified in <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Lee1">&#x0005b;6&#x0005d;</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Merritt1">&#x0005b;39&#x0005d;</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Kuchma1">&#x0005b;44&#x0005d;</xref>, and increased production of c-di-GMP enhances biofilm formation and decreases swarming motility <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Kulasakara1">&#x0005b;4&#x0005d;</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Lee1">&#x0005b;6&#x0005d;</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Merritt1">&#x0005b;39&#x0005d;</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Kuchma1">&#x0005b;44&#x0005d;</xref>. Similarly, enhanced biofilm formation and/or abolished swarming motility were observed in the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant via increased production of cellular c-di-GMP. Since TpbA does not possess GGDEF and EAL domains, this protein indirectly influences cellular c-di-GMP concentrations via its phosphatase activity as shown by activity with both pNPP, a broad substrate for phosphatases, and two phosphotyrosine-specific peptides (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000483-g006">Fig. 6</xref>). We also found that processing the N-terminal signal sequence may be necessary for TpbA activity in the periplasm. Hence, our results reveal a novel regulatory mechanism for cellular c-di-GMP concentration by tyrosine phosphorylation in the periplasm of <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>; control of c-di-GMP by tyrosine phosphorylation has not been shown previously.</p><p>There is little known about the regulation of GGDEF and EAL proteins in regard to regulation of c-di-GMP level. A chemosensory system, encoded by <italic>wspABCDEFR</italic> in PAO1, regulates c-di-GMP production via a His-Asp phosphorylation relay <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Hickman1">&#x0005b;25&#x0005d;</xref>. For the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant, <italic>tpbB</italic> was found to reverse the phenotype of <italic>tpbA</italic>, suggesting that overproduction of c-di-GMP is clearly related to the phenotypes of the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant as overexpression of this gene caused pronounced aggregation (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1000483.s002">Fig. S2</xref>). Probably, TpbB, or another GGDEF protein, might participate in c-di-GMP synthesis in the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant. A comprehensive analysis of all of the <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> GGDEF proteins has been completed, and those GGDEF proteins that abolished or decreased biofilm formation are PA0169, PA1107, TpbB, PA1181, PA1433, PA1727, PA3702, PA4959, and PA5487 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Kulasakara1">&#x0005b;4&#x0005d;</xref>. Among these GGDEF proteins, only PA1107, TpbB, PA3702, and PA5487 increased biofilm formation when their genes were overexpressed <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Kulasakara1">&#x0005b;4&#x0005d;</xref>. Because TpbA is a periplasmic protein, its target GGDEF protein should have periplasmic regions. By a bioinformatics evaluation, of those four GGDEF proteins that increased biofilm formation, only PA1107 and TpbB have transmembrane regions. Taken together with the results of genetic screening, TpbB is the most likely target protein for TpbA. Also, our results imply the periplasmic Y48 and Y62 residues of TpbB are the likely targets for tyrosine phosphorylation. We are now investigating whether TpbA regulates the activity of GGDEF proteins to control cellular c-di-GMP concentrations in <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>.</p><p>The relationship between tyrosine phosphorylation and biofilm formation is not well established. We found that trisodium orthovanadate treatment increased biofilm formation of PA14 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1000483.s004">Fig. S4</xref>), indicating that tyrosine phosphorylation increases biofilm formation in <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>. Recently, Ltp1, a low molecular weight tyrosine phosphatase in non-motile, Gram-negative <italic>P. gingivalis</italic>, was identified as a negative regulator of EPS production and biofilm formation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Maeda1">&#x0005b;45&#x0005d;</xref>. A sequence similarity search shows TpbA is not a homolog of Ltp1, because TpbA has a signal sequence in its N-terminal region, and TpbA is translocated into the periplasm. Other differences were found in the position of the motif for the tyrosine phosphatase, since TpbA has the motif at the position 132 and Lpt1 has it at position 9. It appears the <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> genome encodes another tyrosine phosphatase, annotated as <italic>ptpA</italic>, that has a tyrosine phosphatase motif at the position 7 and does not have a signal sequence at the N-terminus. The function of PtpA is unknown but it is essential <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Liberati1">&#x0005b;46&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><p>In contrast to poorly-investigated Tyr phosphorylation, regulation of biofilm formation by phosphorylation has been identified for several systems; for example, for the His kinase/Asp response regulator phosphorylation systems RocS1/RocA1/RocR of <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> PAK <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Kulasekara1">&#x0005b;47&#x0005d;</xref> and the PAO1 PA1611/PA1976/PA2824/RetS/HptB system of <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Hsu1">&#x0005b;48&#x0005d;</xref>. In addition, in the <italic>B. subtilis</italic> PrkC/PrpC system <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Madec1">&#x0005b;18&#x0005d;</xref>, loss of a membrane-anchored Thr kinase and its phosphatase reduces biofilm formation. Our results indicate that TpbA acts as a negative regulator of cellular c-di-GMP formation and loss of TpbA results in increased c-di-GMP concentrations that enhance biofilm formation and inhibit motility. These results show clearly that posttranslational modification through phosphatase activity is related to bacterial biofilm formation as well as to the regulation of the synthesis of cellular second messengers. In addition, by showing <italic>tpbA</italic> transcription is increased by LasR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000483-g007">Fig. 7</xref>) and by finding AHL-binding motifs, we have now linked quorum sensing to c-di-GMP concentrations and biofilm formation in <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>. Similarly, <italic>Vibrio cholerae</italic> QS was found recently to reduce cellular c-di-GMP concentrations via a c-di-GMP-specific phosphodiesterase which leads to lower biofilm formation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Hammer1">&#x0005b;49&#x0005d;</xref>. A common element in both studies is that QS seems to be a negative regulator of c-di-GMP. The <italic>tpbA</italic> mutation caused a hyper-aggregative phenotype (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000483-g004">Fig. 4</xref>), and this would lead to flat biofilms since the <italic>wspF</italic> mutant, which accumulates increased c-di-GMP, formed flat biofilms <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Hickman1">&#x0005b;25&#x0005d;</xref>. Formation of flat and undifferentiated biofilms is also observed by loss of LasI function <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Davies1">&#x0005b;12&#x0005d;</xref> that can activate <italic>tpbA</italic> expression. Hence, TpbA might participate in developing biofilm structure. These results are important in that the regulatory networks that control c-di-GMP concentrations are now linked to the environment and cell populations.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s4"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s4a"><title>Bacterial strains and growth conditions</title><p>Strains used in this study are listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="ppat-1000483-t002">Table 2</xref>. <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> PA14 wild-type and its isogenic mutants were obtained from the Harvard Medical School <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Liberati1">&#x0005b;46&#x0005d;</xref>. Transposon insertion of the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant was verified as described previously with a minor modification <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Ueda2">&#x0005b;50&#x0005d;</xref>. Briefly, the <italic>tpbA</italic> gene was amplified from chromosomal DNA using primers PA14_13660-VF and PA14_13660-VR (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1000483.s008">Table S3</xref>) which did not amplify chromosomal DNA from the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant. In addition, the DNA fragment corresponding to the end of the transposon and <italic>tpbA</italic> gene was amplified with <italic>tpbA</italic> chromosomal DNA using primers PA14_13660-VF and GB-3a (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1000483.s008">Table S3</xref>) and PA14_13660-VR and R1 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1000483.s008">Table S3</xref>) but these pairs of primers did not amplify PA14 wild-type chromosomal DNA. <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> and <italic>E. coli</italic> were routinely grown in Luria-Bertani (LB) medium at 37&#x000b0;C unless noted. Gentamicin (15 &#x000b5;g/mL) and tetracycline (75 &#x000b5;g/mL) were used for growth of the <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> transposon mutants, carbenicillin (300 &#x000b5;g/mL) was used to maintain <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> plasmids, and kanamycin (50 &#x000b5;g/mL) and chloramphenicol (50 &#x000b5;g/mL) were used to maintain <italic>E. coli</italic> plasmids (<xref ref-type="table" rid="ppat-1000483-t002">Table 2</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="ppat-1000483-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000483.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Strains used in this study.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="ppat-1000483-t002-2" xlink:href="ppat.1000483.t002"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strain</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genotype or description</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold><italic><underline>P. aeruginosa</underline></italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wild-type strain</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Liberati1">&#x0005b;46&#x0005d;</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_13660 (PA3885, <italic>tpbA</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_13660 &#x02126; <italic>Mar2xT7</italic>, Gm<sup>R</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Liberati1">&#x0005b;46&#x0005d;</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_19120 (PA3477, <italic>rhlR</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_19120 &#x02126; <italic>Mar2xT7</italic>, Gm<sup>R</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Liberati1">&#x0005b;46&#x0005d;</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_50360 (PA1086, <italic>flgK</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_50360 &#x02126; <italic>Mar2xT7</italic>, Gm<sup>R</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Liberati1">&#x0005b;46&#x0005d;</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_49880 (PA1121)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_49880 &#x02126; <italic>Mar2xT7</italic>, Gm<sup>R</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Liberati1">&#x0005b;46&#x0005d;</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_49890 (PA1120, <italic>tpbB</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_49890 &#x02126; <italic>Mar2xT7</italic>, Gm<sup>R</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Liberati1">&#x0005b;46&#x0005d;</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_42820 (PA1678)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_42820 &#x02126; <italic>Mar2xT7</italic>, Gm<sup>R</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Liberati1">&#x0005b;46&#x0005d;</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_67780 (PA5132)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_67780 &#x02126; <italic>Mar2xT7</italic>, Gm<sup>R</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Liberati1">&#x0005b;46&#x0005d;</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_24480 (PA3064, <italic>pelA</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_24480 &#x02126; <italic>Mar2xT7</italic>, Gm<sup>R</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Liberati1">&#x0005b;46&#x0005d;</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_24490 (PA3063, <italic>pelB</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_24490 &#x02126; <italic>Mar2xT7</italic>, Gm<sup>R</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Liberati1">&#x0005b;46&#x0005d;</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_24510 (PA3061, <italic>pelD</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_24510 &#x02126; <italic>Mar2xT7</italic>, Gm<sup>R</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Liberati1">&#x0005b;46&#x0005d;</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_24560 (PA3058, <italic>pelG</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_24560 &#x02126; <italic>Mar2xT7</italic>, Gm<sup>R</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Liberati1">&#x0005b;46&#x0005d;</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_61190 (PA4624)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_61190 &#x02126; <italic>Mar2xT7</italic>, Gm<sup>R</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Liberati1">&#x0005b;46&#x0005d;</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_61200 (PA4625)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_61200 &#x02126; <italic>Mar2xT7</italic>, Gm<sup>R</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Liberati1">&#x0005b;46&#x0005d;</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_45940 (PA1432, <italic>lasI</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_45940 &#x02126; <italic>Mar2xT7</italic>, Gm<sup>R</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Liberati1">&#x0005b;46&#x0005d;</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_19130 (PA3476, <italic>rhlI</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_19130 &#x02126; <italic>Mar2xT7</italic>, Gm<sup>R</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Liberati1">&#x0005b;46&#x0005d;</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14_lasR rhlR (PA1431 PA3477, <italic>lasR rhlR</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA14 <italic>&#x00394;lasR &#x00394;rhlR</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Park1">&#x0005b;70&#x0005d;</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold><italic><underline>E. coli</underline></italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BL21(DE3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F<sup>&#x02212;</sup><italic>ompT hsdS<sub>B</sub>(r<sub>B</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup>m<sub>B</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup>) gal dcm &#x003bb;</italic>(DE3) &#x003a9; p<italic>lac</italic>UV5:: T7 polymerase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Novagen</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB101</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>pro leu thi lacY</italic> Str<italic><sup>r</sup> endoI<sup>&#x02212;</sup> recA<sup>&#x02212;</sup> r<sup>&#x02212;</sup> m<sup>&#x02212;</sup></italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Ditta1">&#x0005b;67&#x0005d;</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S17-1(<italic>&#x003bb;pir</italic>)/pUT-miniTn<italic>5</italic>-<italic>luxAB</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tc<sup>R</sup> Sm<sup>R</sup> Tp<sup>R</sup><italic>mod</italic><sup>&#x0002b;</sup><italic>res thi pro recA hsdR17</italic> &#x003a9; RP4-TC::Mu-Km::Tn7 with pUT-miniTn<italic>5-luxAB</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Ramsey1">&#x0005b;59&#x0005d;</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Simon1">&#x0005b;71&#x0005d;</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TG1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K12, <italic>lac&#x02013;pro supE thi hsdD5</italic> (F&#x02032; <italic>traD36 proA</italic><sup>&#x0002b;</sup><italic>B</italic><sup>&#x0002b;</sup><italic>lacI</italic><sup>q</sup><italic>lacZ</italic> M15)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Sambrook1">&#x0005b;61&#x0005d;</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AG1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>recA1 endA1 gyrA96 thi-1 hsdR17(r<sub>K</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> m<sub>K</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup>) supE44 relA1</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Kitagawa1">&#x0005b;72&#x0005d;</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold><underline>Plasmids</underline></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pMQ70</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Car<sup>R</sup>, Ap<sup>R</sup>, P<sub>BAD</sub>, expression vector</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Shanks1">&#x0005b;51&#x0005d;</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pMQ70-<italic>tpbA</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Car<sup>R</sup>, Ap<sup>R</sup>, P<sub>BAD</sub>::<italic>tpbA</italic>, complementation plasmid</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pMQ70-<italic>tpbB</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Car<sup>R</sup>, Ap<sup>R</sup>, P<sub>BAD</sub>::<italic>tpbB</italic>, complementation plasmid</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pMQ70-<italic>tpbB-</italic>Y48F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Car<sup>R</sup>, Ap<sup>R</sup>, P<sub>BAD</sub>::<italic>tpbB</italic>, Y48 of TpbB replaced with F48</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pMQ70-<italic>tpbB-</italic>Y62F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Car<sup>R</sup>, Ap<sup>R</sup>, P<sub>BAD</sub>::<italic>tpbB</italic>, Y62 of TpbB replaced with F62</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pMQ70-<italic>tpbB-</italic>Y95F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Car<sup>R</sup>, Ap<sup>R</sup>, P<sub>BAD</sub>::<italic>tpbB</italic>, Y95 of TpbB replaced with F95</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pRK2013</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mobilizing conjugation plasmid</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Figurski1">&#x0005b;68&#x0005d;</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pET28b</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Km<sup>R</sup>, P<sub>T7</sub> expression vector</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Novagen</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pET28b-13660n</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Km<sup>R</sup>, P<sub>T7</sub>::<italic>tpbA-nHis</italic><sup>&#x0002b;</sup>, expression vector for TpbA-nHis</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pET28b-13660c</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Km<sup>R</sup>, P<sub>T7</sub>::<italic>tpbA-cHis</italic><sup>&#x0002b;</sup>, expression vector for TpbA-cHis</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pLP170</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Car<sup>R</sup> Ap<sup>R</sup>, promoterless-lacZ</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Pesci1">&#x0005b;73&#x0005d;</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pLP-p<italic>tpbA</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Car<sup>R</sup> Ap<sup>R</sup>, p<italic>tpbA</italic>::lacZ</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pPCS1001</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Car<sup>R</sup> Ap<sup>R</sup>, p<italic>lasR</italic>::lacZ</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Pesci1">&#x0005b;73&#x0005d;</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pPCS1002</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Car<sup>R</sup> Ap<sup>R</sup>, p<italic>rhlR</italic>::lacZ</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Pesci1">&#x0005b;73&#x0005d;</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pCA24N</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cm<sup>R</sup>, <italic>lacI</italic><sup>q</sup>, pCA24N</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Kitagawa1">&#x0005b;72&#x0005d;</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pCA24N-<italic>yddV</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cm<sup>R</sup>, <italic>lacI</italic><sup>q</sup>, pCA24N P<sub>T5-lac</sub>::<italic>yddV</italic><sup>&#x0002b;</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Kitagawa1">&#x0005b;72&#x0005d;</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pCA24N-<italic>cpdB</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cm<sup>R</sup>, <italic>lacI</italic><sup>q</sup>, pCA24N P<sub>T5-lac</sub>::<italic>cpdB</italic><sup>&#x0002b;</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Kitagawa1">&#x0005b;72&#x0005d;</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pCA24N-<italic>oxyR</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cm<sup>R</sup>, <italic>lacI</italic><sup>q</sup>, pCA24N P<sub>T5-lac</sub>::<italic>oxyR</italic><sup>&#x0002b;</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Kitagawa1">&#x0005b;72&#x0005d;</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pGEM-T easy</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Car<sup>R</sup> Ap<sup>R</sup>, TA cloning vector</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Qiagen</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt102"><p>Gm<sup>R</sup>, Tc<sup>R</sup>, Km<sup>R</sup>, Car<sup>R</sup>, Cm<sup>R</sup>, and Ap<sup>R</sup> indicate gentamicin, tetracycline, kanamycin, carbenicillin, chloramphenicol, and ampicillin resistance, respectively.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s4b"><title>Complementation of <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> mutants</title><p>For complementation of the <italic>tpbA</italic> and <italic>tpbB</italic> mutations, <italic>tpbA</italic> and <italic>tpbB</italic> were expressed under the control of the pBAD promoter in pMQ70 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Shanks1">&#x0005b;51&#x0005d;</xref>. <italic>tpbA</italic> and <italic>tpbB</italic> were amplified using a Pfu DNA polymerase with primers PA14_13660-F1-NheI and PA14_13660-R-cHis-HindIII and PA14_49890-F1-NheI and PA14_49890-R-cHis-HindIII, respectively (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1000483.s008">Table S3</xref>). PCR products were cloned into the NheI and HindIII sites of pMQ70. The resulting plasmids, pMQ70-<italic>tpbA</italic> and pMQ70-<italic>tpbB</italic>, were transformed into PA14 and the mutants by conjugation. Briefly, 1 mL of overnight culture of the recipient strain (PA14 or the mutant), helper strain (HB101/pRK2013), and donor strain (TG1/pMQ70, TG1/pMQ70-<italic>tpbA</italic>, or pMQ70-<italic>tpbB</italic>) was washed with 1 mL of fresh LB medium. The mixture of three strains was incubated on LB plates at 37&#x000b0;C overnight. PA14 strains with pMQ70-based plasmid were selected on LB plates with 100 &#x000b5;g/mL rifampicin (to kill the donor and helper), 300 &#x000b5;g/mL carbenicillin (to kill <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> without pMQ70-based plasmids), and 15 &#x000b5;g/mL gentamicin (if a recipient was a PA14 mutant constructed using a transposon insertion with the Gm<sup>R</sup> gene). If indicated, 0.05&#x00025; arabinose was added to induce gene expression.</p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title>Biofilm formation</title><p>Biofilm formation was examined in 96-well polystyrene plates using crystal violet staining <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Pratt1">&#x0005b;52&#x0005d;</xref>. Overnight cultures of <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> were diluted to a turbidity of 0.05 at 600 nm with fresh LB medium, and then 150 &#x000b5;L of diluted bacterial culture was incubated in 96-well polystyrene plates for 2, 4, 8, 24, and 50 h. Ten wells were used for each strain and three independent cultures were used for each experiment. Trisodium orthovanadate, a tyrosine phosphatase-specific inhibitor, was added to LB medium at 10 mM.</p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title>Colony morphology</title><p>To observe colony morphology, overnight cultures were diluted to a turbidity of 0.005 at 600 nm with T-broth (10 g/L tryptone), and 2 &#x000b5;L of diluted cultures were spotted on Congo-red plates (10 g/L tryptone, 40 &#x000b5;g/mL Congo-red, and 20 &#x000b5;g/mL Coomassie brilliant blue) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Friedman1">&#x0005b;3&#x0005d;</xref>. Plates were incubated at 37&#x000b0;C or room temperature for 3 to 7 days.</p></sec><sec id="s4e"><title>Motility assays</title><p>Swimming motility was examined with cells grown to a turbidity of 1 at 600 nm using 0.3&#x00025; agar plates with 1&#x00025; tryptone and 0.25&#x00025; NaCl <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Sperandio1">&#x0005b;53&#x0005d;</xref> and swarming motility was examined with BM-2 plates (62 mM potassium phosphate, 2 mM MgSO<sub>4</sub>, 10 &#x000b5;M FeSO<sub>4</sub>, 0.1&#x00025; casamino acid, 0.4&#x00025; glucose, and 0.5&#x00025; Bacto agar) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Overhage1">&#x0005b;54&#x0005d;</xref>. Motility was measured after 24 h. Five plates were tested for each culture, and two independent cultures were used. The <italic>flgK</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-OToole1">&#x0005b;22&#x0005d;</xref> and <italic>rhlR</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Khler1">&#x0005b;23&#x0005d;</xref> mutants were used as negative controls for swimming and swarming, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="s4f"><title>Aggregation assay</title><p>Aggregation was examined by diluting overnight cultures with fresh LB medium in 5 mL screw-capped tubes from 0&#x00025; (no added fresh LB medium) to 100&#x00025; (pure fresh LB medium). Cells were inverted gently several times and placed at room temperature for 15 min.</p></sec><sec id="s4g"><title>Pellicle formation</title><p>Overnight cultures of PA14, the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant, and the <italic>pelA</italic> mutant were diluted to a turbidity of 0.005 at 600 nm in 4 mL T-broth, and the bacterial cultures were placed in a polycarbonate glass tube at 37&#x000b0;C or room temperature <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Friedman1">&#x0005b;3&#x0005d;</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s4h"><title>EPS assay</title><p>Pel-dependent EPS production was quantified as described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Lee1">&#x0005b;6&#x0005d;</xref> based on the amount of Congo red that binds to the EPS. Briefly, 1 mL of overnight culture was washed with 1 mL T-broth. Due to aggregative phenotype of the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant, cell pellets of the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant, wild-type, and <italic>pelA</italic> mutant (negative control) were sonicated three times at 3W for 10 sec. Bacterial suspensions in T-broth (500 &#x000b5;L) were incubated with 40 &#x000b5;g/mL Congo-red at 37&#x000b0;C or room temperature with vigorous shaking. After 2 h, the absorbance of the supernatants of the each suspension was measured at 490 nm using a spectrophotometer. T-broth with 40 &#x000b5;g/mL Congo-red was used as a blank.</p></sec><sec id="s4i"><title>Rhamnolipids assay</title><p>Production of rhamnolipids was determined as described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Wilhelm1">&#x0005b;55&#x0005d;</xref>. Overnight cultures were diluted to a turbidity of 0.05 at 600 nm in 25 mL LB medium and were re-grown at 250 rpm for 24 h to eliminate the effect of antibiotics. The supernatants of the bacterial cultures were used to determine the relative concentrations of rhamnolipids using orcinol/sulfuric acid. Rhamnose (Fisher Scientific, Pittsburgh, PA) was used as a standard.</p></sec><sec id="s4j"><title>Whole-transcriptome analysis</title><p>The <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> genome array (Affymetrix, P/N 510596) was used to investigate differential gene expression in biofilm cells between PA14 and the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant. Biofilm cells were harvested from 10 g of glass wool <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Ren1">&#x0005b;56&#x0005d;</xref> after incubation for 4 h and 7 h in LB with shaking at 250 rpm, and RNA was extracted with a RNeasy Mini Kit (Qiagen) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-GonzlezBarrios1">&#x0005b;57&#x0005d;</xref>; note the RNase inhibitor RNA<italic>later</italic> (Applied Biosystems, Austin, TX) was used for the 4 h and second 7 h set of microarrays. Global scaling was applied so the average signal intensity was 500. The probe array images were inspected for any image artifact. Background values, noise values, and scaling factors of both arrays were examined and were comparable. The intensities of polyadenosine RNA controls were used to monitor the labeling process. If the gene with the larger transcription rate did not have a consistent transcription rate based on the 13 probe pairs (<italic>p</italic>-value less than 0.05), these genes were discarded. A gene was considered differentially expressed when the <italic>p</italic>-value for comparing two chips was lower than 0.05 (to assure that the change in gene expression was statistically significant and that false positives arise less than 5&#x00025;) and when the expression ratio was higher than the standard deviation for the whole microarrays <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Ren2">&#x0005b;58&#x0005d;</xref>, 1.4 for 4 h, 1.7 for the first 7 h replicate, and 2.2 for second 7 h replicate. All three sets of whole-transcriptome data were deposited at the Gene Expression Omnibus (GSE13871).</p></sec><sec id="s4k"><title>qRT-PCR</title><p>qRT-PCR was performed using the StepOnePlus&#x02122; Real-Time PCR System (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA). Expression of <italic>pelA</italic>, the PA4625 gene, and the PA4139 gene was determined using total RNA isolated from two independent biofilm cultures of PA14 and the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant. The biofilm cells were grown and total RNA were isolated in the same manner as described above for the whole-transcriptome analysis. The primers for qRT-PCR are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1000483.s008">Table S3</xref>. The housekeeping gene <italic>rplU</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Kuchma1">&#x0005b;44&#x0005d;</xref> was used to normalize the gene expression data.</p></sec><sec id="s4l"><title>Genetic screening</title><p>To isolate the suppressive loci for TpbA functions, a double mutant library was generated using the Tn<italic>5-luxAB</italic> transposon with the background of the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutation as described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Ramsey1">&#x0005b;59&#x0005d;</xref>. Briefly, 1 mL of overnight culture of the <italic>P. aeruginosa tpbA</italic> mutant and <italic>E. coli</italic> S17-1 (&#x003bb;pir) with Tn<italic>5</italic>-<italic>luxAB</italic> were grown on LB plates together overnight. Cells were harvested from the plate and resuspended in 10 mL of LB medium. Screening of cells with mutations in addition to <italic>tpbA</italic> was performed in three steps. Suppression of the highly-aggregative phenotype of the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant was used first; the cell mixture (<italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> single and double mutants along with <italic>E. coli</italic> S17-1) was placed at room temperature for 15 min and the supernatant was used for secondary screening (cells with the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant aggregative phenotype were therefore discarded). Supernatant cells were spread on Congo-red plates with 50 &#x000b5;g/mL gentamicin (to kill <italic>E. coli</italic>), and 75 &#x000b5;g/mL tetracycline (to kill the <italic>tpbA</italic> single mutant), and incubated for 3&#x02013;4 days. <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> double mutants with smooth surfaces were picked (the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant was red and wrinkled). The crystal violet biofilm assay was used for the third screening, and mutants showing decreased biofilm formation in comparison to that of the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant were chosen as phenotype reversal mutants. The insertion position of Tn<italic>5-luxAB</italic> transposon was determined by two-step PCR as described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Ramsey1">&#x0005b;59&#x0005d;</xref> with primers LuxAB inside and Arb1 for the first round of PCR and LuxAB outside and Arb2 for the second round of PCR (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1000483.s008">Table S3</xref>). The PCR product was ligated into pGEM-T easy (Promega, Madison, MI) and sequenced using a BigDye Terminator Cycle Sequencing Kit (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA).</p></sec><sec id="s4m"><title>Quantification of c-di-GMP</title><p>c-di-GMP was isolated as described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Amikam1">&#x0005b;60&#x0005d;</xref>. <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> was grown in 1 L of LB medium for 16 h at 250 rpm, and formaldehyde (final concentration of 0.18&#x00025;) was added to inactivate degradation of c-di-GMP. Cells were harvested by centrifugation at 8,000 <italic>g</italic> for 10 min at 4&#x000b0;C. Nucleotide extract was prepared as described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Amikam1">&#x0005b;60&#x0005d;</xref>. Cell pellets were washed with 40 mL of phosphate buffered saline (pH 7) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Sambrook1">&#x0005b;61&#x0005d;</xref> with 0.18&#x00025; formaldehyde and centrifuged at 8,000 <italic>g</italic> for 10 min at 4&#x000b0;C. The cell pellets were dissolved in H<sub>2</sub>O and boiled for 10 min. After cooling the samples on ice for 10 min, nucleotides were extracted in 65&#x00025; ethanol. Supernatants were transferred, and the extraction was repeated. Pooled supernatants were lyophilized, and pellets were dissolved in 1 mL of 0.15 M triethyl ammonium acetate (TEAA, pH 5.0). The samples were filtered using a PVDF filter (0.22 &#x000b5;m), and 20 &#x000b5;L of each sample was fractionated using HPLC (Waters 515 with photodiode array detector, Milford, MA) with a reverse-phase column (Nova-Pak&#x000ae; C18 column; Waters, 150&#x000d7;3.9 cm, 4 &#x000b5;m). Separations were conducted in 0.15 M TEAA at a 1 mL/min flow rate using gradient elution with acetonitrile (0&#x00025; to 15&#x00025; concentration). Synthetic c-di-GMP (BIOLOG Life Science Institute, Bremen, Germany) was used as a standard. The peak corresponding to c-di-GMP from the extract of the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant was verified by co-elution with standard c-di-GMP. <italic>E. coli</italic> AG1/pCA24N-<italic>yddV</italic> that has an elevated c-di-GMP concentration <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-MendezOrtiz1">&#x0005b;62&#x0005d;</xref> was also used as a positive control.</p></sec><sec id="s4n"><title>Plasmid construction of pET28b-13660c and purification of recombinant TpbA-cHis</title><p>To determine if TpbA is a phosphatase, <italic>tpbA</italic> was amplified with a Pfu DNA polymerase using primers PA14_13660-F-XbaI and PA14_13660-R-XhoI (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1000483.s008">Table S3</xref>). The PCR product was digested with XbaI and XhoI and was ligated in-frame to the polyhistidine tag sequence of the pET28b vector. The resulting plasmid, pET28b-13660c has the <italic>tpbA</italic> gene fused to a 6&#x000d7; His tag at the C-terminus (TpbA-cHis) and under control of the T7 promoter. The pET28b-13660c plasmid was confirmed by DNA sequencing with the T7 promoter and T7 terminator primers (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1000483.s008">Table S3</xref>). Production of TpbA-cHis was induced in <italic>E. coli</italic> BL21(DE3) cells with 1 mM IPTG at room temperature overnight. TpbA-cHis was purified using a Ni-NTA resin (Qiagen, Valencia, CA) as described in a manufacturer's protocol. Purified TpbA-cHis was dialyzed against buffer (50 mM Tris-HCl, 100 mM NaCl, 10&#x00025; glycerol, 0.01&#x00025; Triton X-100, pH 7.5) at 4&#x000b0;C overnight.</p></sec><sec id="s4o"><title>Phosphatase assay</title><p>The <italic>p</italic>-nitrophenyl phosphate assay (pNPP) was used to examine TpbA-cHis phosphatase activity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Hausmann1">&#x0005b;63&#x0005d;</xref>. Purified TpbA-cHis protein was incubated in 100 &#x000b5;L of reaction buffer (50 mM Tris-acetate, 10 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 10 mM pNPP, 5 mM DTT, pH 5.5) at 37&#x000b0;C for 1 h. The reaction was quenched by adding 900 &#x000b5;L of 1 M NaOH. Trisodium orthovanadate, a specific inhibitor for tyrosine phosphatase <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Gordon1">&#x0005b;30&#x0005d;</xref>, was used at 10 mM. <italic>p</italic>-nitrophenol was measured at an absorbance of 405 nm. An extinction coefficient of 1.78&#x000d7;10<sup>4</sup> M<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> was used to calculate the concentration of <italic>p</italic>-nitrophenol.</p><p>To examine if TpbA is a tyrosine specific phosphatase, a tyrosine phosphatase assay was performed using the Tyrosine Phosphatase Assay System (Qiagen). Eight micrograms of TpbA-cHis were incubated with either 50 &#x000b5;M phosphotyrosine peptide type I (END(pY)INASL) or peptide type II (DADE(pY)LIPQQG) in a reaction buffer (50 mM Tris-Acetate, 10 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, pH 5.5) at 37&#x000b0;C for 3 h. The reaction was quenched using a molybdate dye solution and incubated for 30 min at room temperature. Released phosphate was quantified by measuring the absorbance at 630 nm.</p></sec><sec id="s4p"><title>Determination of the subcellular localization of TpbA</title><p>TpbA-cHis protein was expressed in BL21(DE3) cells with 1 mM IPTG for 4 h at 37&#x000b0;C. Periplasmic proteins were purified using a PeriPreps Periplasting Kit (Epicentre Technologies, Madison, WI) as well as cytoplasmic and membrane proteins. <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> CpdB <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Liu1">&#x0005b;64&#x0005d;</xref> was used as a control of periplasmic protein and the <italic>E. coli</italic> OxyR <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Iuchi1">&#x0005b;65&#x0005d;</xref> was used for the cytoplasmic control. Fractionated proteins as well as TpbB were analyzed by 12&#x00025; SDS-PAGE.</p></sec><sec id="s4q"><title>Site-directed mutagenesis of the TpbB periplasmic tyrosine residues</title><p>Site-directed mutagenesis of the predicted periplasmic tyrosine residues of TpbB was performed to convert them to phenylalanine (Y48F, Y62F, and Y95F); it was reasoned that phenylalanine would provide a similar bulky side chain but remove the hydroxyl moiety needed for phosphorylation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Chen1">&#x0005b;66&#x0005d;</xref>. The mutations were introduced into pMQ70-<italic>tpbB</italic> using Pfu DNA polymerase and QuikChange Site-Directed Mutagenesis Kit (Stratagene, La Jolla, CA), and the primers are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1000483.s008">Table S3</xref>. The resulting plasmids, pMQ70-<italic>tpbB</italic>-Y48F, pMQ70-<italic>tpbB</italic>-Y62F, and pMQ70-<italic>tpbB</italic>-Y95F were transformed into the <italic>tpbB</italic> mutant by conjugation and aggregation was assayed. DNA sequencing was used to confirm the tyrosine mutations and that no other mutations were introduced into the promoter or protein-coding sequences.</p></sec><sec id="s4r"><title>&#x003b2;-galactosidase activity</title><p>The promoter region of <italic>tpbA</italic> (p<italic>tpbA</italic>), including 399 bp upstream of the start codon and 31 bp of the open reading frame, was amplified using Pfu DNA polymerase with primers pPA14_13660-F-HindIII and pPA14_13660-R-BamHI (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1000483.s008">Table S3</xref>). The PCR product (430 bp) was cloned into the HindIII/BamHI sites of pLP170 to produce pLP-p<italic>tpbA</italic>, and it was conjugated into PA14 and the QS-related mutants using helper strain HB101/pRK2013 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Ditta1">&#x0005b;67&#x0005d;</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Figurski1">&#x0005b;68&#x0005d;</xref>. Transformants were grown overnight in LB medium with 300 &#x000b5;g/mL carbenicillin, reinoculated at a turbidity of 0.05 at 600 nm, and grown for another 6 h. Biofilm cells were harvested from 4 g of glass wool after incubation for 6 h in LB at 37&#x000b0;C with shaking at 250 rpm. &#x003b2;-galactosidase activity was measured using suspension cells and biofilm cells as described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ppat.1000483-Wood1">&#x0005b;69&#x0005d;</xref>. Similarly, &#x003b2;-galactosidase activity of p<italic>lasR</italic>::<italic>lacZ</italic> (pPCS1001) and p<italic>rhlR</italic>::<italic>lacZ</italic> (pPCS1002) was examined in PA14 and the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ppat.1000483.s001"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p>Complementation of the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant using biofilm formation and aggregation. Total biofilm formation (A) and bottom biofilm formation on polystyrene plates (B) by <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> PA14 and the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant with either pMQ70 or pMQ70-<italic>tpbA</italic> in LB with 300 &#x000b5;g/mL carbenicillin and 0.05&#x00025; arabinose after 24 h at 37&#x000b0;C. Six wells were used for each culture. Data show the average of the two to four independent experiments&#x000b1;s.d. Cell aggregation of PA14 and the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant with either pMQ70 or pMQ70-<italic>tpbA</italic> (C). Overnight cultures (1 mL) were mixed with 3 mL of fresh LB medium, and the tubes were placed at room temperature for 15 min.</p><p>(2.54 MB TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="ppat.1000483.s001.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ppat.1000483.s002"><label>Figure S2</label><caption><p>Complementation of the <italic>tpbB</italic> mutant using aggregation. Bacterial cultures were grown at 37&#x000b0;C at 250 rpm overnight.</p><p>(6.07 MB TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="ppat.1000483.s002.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ppat.1000483.s003"><label>Figure S3</label><caption><p>Quantification of cellular c-di-GMP concentrations by HPLC from 30 mg of cells. 10 &#x000b5;M synthetic c-di-GMP (A), nucleotide extract from PA14 (B), nucleotide extract from the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant (C), and nucleotide extract from the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant spiked with 10 &#x000b5;M c-di-GMP (D). Spectra of synthetic c-di-GMP (E) and nucleotide extract from the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant (F).</p><p>(1.71 MB TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="ppat.1000483.s003.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ppat.1000483.s004"><label>Figure S4</label><caption><p>Normalized biofilm formation of PA14 at 37&#x000b0;C in LB after 24 h with and without tyrosine phosphatase inhibitor Na<sub>3</sub>VO<sub>4</sub> (10 mM). Six wells were used for each culture. Data show the average of the two independent experiments&#x000b1;s.d.</p><p>(0.49 MB TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="ppat.1000483.s004.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ppat.1000483.s005"><label>Figure S5</label><caption><p>Aggregation is reduced by site-directed mutagenesis at Y48 and Y62 of TpbB. The <italic>tpbB</italic> mutant was grown in 25 mL of LB medium supplemented with carbenicillin (300 &#x000b5;g/mL) and gentamicin (15 &#x000b5;g/mL) with pMQ70 (negative control) and pMQ70-<italic>tpbB</italic> (positive control) (A), pMQ70-<italic>tpbB</italic>-Y48F (B), pMQ70-<italic>tpbB</italic>-Y62F (C) and pMQ70-<italic>tpbB</italic>-Y95F (data not shown). Percentage of cultures with each phenotype (aggregation or no aggregation are indicated). A total of 46 and 37 independent cultures was tested for <italic>tpbB</italic>/pMQ70-<italic>tpbB</italic>-Y48F and <italic>tpbB</italic>/pMQ70-<italic>tpbB</italic>-Y62F, respectively, and representative images are shown. Note that aggregates were always formed with <italic>tpbB</italic>/pMQ70-<italic>tpbB</italic> (positive control) and <italic>tpbB</italic>/pMQ70-<italic>tpbB</italic>-Y95F, but not with <italic>tpbB</italic>/pMQ70 (negative control).</p><p>(9.95 MB TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="ppat.1000483.s005.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ppat.1000483.s006"><label>Table S1</label><caption><p>Partial list of induced genes in biofilm cells in LB medium after 4 and 7 h at 37&#x000b0;C for the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant versus wild-type PA14 using three sets of DNA microarrays (note RNA<italic>later</italic> was used for the 4 h set and the second set at 7 h).</p><p>(0.07 MB DOC)</p></caption><media xlink:href="ppat.1000483.s006.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ppat.1000483.s007"><label>Table S2</label><caption><p>Partial list of repressed genes in biofilm cells in LB medium after 4 and 7 h at 37&#x000b0;C for the <italic>tpbA</italic> mutant versus wild-type PA14 using three sets of DNA microarrays (note RNA<italic>later</italic> was used for the 4 h set and the second set at 7 h).</p><p>(0.10 MB DOC)</p></caption><media xlink:href="ppat.1000483.s007.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ppat.1000483.s008"><label>Table S3</label><caption><p>Primers used in this study.</p><p>(0.05 MB DOC)</p></caption><media xlink:href="ppat.1000483.s008.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We are grateful to Professor Frederick Ausubel for the PA14 transposon mutant library, Professor Barbara Iglewski for the pLP170 plasmid, Professor Marvin Whiteley for Tn<italic>5-luxAB</italic>, Professor You-Hee Cho for the PA14 <italic>lasR rhlR</italic> mutant, and the National Institute of Genetics for the ASKA clones.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ppat.1000483-Ryder1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ryder</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Byrd</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wozniak</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Role of polysaccharides in <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> biofilm development.</article-title><source>Curr Opin Microbiol</source><volume>10</volume><fpage>644</fpage><lpage>648</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17981495</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Jackson1"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Starkey</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kremer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Parsek</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wozniak</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Identification of <italic>psl</italic>, a locus encoding a potential exopolysaccharide that is essential for <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> PAO1 biofilm formation.</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><volume>186</volume><fpage>4466</fpage><lpage>4475</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15231778</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Friedman1"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolter</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Genes involved in matrix formation in <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> PA14 biofilms.</article-title><source>Mol Microbiol</source><volume>51</volume><fpage>675</fpage><lpage>690</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14731271</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Kulasakara1"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kulasakara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Brencic</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Liberati</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Urbach</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Analysis of <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> diguanylate cyclases and phosphodiesterases reveals a role for bis-(3&#x02032;&#x02013;5&#x02032;)-cyclic-GMP in virulence.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>103</volume><fpage>2839</fpage><lpage>2844</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16477007</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Ross1"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinhouse</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Amikam</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Huggirat</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1990</year><article-title>The cyclic diguanylic acid regulatory system of cellulose synthesis in <italic>Acetobacter xylinum</italic>. Chemical synthesis and biological activity of cyclic nucleotide dimer, trimer, and phosphothioate derivatives.</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>265</volume><fpage>18933</fpage><lpage>18943</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2172238</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Lee1"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>VT</given-names></name><name><surname>Matewish</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kessler</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hyodo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayakawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>A cyclic-di-GMP receptor required for bacterial exopolysaccharide production.</article-title><source>Mol Microbiol</source><volume>65</volume><fpage>1474</fpage><lpage>1484</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17824927</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Sakuragi1"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sakuragi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolter</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Quorum-sensing regulation of the biofilm matrix genes (<italic>pel</italic>) of <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>.</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><volume>189</volume><fpage>5383</fpage><lpage>5386</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17496081</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Passador1"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Passador</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gambello</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rust</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Iglewski</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name></person-group><year>1993</year><article-title>Expression of <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> virulence genes requires cell-to-cell communication.</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>260</volume><fpage>1127</fpage><lpage>1130</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8493556</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Ochsner1"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ochsner</surname><given-names>UA</given-names></name><name><surname>Reiser</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>1995</year><article-title>Autoinducer-mediated regulation of rhamnolipid biosurfactant synthesis in <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>92</volume><fpage>6424</fpage><lpage>6428</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7604006</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Diggle1"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Diggle</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Cornelis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>C&#x000e1;mara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>4-quinolone signalling in <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>: old molecules, new perspectives.</article-title><source>Int J Med Microbiol</source><volume>296</volume><fpage>83</fpage><lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16483840</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Wagner1"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name><name><surname>Bushnell</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Passador</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name><name><surname>Iglewski</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Microarray analysis of <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> quorum-sensing regulons: effects of growth phase and environment.</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><volume>185</volume><fpage>2080</fpage><lpage>2095</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12644477</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Davies1"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Parsek</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Iglewski</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Costerton</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>The involvement of cell-to-cell signals in the development of a bacterial biofilm.</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>280</volume><fpage>295</fpage><lpage>298</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9535661</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Davey1"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davey</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Caiazza</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Toole</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Rhamnolipid surfactant production affects biofilm architecture in <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> PAO1.</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><volume>185</volume><fpage>1027</fpage><lpage>1036</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12533479</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Deutscher1"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deutscher</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Saier</surname><given-names>MH</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Ser/Thr/Tyr protein phosphorylation in bacteria - for long time neglected, now well established.</article-title><source>J Mol Microbiol Biotechnol</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>125</fpage><lpage>131</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16415586</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Stover1"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stover</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name><surname>Pham</surname><given-names>XQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Erwin</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Mizoguchi</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Warrener</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Complete genome sequence of <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> PA01, an opportunistic pathogen.</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>406</volume><fpage>959</fpage><lpage>964</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10984043</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Rodrigue1"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodrigue</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Quentin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Lazdunski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000e9;jean</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Foglino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Two-component systems in <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>: why so many?</article-title><source>Trends Microbiol</source><volume>8</volume><fpage>498</fpage><lpage>504</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11121759</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Mougous1"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mougous</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Gifford</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramsdell</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Mekalanos</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Threonine phosphorylation post-translationally regulates protein secretion in <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>.</article-title><source>Nat Cell Biol</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>797</fpage><lpage>803</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17558395</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Madec1"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Madec</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Laszkiewicz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwanicki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Obuchowski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>S&#x000e9;ror</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Characterization of a membrane-linked Ser/Thr protein kinase in <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic>, implicated in developmental processes.</article-title><source>Mol Microbiol</source><volume>46</volume><fpage>571</fpage><lpage>586</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12406230</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Rajagopal1"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rajagopal</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Clancy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubens</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>A eukaryotic type serine/threonine kinase and phosphatase in <italic>Streptococcus agalactiae</italic> reversibly phosphorylate an inorganic pyrophosphatase and affect growth, cell segregation, and virulence.</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>278</volume><fpage>14429</fpage><lpage>14441</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12562757</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Ueda1"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ueda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Attila</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Whiteley</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Uracil influences quorum sensing and biofilm formation in <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> and fluorouracil is an antagonist.</article-title><source>Microb Biotechnol</source><volume>2</volume><fpage>62</fpage><lpage>74</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Caiazza1"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caiazza</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Merritt</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Brothers</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Toole</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Inverse regulation of biofilm formation and swarming motility by <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> PA14.</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><volume>189</volume><fpage>3603</fpage><lpage>3612</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17337585</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-OToole1"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O'Toole</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolter</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Flagellar and twitching motility are necessary for <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> biofilm development.</article-title><source>Mol Microbiol</source><volume>30</volume><fpage>295</fpage><lpage>304</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9791175</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Khler1"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>K&#x000f6;hler</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Curty</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name><surname>Barja</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>van Delden</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pech&#x000e8;re</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Swarming of <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> is dependent on cell-to-cell signaling and requires flagella and pili.</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><volume>182</volume><fpage>5990</fpage><lpage>5996</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11029417</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Lindum1"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lindum</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Anthoni</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Christophersen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Eberl</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Molin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title><italic>N</italic>-Acyl-L-homoserine lactone autoinducers control production of an extracellular lipopeptide biosurfactant required for swarming motility of <italic>Serratia liquefaciens</italic> MG1.</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><volume>180</volume><fpage>6384</fpage><lpage>6388</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9829950</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Hickman1"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hickman</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Tifrea</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Harwood</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>A chemosensory system that regulates biofilm formation through modulation of cyclic diguanylate levels.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>102</volume><fpage>14422</fpage><lpage>14427</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16186483</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Sherlock1"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sherlock</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Vejborg</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Klemm</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>The TibA adhesin/invasin from enterotoxigenic <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> is self recognizing and induces bacterial aggregation and biofilm formation.</article-title><source>Infect Immun</source><volume>73</volume><fpage>1954</fpage><lpage>1963</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15784535</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Meissner1"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meissner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wild</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Simm</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rohde</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Erck</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title><italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa cupA</italic>-encoded fimbriae expression is regulated by a GGDEF and EAL domain-dependent modulation of the intracellular level of cyclic diguanylate.</article-title><source>Environ Microbiol</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>2475</fpage><lpage>2485</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17803773</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Denu1"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Denu</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><year>1995</year><article-title>A catalytic mechanism for the dual-specific phosphatases.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>92</volume><fpage>5910</fpage><lpage>5914</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7597052</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Lubben1"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lubben</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Clampit</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Stashko</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Trevillyan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jirousek</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><source>Current Protocols in Pharmacology</source><publisher-loc>NY</publisher-loc><publisher-name>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Inc</publisher-name><fpage>3.8.1</fpage><lpage>3.8.18</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Gordon1"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><year>1991</year><article-title>Use of vanadate as protein-phosphotyrosine phosphatase inhibitor.</article-title><source>Methods Enzymol</source><volume>201</volume><fpage>477</fpage><lpage>482</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1943774</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Nakai1"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanehisa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>1991</year><article-title>Expert system for predicting protein localization sites in gram-negative bacteria.</article-title><source>Proteins</source><volume>11</volume><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1946347</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Hirokawa1"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hirokawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Boon-Chieng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitaku</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>SOSUI: classification and secondary structure prediction system for membrane proteins.</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>14</volume><fpage>378</fpage><lpage>379</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9632836</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Barford1"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barford</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Egloff</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>The structure and mechanism of protein phosphatases: insights into catalysis and regulation.</article-title><source>Annu Rev Biophys Biomol Struct</source><volume>27</volume><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>164</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9646865</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Cozzone1"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cozzone</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Grangeasse</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Doublet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Duclos</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Protein phosphorylation on tyrosine in bacteria.</article-title><source>Arch Microbiol</source><volume>181</volume><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>181</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14745484</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Seed1"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seed</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Passador</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Iglewski</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name></person-group><year>1995</year><article-title>Activation of the <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa lasI</italic> gene by LasR and the <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> autoinducer PAI: an autoinduction regulatory hierarchy.</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><volume>177</volume><fpage>654</fpage><lpage>659</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7836299</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Whiteley1"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whiteley</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>Identification of genes controlled by quorum sensing in <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>96</volume><fpage>13904</fpage><lpage>13909</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10570171</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Schell1"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schell</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><year>1993</year><article-title>Molecular biology of the LysR family of transcriptional regulators.</article-title><source>Annu Rev Microbiol</source><volume>47</volume><fpage>597</fpage><lpage>626</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8257110</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Xiao1"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahme</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Mutation analysis of the <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa mvfR</italic> and <italic>pqsABCDE</italic> gene promoters demonstrates complex quorum-sensing circuitry.</article-title><source>Microbiology</source><volume>152</volume><fpage>1679</fpage><lpage>1686</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16735731</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Merritt1"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Merritt</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Brothers</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuchma</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Toole</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>SadC reciprocally influences biofilm formation and swarming motility via modulation of exopolysaccharide production and flagellar function.</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><volume>189</volume><fpage>8154</fpage><lpage>8164</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17586642</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Rmling1"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>R&#x000f6;mling</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Amikam</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Cyclic di-GMP as a second messenger.</article-title><source>Curr Opin Microbiol</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>218</fpage><lpage>228</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16530465</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Dunne1"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dunne</surname><given-names>WM</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Bacterial adhesion: seen any good biofilms lately?</article-title><source>Clin Microbiol Rev</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>155</fpage><lpage>166</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11932228</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Verstraeten1"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Verstraeten</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Braeken</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Debkumari</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Fauvart</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fransaer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Living on a surface: swarming and biofilm formation.</article-title><source>Trends Microbiol</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>496</fpage><lpage>506</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18775660</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Hickman2"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hickman</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Harwood</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Identification of FleQ from <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> as a c-di-GMP-responsive transcription factor.</article-title><source>Mol Microbiol</source><volume>69</volume><fpage>376</fpage><lpage>389</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18485075</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Kuchma1"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuchma</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Brothers</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Merritt</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Liberati</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></name><name><surname>Ausubel</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>BifA, a cyclic-Di-GMP phosphodiesterase, inversely regulates biofilm formation and swarming motility by <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> PA14.</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><volume>189</volume><fpage>8165</fpage><lpage>8178</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17586641</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Maeda1"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maeda</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tribble</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Tucker</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Anaya</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Shizukuishi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>A <italic>Porphyromonas gingivalis</italic> tyrosine phosphatase is a multifunctional regulator of virulence attributes.</article-title><source>Mol Microbiol</source><volume>69</volume><fpage>1153</fpage><lpage>1164</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18573179</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Liberati1"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liberati</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></name><name><surname>Urbach</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyata</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Drenkard</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>An ordered, nonredundant library of <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> strain PA14 transposon insertion mutants.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>103</volume><fpage>2833</fpage><lpage>2838</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16477005</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Kulasekara1"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kulasekara</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name><name><surname>Ventre</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Kulasekara</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lazdunski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Filloux</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>A novel two-component system controls the expression of <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> fimbrial <italic>cup</italic> genes.</article-title><source>Mol Microbiol</source><volume>55</volume><fpage>368</fpage><lpage>380</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15659157</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Hsu1"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Characterization of the histidine-containing phosphotransfer protein B-mediated multistep phosphorelay system in <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> PAO1.</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>283</volume><fpage>9933</fpage><lpage>9944</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18256026</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Hammer1"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hammer</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><name><surname>Bassler</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Distinct sensory pathways in <italic>Vibrio cholerae</italic> El Tor and classical biotypes modulate cyclic dimeric GMP levels to control biofilm formation.</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><volume>191</volume><fpage>169</fpage><lpage>177</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18952786</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Ueda2"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ueda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Potassium and sodium transporters of <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> regulate virulence to barley.</article-title><source>Appl Microbiol Biotechnol</source><volume>79</volume><fpage>843</fpage><lpage>858</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18481058</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Shanks1"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shanks</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Caiazza</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hinsa</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Toutain</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Toole</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title><italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>-based molecular tool kit for manipulation of genes from gram-negative bacteria.</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><volume>72</volume><fpage>5027</fpage><lpage>5036</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16820502</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Pratt1"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pratt</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolter</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Genetic analysis of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> biofilm formation: roles of flagella, motility, chemotaxis and type I pili.</article-title><source>Mol Microbiol</source><volume>30</volume><fpage>285</fpage><lpage>293</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9791174</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Sperandio1"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sperandio</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Torres</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaper</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Quorum sensing <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> regulators B and C (QseBC): a novel two-component regulatory system involved in the regulation of flagella and motility by quorum sensing in <italic>E. coli</italic>.</article-title><source>Mol Microbiol</source><volume>43</volume><fpage>809</fpage><lpage>821</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11929534</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Overhage1"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Overhage</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bains</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Brazas</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Hancock</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Swarming of <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> is a complex adaptation leading to increased production of virulence factors and antibiotic resistance.</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><volume>190</volume><fpage>2671</fpage><lpage>2679</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18245294</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Wilhelm1"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilhelm</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gdynia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tielen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenau</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaeger</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>The autotransporter esterase EstA of <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> is required for rhamnolipid production, cell motility, and biofilm formation.</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><volume>189</volume><fpage>6695</fpage><lpage>6703</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17631636</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Ren1"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bedzyk</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Gene expression in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> biofilms.</article-title><source>Appl Microbiol Biotechnol</source><volume>64</volume><fpage>515</fpage><lpage>524</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14727089</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-GonzlezBarrios1"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez Barrios</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Zuo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hashimoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bentley</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Autoinducer 2 controls biofilm formation in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> through a novel motility quorum-sensing regulator (MqsR, B3022).</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><volume>188</volume><fpage>305</fpage><lpage>316</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16352847</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Ren2"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bedzyk</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Differential gene expression shows natural brominated furanones interfere with the autoinducer-2 bacterial signaling system of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>.</article-title><source>Biotechnol Bioeng</source><volume>88</volume><fpage>630</fpage><lpage>642</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15470704</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Ramsey1"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramsey</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Whiteley</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title><italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> attachment and biofilm development in dynamic environments.</article-title><source>Mol Microbiol</source><volume>53</volume><fpage>1075</fpage><lpage>1087</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15306012</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Amikam1"><label>60</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Amikam</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Steinberger</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Shkolnik</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ben-Ishai</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><year>1995</year><article-title>The novel cyclic dinucleotide 3&#x02032;&#x02013;5&#x02032; cyclic diguanylic acid binds to p21<sup>ras</sup> and enhances DNA synthesis but not cell replication in the Molt 4 cell line.</article-title><source>Biochem J</source><volume>311 (Pt 3)</volume><fpage>921</fpage><lpage>927</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7487952</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Sambrook1"><label>61</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sambrook</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fritsch</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><name><surname>Maniatis</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year>1989</year><source>Molecular Cloning: A Laboratory Manual</source><publisher-loc>Cold Spring Harbor, NY</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-MendezOrtiz1"><label>62</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mendez-Ortiz</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hyodo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayakawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Membrillo-Hernandez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Genome-wide transcriptional profile of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> in response to high levels of the second messenger 3&#x02032;,5&#x02032;-cyclic diguanylic acid.</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>281</volume><fpage>8090</fpage><lpage>8099</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16418169</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Hausmann1"><label>63</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hausmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shuman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Defining the active site of <italic>Schizosaccharomyces pombe</italic> C-terminal domain phosphatase Fcp1.</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>278</volume><fpage>13627</fpage><lpage>13632</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12556522</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Liu1"><label>64</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Burns</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Beacham</surname><given-names>IR</given-names></name></person-group><year>1986</year><article-title>Isolation and sequence analysis of the gene (<italic>cpdB</italic>) encoding periplasmic 2&#x02032;,3&#x02032;-cyclic phosphodiesterase.</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><volume>165</volume><fpage>1002</fpage><lpage>1010</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3005231</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Iuchi1"><label>65</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iuchi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiner</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year>1996</year><article-title>Cellular and molecular physiology of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> in the adaptation to aerobic environments.</article-title><source>J Biochem</source><volume>120</volume><fpage>1055</fpage><lpage>1063</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9010748</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Chen1"><label>66</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Reilly</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name><name><surname>Smithgall</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Engen</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Tyrosine phosphorylation in the SH3 domain disrupts negative regulatory interactions within the c-Abl kinase core.</article-title><source>J Mol Biol</source><volume>383</volume><fpage>414</fpage><lpage>423</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18775435</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Ditta1"><label>67</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ditta</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Stanfield</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Corbin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Helinski</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group><year>1980</year><article-title>Broad host range DNA cloning system for gram-negative bacteria: construction of a gene bank of <italic>Rhizobium meliloti</italic>.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>77</volume><fpage>7347</fpage><lpage>7351</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7012838</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Figurski1"><label>68</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Figurski</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Helinski</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group><year>1979</year><article-title>Replication of an origin-containing derivative of plasmid RK2 dependent on a plasmid function provided in <italic>trans</italic>.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>76</volume><fpage>1648</fpage><lpage>1652</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">377280</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Wood1"><label>69</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><name><surname>Peretti</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name></person-group><year>1991</year><article-title>Effect of chemically-induced, cloned-gene expression on protein synthesis in <italic>E. coli</italic>.</article-title><source>Biotechnol Bioeng</source><volume>38</volume><fpage>397</fpage><lpage>412</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18600776</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Park1"><label>70</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Heo</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x000e9;ziel</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Conserved virulence factors of <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> are required for killing <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic>.</article-title><source>J Microbiol</source><volume>43</volume><fpage>443</fpage><lpage>450</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16273037</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Simon1"><label>71</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Priefer</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>P&#x000fc;hler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year>1983</year><article-title>A broad host range mobilization system for <italic>in vivo</italic> genetic engineering: Transposon mutagenesis in gram negative bacteria.</article-title><source>Bio/technology</source><fpage>784</fpage><lpage>791</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Kitagawa1"><label>72</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kitagawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Arifuzzaman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ioka-Nakamichi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Inamoto</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Complete set of ORF clones of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> ASKA library (<italic>a</italic> complete <italic>s</italic>et of E. coli <italic>K</italic>-12 ORF <italic>a</italic>rchive): unique resources for biological research.</article-title><source>DNA Res</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>291</fpage><lpage>299</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16769691</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000483-Pesci1"><label>73</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pesci</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Seed</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Iglewski</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name></person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>Regulation of <italic>las</italic> and <italic>rhl</italic> quorum sensing in <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>.</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><volume>179</volume><fpage>3127</fpage><lpage>3132</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9150205</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list><fn-group><fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p>This work was supported by grants from the National Institutes of Health (R01 EB003872) and the Army Research Office (W911NF-06-1-0408) to TKW, and by the Japan Society for the Promotion of Science as a postdoctoral fellowship to AU. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>