<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25111598</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4128642</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-17422</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0102087</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Agriculture</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Biophysics</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Biotechnology</subject><subj-group><subject>Applied Microbiology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Plant Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Plant Physiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Drought Adaptation</subject><subject>Solute Transport</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Exploring Three PIPs and Three TIPs of Grapevine for Transport of Water and Atypical Substrates through Heterologous Expression in <italic>aqy-null</italic> Yeast</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Cloning and Characterization of PIPs and TIPs Grapevine Aquaporins</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sabir</surname><given-names>Farzana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Leandro</surname><given-names>Maria Jos&#x000e9;</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>Ana Paula</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Loureiro-Dias</surname><given-names>Maria C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Moura</surname><given-names>Teresa F.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Soveral</surname><given-names>Gra&#x000e7;a</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Prista</surname><given-names>Catarina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Centre for Botany Applied to Agriculture (CBAA), Instituto Superior de Agronomia, University of Lisbon, Lisbon, Portugal</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Instituto de Investiga&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o do Medicamento (iMed.ULisboa), Faculdade de Farm&#x000e1;cia, Universidade de Lisboa, Lisboa, Portugal</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Dept. de Bioqu&#x000ed;mica e Biologia Humana, Faculdade de Farm&#x000e1;cia, Universidade de Lisboa, Lisboa, Portugal</addr-line></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Zilberstein</surname><given-names>Dan</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Technion-Israel Institute of Technology Haifa 32000 Israel, Israel</addr-line></aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>cprista@isa.ulisboa.pt</email></corresp><fn fn-type="conflict"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: FS MJL MCD TFM GS CP. Performed the experiments: FS MJL APM CP. Analyzed the data: FS APM MCD TFM GS CP. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: MCD GS. Contributed to the writing of the manuscript: FS MJL APM MCD TFM GS CP.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>11</day><month>8</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue>8</issue><elocation-id>e102087</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>4</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>6</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Sabir et al</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Aquaporins are membrane channels that facilitate the transport of water and other small molecules across the cellular membranes. We examined the role of six aquaporins of <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> (cv. Touriga nacional) in the transport of water and atypical substrates (other than water) in an <italic>aqy-null</italic> strain of <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>. Their functional characterization for water transport was performed by stopped-flow fluorescence spectroscopy. The evaluation of permeability coefficients (<italic>P<sub>f</sub></italic>) and activation energies (<italic>Ea</italic>) revealed that three aquaporins (<italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;1, <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP1;1 and <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP2;2) are functional for water transport, while the other three (<italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP1;4, <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;3 and <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP4;1) are non-functional. TIPs (<italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP1;1 and <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP2;2) exhibited higher water permeability than <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;1. All functional aquaporins were found to be sensitive to HgCl<sub>2</sub>, since their water conductivity was reduced (24&#x02013;38%) by the addition of 0.5 mM HgCl<sub>2</sub>. Expression of <italic>Vitis</italic> aquaporins caused different sensitive phenotypes to yeast strains when grown under hyperosmotic stress generated by KCl or sorbitol. Our results also indicate that <italic>Vitis</italic> aquaporins are putative transporters of other small molecules of physiological importance. Their sequence analyses revealed the presence of signature sequences for transport of ammonia, boron, CO<sub>2</sub>, H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and urea. The phenotypic growth variations of yeast cells showed that heterologous expression of <italic>Vitis</italic> aquaporins increased susceptibility to externally applied boron and H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, suggesting the contribution of <italic>Vitis</italic> aquaporins in the transport of these species.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work is supported by Funda&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o para a Ci&#x000ea;ncia e Tecnologia (FCT), Portugal (Post-Doctral grants-SFRH/BPD/89427/2012 to F. S. and SFRH/BPD/41812/2007 to M. J. L., Ci&#x000ea;ncia 2007 to C. P. and project grant PTDC/AGR/AAM/099154/2008). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="13"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>The authors confirm that all data underlying the findings are fully available without restriction. All gene sequences are available from GeneBank VvTnPIP1;4 accession&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;KJ697714, VvTnPIP2;1 accession&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;KJ697715, VvTnPIP2;3 accession&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;KJ697716, VvTnTIP1;1 accession&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;KJ697717, VvTnTIP2;2 accession&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;KJ697718, VvTnTIP4;1 accession&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;KJ697719.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><title>Data Availability</title><p>The authors confirm that all data underlying the findings are fully available without restriction. All gene sequences are available from GeneBank VvTnPIP1;4 accession&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;KJ697714, VvTnPIP2;1 accession&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;KJ697715, VvTnPIP2;3 accession&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;KJ697716, VvTnTIP1;1 accession&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;KJ697717, VvTnTIP2;2 accession&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;KJ697718, VvTnTIP4;1 accession&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;KJ697719.</p></notes></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Aquaporins play a crucial role in maintaining water and ion homeostasis of plants, essential for plant cell integrity, growth and survival in their ever-changing environment. These water channels can provide rapid and reversible changes to cells hydraulic conductance by modulating membrane water permeability <xref rid="pone.0102087-Vandeleur1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>. Aquaporins belong to Major Intrinsic Proteins (MIPs) family and based on their sequence similarity and sub-cellular localization, plant aquaporins are divided in seven subfamilies: the plasma membrane intrinsic proteins (PIPs), the tonoplast intrinsic proteins (TIPs), the nodulin-26-like intrinsic proteins (NIPs), the small intrinsic proteins (SIPs), the GlpF-like intrinsic proteins (GIPs), the hybrid intrinsic proteins (HIPs) and the uncategorized X intrinsic proteins (XIPs) <xref rid="pone.0102087-Danielson1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>. Studies on plant aquaporins revealed their role far beyond the membrane water transport. Besides water, they are reported to transport also other small molecules and/or gases of physiological importance (reviewed by <xref rid="pone.0102087-Maurel1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>), suggesting their versatile functions in plants. Putative substrate specificities of aquaporins are generally assigned by the presence of specific amino acid residues at well-defined positions in the sequences <xref rid="pone.0102087-Hove1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>.</p><p>Since aquaporins establish a tight association between water transport and plant development and adaptation under stress conditions, a rigorous regulation of aquaporin activity is essential to fine-tune the overall hydraulic conductivity in plants <xref rid="pone.0102087-Maurel2" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. Expression of aquaporin genes can be altered under various environmental conditions as well as according to cell/tissue type and plant developmental stages <xref rid="pone.0102087-Chaumont1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. Besides these initial regulatory steps of gene expression, the activity of translated and targeted aquaporin proteins can be further regulated by various post-translational modifications such as methylation, glycosylation, phosphorylation, membrane trafficking, heteromerization, and their gating can also be regulated by pH, divalent ions and membrane tension <xref rid="pone.0102087-Soveral1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. Various stress conditions like anoxia, salt and water stress have also been reported to affect the activity of aquaporins in plants (reviewed by <xref rid="pone.0102087-Maurel1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0102087-Chaumont1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>).</p><p><italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> cv. Touriga nacional is an important Portuguese cultivar. This variety is a key ingredient in both dry red and fortified wines (particularly, Port wine). Grapevines are known to be extremely stress-tolerant plants, especially for dry environment <xref rid="pone.0102087-Baiges1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>. In fact, deficit irrigation techniques are commonly used to achieve high fruit quality <xref rid="pone.0102087-Flexas1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>. Since the water status of the plant greatly influences the fruit quality and hence the characteristics of wine <xref rid="pone.0102087-Hayes1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, it is significant to study the molecular cell entry point of water, i.e. aquaporins in these plants. Release of full genomic sequence of grapevine revealed the occurrence of 28 genes encoding putative aquaporins in <italic>V. vinifera</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0102087-Jaillon1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. Comprehensive phylogenetic analyses of the deduced amino acid sequences suggest that the <italic>V. vinifera</italic> (cv. Cabernet Sauvignon and cv. Pinot Noir) aquaporins can be distributed in the four main subfamilies: PIPs (8 genes), TIPs (10 genes), NIPs (8 genes) and SIPs (2 genes) <xref rid="pone.0102087-Shelden1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. Despite being a very important economical plant, only few reports are available on <italic>Vitis</italic> aquaporins, explaining their quantitative expression in various rootstocks <xref rid="pone.0102087-Gambetta1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, during water stress <xref rid="pone.0102087-Galms1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0102087-Pou1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref> and their cloning and expression <italic>in planta</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0102087-Baiges1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0102087-Fouquet1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref> or in heterologous systems, such as <italic>Xenopus</italic> oocytes <xref rid="pone.0102087-Vandeleur1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0102087-Shelden1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref> and <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0102087-Leito1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0102087-Noronha1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>. Although from a molecular point of view the presence of aquaporins can be easily recognized in a genome, their physiological role <italic>in planta</italic> is still difficult to understand. At transcript level, plant aquaporins respond variedly to stress, depending on the plant tissue/organ, cultivars/species and types/degree of stress <xref rid="pone.0102087-Vandeleur1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, impairing the interpretation of the role of an individual aquaporin. To study the physiological role of each aquaporin, we used <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> as a simple and well-characterized heterologous expression system <xref rid="pone.0102087-Pettersson1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>. The evaluation of water transport activity in intact yeast cells through stopped-flow fluorescence spectroscopy is already well-established <xref rid="pone.0102087-Leito1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0102087-Soveral2" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>.</p><p>The present work is focused on the cloning and expression of putative aquaporins (three PIPs and three TIPs) of <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> (cv. Touriga nacional) in an <italic>aqy-null</italic> strain of <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>. Their functional characterization for water transport was performed through stopped-flow spectroscopy. Further, tolerance/sensitivity of these aquaporins expressing strains was tested under hyperosmotic stress exerted by KCl or sorbitol. This study also includes the analysis of signature sequences for transport of atypical substrates and growth assays of yeast strains expressing <italic>Vitis</italic> aquaporins in the presence of these substrates, to explore their putative route of transport.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Yeast strain, plasmid and growth conditions</title><p><italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> 10560-6B <italic>MAT&#x003b1; leu2::hisG trp1::hisG his3::hisG ura3-52 aqy1::KanMX4 aqy2::HIS3</italic> (from now on designated as <italic>aqy-null</italic>) was used as host strain for heterologous expression of putative aquaporins from <italic>V. vinifera</italic> cv. Touriga nacional. The centromeric plasmid pUG35 was used for cloning, conferring C-terminal GFP tagging, MET25 promoter and CYC1-T terminator <xref rid="pone.0102087-Gldener1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. For propagation of these plasmids, <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> DH5&#x003b1; strain was used as host <xref rid="pone.0102087-Hanahan1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. <italic>E. coli</italic> transformants were grown in Luria-Bertani (LB) medium supplemented with ampicillin (100 &#x000b5;g ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), at 37&#x000b0;C. The host <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> strain (<italic>aqy-null</italic>) was maintained in YPD medium (5 g l<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> yeast extract, 10 g l<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> peptone, 20 g l<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> glucose and 20 g l<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> agar). Transformed yeast strains were grown and maintained in YNB medium without amino acids (DIFCO) with 2% (w/v) glucose supplemented with the adequate requirements for prototrophic growth <xref rid="pone.0102087-Pronk1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Cloning and heterologous expression of <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> aquaporins in <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic></title><p>To clone the putative aquaporins from <italic>V. vinifera</italic> cv. Touriga nacional, their cDNA (kindly provided by Dr. Lu&#x000ed;sa Carvalho, ISA-ULisboa) amplification, cloning and expression in <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> were performed according to previously described methods <xref rid="pone.0102087-Leito1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>. Primers used in this study are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0102087.s009">Table S1</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Sequence analysis</title><p>Nucleotide sequences identified in the present study are submitted to National Center for Biotechnological Information (NCBI) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov</ext-link>). These sequences were translated by ExPASy translate tool (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://web.expasy.org/translate/">http://web.expasy.org/translate/</ext-link>). Deduced amino acid sequences were analysed and compared with database sequences of <italic>V. Vinifera</italic> cv. Pinot noir, available at Grape Genome Browser (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genoscope.cns.fr/externe/Genome">http://www.genoscope.cns.fr/externe/Genome</ext-link> Browser/Vitis/) and NCBI. Multiple protein sequence alignments were generated by using the ClustalX <xref rid="pone.0102087-Thompson1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref> and BioEdit <xref rid="pone.0102087-Hall1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref> programs. Phylogenetic tree was constructed from the alignment of deduced amino acid sequences obtained from the present study and our previous study <xref rid="pone.0102087-Leito1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref> with twenty-eight amino acid sequences of aquaporins of <italic>V. vinifera</italic> cv. Pinot noir, by MEGA5.1 software using neighbor-joining method <xref rid="pone.0102087-Tamura1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>. Topology and hydrophobicity of deduced amino acid sequences were predicted by using various ExPASy tools e.g. TMHMM <xref rid="pone.0102087-Krogh1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>, HMMTOP <xref rid="pone.0102087-Tusnady1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref> and TMPred <xref rid="pone.0102087-Hofmann1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>.</p><p>All gene sequences are available from at GeneBank VvTnPIP1;4 accession&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;KJ697714, VvTnPIP2;1 accession&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;KJ697715, VvTnPIP2;3 accession&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;KJ697716, VvTnTIP1;1 accession&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;KJ697717, VvTnTIP2;2 accession&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;KJ697718, VvTnTIP4;1 accession&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;KJ697719.</p><p>To search the signature sequences for transport of atypical substrates, obtained amino acid sequences were grouped with reference sequences as per their reported substrates for transport, described by <xref rid="pone.0102087-Hove1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref> and were aligned using ClustalX. Conserved amino acid residues at NPA, ar/R constriction and P1&#x02013;P5 regions were determined from the alignment and matched with reference sequences of transporters of various substrates. Based on the conserved residues at these positions, selectivity profiles of cloned aquaporins were predicted.</p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>Water transport assays of <italic>Vitis</italic> aquaporins expressed in <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic></title><p>Functional analyses of heterologously expressed <italic>Vitis</italic> aquaporins for water conductivity were performed by stopped-flow fluorescence spectroscopy as previously described <xref rid="pone.0102087-Leito1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>. Briefly, yeast strains grown in liquid YNB medium were harvested at mid exponential phase (OD<sub>640 nm</sub>&#x02248;1.0) (Ultrospec 2100 pro, Amersham Biosciences) and incubated for 1 hour at 28&#x000b0;C in YPD medium (6 g l<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> wet weight). Further, cells were washed and re-suspended in ice-cold 1.4 M sorbitol (3 ml g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> wet weight) and incubated on ice for at least 90 minutes. Cells were pre-loaded with the membrane permeable nonfluorescent precursor 5-(and-6)-carboxyfluorescein diacetate (CFDA), which is intracellularly hydrolyzed releasing the membrane impermeable fluorescent form. For water transport assays, hyperosmotic shocks were applied on stopped-flow apparatus (HI-TECH Scientific PQ/SF-53). Cells equilibrated with 1.4 M sorbitol were mixed with an equal volume of 2.1 M sorbitol. The resulting cell shrinkage caused a quenching of the fluorescence intensity. Signals were fitted to a single exponential, from which the rate constant (<italic>k</italic>) was calculated. Permeability coefficient (<italic>P<sub>f</sub></italic>) and activation energy (<italic>Ea</italic>) were estimated as described by <xref rid="pone.0102087-Leito1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0102087-Soveral2" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>.</p><p>Inhibition of water transport in <italic>Vitis</italic> aquaporins expressing yeast strains was tested with mercury chloride (HgCl<sub>2</sub>), a well-known inhibitor of aquaporins. Yeast strains expressing functional <italic>Vitis</italic> aquaporins were incubated with HgCl<sub>2</sub> (0.5 and 1 mM, in 50 mM potassium citrate buffer, pH 5.0) for 15 and 30 minutes before the osmotic shock at 23&#x000b0;C. The yeast strain with the empty plasmid was treated in the same way and considered as control. Osmotic shocks were applied without and after incubation with HgCl<sub>2</sub> and the signals obtained were compared and used to calculate the <italic>P<sub>f</sub></italic> in both conditions.</p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title>Growth assays under osmotic stress and sensitivity tests on atypical substrates</title><p><italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> strains harboring <italic>Vitis</italic> aquaporins were tested for their ability to grow under osmotic stress. Moreover, possibility to transport atypical substrates, such as ammonia, boron, hydrogen peroxide (H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>) and urea was also investigated. Growth assays were performed on solid YNB medium (pH 5.0) supplemented with 2% (w/v) glucose. NaCl (0.5, 1.0 and 1.5 M), KCl (0.5, 1.0 and 1.5 M) and osmoequivalent concentration of sorbitol (0.84, 1.4 and 2.1 M) were added to growth media for osmotic stress experiments. Hydrogen peroxide (0.5, 0.75, 1.0, 1.5 and 2.0 mM) and boron (as boric acid, 20, 40, 50 and 60 mM), were used as atypical substrates for transport. Media with H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> was freshly prepared at the time of inoculation. Moreover, in order to test the putative transport of ammonia (1.0, 2.0 and 3.0 mM) and urea (1.0, 2.0, 2.5 and 3.5 mM), either of them was used as sole nitrogen source. Yeast strains were initially grown in liquid YNB medium supplemented with 2% (w/v) glucose, with orbital shaking (180 rpm) at 28&#x000b0;C, up to OD<sub>640 nm</sub>&#x02248;1.0 corresponding to 1&#x000d7;10<sup>7</sup> cells/ml. Cells were centrifuged and washed in sterile distilled water and re-suspended to OD<sub>640 nm</sub>&#x02248;10. Multi-well plates were prepared with serial 10-fold dilutions of the original concentrated culture, 3 &#x000b5;l suspensions was spotted with replica platter for 96-well plates device on plates containing YNB solid medium with ammonia, boric acid, H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and urea, separately and incubated at 28&#x000b0;C. Strain with the empty plasmid (pUG35) was considered as control. Differences in growth phenotypes of yeast strains were recorded after 1 and 2 weeks of incubation.</p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title>Microscopy</title><p>For the localization of GFP-tagged proteins in <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>, mid-exponential phase cells were observed under Leitz Wetzlar Germany 513558 epifluorescence microscope equipped with a Leitz Wetzlar Germany Type 307-148002 514687 mercury bulb and BP 340&#x02013;380; BP 450&#x02013;490 (for GFP visualizing); BP 515&#x02013;560 filter sets. Images were obtained with a digital camera Axiocam Zeiss using AxioVision Rel. 4.8.2 Software.</p></sec><sec id="s2g"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>All the data were collected from at least three independent experiments. For stopped-flow experiments, usually five runs at each temperature and ten runs for <italic>P<sub>f</sub></italic> at 23&#x000b0;C were stored and analyzed in each experiment. Student's t test was used for statistical analysis. P&#x0003c;0.05 (marked as *) was considered to be statistically significant. Data are presented as mean &#x000b1; standard deviation (SD).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec id="s3a"><title>Cloning and heterologous expression of <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> aquaporins in <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic></title><p>Specific primers designed from the sequences of aquaporins of <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> (cv. Pinot Noir) were able to amplify six full-length cDNAs of putative aquaporins from <italic>V. vinifera</italic> (cv. Touriga nacional). The predicted amino acid sequences were aligned and compared with the Pinot noir variety (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0102087.s001">Figure S1</xref>), all of them shared high identity (&#x0003e;96%) in both varieties. As expected, the six amino acids sequences corresponding to the cDNAs cloned from <italic>V. vinifera</italic> cv. Touriga nacional in this study were clearly identified in the genome of Pinot noir variety and three of them were clustered in their subsequent groups of PIPs, while other three in TIPs subfamilies (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0102087-g001">Figure 1</xref>). Based on BLASTN (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Blast.cgi">http://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Blast.cgi</ext-link>) alignment, sequences were classified as <italic>PIP1;4</italic> (858 bp), <italic>PIP2;1</italic> (852 bp), <italic>PIP2;3</italic> (861 bp) and <italic>TIP1;1</italic> (753 bp), <italic>TIP2;2</italic> (750 bp), <italic>TIP4;1</italic> (759 bp) and their encoded proteins were named as <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP1;4 (286 aa), <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;1 (284 aa), <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;3 (287 aa) and <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP1;1 (251 aa), <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP2;2 (250 aa), <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP4;1 (253 aa) following the nomenclature proposed for plant aquaporins <xref rid="pone.0102087-Johanson1" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>. <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP1;4 has 96.5% identity with nine substitution of amino acids (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0102087.s001">Figure S1A</xref>), while <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;1 is 98.6% identical with difference at four positions (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0102087.s001">Figure S1B</xref>). <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP2;2 shares 99.2% identity of amino acids with substitution at two positions (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0102087.s001">Figure S1C</xref>), similarly <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP1;1 has 99.6% identity with substitution at only one amino acid position (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0102087.s001">Figure S1D</xref>). On the other hand, <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;3 and <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP4;1 were 100% identical to their respective proteins of the other variety (Figures S1E and S1F, respectively).</p><fig id="pone-0102087-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0102087.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Phylogenetic tree based on protein sequences of aquaporins from <italic>V. vinifera</italic> cv. Pinot noir and cv. Touriga nacional.</title><p>Dendrogram depicting the phylogenetic relationship between the aquaporins of Touriga nacional variety cloned in this study (framed in rectangular shape), previous study (oval shape frame) <xref rid="pone.0102087-Leito1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref> with the aquaporins of Pinot noir variety. Dendogram was generated by neighbor-joining method (applied to 1000 bootstrap data sets) using the MEGA5.1 program <xref rid="pone.0102087-Tamura1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>. Accession numbers of presented protein sequences are: <italic>Vv</italic>PnPIP1;1 (CAO41326, GSVIVT00029248001), <italic>Vv</italic>PnPIP1;3 (CAO62835, GSVIVT00000433001), <italic>Vv</italic>PnPIP1;4 (CAO39626, GSVIVT00026881001), <italic>Vv</italic>PnPIP1;5 (CAO39627, GSVIVT00026882001), <italic>Vv</italic>PnPIP2;1 (CAN75442), <italic>Vv</italic>PnPIP2;2 (CAO47394, GSVIVT00036133001), <italic>Vv</italic>PnPIP2;3 (CAO18152, GSVIVT00023192001), <italic>Vv</italic>PnPIP2;4 (CAO21844, GSVIVT00024536001), <italic>Vv</italic>PnTIP1;1 (CAO69259, GSVIVT00018548001), <italic>Vv</italic>PnTIP1;2 (CAO63006, GSVIVT00000605001), <italic>Vv</italic>PnTIP1;3 (CAO16745, GSVIVT00022146001), <italic>Vv</italic>PnTIP1;4 (CAO21720, GSVIVT00024394001), <italic>Vv</italic>PnTIP2;1 (CAO45860, GSVIVT00034350001), <italic>Vv</italic>PnTIP2;2 (CAO23095, GSVIVT00012703001), <italic>Vv</italic>PnTIP3;1 (CAO62035, GSVIVT00013854001), <italic>Vv</italic>PnTIP4;1 (CAO44039, GSVIVT00032441001), <italic>Vv</italic>PnTIP5;1 (CAO42713, GSVIVT00029946001), <italic>Vv</italic>PnTIP5;2 (CAO70596, GSVIVT00019170001), <italic>Vv</italic>PnNIP1;1 (CAO48005, GSVIVT00035815001), <italic>Vv</italic>PnNIP2;1 (CAO15462, GSVIVT00011149001), <italic>Vv</italic>PnNIP3;1 (CAO17108, GSVIVT00022377001), <italic>Vv</italic>PnNIP4;1 (CAO70192, GSVIVT00007127001), <italic>Vv</italic>PnNIP4;2 (CAO43338, GSVIVT00003903001), <italic>Vv</italic>PnNIP5;1 (CAO62847, GSVIVT00000446001), <italic>Vv</italic>PnNIP6;1 (CAO45476, GSVIVT00033750001), <italic>Vv</italic>PnNIP7;1 (CAO71103, GSVIVT00019910001), <italic>Vv</italic>PnSIP1;1 (CAO23510, GSVIVT00025504001) and <italic>Vv</italic>PnSIP2;1 (CAO18284, GSVIVT00023346001) (for Pinot noir cultivar sequences) and <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP1;1 (HQ913643), <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP1;4 (KJ697714), <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;1 (KJ697715), <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;2 (HQ913642), <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;3 (KJ697716), <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP1;1 (KJ697717), <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP2;1 (HQ913640), <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP2;2 (KJ697718) and <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP4;1 (KJ697719) (for Touriga nacional cultivar sequences).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0102087.g001"/></fig><p>Expression and localization of these cloned proteins in selected yeast transformants were verified by GFP tagging under fluorescent microscopy. Most of the GFP-tagged aquaporins were localized in the plasma membrane of <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0102087-g002">Figure 2</xref>). Besides plasma membrane, some of the GFP-tagged proteins were also observed retained inside the cell, probably in the endoplasmic reticulum or vesicles of the secretory pathway.</p><fig id="pone-0102087-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0102087.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Localization of GFP-tagged aquaporins from <italic>V. Vinifera</italic> expressed in <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> strains.</title><p>Cytosolic GFP localization in (A) control cells (transformed with empty plasmid pUG35) and in the membrane of cells expressing (B) <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP1;4, (C) <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;1, (D) <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;3, (E) <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP1;1, (F) <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP2;2, (G) <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP4;1. Images were taken under phase contrast (upper panel) and fluorescence (lower panel) microscopy.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0102087.g002"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3b"><title>Topology prediction and analysis of conserved sequences of <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> aquaporins</title><p>The hypothetical transmembrane topology of deduced amino acid sequences revealed that, as expected, all cloned aquaporins exhibit typical features common to orthodox plant aquaporins (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0102087-g003">Figure 3</xref>): (i) six transmembrane-spanning hydrophobic &#x003b1;-helices (TMH1&#x02013;TMH6) connected with five alternating extracellular and intracellular loops (LA-LE), (ii) intracellular facing amino and carboxyl terminals, (iii) two highly conserved NPA (Asn-Pro-Ala) motifs on LB and LE loops important for configuration of aqueous pore in aquaporins <xref rid="pone.0102087-Forrest1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>, and (iv) a Serine residue near the second NPA motif (GXXXNPAR(S/D)XG), specific for water transport <xref rid="pone.0102087-Froger1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0102087-Heymann1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>.</p><fig id="pone-0102087-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0102087.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Schematic representation of predicted topology of <italic>V. vinifera</italic> aquaporins (PIP1s, PIP2s and TIPs) obtained in this study.</title><p>These aquaporins consist of six transmembrane domains (TMH1&#x02013;TMH6), five connecting loops (LA&#x02013;LE) and N- and C-terminal extremities. The conserved NPA motifs (filter 1) are shown in yellow circles, while residues for ar/R constriction (filter 2) and P1&#x02013;P5 positions for selectivity of atypical substrates (according to <xref rid="pone.0102087-Hove1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>) are shown in purple and blue ovals, respectively. Putative phosphorylation sites are marked as red stars, pH regulation sites are shown as pink rounds, green and yellow rectangles represent methylation and sorting signals. (A) PIP1s subfamily consisting of longer N-terminal with methylation and sorting signals, two putative phosphorylation sites in loop B and D, conserved His in loop D for pH regulation site and shorter C-terminal. (B) PIP2s subfamily having slightly shorter N-terminal with methylation and sorting signals conserved His in loop D for pH regulation, four Ser for putative phosphorylation: one in loop B, two in loop D and two in long C-terminal. (C) TIPs with very short N-terminal without sorting or methylation signals, only one conserved Thr residue instead of Ser residue for putative phosphorylation in loop B, Cys residue (red rectangle) in TMH4 for mercury sensitivity and His residue in loop D for pH regulation.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0102087.g003"/></fig><p>Besides the general characteristics of aquaporins, special features attributed to the PIP aquaporin family and subfamilies (PIP1s and PIP2s) of <italic>Vitis</italic> aquaporins were found, such as: (i) longer N-terminal in <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP1;4 (PIP1 subfamily) than <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;1 and <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;3 (PIP2 subfamily) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0102087-g003">Figures 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0102087.s002">S2A</xref>), (ii) longer C-terminal in <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;1 and <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;3 than <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP1;4 <xref rid="pone.0102087-Shelden1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0102087-Johansson1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0102087-g003">Figures 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0102087.s002">S2B</xref>), (iii) methylation site (K3/4 and E6) <xref rid="pone.0102087-Santoni1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref> and diacidic motif (D/E-I/X-E/D) <xref rid="pone.0102087-Zelazny1" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref> at N-terminal (<italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP1;4, <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;1 and <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;3) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0102087-g003">Figures 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0102087.s003">S3A</xref>), (iv) His residue for pH sensitivity in loop D (<italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP1;4-H<sup>206</sup>, <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;1-H<sup>196</sup>, <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;3-H<sup>199</sup>) <xref rid="pone.0102087-TournaireRoux1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0102087-g003">Figures 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0102087.s004">S4B</xref>), (v) multiple conserved Ser residues for phosphorylation in loop B, loop D and C-terminal positions, such as 1) in loop B (<italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP1;4-S<sup>128</sup>, <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;1-S<sup>118</sup> and <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;3-S<sup>121</sup>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0102087-g003">Figures 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0102087.s004">S4A</xref>), 2) in loop D two positions of conserved Ser in consensus sequence N/SARDSHVP, in which the first Ser is present only in <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;1 (S<sup>191</sup>) <xref rid="pone.0102087-Nyblom1" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>, while second Ser is present in all cloned PIPs (<italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP1;4-S<sup>205</sup>, <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;1-S<sup>195</sup> and <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;3-S<sup>198</sup>) <xref rid="pone.0102087-VanWilder1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0102087-g003">Figures 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0102087.s004">S4B</xref>), 3) at C-terminal, consensus phosphorylation site (Lys-x-x-x-Ser-x-Arg) is conserved only in PIP2 subfamily members (<italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;1-S<sup>277</sup> and S<sup>280</sup>, <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;3-S<sup>280</sup> and S<sup>283</sup>) <xref rid="pone.0102087-Prak1" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0102087-Johansson2" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0102087-g003">Figures 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0102087.s004">S4C</xref>).</p><p>Distinct characteristics found in cloned TIPs were: (i) shorter N-terminals than PIPs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0102087-g003">Figures 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0102087.s002">S2A</xref>) (ii) slightly longer C-terminal than PIP1s, but shorter than PIP2s subfamily members (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0102087-g003">Figures 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0102087.s002">S2B</xref>) <xref rid="pone.0102087-Johansson1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref> (iii) Cys residue for mercury sensitive site (<italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP1;1-C<sup>118</sup>, <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP2;2-C<sup>116</sup> and <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP4;1- C<sup>113</sup>) <xref rid="pone.0102087-Daniels1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0102087-g003">Figures 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0102087.s005">S5A</xref>), (iv) His residue for pH sensitive site (<italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP2;2-H<sup>131</sup> and <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP4;1-H<sup>128</sup>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0102087-g003">Figures 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0102087.s005">S5B</xref>) <xref rid="pone.0102087-Leito1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>. (viii) Thr residue for putative phosphorylation site (<italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP1;1-T<sup>99</sup>, <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP2;2-T<sup>97</sup> and <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP4;1-T<sup>94</sup>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0102087-g003">Figures 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0102087.s004">S4A</xref>) <xref rid="pone.0102087-Prak1" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0102087-Kjellbom1" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s3c"><title>Presence of signature sequences for transport of substrates other than water</title><p>Signature sequences for transport of atypical substrates in all cloned aquaporins were explored according to <xref rid="pone.0102087-Hove1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0102087-t001">Table 1</xref>), in particular the ar/R (aromatic/Arginine) constriction (filter 2) that consists of four residues (one in the second and one in the fifth helix (TMH2 and TMH5) and two in the fifth loop (LE1 and LE2 or R)) and P1&#x02013;P5 positions (P1 in the third loop (LC), P2 and P3 in the fifth loop (LE), P4 and P5 in sixth helix (TMH6)) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0102087-g003">Figure 3</xref>). The analysis showed the presence of signature sequences deciphered for boron (filter 2: F/A/G-H/I/S-T/G/A-R and P1&#x02013;P5 residues: Q/F/I-S/T-A-F/Y-W/L) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0102087.s006">Figure S6A</xref>) and CO<sub>2</sub> (filter 2: F-H-T-R and P1&#x02013;P5 residues: Q/M-S-A-F-W) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0102087.s006">Figure S6B</xref>) transport in all cloned PIPs: <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP1;4 (filter 2: F<sup>94</sup>-H<sup>223</sup>-T<sup>232</sup>-R<sup>238</sup> and P1&#x02013;P5: Q<sup>154</sup>-S<sup>239</sup>-A<sup>243</sup>-F<sup>258</sup>-W<sup>259</sup>), <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;1 (filter 2: F<sup>84</sup>-H<sup>213</sup>-T<sup>222</sup>-R<sup>228</sup> and P1&#x02013;P5: Q<sup>144</sup>-S<sup>229</sup>-A<sup>233</sup>-F<sup>248</sup>-W<sup>249</sup>) and <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;3 (filter 2: F<sup>87</sup>-H<sup>216</sup>-T<sup>225</sup>-R<sup>231</sup> and P1&#x02013;P5: Q<sup>147</sup>-S<sup>232</sup>-A<sup>236</sup>-F<sup>251</sup>-W<sup>252</sup>) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0102087-t001">Table 1</xref>). Whereas, sequences for ammonia transport (filter 2: H/W-I/V-G/A-R and P1&#x02013;P5 residues: T/F-S-A-Y-W/L) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0102087.s007">Figure S7</xref>) were found in all the TIPs: <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP1;1 (filter 2: H<sup>65</sup>-I<sup>187</sup>-A<sup>196</sup>-V<sup>202</sup> and P1&#x02013;P5 residues: T<sup>125</sup>-S<sup>203</sup>-A<sup>207</sup>-V<sup>219</sup>-W<sup>220</sup>), <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP2;2 (filter 2: H<sup>63</sup>-I<sup>185</sup>-G<sup>194</sup>-R<sup>20</sup>0 and P1&#x02013;P5 residues: T<sup>123</sup>-S<sup>201</sup>-A<sup>205</sup>-V<sup>217</sup>-W<sup>218</sup> and <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP4;1 (filter 2: H<sup>60</sup>-V<sup>183</sup>-A<sup>192</sup>-R<sup>198</sup> and P1&#x02013;P5 residues: T<sup>120</sup>-S<sup>199</sup>-A<sup>203</sup>-V<sup>215</sup>-W<sup>216</sup>) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0102087-t001">Table 1</xref>). On the other hand, all cloned aquaporins exhibited the signature sequences for H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> transport (filter 2: H/F/W-I/H/V-A/T/G-R/V and P1&#x02013;P5 residues: T/Q/F-S/A-A-Y/F-W/I) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0102087.s008">Figure S8A</xref>) and urea transport (filter 2: F/H/G/A/N-I/H/S/V-T/A/G-R/V and P1&#x02013;P5 residues: M/T/Q/L/F/V/I-S/A/T-A-F/Y-W/F/L) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0102087.s008">Figure S8B</xref>) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0102087-t001">Table 1</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="pone-0102087-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0102087.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Specific amino acid residues for atypical substrates at ar/R constrictions and P1&#x02013;P5 positions (based on <xref rid="pone.0102087-Hove1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>).</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0102087-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0102087.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aquaporins</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative substrates</td><td colspan="4" align="left" rowspan="1">ar/R constrictions (filter 2)</td><td colspan="5" align="left" rowspan="1">P1&#x02013;P5 positions</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TMH2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TMH5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LE1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LE2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P5</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP1;4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Boron, CO<sub>2</sub>, H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, urea</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F<sup>94</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H<sup>223</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T<sup>232</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R<sup>238</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q<sup>154</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S<sup>239</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A<sup>243</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F<sup>258</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">W<sup>259</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Boron, CO<sub>2</sub>, H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, urea</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F<sup>84</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H<sup>213</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T<sup>222</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R<sup>228</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q<sup>144</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S<sup>229</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A<sup>233</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F<sup>248</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">W<sup>249</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Boron, CO<sub>2</sub>, H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, urea</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F<sup>87</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H<sup>216</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T<sup>225</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R<sup>231</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q<sup>147</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S<sup>232</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A<sup>236</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F<sup>251</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">W<sup>252</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP1;1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urea, NH<sub>3</sub>, H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H<sup>65</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I<sup>187</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A<sup>196</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V<sup>202</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T<sup>125</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S<sup>203</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A<sup>207</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V<sup>219</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">W<sup>220</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP2;2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urea, NH<sub>3</sub>, H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H<sup>63</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I<sup>185</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G<sup>194</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R<sup>200</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T<sup>123</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S<sup>201</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A<sup>205</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V<sup>217</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">W<sup>218</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP4;1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urea, NH<sub>3</sub>, H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H<sup>60</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V<sup>183</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A<sup>192</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R<sup>198</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T<sup>120</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S<sup>199</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A<sup>203</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V<sup>215</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">W<sup>216</sup></td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3d"><title>Functional characterization of water transport in yeast strains expressing <italic>V. vinifera</italic> aquaporins</title><p>Water transport activity of heterologously expressed <italic>Vitis</italic> aquaporins in yeast strains was assayed by stopped-flow fluorescence spectroscopy. The shrinking rate of yeast cells upon a sorbitol hyperosmotic shock was monitored as change in fluorescence signals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0102087-g004">Figure 4A</xref>). The strain with empty plasmid (pUG35), devoid of water channels, was used as control (<italic>P<sub>f</sub></italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;4.30&#x000b1;0.28&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup> cm s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>). Water permeability (<italic>P<sub>f</sub></italic>) of yeast cells was not affected by the expression of <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP1;4 (4.0&#x000b1;0.35&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup> cm s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;3 (5.30&#x000b1;0.63&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup> cm s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) and <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP4;1 (3.3&#x000b1;0.08&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup> cm s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0102087-t002">Table 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0102087-g004">Figure 4B</xref>). Thus, these strains were considered as non-functional for water transport. On the other hand, heterologous expression of <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;1 (7.43&#x000b1;0.64&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup> cm s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP1;1 (8.06&#x000b1;0.34&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup> cm s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) and <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP2;2 (9.65&#x000b1;0.026&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup> cm s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0102087-t002">Table 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0102087-g004">Figure 4B</xref>) led to 73%, 88% and 125%, respectively, higher water permeability and were stated as functional for water transport. Among all cloned <italic>Vitis</italic> aquaporins, TIPs (<italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP1;1, <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP2;2) exhibited higher water conductivity as compared to <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;1.</p><fig id="pone-0102087-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0102087.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Stopped-flow assays for measurement of water transport activity of <italic>V. vinifera</italic> aquaporins expressed in yeast.</title><p>(A) Typical traces obtained from stopped-flow spectroscopy after hyperosmotic shock. Presented signals are illustrative of ten traces at 23&#x000b0;C obtained from strains expressing functional (<italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;1) and non-functional (<italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP4;1) aquaporins for water transport, and control (transformed with empty plasmid pUG35). (B) Water permeability coefficients (<italic>P<sub>f</sub></italic> at 23&#x000b0;C) of <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;1, <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP1;1 and <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP2;2 were higher than control strain. Expression of <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP1;4, <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;3 and <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP4;1 did not increase water permeability in yeast cells. Data are mean &#x000b1; SD of three independent experiments with at least ten traces.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0102087.g004"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone-0102087-t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0102087.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Water transport activity in <italic>V. vinifera</italic> aquaporins expressed in <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0102087-t002-2" xlink:href="pone.0102087.t002"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yeast strains expressing <italic>Vitis</italic> aquaporins</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Permeability coefficient (<italic>P<sub>f</sub></italic>) (cm s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Activation energy (<italic>Ea</italic>) (kcal mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pUG35</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.3&#x000b1;0.28</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.05&#x000b1;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP1;4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0&#x000b1;0.35</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.74&#x000b1;0.62</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.43&#x000b1;0.64</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.84&#x000b1;0.83</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.30&#x000b1;0.63</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.53&#x000b1;0.55</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP1;1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.06&#x000b1;0.34</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.79&#x000b1;0.77</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP2;2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.65&#x000b1;0.03</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.77&#x000b1;0.62</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP4;1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.31&#x000b1;0.08</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.86&#x000b1;0.22</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p>Data are mean &#x000b1; SD of three independent experiments with at least ten traces.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>To evaluate the activation energy for water transport, <italic>P<sub>f</sub></italic> values of all yeast strains were analyzed in a range of temperatures (9&#x02013;37&#x000b0;C) and Arrhenius plots were drawn (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0102087-g005">Figure 5A</xref>). As expected, transport of water was strongly dependent on temperature in control yeast strain, as reflected by higher activation energy <italic>Ea</italic> (14.05&#x000b1;0.01 kcal mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0102087-g005">Figure 5B</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0102087-t002">Table 2</xref>). Arrhenius plots for <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP1;4, <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;3 and <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP4;1 expressing yeast strains exhibited parallel steep slopes, overlapped with control strain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0102087-g005">Figure 5A</xref>) and almost similar activation energies (14.74&#x000b1;0.62, 14.53&#x000b1;0.55, 14.86&#x000b1;0.22 kcal mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, respectively) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0102087-g005">Figure 5B</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0102087-t002">Table 2</xref>). On the other hand, expression of <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;1, <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP1;1 and <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP2;2 led to drastic reduction in the activation energies to 10.84&#x000b1;0.83, 8.8&#x000b1;0.77 and 8.77&#x000b1;0.62 kcal mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0102087-g005">Figure 5B</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0102087-t002">Table 2</xref>), demonstrating that transport of water was majorly mediated by aquaporins in these yeast strains.</p><fig id="pone-0102087-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0102087.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Activation energies (<italic>Ea</italic>) of water transport in <italic>V. vinifera</italic> aquaporins expressed in yeast.</title><p>(A) Arrhenius plot of <italic>P<sub>f</sub></italic> at temperature range (9&#x02013;37&#x000b0;C), where T is temperature in Kelvin. <italic>Ea</italic> was evaluated from the slopes. Strains expressing <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP1;4, <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP4;1 and empty plasmid (pUG35) showed steeper slope, while strains expressing <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;1, <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP1;1 and <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP2;2 exhibited shallow slope. (B) Calculated <italic>Ea</italic> from the slope showed that <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;1, <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP1;1 and <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP2;2 expressing strains exhibited lower <italic>Ea</italic>, while <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP1;4, <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;3 and <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP4;1 expressing strains showed were almost equal to control strain (pUG35). Data are mean &#x000b1; SD of three independent experiments with at least five traces (ten traces in case of <italic>P<sub>f</sub></italic> at 23&#x000b0;C) at each temperature.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0102087.g005"/></fig><p>To examine the dose and time dependent effects of mercurial inhibition, yeast strains expressing functional <italic>Vitis</italic> aquaporins (<italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;1, <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP1;1 and <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP2;2) as well as the control strain were pretreated with various concentrations (0.5 and 1.0 mM) of HgCl<sub>2</sub> for 15 to 30 minutes at room temperature, before hyperosmotic shock. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0102087-g006">Figure 6A</xref> compares the stopped-flow signals of yeast cells expressing <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP2;2, obtained after hyperosmotic shock either in the absence or presence of mercury chloride (0.5 mM) after 15 minutes of incubation. It is clear from the signals that HgCl<sub>2</sub> reduced the shrinking rates of the cells. All the functional aquaporins tested were mercury sensitive. TIPs were more sensitive than PIP. <italic>P<sub>f</sub></italic> was markedly decreased when cells were incubated with 0.5 mM HgCl<sub>2</sub> for 15 minutes before the osmotic shock. <italic>P<sub>f</sub></italic> of <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;1 expressing strain was reduced by 24% while <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP1;1 and <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP2;2 expressing strains exhibited 38% and 36% reduction (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0102087-g006">Figure 6B</xref>). Water transport in control cells was not affected by 0.5 mM HgCl<sub>2</sub>, even after 30 minutes of incubation, while higher concentration (1 mM) reduced the <italic>P<sub>f</sub></italic> of all yeast strains including the control strain, indicating a general toxicity at this concentration (data not shown).</p><fig id="pone-0102087-g006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0102087.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Inhibition of water permeability by mercury chloride (HgCl<sub>2</sub>) in yeast strains expressing <italic>V. vinifera</italic> aquaporins.</title><p>(A) Inhibition of water permeability in yeast cells expressing functional aquaporin (<italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP2;2) by HgCl<sub>2</sub>. The green signal represents water permeability without HgCl<sub>2</sub> and the red signal shows the lower permeability when cells were incubated with 0.5 mM HgCl<sub>2</sub> for 15 minutes prior to osmotic shock. (B) Water permeability coefficients (<italic>P<sub>f</sub></italic> at 23&#x000b0;C) of <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;1, <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP1;1 and <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP2;2 were reduced by 0.5 mM HgCl<sub>2</sub>. Data are mean &#x000b1; SD of three independent experiments with at least five traces. The data were analyzed by <italic>t-test</italic> and asterisks above bars indicate statistically significant differences, where **p&#x0003c;0.01, ***p&#x0003c;0.001.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0102087.g006"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3e"><title>Growth assays under osmotic stress and in the presence of atypical substrates</title><p>Expression of <italic>Vitis</italic> aquaporins in <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> was not deleterious to yeast cells, since neither the specific growth rate nor the final biomass of the yeast were affected during growth in standard YNB media. Accordingly, all the strains showed approximately 3.5 hours of doubling time and grew up to similar final biomass in liquid YNB media (data not shown).</p><sec id="s3e1"><title>Expression of Vitis aquaporins affects the growth of yeast cells under osmotic stress</title><p>Osmotic tolerance/susceptibility of heterologously expressed <italic>Vitis</italic> aquaporins was examined in the presence of NaCl, KCl and sorbitol. When exposed to hyperosmotic stress, yeast cells expressing <italic>Vitis</italic> aquaporins exhibited decreased growth to a variable degree, depending on the types of aquaporins expressed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0102087-g007">Figure 7</xref>). Growth of all yeast strains (including empty plasmid strain) was equally inhibited in the presence of NaCl, even at lower concentration (0.5 M) (data not shown). At the highest concentration of KCl (1.5 M), cells expressing <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP4;1 were least inhibited by KCl, while growth of <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP2;2 and <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP1;4 expressing cells displayed a clear osmosensitive phenotype followed by <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP1;1, <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;3 and <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0102087-g007">Figure 7</xref>). Growth of these strains was reduced under osmoequivalent concentration of sorbitol (2.1 M), but did not show any clear phenotype (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0102087-g007">Figure 7</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0102087-g007" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0102087.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>Growth assays of <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> strains expressing <italic>V. vinifera</italic> aquaporins under osmotic stress.</title><p>Hyperosmotic stress was exerted by osmo-equivalent concentration of either KCl or sorbitol. Yeast strain transformed with empty pUG35 plasmid was used as control (pUG35). Yeast suspensions were spotted in 10-fold dilution on solid YNB plates without or with 1.5 M KCl or 2.1 M sorbitol. Growth was recorded after two weeks at 28&#x000b0;C. Photographs shown are representative of three independent experiments with consistent results.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0102087.g007"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3e2"><title>Expression of <italic>V. vinifera</italic> aquaporins increases the sensitivity of yeast to H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and boron</title><p>Ability of <italic>Vitis</italic> aquaporins to facilitate the transport of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and boron was examined by drop test assays in the presence of these substrates on solid YNB (pH 5.0). Impaired growth of yeast strains due to the expression <italic>Vitis</italic> aquaporins was tested in the presence of these substrates.</p><p>Growth of <italic>Vitis</italic> aquaporins (<italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP1;4, <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;1, <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;3, <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP1;1 and <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP2;2) expressing strains was affected by externally supplied H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> in a dose dependent manner (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0102087-g008">Figure 8</xref>). Impaired growth of <italic>Vitis</italic> aquaporins expressing strains was observed at higher concentration of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (0.75 mM) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0102087-g008">Figure 8</xref>), while the control strain was able to grow up to the last dilution at 1.0 mM H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>. Growth of the strain expressing <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP2;2 was most severely inhibited, followed by <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP1;1, <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;3, <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP1;4 and <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;1 expressing strains (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0102087-g008">Figure 8</xref>)<sub>.</sub> Cells expressing <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP4;1 were least sensitive toward H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and exhibited similar growth as the control strain.</p><fig id="pone-0102087-g008" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0102087.g008</object-id><label>Figure 8</label><caption><title>Growth assays of <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> strains expressing <italic>V. vinifera</italic> aquaporins on H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> containing minimal media.</title><p>Yeast strain transformed with empty pUG35 plasmid was used as control (pUG35). Yeast suspensions were spotted in 10-fold dilution on solid YNB plates without or with 0.75 mM and 1.0 mM H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>. Growth was recorded after two weeks at 28&#x000b0;C. Photographs shown are representative of three independent experiments with consistent results.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0102087.g008"/></fig><p>The ability of <italic>Vitis</italic> aquaporins to facilitate boron transport was tested in the same way as H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>. Yeast transformants were spotted on YNB plates containing various concentrations of boron as boric acid (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0102087-g009">Figure 9</xref>)<sub>.</sub> The exposure to boric acid (40 mM) caused reduced growth of strains expressing <italic>Vitis</italic> aquaporin. Interestingly, at 40 mM boric acid, cells transformed with <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP4;1 grew better in comparison to control strain, but these cells showed clear sensitivity toward boric acid when exposed to higher concentration (60 mM) of boric acid. Heterologous expression of all cloned <italic>Vitis</italic> aquaporins, except <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;1, showed increased sensitivity to 60 mM boric acid. <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;1 expressing strain was the most tolerant to externally supplied boric acid and was able to grow as the control strain. Growth of <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP2;2 expressing strain was severely inhibited by boric acid exposure (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0102087-g009">Figure 9</xref>)<sub>.</sub></p><fig id="pone-0102087-g009" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0102087.g009</object-id><label>Figure 9</label><caption><title>Growth assays of <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> strains expressing <italic>V. Vinifera</italic> aquaporins on minimal medium containing boric acid.</title><p>Yeast strain transformed with empty pUG35 plasmid was the control (pUG35). Yeast suspensions were spotted in 10-fold dilution on solid YNB plates without or with 40 mM and 60 mM boric acid. Growth was recorded after two weeks at 28&#x000b0;C. Photographs shown are representative of three independent experiments with consistent results.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0102087.g009"/></fig><p>We also performed the growth assays of yeast strains expressing <italic>Vitis</italic> aquaporins in the presence of ammonia and urea, to explore their possible transport by aquaporins. We observed that growth of yeast strains was not affected by these substrates at any tested concentrations, since no distinct growth phenotypes were observed (results not shown).</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>In this study we have cloned and characterized three plasma membrane (PIPs) and three tonoplast (TIPs) aquaporins from <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> cv. Touriga nacional, an important Portuguese cultivar, widely believed to produce the finest red wines of Portugal.</p><p>All the cloned full length aquaporin genes from <italic>V. vinifera</italic> (cv. Touriga nacional) encoding three PIPs (<italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP1;4, <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;1 and <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;3) and TIPs (<italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP1;1, <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP2;2 and <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP4;1) proteins showed obvious similarity with the same proteins of the database variety of <italic>V. vinifera</italic> (cv. Pinot noir). Their plasma membrane localization was confirmed by GFP-tagging, although we observed a partial retention in intracellular structures, probably in endoplasmic reticulum or in vesicles of secretory pathway (reviewed by <xref rid="pone.0102087-Chaumont1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>). Several reports suggest that a fraction of intracellular plant aquaporins (TIPs) is generally &#x0201c;miss-targeted&#x0201d; to the plasma membrane of heterologous models, which enabled the researchers to measure their water transport activity in <italic>Xenopus</italic> and yeast (reviewed by <xref rid="pone.0102087-Wudick1" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>).</p><p>Their sequence analysis for topological prediction revealed all the characteristics of typical aquaporin subfamilies. Specific residues for transport of ammonia (filter 2: H/W-I/V-G/A-R and P1&#x02013;P5 residues: T/F-S-A-Y-W/L), boron (filter 2: F/A/G-H/I/S-T/G/A-R and P1&#x02013;P5 residues: Q/F/I-S/T-A-F/Y-W/L), CO<sub>2</sub> (filter 2: F-H-T-R and P1&#x02013;P5 residues: Q/M-S-A-F-W), H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (filter 2: H/F/W-I/H/V-A/T/G-R/V and P1&#x02013;P5 residues: T/Q/F-S/A-A-Y/F-W/I) and urea (filter 2: F/H/G/A/N-I/H/S/V-T/A/G-R/V and P1&#x02013;P5 residues: M/T/Q/L/F/V/I-S/A/T-A-F/Y-W/F/L) were present at ar/R constriction and P1&#x02013;P5 positions <xref rid="pone.0102087-Hove1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref> of the cloned <italic>Vitis</italic> aquaporins, depending on their subfamilies (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0102087-t001">Table 1</xref>).</p><p>Expression of functional aquaporins <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;1, <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP1;1 and <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP2;2 increased the water permeability coefficient (<italic>P<sub>f</sub></italic>) and reduced the activation energy (<italic>Ea</italic>) required for water transport in yeast cells, while expression of non-functional aquaporins <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP1;4, <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;3 and <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP4;1 expression exhibited higher <italic>Ea</italic> and did not affect <italic>P<sub>f</sub></italic>. The obtained higher <italic>Ea</italic> and lower <italic>P<sub>f</sub></italic> can not be correlated with their lower plasma membrane expression since all the functional aquaporins were also partially retained at various subcellular regions and, on the other hand, one of the aquaporins (<italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP4;1) showed to be localized at the plasma membrane of <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> and exhibited low water transport.</p><p>TIPs (<italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP1;1 and <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP2;2) exhibited higher water conductivity in comparison to PIP (<italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;1). This finding is in agreement with previous reports of heterologously expressed plant aquaporins <xref rid="pone.0102087-Johansson2" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0102087-Maurel3" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0102087-Daniels2" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>. Higher water permeability of TIPs may be required for the central role of vacuole in osmoregulation of the cytoplasm. Constitutively higher water permeability of tonoplast aquaporins may allow the cells to use the vacuolar space to maintain the cellular integrity, in case of osmotic fluctuations caused by rapid water exchange during stress or developmental stages of plants (reviewed in <xref rid="pone.0102087-Kjellbom1" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0102087-Maurel3" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>).</p><p>All functional <italic>Vitis</italic> aquaporins were found to be mercury-sensitive, as their <italic>P<sub>f</sub></italic> was reduced by mercury chloride. Many plant aquaporins have been inhibited by mercurial reagents, which bind to a conserved cysteine residue located downstream to first NPA motif, subsequently blocking the pore and shutting-down the aqueous pathway (reviewed in <xref rid="pone.0102087-Maurel1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>). Notably all cloned TIPs showed the conserved cysteine residue responsible for mercury sensitivity (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0102087.s005">Figure S5A</xref>). Although PIPs (except <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;3) did not have the conserved cysteine at the same position of alignment, they have four conserved cysteine residues in second and third transmembrane helices and one of these residues may represent the mercury sensitive site <xref rid="pone.0102087-Suga1" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>.</p><p>Transport of solutes of physiological significance, such as CO<sub>2</sub>, H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, boron or silicic acid is now well established and has linked aquaporins to many functions, including carbon metabolism, oxidative stress responses, and plant mineral nutrition <xref rid="pone.0102087-Maurel1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>. We performed a broad screening of growth sensitivity test of all cloned <italic>Vitis</italic> aquaporins on H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and boric acid containing plates to investigate their ability to transport these atypical substrates. The phenotypic growth variations showed that heterologous expression of all cloned <italic>Vitis</italic> aquaporins (except <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP4;1) caused more susceptibility to externally applied H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, indicating their putative role in H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> transport. In principle, increased level of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> can disturb the cellular metabolism in an unidentified manner, which may lead to reduced or impaired growth of yeast cells. A higher permeability of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> by heterologously expressed aquaporins might have increased the influx of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> into yeast cells and eventually triggered the cell death or growth inhibition. H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2,</sub> a long-lived reactive oxygen species (ROS) shares molecular properties with water, it can form hydrogen bonds and has similar permeability as water <xref rid="pone.0102087-Neill1" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0102087-Antunes1" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>. Based on the sensitivity of yeast cells expressing <italic>Vitis</italic> aquaporins, we assume that both <italic>Vitis</italic> PIPs and TIPs may permeate H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>. Similar results were previously reported in heterologously expressed <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0102087-Bienert1" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0102087-Dynowski1" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref> and maize aquaporins <xref rid="pone.0102087-Bienert3" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref> expressed in <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>. It is noteworthy that putative amino acids for H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> transport were found at ar/R constriction of all cloned <italic>Vitis</italic> aquaporins. Besides a potential threat to biological components, H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> also acts as a physiologically important molecule to activate Ca<sup>2+</sup> channels for NADPH oxidase activity required during root hair growth and stomatal movement <xref rid="pone.0102087-Mori1" ref-type="bibr">[54]</xref>. Under stress, H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> can be compartmentalized in various intracellular organelles as well as outside of the cells in apoplastic regions <xref rid="pone.0102087-Foyer1" ref-type="bibr">[55]</xref>. Further, the extracellular accumulated H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> can act as a regulator of water homeostasis by triggering the PIP internalization in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> roots and consequently reduces the water permeability in roots under stress <xref rid="pone.0102087-Boursiac1" ref-type="bibr">[56]</xref>. The role of <italic>Vitis</italic> PIPs may be involved in apoplastic exclusion of excess H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>. Our results indicate that not only plasma membrane aquaporins (PIPs), but also tonoplast aquaporins (TIPs) are involved in H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> transport. Results of growth assays suggest that the cells expressing TIPs were more sensitive as compared with the cells expressing PIPs. TIPs are reported to be more diverse transporters and can conduct many solutes other than water due to having relatively weak selectivity (reviewed in <xref rid="pone.0102087-Dynowski1" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0102087-Azad1" ref-type="bibr">[57]</xref>). Under elevated stress conditions, plant TIPs are suggested to transport high amounts of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> into vacuoles, resulting in their further detoxification by vacuolar peroxidases using vacuole stored flavanoids as an electron donors <xref rid="pone.0102087-Bienert1" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>. Expression level of TIPs was found to be affected by H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> in tulip flowers <xref rid="pone.0102087-Azad2" ref-type="bibr">[58]</xref> and it was suggested that TIPs triggered the ROS translocation into the vacuoles for their detoxification <xref rid="pone.0102087-Azad1" ref-type="bibr">[57]</xref>.</p><p>When exposed to H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, all yeast cells exhibited fluffy and larger colony morphology with rough edges (results not shown). H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> induces aging of the cells by releasing free radicals, leading to higher number of old cells which are bigger in size in comparison to young cells and eventually make the larger colonies with mature cells <xref rid="pone.0102087-Canetta1" ref-type="bibr">[59]</xref>. Fluffy and rough surface colonies may represent a metabolic strategy of growth under unfavorable conditions <xref rid="pone.0102087-Kuthan1" ref-type="bibr">[60]</xref>.</p><p>Growth assays in the presence of boric acid showed that strains expressing <italic>Vitis</italic> aquaporins were more sensitive in comparison to control strain. Heterologous expression of plant aquaporins either in <italic>Xenopus laevis</italic> oocytes or <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>, suggests that besides other routes, boron can be transported through PIPs <xref rid="pone.0102087-Dordas1" ref-type="bibr">[61]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0102087-Fitzpatrick1" ref-type="bibr">[62]</xref> and NIPs <xref rid="pone.0102087-Takano1" ref-type="bibr">[63]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0102087-Schnurbusch1" ref-type="bibr">[66]</xref>. NIP5;1 and NIP6;1 of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> were identified as boric acid channels and were up-regulated under limited boron supply to accomplish the demand of boric acid <xref rid="pone.0102087-Takano1" ref-type="bibr">[63]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0102087-Tanaka1" ref-type="bibr">[64]</xref>. Although boron is an essential micronutrient for plants, when accumulated at higher concentration it leads to toxicity. Being a non-charged molecule, boric acid can passively diffuse across lipid bilayer, but only significantly at high concentration gradient caused by high boron supply <xref rid="pone.0102087-Tanaka2" ref-type="bibr">[67]</xref>. In plants, urea (<italic>DUR3</italic>) and glycerol (<italic>FPS1</italic>) transporters were identified as boron importers, while <italic>BOR1</italic> and its homolog <italic>ScBOR1</italic> of <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> were characterized as boron exporters, exporting boron and protecting the cells from boron toxicity <xref rid="pone.0102087-Nozawa1" ref-type="bibr">[68]</xref>. In this work, all the yeast strains expressing <italic>Vitis</italic> aquaporins have the same background for passive diffusion or importers and exporters of boric acid in their native membrane. Since different levels of toxicity were detected (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0102087-g009">Figure 9</xref>), we can speculate the putative transport of boron by <italic>Vitis</italic> aquaporins resulting in growth inhibition. Similarly, heterologously expressed barley <italic>Hv</italic>NIP2;1 <xref rid="pone.0102087-Schnurbusch1" ref-type="bibr">[66]</xref>, <italic>Hv</italic>PIP1;3 and <italic>Hv</italic>PIP1;4 <xref rid="pone.0102087-Fitzpatrick1" ref-type="bibr">[62]</xref> displayed sensitive growth phenotype in the presence of boron and were identified as boron transporters. Interestingly, all PIPs exhibited the signature sequences for boron transport and showed sensitivity (except <italic>Vv</italic>TnPI2;1) to boric acid. On the contrary, these conserved residues were not present in TIPs, although yeast strains expressing TIPs also exhibited increased sensitivity toward boron.</p><p>Although these studies are based on the molecular analysis of ar/R regions of <italic>Vitis</italic> aquaporins and indirect yeast based sensitivity growth assays on these substrates, transport of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and boron by <italic>Vitis</italic> aquaporins can be hypothesized.</p><p>In conclusion, we have cloned six PIPs and TIPs aquaporins from grapevine (cv. Touriga nacional) in <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>, and have shown that three of them facilitate the transport of water. Reduced growth and survival of <italic>Vitis</italic> aquaporins expressing yeast cells in the presence of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and boron, indicates their probable role in transport of these non-aqua substrates. Additionally, expression of three aquaporins in yeast, which were found non-functional for water transport, exhibited sensitive phenotype when grown in the presence of these substrates, suggests their possible role in transport of substrates other than water. The combined use of molecular analysis of their sequences and functional investigation of growth sensitivity assays provided the initial insight on the selectivity profiles of <italic>Vitis</italic> aquaporins. Further studies are required to ascertain the role of <italic>Vitis</italic> aquaporins in transport of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and boron. Moreover, co-expression of aquaporins in <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> may represent the next step for better understanding their interaction and regulation in plants.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0102087.s001"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p><bold>Comparison of </bold><bold><italic>V. vinifera</italic></bold><bold> aquaporins from Pinot noir and Touriga nacional cultivars.</bold> Alignment of deduced amino acid sequences of <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP1;4 (A), <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;1 (B), <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;3 (C), <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP1;1 (D), <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP2;2 (E), <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP4;1 (F) obtained from the present study (Touriga nacional) with the database variety (Pinot noir). Accession numbers of presented protein sequences are: <italic>Vv</italic>PnPIP1;4 (CAO39626), <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP1;4 (KJ697714), <italic>Vv</italic>PnPIP2;1 (CAN75442), <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;1 (KJ697715), <italic>Vv</italic>PnPIP2;3 (CAO18152), <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;3 (KJ697716), <italic>Vv</italic>PnTIP1;1 (CAO69259), <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP1;1 (KJ697717), <italic>Vv</italic>PnTIP2;2 (CAO23095), <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP2;2 (KJ697718), <italic>Vv</italic>PnTIP4;1 (CAO44039), <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP4;1 (KJ697719).</p><p>(PDF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0102087.s001.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0102087.s002"><label>Figure S2</label><caption><p><bold>Comparison of N- (A) and C- (B) terminals of PIP1s, PIP2s and TIPs aquaporins.</bold> Aquaporins cloned in the present study are marked with red arrows. Accession numbers of presented protein sequences are: <italic>At</italic>PIP2;1 (P43286), <italic>At</italic>-deltaTIP2 (CAB10515), <italic>At</italic>-gammaTIP3 (AAC62778), <italic>At</italic>-epsilonTIP (AAC42249), <italic>Fa</italic>PIP2;1 (ADJ67992), <italic>Pv</italic>-alphaTIP (CAA44669), <italic>So</italic>PIP2;1 (4JC6_N), <italic>Vv</italic>PnPIP1;1 (CAO41326), <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP1;1 (HQ913643), <italic>Vv</italic>PnPIP1;4 (CAO39626), <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP1;4 (KJ697714), <italic>Vv</italic>PnPIP2;1 (CAN75442), <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;1 (KJ697715), <italic>Vv</italic>PnPIP2;2 (CAO47394), <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;2 (HQ913642), <italic>Vv</italic>PnPIP2;3 (CAO18152), <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;3 (KJ697716), <italic>Vv</italic>PnTIP1;1 (CAO69259), <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP1;1 (KJ697717), <italic>Vv</italic>PnTIP2;1 (CAO45860), <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP2;1 (HQ913640), <italic>Vv</italic>PnTIP2;2 (CAO23095), <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP2;2 (KJ697718), <italic>Vv</italic>PnTIP4;1 (CAO44039), <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP4;1 (KJ697719), <italic>Zm</italic>PIP2;1 (Q84RL7), <italic>Zm</italic>PIP2;5 (Q9XF58). <italic>At</italic>: <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>, <italic>Fa</italic>: <italic>Fragaria&#x000d7;ananassa</italic>, <italic>Pv</italic>: <italic>Phaseolus vulgaris</italic>, <italic>So</italic>: <italic>Spinacia oleracea</italic>, <italic>Vv</italic>Pn: <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> cv. Pinot noir, <italic>Vv</italic>Tn: <italic>V. vinifera</italic> cv. Touriga nacional.</p><p>(PDF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0102087.s002.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0102087.s003"><label>Figure S3</label><caption><p><bold>Presence of methylation and sorting signal sequences (D/E-X-D/E) at N-terminal (A) and pH regulation site (His residue) for gating (B) of PIPs aquaporins.</bold> Consensus sequences are framed and conserved residues are indicated as red triangle. Aquaporins cloned in the present study are marked with red arrows. Accession numbers of presented protein sequences are: <italic>At</italic>PIP2;1 (P43286), <italic>At</italic>PIP1;2 (Q06611), <italic>At</italic>PIP1;4 (Q39196), <italic>Fa</italic>PIP2;1 (ADJ67992), <italic>So</italic>PIP2;1 (4JC6_N), <italic>Vv</italic>PnPIP1;1 (CAO41326), <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP1;1 (HQ913643), <italic>Vv</italic>PnPIP1;4 (CAO39626), <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP1;4 (KJ697714), <italic>Vv</italic>PnPIP2;1 (CAN75442), <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;1 (KJ697715), <italic>Vv</italic>PnPIP2;2 (CAO47394), <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;2 (HQ913642), <italic>Vv</italic>PnPIP2;3 (CAO18152), <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;3 (KJ697716), <italic>Zm</italic>PIP2;1 (Q84RL7), <italic>Zm</italic>PIP2;5 (Q9XF58), <italic>Zm</italic>PIP2;4 (Q9ATM6). <italic>At</italic>: <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>, <italic>Fa</italic>: <italic>Fragaria&#x000d7;ananassa</italic>, So: <italic>Spinacia oleracea</italic>, <italic>Vv</italic>Pn: <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> cv. Pinot noir, <italic>Vv</italic>Tn: <italic>V. vinifera</italic> cv. Touriga nacional, <italic>Zm</italic>: <italic>Zea mays</italic>.</p><p>(PDF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0102087.s003.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0102087.s004"><label>Figure S4</label><caption><p><bold>Putative phosphorylation sites in aquaporins.</bold> Ser residue in PIPs and Thr residue in TIPs aquaporins in loop B (A), loop D (B) and C-terminal (C) are tentative phosphorylation sites. Consensus sequences are framed and conserved residues are indicated as red triangle. Aquaporins cloned in the present study are marked with red arrows. Accession numbers of presented protein sequences are: <italic>At</italic>PIP1;2 (Q06611), <italic>At</italic>PIP1;4 (Q39196), <italic>At</italic>PIP2;1 (P43286), <italic>At</italic>-deltaTIP2 (CAB10515), <italic>At</italic>-gammaTIP3 (AAC62778), <italic>At</italic>-alphaTIP (AAC42249), <italic>Fa</italic>PIP2;1 (ADJ67992), <italic>So</italic>PIP2;1 (4JC6_N), <italic>Vv</italic>PnPIP1;1 (CAO41326), <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP1;1 (HQ913643), <italic>Vv</italic>PnPIP1;4 (CAO39626), <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP1;4 (KJ697714), <italic>Vv</italic>PnPIP2;1 (CAN75442), <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;1 (KJ697715), <italic>Vv</italic>PnPIP2;2 (CAO47394), <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;2 (HQ913642), <italic>Vv</italic>PnPIP2;3 (CAO18152), <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;3 (KJ697716), <italic>Vv</italic>PnTIP1;1 (CAO69259), <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP1;1 (KJ697717), <italic>Vv</italic>PnTIP2;1 (CAO45860), <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP2;1 (HQ913640), <italic>Vv</italic>PnTIP2;2 (CAO23095), <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP2;2 (KJ697718), <italic>Vv</italic>PnTIP4;1 (CAO44039), <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP4;1 (KJ697719), <italic>Zm</italic>PIP2;1 (Q84RL7), <italic>Zm</italic>PIP2;4 (Q9ATM6), <italic>Zm</italic>PIP2;5 (Q9XF58). <italic>At</italic>: <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>, <italic>Fa</italic>: <italic>Fragaria&#x000d7;ananassa</italic>, <italic>Pv</italic>: <italic>Phaseolus vulgaris</italic>, <italic>So</italic>: <italic>Spinacia oleracea</italic>, <italic>Vv</italic>Pn: <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> cv. Pinot noir, <italic>Vv</italic>Tn: <italic>V. vinifera</italic> cv. Touriga nacional, <italic>Zm</italic>: <italic>Zea mays</italic>.</p><p>(PDF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0102087.s004.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0102087.s005"><label>Figure S5</label><caption><p><bold>Mercury sensitive site and pH regulation site in TIPs.</bold> Alignment of TIPs aquaporins for (A) mercury sensitive site (Cys residue) and (B) pH regulation site (His residue) for gating. Consensus sequences are framed and conserved residues are indicated as red triangle. TIPs cloned in the present study are marked with red arrows. Accession numbers of presented protein sequences are: <italic>At</italic>-deltaTIP2 CAB10515), <italic>At</italic>-gammaTIP3 (AAC62778), <italic>At</italic>-alphaTIP (AAC42249), <italic>Pv</italic>-alphaTIP (CAA44669), <italic>Vv</italic>PnTIP1;1 (CAO69259), <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP1;1 (KJ697717), <italic>Vv</italic>PnTIP2;1 (CAO45860), <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP2;1 (HQ913640), <italic>Vv</italic>PnTIP2;2 (CAO23095), <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP2;2 (KJ697718), <italic>Vv</italic>PnTIP4;1 (CAO44039), <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP4;1 (KJ697719). <italic>At</italic>: <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>, <italic>Pv</italic>: <italic>Phaseolus vulgaris</italic>, <italic>Vv</italic>Pn: <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> cv. Pinot noir, <italic>Vv</italic>Tn: <italic>V. Vinifera</italic> (cv. Touriga nacional).</p><p>(PDF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0102087.s005.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0102087.s006"><label>Figure S6</label><caption><p><bold>Consensus sequences for transport of boron and CO<sub>2</sub>.</bold> Alignment of putative amino acids of aquaporins of <italic>V. Vinifera</italic> (cv. Touriga nacional) obtained from present study and previous study <xref rid="pone.0102087-Leito1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref> with the sequences of aquaporins reported to transport (A) boron and (B) CO<sub>2</sub>. ar/R constrictions and P1&#x02013;P5 positions are shown to demonstrate the conserved amino acid residue. Accession numbers of presented protein sequences are: <italic>At</italic>PIP1;2 (Q06611), <italic>At</italic>NIP5;1 (NP_192776), <italic>Hv</italic>PIP1;3 (BAA23745), <italic>Hv</italic>PIP2;1 (BAA23744), <italic>Nt</italic>AQP1 (O24662), <italic>Os</italic>NIP2;1 (Q6Z2T3), <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP1;1 (HQ913643), <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP1;4 (KJ697714), <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;1 (KJ697715), <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;2 (HQ913642), <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;3 (KJ697716), <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP1;1 (KJ697717), <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP2;1 (HQ913640), <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP2;2 (KJ697718), <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP4;1 (KJ697719), <italic>Zm</italic>PIP1;1 (Q41870). <italic>At</italic>: <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>, <italic>Hv</italic>: <italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic>, <italic>Vv</italic>Tn: <italic>V. vinifera</italic> (cv. Touriga nacional), <italic>Zm</italic>: <italic>Zea mays</italic>.</p><p>(PDF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0102087.s006.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0102087.s007"><label>Figure S7</label><caption><p><bold>Consensus sequences for transport of ammonia.</bold> Alignment of putative amino acids of aquaporins of <italic>V. Vinifera</italic> (cv. Touriga nacional) obtained from present study and previous study <xref rid="pone.0102087-Leito1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref> with sequences of aquaporins reported to transport ammonia. ar/R constrictions and P1&#x02013;P5 positions are shown to demonstrate the conserved amino acid residue. Accession numbers of presented protein sequences are: <italic>At</italic>TIP2;1 (Q41951), <italic>At</italic>TIP2;3 (Q9FGL2), <italic>Gm</italic>NOD26 (P08995), <italic>Ta</italic>TIP2;1 (AAS19468),<italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP1;1 (HQ913643), <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP1;4 (KJ697714), <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;1 (KJ697715), <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;2 (HQ913642), <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;3 (KJ697716), <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP1;1 (KJ697717), <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP2;1 (HQ913640), <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP2;2 (KJ697718), <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP4;1 (KJ697719). <italic>At</italic>: <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>, <italic>Gm</italic>: <italic>Glycine max</italic>, <italic>Ta</italic>: <italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>, <italic>Vv</italic>Tn: <italic>V. Vinifera</italic> (cv. Touriga nacional).</p><p>(PDF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0102087.s007.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0102087.s008"><label>Figure S8</label><caption><p><bold>Consensus sequences for transport of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and urea.</bold> Alignment of putative amino acids of aquaporins of <italic>V. Vinifera</italic> (cv. Touriga nacional) obtained from present study and previous study <xref rid="pone.0102087-Leito1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref> with sequences of aquaporins reported to transport (A) H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and (B) urea. ar/R constrictions and P1&#x02013;P5 positions are shown to demonstrate the conserved amino acid residue. Accession numbers of presented protein sequences are: <italic>At</italic>TIP1;1 (P25818), <italic>At</italic>TIP1;2 (Q41963), <italic>At</italic>TIP1;3 (NP_192056), <italic>At</italic>TIP2;1 (Q41951), <italic>At</italic>TIP2;3 (Q9FGL2), <italic>At</italic>PIP2;4 (Q9FF53), <italic>Cp</italic>NIP1 (CAD67694), <italic>Nt</italic>AQP1 (O24662), <italic>Nt</italic>TIPa (Q9XG70), <italic>Os</italic>NIP2;1 (Q6Z2T3), <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP1;1 (HQ913643), <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP1;4 (KJ697714), <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;1 (KJ697715), <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;2 (HQ913642), <italic>Vv</italic>TnPIP2;3 (KJ697716), <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP1;1 (KJ697717), <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP2;1 (HQ913640), <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP2;2 (KJ697718), <italic>Vv</italic>TnTIP4;1 (KJ697719), <italic>Zm</italic>PIP1;5 (Q9AR14). <italic>At</italic>: <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>, <italic>Cp</italic>: <italic>Cucurbita pepo</italic>, <italic>Nt</italic>: <italic>Nicotiana tabacum</italic>, <italic>Os</italic>: <italic>Oryza sativa</italic>, <italic>Vv</italic>Tn: <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> (cv. Touriga nacional), <italic>Zm</italic>: <italic>Zea mays</italic>.</p><p>(PDF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0102087.s008.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0102087.s009"><label>Table S1</label><caption><p><bold>Primers used in this work (restriction sites are underlined).</bold></p><p>(PDF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0102087.s009.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Sara Am&#x000e2;ncio and Lu&#x000ed;sa Carvalho, ISA-ULisboa for providing cDNAs of <italic>V. vinifera</italic> cv. Touriga nacional.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0102087-Vandeleur1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vandeleur</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mayo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shelden</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gilliham</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kaiser</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The role of plasma membrane intrinsic protein aquaporins in water transport through roots: diurnal and drought stress responses reveal different strategies between isohydric and anisohydric cultivars of grapevine</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>
<volume>149</volume>: <fpage>445</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>460</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18987216</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Danielson1"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Danielson</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Johanson</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Unexpected complexity of the aquaporin gene family in the moss <italic>Physcomitrella patens</italic></article-title>. <source>BMC Plant Biol</source>
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>45</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18430224</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Maurel1"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Maurel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Verdoucq</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Luu</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Santoni</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Plant aquaporins: membrane channels with multiple integrated functions</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Plant Biol</source>
<volume>59</volume>: <fpage>595</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>624</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18444909</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Hove1"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hove</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bhave</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Plant aquaporins with non-aqua functions: deciphering the signature sequences</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol</source>
<volume>75</volume>: <fpage>413</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>430</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21308399</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Maurel2"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Maurel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chrispeels</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Aquaporins. A molecular entry into plant water relations</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>
<volume>125</volume>: <fpage>135</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>138</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11154316</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Chaumont1"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chaumont</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moshelion</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Daniels</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Regulation of plant aquaporin activity</article-title>. <source>Biol Cell</source>
<volume>97</volume>: <fpage>749</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>764</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16171457</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Soveral1"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Soveral</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Madeira</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Loureiro-Dias</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moura</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Membrane tension regulates water transport in yeast</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source>
<volume>1778</volume>: <fpage>2573</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2579</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18708027</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Baiges1"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Baiges</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sch&#x000e4;ffner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Eight cDNA encoding putative aquaporins in <italic>Vitis</italic> hybrid Richter-110 and their differential expression</article-title>. <source>J Exp Bot</source>
<volume>52</volume>: <fpage>1949</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1951</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11520885</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Flexas1"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Flexas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Galm&#x000e9;s</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gall&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gul&#x000ed;as</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Improving water use efficiency in grapevines: potential physiological targets for biotechnological improvement</article-title>. <source>Aust J Grape and Wine</source>
<volume>16</volume>: <fpage>106</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>121</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Hayes1"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dry</surname><given-names>IB</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Isolation, functional characterization, and expression analysis of grapevine (<italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> L.) hexose transporters: differential roles in sink and source tissues</article-title>. <source>J Exp Bot</source>
<volume>58</volume>: <fpage>1985</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1997</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17452752</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Jaillon1"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jaillon</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Aury</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Noel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Policriti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Clepet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The grapevine genome sequence suggests ancestral hexaploidization in major angiosperm phyla</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>449</volume>: <fpage>463</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>467</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17721507</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Shelden1"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shelden</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Howitt</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kaiser</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tyerman</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Identification and functional characterisation of aquaporins in the grapevine, <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic></article-title>. <source>Funct Plant Biol</source>
<volume>36</volume>: <fpage>1065</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1078</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Gambetta1"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gambetta</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Manuck</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Drucker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shaghasi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fort</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The relationship between root hydraulics and scion vigour across <italic>Vitis</italic> rootstocks: what role do root aquaporins play?</article-title>
<source>J Exp Bot</source>
<volume>63</volume>: <fpage>6445</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6455</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23136166</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Galms1"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Galm&#x000e9;s</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alsina</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tom&#x000e0;s</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Medrano</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Aquaporin expression in response to different water stress intensities and recovery in Richter-110 (<italic>Vitis</italic> sp.): relationship with ecophysiological status</article-title>. <source>Planta</source>
<volume>226</volume>: <fpage>671</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>681</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17447082</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Pou1"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Medrano</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Flexas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tyerman</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>A putative role for TIP and PIP aquaporins in dynamics of leaf hydraulic and stomatal conductances in grapevine under water stress and re-watering</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Environ</source>
<volume>36</volume>: <fpage>828</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>843</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23046275</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Fouquet1"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fouquet</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Leon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ollat</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Barrieu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Identification of grapevine aquaporins and expression analysis in developing berries</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Rep</source>
<volume>27</volume>: <fpage>1541</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1550</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18560835</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Leito1"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Leit&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Prista</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moura</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Loureiro-Dias</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Soveral</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Grapevine aquaporins: gating of a tonoplast intrinsic protein (TIP2;1) by cytosolic pH</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e33219</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22427995</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Noronha1"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Noronha</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Agasse</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Berny</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gomes</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>The grape aquaporin VvSIP1 transports water across the ER membrane</article-title>. <source>J Exp Bot</source>
<volume>65</volume>: <fpage>981</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>993</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24376256</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Pettersson1"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pettersson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hagstrom</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bill</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hohmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Expression of heterologous aquaporins for functional analysis in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic></article-title>. <source>Curr Genet</source>
<volume>50</volume>: <fpage>247</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>255</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16917763</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Soveral2"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Soveral</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Madeira</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Loureiro-Dias</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moura</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Water transport in intact yeast cells as assessed by fluorescence self-quenching</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>
<volume>73</volume>: <fpage>2341</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2343</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17277218</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Gldener1"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">G&#x000fc;ldener U, Hegemann J (1998) A second generation of GFP-vectors for subcellular localization studies in budding yeast. Technical report, Heinrich-Heine Universit&#x000e4;t, Inst. f&#x000fc;r Mikrobiologie. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mips.helmholtz-muenchen.de/proj/yeast/info/tools/hegemann/gfp.html">http://mips.helmholtz-muenchen.de/proj/yeast/info/tools/hegemann/gfp.html</ext-link> Accessed 2014 April 16.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Hanahan1"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hanahan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>Techniques for transformation of <italic>E. coli</italic>. In DNA cloning: A Practical Approach</article-title>. <source>(ed DM Glover)</source>
<volume>1</volume>: <fpage>109</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>135</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Pronk1"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pronk</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Auxotrophic yeast strains in fundamental and applied research</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>
<volume>68</volume>: <fpage>2095</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2100</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11976076</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Thompson1"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Plewniak</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jeanmougin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>The CLUSTAL_X windows interface: flexible strategies for multiple sequence alignment aided by quality analysis tools</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
<volume>25</volume>: <fpage>4876</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4882</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9396791</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Hall1"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>BioEdit: a user-friendly biological sequence alignment editor and analysis program for Windows 95/98/NT</article-title>. <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>95</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>98</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Tamura1"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stecher</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>MEGA5: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis using maximum likelihood, evolutionary distance, and maximum parsimony methods</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>
<volume>28</volume>: <fpage>2731</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2739</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21546353</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Krogh1"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Krogh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Larsson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>von Heijne</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sonnhammer</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Predicting transmembrane protein topology with a hidden Markov model: application to complete genomes</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biol</source>
<volume>305</volume>: <fpage>567</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>580</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11152613</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Tusnady1"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tusnady</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>The HMMTOP transmembrane topology prediction server</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>17</volume>: <fpage>849</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>850</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11590105</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Hofmann1"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hofmann</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stoffel</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>TMbase - A database of membrane spanning proteins segments</article-title>. <source>Biol Chem Hoppe-Seyler</source>
<volume>374</volume>: <fpage>166</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Johanson1"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Johanson</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Karlsson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gustavsson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sj&#x000f6;vall</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>The complete set of genes encoding major intrinsic proteins in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> provides a framework for a new nomenclature for major intrinsic proteins in plants</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>
<volume>126</volume>: <fpage>1358</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1369</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11500536</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Forrest1"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Forrest</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bhave</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Major intrinsic proteins (MIPs) in plants: a complex gene family with major impacts on plant phenotype</article-title>. <source>Funct Integr Genomics</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>263</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>289</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17562090</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Froger1"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Froger</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tallur</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Delamarche</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Prediction of functional residues in water channels and related proteins</article-title>. <source>Protein Sci</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>1458</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1468</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9655351</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Heymann1"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Heymann</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Engel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Structural clues in the sequences of the aquaporins</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biol</source>
<volume>295</volume>: <fpage>1039</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1053</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10656809</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Johansson1"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Karlsson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Johanson</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Larsson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kjellbom</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>The role of aquaporins in cellular and whole plant water balance</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source>
<volume>1465</volume>: <fpage>324</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>342</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10748263</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Santoni1"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Santoni</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Verdoucq</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sommerer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vinh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pflieger</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Methylation of aquaporins in plant plasma membrane</article-title>. <source>Biochem J</source>
<volume>400</volume>: <fpage>189</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>197</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16839310</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Zelazny1"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zelazny</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Miecielica</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Borst</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hemminga</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chaumont</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>An N-terminal diacidic motif is required for the trafficking of maize aquaporins ZmPIP2;4 and ZmPIP2;5 to the plasma membrane</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source>
<volume>57</volume>: <fpage>346</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>355</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18808456</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-TournaireRoux1"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tournaire-Roux</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sutka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Javot</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gout</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gerbeau</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Cytosolic pH regulates root water transport during anoxic stress through gating of aquaporins</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>425</volume>: <fpage>393</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>397</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14508488</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Nyblom1"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nyblom</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Frick</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ekvall</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hallgren</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Structural and functional analysis of SoPIP2;1 mutants adds insight into plant aquaporin gating</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biol</source>
<volume>387</volume>: <fpage>653</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>668</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19302796</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-VanWilder1"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Van Wilder</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Miecielica</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Degand</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Derua</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Waelkens</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Maize plasma membrane aquaporins belonging to the PIP1 and PIP2 subgroups are <italic>in vivo</italic> phosphorylated</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol</source>
<volume>49</volume>: <fpage>1364</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1377</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18682426</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Prak1"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Prak</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hem</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Boudet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Viennois</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sommerer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Multiple phosphorylations in the C-terminal tail of plant plasma membrane aquaporins role in subcellular trafficking of AtPIP2; 1 in response to salt stress</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell Proteomics</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>1019</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1030</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18234664</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Johansson2"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Karlsson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shukla</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chrispeels</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Larsson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Water transport activity of the plasma membrane aquaporin PM28A is regulated by phosphorylation</article-title>. <source>The Plant Cell Online</source>
<volume>10</volume>: <fpage>451</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>459</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Daniels1"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Daniels</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Characterization of a new vacuolar membrane aquaporin sensitive to mercury at a unique site</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>587</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>599</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8624437</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Kjellbom1"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kjellbom</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Larsson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Karlsson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Johanson</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Aquaporins and water homeostasis in plants</article-title>. <source>Trends Plant Sci</source>
<volume>4</volume>: <fpage>308</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>314</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10431220</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Wudick1"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wudick</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Luu</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Maurel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>A look inside: localization patterns and functions of intracellular plant aquaporins</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source>
<volume>184</volume>: <fpage>289</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>302</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19674338</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Maurel3"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Maurel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reizer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schroeder</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chrispeels</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>The vacuolar membrane protein gamma-TIP creates water specific channels in <italic>Xenopus</italic> oocytes</article-title>. <source>The EMBO Journal</source>
<volume>12</volume>: <fpage>2241</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2247</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8508761</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Daniels2"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Daniels</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mirkov</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chrispeels</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>The plasma membrane of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> contains a mercury-insensitive aquaporin that is a homolog of the tonoplast water channel protein TIP</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>
<volume>106</volume>: <fpage>1325</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1333</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7846153</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Suga1"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Suga</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Maeshima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Water channel activity of radish plasma membrane aquaporins heterologously expressed in yeast and their modification by site-directed mutagenesis</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol</source>
<volume>45</volume>: <fpage>823</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>830</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15295065</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Neill1"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Neill</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Desikan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hancock</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Hydrogen peroxide signalling</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source>
<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>388</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>395</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12183176</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Antunes1"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Antunes</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cadenas</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brunk</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Apoptosis induced by exposure to a low steady-state concentration of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> is a consequence of lysosomal rupture</article-title>. <source>Biochem J</source>
<volume>356</volume>: <fpage>549</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>555</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11368784</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Bienert1"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bienert</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schjoerring</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jahn</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Membrane transport of hydrogen peroxide</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta - Biomembranes</source>
<volume>1758</volume>: <fpage>994</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1003</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Bienert2"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bienert</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>M&#x000f8;ller</surname><given-names>ALB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kristiansen</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>M&#x000f8;ller</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Specific aquaporins facilitate the diffusion of hydrogen peroxide across membranes</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>282</volume>: <fpage>1183</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1192</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17105724</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Dynowski1"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dynowski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schaaf</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Loque</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moran</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ludewig</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Plant plasma membrane water channels conduct the signalling molecule H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub></article-title>. <source>Biochem J</source>
<volume>414</volume>: <fpage>53</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>61</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18462192</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Bienert3"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bienert</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Heinen</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Berny</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chaumont</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Maize plasma membrane aquaporin ZmPIP2;5, but not ZmPIP1;2, facilitates transmembrane diffusion of hydrogen peroxide</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source>
<volume>1838</volume>: <fpage>216</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>222</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23994602</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Mori1"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schroeder</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Reactive oxygen species activation of plant Ca<sup>2+</sup> channels. A signaling mechanism in polar growth, hormone transduction, stress signaling, and hypothetically mechanotransduction</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>
<volume>135</volume>: <fpage>702</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>708</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15208417</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Foyer1"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Foyer</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Noctor</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Redox sensing and signalling associated with reactive oxygen in chloroplasts, peroxisomes and mitochondria</article-title>. <source>Physiol Plant</source>
<volume>119</volume>: <fpage>355</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>364</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Boursiac1"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Boursiac</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Boudet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Postaire</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Luu</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tournaire-Roux</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Stimulus-induced downregulation of root water transport involves reactive oxygen species-activated cell signalling and plasma membrane intrinsic protein internalization</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source>
<volume>56</volume>: <fpage>207</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>218</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18573191</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Azad1"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Azad</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yoshikawa</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ishikawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shibata</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Substitution of a single amino acid residue in the aromatic/arginine selectivity filter alters the transport profiles of tonoplast aquaporin homologs</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source>
<volume>1818</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21963407</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Azad2"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Azad</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ishikawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ishikawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shibata</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Intracellular energy depletion triggers programmed cell death during petal senescence in tulip</article-title>. <source>J Exp Bot</source>
<volume>59</volume>: <fpage>2085</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2095</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18515833</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Canetta1"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Canetta</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Adya</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Nanoscopic morphological changes in yeast cell surfaces caused by oxidative stress: an atomic force microscopic study</article-title>. <source>J Microbiol Biotechnol</source>
<volume>19</volume>: <fpage>547</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>555</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19597311</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Kuthan1"><label>60</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kuthan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Devaux</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Janderov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Slaninov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jacq</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Domestication of wild <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> is accompanied by changes in gene expression and colony morphology</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>47</volume>: <fpage>745</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>754</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12535073</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Dordas1"><label>61</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dordas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chrispeels</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Permeability and channel-mediated transport of boric acid across membrane vesicles isolated from squash roots</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>
<volume>124</volume>: <fpage>1349</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1362</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11080310</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Fitzpatrick1"><label>62</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fitzpatrick</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The involvement of aquaglyceroporins in transport of boron in barley roots</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Environ</source>
<volume>32</volume>: <fpage>1357</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1365</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19552667</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Takano1"><label>63</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Takano</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ludewig</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schaaf</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>von Wiren</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> major intrinsic protein NIP5;1 is essential for efficient boron uptake and plant development under boron limitation</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>18</volume>: <fpage>1498</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1509</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16679457</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Tanaka1"><label>64</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Takano</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fujiwara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>NIP6;1 is a boric acid channel for preferential transport of boron to growing shoot tissues in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>20</volume>: <fpage>2860</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2875</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18952773</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Mitani1"><label>65</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mitani</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yamaji</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Characterization of substrate specificity of a rice silicon transporter, Lsi1</article-title>. <source>Pflugers Arch, EJP</source>
<volume>456</volume>: <fpage>679</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>686</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18214526</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Schnurbusch1"><label>66</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schnurbusch</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hrmova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baumann</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ramesh</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Boron toxicity tolerance in barley through reduced expression of the multifunctional aquaporin HvNIP2;1</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>
<volume>153</volume>: <fpage>1706</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1715</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20581256</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Tanaka2"><label>67</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fujiwara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Physiological roles and transport mechanisms of boron: perspectives from plants</article-title>. <source>Pflugers Arch</source>
<volume>456</volume>: <fpage>671</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>677</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17965876</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0102087-Nozawa1"><label>68</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nozawa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Takano</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>von Wiren</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fujiwara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Roles of <italic>BOR1</italic>, <italic>DUR3</italic>, and <italic>FPS1</italic> in boron transport and tolerance in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic></article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol Lett</source>
<volume>262</volume>: <fpage>216</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>222</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16923078</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>