<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21490961</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3072378</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10-PONE-RA-17481R3</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0014793</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Genetics and Genomics</subject><subject>Respiratory Medicine</subject><subject>Respiratory Medicine/COPD and Allied Disorders</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Down-Regulation of the Canonical Wnt &#x003b2;-Catenin Pathway in the Airway Epithelium of Healthy Smokers and Smokers with COPD</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Smoking Suppresses Wnt Pathway</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Rui</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>Joumana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Guoqing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hassan</surname><given-names>Ibrahim</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Strulovici-Barel</surname><given-names>Yael</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hackett</surname><given-names>Neil R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Crystal</surname><given-names>Ronald G.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>&#x0002a;</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><addr-line>Department of Genetic Medicine, Weill Cornell Medical College, New York, New York, United States of America</addr-line></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Koenigshoff</surname><given-names>Melanie</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Comprehensive Pneumology Center, Germany</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">&#x0002a; E-mail: <email>geneticmedicine@med.cornell.edu</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: RW NH RGC. Performed the experiments: RW JA GW IH. Analyzed the data: RW JA GW YSB NH RGC. Wrote the paper: RW RGC.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>7</day><month>4</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>4</issue><elocation-id>e14793</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>3</month><year>2010</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>2</month><year>2011</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Wang et al. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</copyright-statement></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>The Wnt pathway mediates differentiation of epithelial tissues&#x0003b; depending on the tissue types, Wnt can either drive or inhibit the differentiation process. We hypothesized that key genes in the Wnt pathway are suppressed in the human airway epithelium under the stress of cigarette smoking, a stress associated with dysregulation of the epithelial differentiated state.</p></sec><sec><title>Methodology/Principal Findings</title><p>Microarrays were used to assess the expression of Wnt-related genes in the small airway epithelium (SAE) obtained via bronchoscopy and brushing of healthy nonsmokers, healthy smokers, and smokers with COPD. Thirty-three of 56 known Wnt-related genes were expressed in the SAE. Wnt pathway downstream mediators &#x003b2;-catenin and the transcription factor 7-like 1 were down-regulated in healthy smokers and smokers with COPD, as were many Wnt target genes. Among the extracellular regulators that suppress the Wnt pathway, secreted frizzled-related protein 2 (SFRP2), was up-regulated 4.3-fold in healthy smokers and 4.9-fold in COPD smokers, an observation confirmed by TaqMan Real-time PCR, Western analysis and immunohistochemistry. Finally, cigarette smoke extract mediated up-regulation of SFRP2 and down-regulation of Wnt target genes in airway epithelial cells <italic>in vitro</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions/Significance</title><p>Smoking down-regulates the Wnt pathway in the human airway epithelium. In the context that Wnt pathway plays an important role in differentiation of epithelial tissues, the down-regulation of Wnt pathway may contribute to the dysregulation of airway epithelium differentiation observed in smoking-related airway disorders.</p></sec></abstract><counts><page-count count="14"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>The human airway epithelium, a pseudostratified layer of cells derived from the endoderm, serves as a physical barrier against inhaled pathogens, xenobiotics, and other noxious substances in the environment <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Knight1">&#x0005b;1&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Crystal1">&#x0005b;2&#x0005d;</xref>. The normal airway epithelium has the capacity of regeneration and repair <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Bishop1">&#x0005b;3&#x0005d;</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Rock1">&#x0005b;7&#x0005d;</xref>. Of the major cell types, the airway epithelial progenitor cells are in the basal cell population, cells capable of self renewal and differentiation into columnar cells and eventually, the differentiated secretory and ciliated cell populations that function to defend the airway against environmental stress <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Bishop1">&#x0005b;3&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Rock1">&#x0005b;7&#x0005d;</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Snyder1">&#x0005b;9&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><p>There are several lines of evidence that demonstrate controlling this differentiation process, in part, is through the canonical Wnt/&#x003b2;-catenin signaling pathway <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-DeLanghe1">&#x0005b;10&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Pongracz1">&#x0005b;11&#x0005d;</xref>. The canonical Wnt pathway plays a central role in lung development and is critical for generation of the lung epithelium <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-DeLanghe1">&#x0005b;10&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Mucenski1">&#x0005b;12&#x0005d;</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Shu1">&#x0005b;14&#x0005d;</xref>. Components of the canonical Wnt signaling pathway are expressed in embryonic and adult lung cell lines, as well as in the developing lung in a specific, spatio-temporal pattern <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Pongracz1">&#x0005b;11&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Li1">&#x0005b;15&#x0005d;</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Weidenfeld1">&#x0005b;17&#x0005d;</xref>. When canonical Wnt signaling is active, the pathway maintains cells in a low differentiation state <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Korinek1">&#x0005b;18&#x0005d;</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Sato1">&#x0005b;23&#x0005d;</xref>. However, when the canonical Wnt pathway is suppressed, undifferentiated progenitor cells are allowed to proceed toward differentiation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Korinek1">&#x0005b;18&#x0005d;</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Sato1">&#x0005b;23&#x0005d;</xref>. Modulation of Wnt expression in embryonic and adult mouse lung suggests that the Wnt pathway is important for cell fate decisions and differentiation of lung cell type <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Shu2">&#x0005b;24&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Li2">&#x0005b;25&#x0005d;</xref>. The agonists of the canonical Wnt/&#x003b2;-catenin pathway include multiple Wnt proteins that function through frizzled receptors to up-regulate &#x003b2;-catenin, resulting in activation of the T cell factor (LEF1, TCF7, TCF7L1, TCF7L2) transcription factor family <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-VanScoyk1">&#x0005b;26&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-vanAmerongen1">&#x0005b;27&#x0005d;</xref>. The extracellular antagonists of Wnt signaling are the secreted fizzled-related (SFRP) and the Dickkopf (DKK) family of proteins <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Kawano1">&#x0005b;28&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Niehrs1">&#x0005b;29&#x0005d;</xref>. When the SFRPs and/or DKKs are up-regulated, the Wnt pathway is suppressed, allowing differentiation to proceed <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Kawano1">&#x0005b;28&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Niehrs1">&#x0005b;29&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><p>Based on this background, we hypothesized that the canonical Wnt/&#x003b2;-catenin signaling pathway may be deranged in the airway epithelium when it is in a state of constant stress such as in cigarette smokers. To assess this hypothesis, we used microarrays to survey the mRNA levels of the canonical Wnt/&#x003b2;-catenin pathway in the small airway epithelium, the initial site of smoking-induced lung disease <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Hogg1">&#x0005b;30&#x0005d;</xref>. Pure populations of small airway epithelium were obtained by fiberoptic bronchoscopy of healthy nonsmokers, healthy smokers, and smokers with established COPD. The data demonstrate that most components of the Wnt/&#x003b2;-catenin pathway are expressed in the small airway epithelium. Interestingly, the downstream mediators &#x003b2;-catenin and the TCF transcription factor TCF7L1, as well as several downstream Wnt pathway target genes, are down-regulated in healthy smokers and smokers with COPD. Consistent with the down-regulation of Wnt/&#x003b2;-catenin pathway associated with smoking, the mRNA and protein levels of the Wnt inhibitor secreted frizzled-related protein 2 were greatly up-regulated in the small airway epithelium of healthy smokers and smokers with COPD, with expression primarily in ciliated cells. Finally, <italic>in vitro</italic> exposure of lung epithelium to cigarette smoke extract demonstrated similar results, with up-regulation of SFRP2 and down-regulation of the Wnt pathway. Together, these results show that smoking is associated with abnormal regulation of the Wnt pathway in the airway epithelium, an observation consistent with the disordered epithelial differentiation observed in smoking-related airway disorders.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Study Population</title><p>All individuals were evaluated at the Weill Cornell NIH Clinical and Translational Science Center and Department of Genetic Medicine Clinical Research Facility using protocols approved by the Weill Cornell Medical College Institutional Review Board. All subjects provided written consent before any study procedures were undertaken. Healthy nonsmokers and healthy smokers were characterized on the basis of clinical history and physical examination, routine blood screening tests, chest X-ray, electrocardiogram, urinalysis, and pulmonary function testing. Current smoking status was confirmed by history, venous carboxyhemoglobin levels, and urinalysis for nicotine levels and its derivative cotinine. Smokers with established COPD were defined according to Global Initiative for Chronic Obstructive Lung Disease criteria <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Pauwels1">&#x0005b;31&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Rabe1">&#x0005b;32&#x0005d;</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Collection of Small Airway Epithelium</title><p>Small airway epithelium was collected using flexible bronchoscopy as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Harvey1">&#x0005b;33&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Tilley1">&#x0005b;34&#x0005d;</xref>. Smokers were asked not to smoke the evening prior to the procedure. A flexible bronchoscope (Pentax, EB-1530T3) was advanced to the desired bronchus after achieving mild sedation and anesthesia of vocal cords. Small airway samples were collected from 10<sup>th</sup> to 12<sup>th</sup> order bronchi using methods previously described. The airway epithelial cells were subsequently collected separately in 5 ml of LHC8 medium (GIBO, Grand Island, NY). An aliquot of this was used for cytology and differential cell count and the remainder was processed immediately for RNA extraction. Total cell counts were obtained using a hemocytometer while differential cell counts were determined on sedimented cells prepared by centrifugation (Cytospin 11, Shandon Instruments, Pittsburg, PA) and stained with DiffQuik (Baxter Healthcare, Miami, FL).</p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>RNA Extraction and Microarray Processing</title><p>Microarray analysis was performed using Affymetrix (Santa Clara, CA) microarray HG-U133 Plus 2.0 (54,675 probe sets) and associated protocols. Total RNA was extracted from epithelial cells using TRIzol (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA) followed by DNAnase (Qiagen, Valencia, CA) to remove residual DNA. An aliquot of each RNA sample was run on an Agilent Bioanalyzer (Agilent Technologies, Palo Alto, CA) to visualize and quantify the degree of RNA integrity. The concentration was determined using a NanoDrop ND-1000 spectrophotometer (NanoDrop Technologies, Wilmington, DE). Double-stranded complementary DNA was synthesized from 3 &#x000b5;g of total RNA using the GeneChip One-Cycle cDNA Synthesis Kit, followed by a cleanup step using GeneChip Sample Cleanup Module. Next, an <italic>in vitro</italic> transcription (IVT) reaction was performed with GeneChip IVT Labeling Kit after which further cleanup was carried out and quantification of the resulting biotin-labeled cRNA by spectrophotometry (all reagents from Affymetrix). Hybridizations to test chips and when permissible, to the microarrays, were conducted according to Affymetrix protocols. The Affymetrix GeneChip Fluidics Station 450 was used for processing the arrays with appropriate reagents/washes, prior to scanning with an Affymetrix GeneChip Scanner 3000 7G (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://affymetrix.com/support/technical/manual/expression_manual.affx">http://affymetrix.com/support/technical/manual/expression_manual.affx</ext-link>).</p><p>Captured images were analyzed using Microarray Suite version 5.0 (MAS 5.0) algorithm (Affymetrix) as previously described. Samples used for analysis were required to satisfy quality control criteria including: (1) RNA Integrity Number (RIN) &#x02265;7.0&#x0003b; (2) 3&#x02032;/5&#x02032; ratio for GAPDH&#x02264;3&#x0003b; and (3) scaling factor &#x02264;10.0 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Raman1">&#x0005b;35&#x0005d;</xref>. This data were normalized using GeneSpring version 7.3 software (Agilent Technologies, Palo Alto, CA) per array, by dividing the raw data by the 50<sup>th</sup> percentile of all measurements. The data sets were assessed for expression of 56 Wnt signaling pathway genes and 55 Wnt target genes (based on the Wnt homepage, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.stanford.edu/~rnusse/wntwindow.html">http://www.stanford.edu/~rnusse/wntwindow.html</ext-link>) using criteria of present (P call) of &#x0003e;20&#x00025; of healthy nonsmokers.</p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>TaqMan RT-PCR Confirmation of Microarray Expression Levels</title><p>To confirm the microarray findings, TaqMan real-time RT-PCR was performed on RNA samples from the small airway samples of healthy nonsmokers, healthy smokers and smokers with COPD (n&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;9 each, except for &#x003b2;-catenin, n&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;11 each) that had been used for HG-U133 Plus 2.0 microarray analysis. First, cDNA was synthesized from 2 &#x000b5;g RNA in a 100 &#x000b5;l reaction volume, using the TaqMan Reverse Transcriptase Reaction Kit (Applied Biosystems), with random hexamers as primers. Dilutions of 1&#x02236;10 and 1&#x02236;100 were made from each sample and triplicate wells were run for each dilution. TaqMan PCR reactions were carried out using primers (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA), and 2 &#x000b5;l of cDNA was used in each 25 &#x000b5;l reaction volume. The endogenous control was 18S ribosomal RNA and relative expression levels were determined using the &#x00394;&#x00394;Ct method (Applied Biosystems). The rRNA probe was labeled with VIC and the probe for each gene of interest (&#x003b2;-catenin, TCF7L1, SOX9, MMP7) was labeled with FAM. The PCR reactions were run in an Applied Biosystems Sequence Detection System 7500.</p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title>Western Analysis</title><p>Western analysis was used to quantitatively assess SFRP2 protein expression in small airway brushing samples from healthy nonsmokers, healthy smokers and smokers with COPD. Red blood cells were lysed (red blood cell lysis buffer, eBioscience, San Diego, CA), and proteins were extracted using RIPA buffer (Sigma-Aldrich, Saint Louis, MO) following the manufacture's instructions. Protein concentrations were assessed using a bicinchoninic acid (BCA) protein concentration kit (Pierce, Rockford, IL). Equal concentration of protein mixed with NuPAGE LDS Sample Buffer and NuPAGE Reducing Agent was heated at 70&#x000b0;C for 10 min. Then samples were loaded on NuPAGE 4 to12&#x00025; Bis-Tris Gel (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA). Protein electrophoresis was carried out at 200 V, 1 hr, 23&#x000b0;C. Sample proteins were transferred (30 V, 1 hr, 4&#x000b0;C) to a 0.2 &#x000b5;m PVDF membrane (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA) in NuPAGE transfer buffer. The membranes were then blocked with 5&#x00025; non-fat milk in Phosphate Buffered Saline with 0.1&#x00025; tween-20 (PBST) for 1 hr. The membranes were incubated with primary rabbit polyclonal anti-SFRP2 antibodies (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Santa Cruz, CA) at 1&#x02236;200 dilution 4&#x000b0;C overnight. Detection was performed using secondary horseradish peroxidase-labeled goat anti-rabbit antibody (1&#x02236;2,000 dilution, Santa Cruz Biotechnology) and then enhanced chemiluminescent reagent system (GE Healthcare, Pittsburgh, PA). To assess the Western analysis quantitatively, the film was digitally imaged, maintaining exposure within the linear range of detection. The contrast was inverted, the pixel intensity of each band determined, and the background pixel intensity for a negative area of the film of identical size subtracted using MetaMorph image analysis software (Universal Imaging, Downingtown, PA). The membrane was subsequently stripped and reincubated with monoclonal anti-&#x003b2;-actin antibody (Sigma-Aldrich, Saint Louis, MO) as a control for equal protein concentration.</p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title>Localization of SFRP2 in the Airway Epithelium</title><p>To determine the distribution of SFRP2 expression in small airway epithelial cells, cytospin preparation of bronchial brushes obtained from the small airway epithelium of healthy nonsmoker, healthy smokers and smokers with COPD were assessed by SFRP2-specific immunofluorescence. Sections were fixed in 4&#x00025; paraformaldehyde for 15 min, and washed twice in PBS. Samples were blocked in normal goat serum to reduce background staining and then incubated with the rabbit anti-human SFRP2 primary antibody (Atlas Antibodies, Stockholm, Sweden) diluted 1&#x02236;250 and rabbit IgG (Jackson Immunoresearch, West Grove, PA) as the isotype control at 4&#x000b0;C overnight. Goat anti-rabbit Cy3 conjugated AffiniPure IgG (Jackson ImmunoResearch) at 1&#x02236;50 dilution was used as a secondary antibody for SFRP2. Nuclei were counter stained with 4&#x02032;, 6-diamidino-2-phenylindole (DAPI, 1&#x02236;2,000 dilution&#x0003b; Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA). Images were captured using an Olympus IX 70 fluorescence microscope with 60-fold magnification. Images were analyzed using MetaMorph software (Universal Imaging Corporation, Downingtown, PA).</p><p>As a further assessment at the morphologic level, bronchial biopsies from large airway of healthy nonsmokers, healthy smokers and smokers with COPD were assessed by immunofluorescence for SFRP2. Sections were deparaffinized and rehydrated through a series of xylenes and alcohol. Further staining procedures were as described above.</p><p>Colocalizations of SFRP2 with a ciliated cell-specific marker &#x003b2;-tubulin IV, secretory cell-specific marker mucin 5AC and neuroendocrine-specific marker chromogranin A were also performed with cytospin preparations and biopsies. The following antibodies were used: for &#x003b2;-tubulin IV, mouse monoclonal anti-human &#x003b2;-tubulin IV (1&#x02236;2000&#x0003b; Biogenex, San Ramon, CA) and mouse IgG as the isotype control (Sigma, St Louis, MO)&#x0003b; for mucin 5AC, mouse monoclonal (CLH2) anti-human mucin 5AC (1&#x02236;50&#x0003b; Vector Laboratories, Burlingame, CA) and mouse IgG as the isotype control (Sigma, St Louis, MO)&#x0003b; for chromogranin A, mouse monoclonal (LK2H10&#x0002b;PHE5) anti-human chromogranin (1&#x02236;500 dilution&#x0003b; Thermo Scientific, Waltham, MA) and mouse IgG as the isotype control (Sigma, St Louis, MO). Following incubation with the primary antibodies, goat anti-rabbit Cy5 (Jackson ImmunoResearch) was used as a secondary antibody for SFPR2 and goat anti-mouse Cy3 (Jackson ImmunoResearch) was used as a secondary antibody for &#x003b2;-tubulin IV, mucin 5AC and chromogranin A. Further staining procedures were as described above.</p></sec><sec id="s2g"><title>Down-regulation of Wnt Pathway Target Genes in Human Small Airway Epithelial Cells Exposed to Cigarette Smoke Extract <italic>In Vitro</italic></title><p>Aqueous cigarette cell extract (CSE) was generated from the combustion of 1 cigarette (Marlboro Red) bubbled through 12.5 ml of culture medium <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Ning1">&#x0005b;36&#x0005d;</xref>. This medium, defined as &#x0201c;100&#x00025; CSE,&#x0201d; was adjusted to pH 7.4 and filtered through a 0.22 &#x000b5;m filter. Different concentrations of CSE diluted with the culture medium were employed, ranging from 0.1 to 20&#x00025;. The human airway epithelial cell line 16HBE <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Cozens1">&#x0005b;37&#x0005d;</xref> was exposed to freshly prepared CSE for 72 hr. Cell viability was assessed by 3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyltetrazolium bromide (MTT) assay (Roche Applied Science) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Berridge1">&#x0005b;38&#x0005d;</xref>. Viability was expressed as percentage of the values (corresponding to 100&#x00025;) of untreated cells. SFRP2, MMP7, SOX9 gene expression was assessed with TaqMan real-time PCR.</p></sec><sec id="s2h"><title>Wnt Reporter Assay</title><p>HEK293 cells were transiently transfected with the reporter construct Topflash or Fopflash (kindly provided by R. Moon, University of Washington, Seattle) using Lipofectamine LTX (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Jaluria1">&#x0005b;39&#x0005d;</xref>. The Topflash construct contains 8 Tcf/Lef binding sites upstream of a minimal TA viral promoter and the firefly luciferase cDNA. The Fopflash construct is identical except that it contains mutated copies of TCf/Lef binding sites and is used as a control for measuring nonspecific activation of the reporter construct. Expression of Renilla luciferase provides an internal control value to which expression of the experimental firefly luciferase reporter gene will be normalized. The experiment was divided into 6 groups: Topflash plus CMV-renilla&#x0003b; Fopflash plus CMV-renilla&#x0003b; Topflash plus CMV-renilla plus WNT1&#x0003b; Fopflash plus CMV-renilla plus WNT1&#x0003b; Topflash plus CMV-renilla plus WNT1 plus SFRP2&#x0003b; Fopflash plus CMV-renilla plus WNT1 plus SFRP2. After 48 hr, luciferase activities were determined using the Dual Luciferase Assay System (Promega) on a tube luminometer (Berthold detection systems).</p></sec><sec id="s2i"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>HG-U133 Plus 2.0 microarrays were analyzed using GeneSpring software. Average expression values were calculated from normalized expression levels for healthy nonsmokers, healthy smokers, and smokers with COPD. p values were obtained using Benjamini-Hochberg correction to limit the false positive rate. Statistical comparisons between continuous variables were calculated using an unpaired, two-tailed t-test with unequal variance. Statistical comparisons for categorical data were achieved using Chi-squared test. A p value&#x0003c;0.05 was considered significant. p values for TaqMan data were calculated using two-tailed Student's t-test.</p></sec><sec id="s2j"><title>Web Deposition of Data</title><p>All MIAME-compliant microarray data have been deposited in the Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO) site (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo</ext-link>), which is curated by the National Center for Bioinformatics. Accession number for small airways HG-U133 Plus 2.0 is GSE19407.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec id="s3a"><title>Study Population</title><p>Small airway samples from a total of 127 individuals, including 47 healthy nonsmokers, 58 healthy smokers and 22 smokers with established COPD were analyzed with microarray HG-U133 Plus 2.0 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0014793-t001">Table 1</xref>). There were no differences with respect to gender among the groups (p&#x0003e;0.3), but the COPD smokers were older than the other groups (p&#x0003c;0.05). There were no differences among groups with regard to ancestral background (p&#x0003e;0.3). All individuals were HIV negative. Smokers had urine nicotine and cotinine and venous blood carboxyhemoglobin levels confirming their current smoking status.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0014793-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0014793.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Demographics of the Study Population and Biologic Samples<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">1</xref>.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0014793-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0014793.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameter</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy nonsmokers</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy smokers</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">COPD smokers<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">2</xref></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex (male/female)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33/14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38/20</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18/4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (yr)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.9&#x000b1;11.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.9&#x000b1;7.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.5&#x000b1;8.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Race (B/W/O)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">3</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23/18/6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35/14/9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/9/5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking history (pack-yr)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.5&#x000b1;16.6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.9&#x000b1;28.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urine nicotine (ng/ml)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1298&#x000b1;1676</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1114&#x000b1;1132</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urine cotinine (ng/ml)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1246&#x000b1;965</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1357&#x000b1;598</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blood carboxyhemoglobin (&#x00025;)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4&#x000b1;0.7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8&#x000b1;1.9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0&#x000b1;2.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pulmonary function parameters<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">4</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FVC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">107&#x000b1;14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">109&#x000b1;13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97&#x000b1;20</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FEV1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">106&#x000b1;15</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">107&#x000b1;14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74&#x000b1;21</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FEV1/FVC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82&#x000b1;6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80&#x000b1;5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61&#x000b1;9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TLC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">101&#x000b1;13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100&#x000b1;12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">102&#x000b1;22</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DLCO</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99&#x000b1;15</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94&#x000b1;11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75&#x000b1;19</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gold stage (I/II/III)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">2</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9/11/2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medication use</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b2;-agonist</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anticholinergic</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inhaled corticosteroid</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Epithelial cells<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">5</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number recovered&#x000d7;10<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">6</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.4&#x000b1;2.9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.2&#x000b1;3.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.7&#x000b1;3.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x00025; epithelial cells<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">6</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.3&#x000b1;1.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.1&#x000b1;1.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.9&#x000b1;1.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x00025; inflammatory cells</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7&#x000b1;1.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8&#x000b1;1.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1&#x000b1;1.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Differential cell count</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ciliated (&#x00025;)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74&#x000b1;7.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.7&#x000b1;12.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.5&#x000b1;10.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Secretory (&#x00025;)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.7&#x000b1;3.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.1&#x000b1;4.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.9&#x000b1;5.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Basal (&#x00025;)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.1&#x000b1;5.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.7&#x000b1;6.6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.9&#x000b1;6.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Undifferentiated (&#x00025;)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.3&#x000b1;3.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.9&#x000b1;6.6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.6&#x000b1;3.7</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label>1</label><p>Data are presented as mean &#x000b1; standard deviation.</p></fn><fn id="nt102"><label>2</label><p>Smokers with &#x0201c;established COPD&#x0201d; defined by the GOLD criteria <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Pauwels1">&#x0005b;31&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Rabe1">&#x0005b;32&#x0005d;</xref>&#x0003b; the COPD smoker group included: GOLD I n&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;9, GOLD II n&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;11, and GOLD III n&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;2.</p></fn><fn id="nt103"><label>3</label><p>B&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;black, W&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;white, O&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;other.</p></fn><fn id="nt104"><label>4</label><p>Pulmonary function testing parameters are given as &#x00025; of predicted value with the exception of FEV1/FVC, which is reported as &#x00025; observed&#x0003b; FVC - forced vital capacity, FEV1 - forced expiratory volume in 1 sec, TLC - total lung capacity, DLCO - diffusing capacity. For individuals with COPD, FVC, FEV1, and FEV1/FVC are post-bronchodilator values.</p></fn><fn id="nt105"><label>5</label><p>Small airway epithelium.</p></fn><fn id="nt106"><label>6</label><p>As a &#x00025; of small airway epithelium recovered.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3b"><title>Sampling of Airway Epithelium</title><p>Airway epithelial cells were obtained by fiberoptic bronchoscopy and brushing of small (10<sup>th</sup> to 12<sup>th</sup> order) airways. The number of cells recovered averaged from 2.1 to 21&#x000d7;10<sup>6</sup>, with an average of &#x0003e;96&#x00025; epithelium (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0014793-t001">Table 1</xref>). The various categories of airway epithelial cells were, as expected, from the small airway epithelium <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Harvey1">&#x0005b;33&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Tilley1">&#x0005b;34&#x0005d;</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s3c"><title>Expression of Wnt Signaling Pathway Genes in Small Epithelium of Healthy Nonsmokers, Healthy Smokers and Smokers with COPD</title><p>The genome-wide microarrays were used to analyze the gene expression profiles of canonical Wnt signaling components at the mRNA level in the small airway epithelium of healthy nonsmokers, healthy smokers, and smokers with established COPD. In the small airway epithelium of healthy nonsmokers, 33 of 56 (60&#x00025;) genes in the Wnt pathway were expressed (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0014793.s001">Table S1</xref>). These expressed genes included Wnt extracellular ligands (WNT3, 4, 7B, 9A, 10A), frizzled receptors (FZD1, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8), co-receptors (LRP5, LRP6), extracellular inhibitors (SFRP2, DKK1, DKK3, DKK4), intracellular mediators (&#x003b2;-catenin, GSK-3B, DVL1, 2, 3, AES, APC1, AXIN1, AXIN2, FRAT1, FRAT2), nuclear transcription factors (TCF7, TCF7L1, TCF7L2, LEF1). For Wnt target genes, 27 out of 55 genes are present in small airway epithelium, including MMP7, CLDN1, VEGFA, CCND1, SOX9, ID2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0014793-g001">Figure 1A</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0014793.s001">Table S1</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0014793-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0014793.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>The Wnt pathway expression in the small airway epithelium of human healthy nonsmokers.</title><p><bold>A</bold>. Schematic of the pathway, showing which (in bold) ligands, soluble antagonists, receptors, co-receptors, intracellular activators, transcription factors and downstream effectors are expressed. <bold>B</bold>. Gene expression in canonical Wnt &#x003b2;-catenin pathway in healthy nonsmokers in small airway epithelium. Small airway epithelium from 47 normal nonsmokers were analyzed using the HG-U133 Plus 2.0 array and expression level normalized by chip only is plotted. Error bars represent the standard error.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0014793.g001"/></fig><p>In healthy nonsmokers the relative expression of WNT9A was the most highly expressed Wnt ligand, with average expression approximately 3.3-fold greater than WNT3, and 4.7-fold greater than WNT10A (both p&#x0003c;0.0001). For receptors, the most highly expressed receptor was FZD6, which was expressed 44.4-fold higher than FZD7 (p&#x0003c;0.0001), the lowest expressed receptor. For transcription factors in the Wnt pathway, TCF7 was the downstream gene most highly expressed in the small airway samples, 2.3-fold more highly expressed than TCF7L1, 4.4-fold more than TCF7L2, and 2.7-fold more than LEF1 (p&#x0003c;0.0001, all comparisons).</p><p>Compared to healthy nonsmokers, the Wnt intracellular modulators, transcription factors and target genes were down-regulated in healthy smokers and smokers with established COPD. &#x003b2;-catenin, a central molecule in the Wnt signaling pathway, was down-regulated 1.5-fold in healthy smokers and 1.8-fold in smokers with COPD (both comparisons, p&#x0003c;0.05, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0014793-g002">Figure 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0014793-t002">Table 2</xref>). Consistent with this observation, TCF7L1, a transcription factor in Wnt pathway, was down-regulated 1.7-fold in smokers and 1.7-fold in smokers with established COPD (p&#x0003c;0.01, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0014793-g002">Figure 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0014793-t002">Table 2</xref>). Wnt target genes, including MMP7, VEGFA, CLDN1, CCND1, SOX9, RHOU, were also down-regulated in healthy smokers and smokers with COPD compared to healthy nonsmokers (p&#x0003c;0.05 for VEGFA and p&#x0003c;0.01 for the other genes&#x0003b; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0014793-g002">Figure 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0014793-t003">Table 3</xref>). The network of the WNT/&#x003b2;-catenin genes in healthy smokers and smokers with COPD compared to healthy nonsmokers were analyzed with Ingenuity Pathway Analysis (Ingenuity Systems, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ingenuity.com">http://www.ingenuity.com</ext-link>&#x0003b; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0014793.s002">Figure S1</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0014793-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0014793.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Comparison of the relative expression of the Wnt pathway downstream and target genes in healthy nonsmokers (n&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;47), healthy smokers (n&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;58), and smokers with COPD (n&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;22).</title><p>Analysis was carried out with HG-U133 plus 2.0 microarrays normalized by chip and gene. Each bar represents mean expression with standard error&#x0003b; &#x0002a; p&#x0003c;0.05 compared to healthy nonsmokers, &#x0002a; &#x0002a; p&#x0003c;0.01 compared to healthy nonsmokers.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0014793.g002"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone-0014793-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0014793.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Small Airway Epithelium Wnt Pathway Genes with Suppressed Expression in Healthy Smokers and COPD Smokers Compared to Healthy Nonsmokers<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">1</xref>.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0014793-t002-2" xlink:href="pone.0014793.t002"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Category</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene symbol</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene title</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Probeset ID</td><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">P call (&#x00025;)</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Smoker/nonsmoker</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">COPD/nonsmoker</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nonsmoker</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoker</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">COPD smoker</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fold-change</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p value</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fold-change</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p value</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Receptors</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FZD1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">frizzled homolog 1 (Drosophila)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">204451&#x0005f;at</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FZD4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">frizzled homolog 4 (Drosophila)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">218665&#x0005f;at</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.15</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.23</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FZD6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">frizzled homolog 6 (Drosophila)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">203987&#x0005f;at</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.16</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FZD8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">frizzled homolog 8 (Drosophila)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">224325&#x0005f;at</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.54</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.41</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intracellular modulators</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FRAT1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">frequently rearranged in advanced T-cell lymphomas</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">219889&#x0005f;at</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.22</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FRAT2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">frequently rearranged in advanced T-cell lymphomas 2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">209864&#x0005f;at</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.34</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.22</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DVL1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">dishevelled, dsh homolog 1 (Drosophila)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">203230&#x0005f;at</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.04</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DVL3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">dishevelled, dsh homolog 3 (Drosophila)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201908&#x0005f;at</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.24</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.18</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b2;-catenin</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">catenin (cadherin-associated protein), beta 1, 88 kDa</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1554411&#x0005f;at</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.46</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.84</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AXIN2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">axin 2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">222696&#x0005f;at</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.16</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.22</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transcription factors</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TCF7L1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">transcription factor 7-like 1 (T-cell specific, HMG-box)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">221016&#x0005f;s&#x0005f;at</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.71</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.72</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt107"><label>1</label><p>NS, not significant.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone-0014793-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0014793.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Small Airway Epithelium Wnt Pathway Target Genes with Suppressed Expression in Healthy Smokers and COPD Smokers Compared to Healthy Nonsmokers<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">1</xref>.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0014793-t003-3" xlink:href="pone.0014793.t003"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene symbol</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene title</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Probe set ID</td><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">P call (&#x00025;)</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Smoker/nonsmoker</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">COPD/nonsmoker</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-smoker</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoker</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">COPD smoker</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fold-change</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p value</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fold-change</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p value</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SOX9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SRY (sex determining region Y)-box 9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">202936&#x0005f;s&#x0005f;at</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.88</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2.29</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RHOU</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ras homolog gene family, member U</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">223168&#x0005f;at</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.60</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.88</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RUNX2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">runt-related transcription factor 2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">232231&#x0005f;at</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.51</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.32</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JAG1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">jagged 1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">209099&#x0005f;x&#x0005f;at</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.33</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.32</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCND1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cyclin D1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">208712&#x0005f;at</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.34</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.39</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CLDN1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">claudin 1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">218182&#x0005f;s&#x0005f;at</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.37</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.70</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CDH1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cadherin 1, type 1, E-cadherin (epithelial)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201131&#x0005f;s&#x0005f;at</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.25</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AXIN2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">axin 2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">222696&#x0005f;at</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.16</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.22</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MMP7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">matrix metallopeptidase 7 (matrilysin, uterine)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">204259&#x0005f;at</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.66</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2.62</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ID2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">inhibitor of DNA binding 2, dominant negative helix-loop-helix protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201565&#x0005f;s&#x0005f;at</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.16</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VEGFA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">vascular endothelial growth factor A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">210512&#x0005f;s&#x0005f;at</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.58</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SOX2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SRY (sex determining region Y)-box 2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">228038&#x0005f;at</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.07</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt108"><label>1</label><p>NS, not significant.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Modulation of the Wnt signaling pathway in the small airway epithelium of healthy smokers and smokers with COPD compared to healthy nonsmokers was verified using TaqMan PCR for selected central genes in the pathway (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0014793.s003">Figure S2</xref>). Consistent with microarray data, &#x003b2;-catenin was down-regulated 1.7-fold in smokers compared to nonsmokers, and 1.9-fold in smokers with COPD compared with healthy nonsmokers (p&#x0003c;0.05). For transcription factors, TCF7L1 was confirmed to be down-regulated in healthy smokers and smokers with COPD compared to healthy nonsmokers (p&#x0003c;0.05). Wnt signaling pathway target genes were also confirmed to be down-regulated. MMP7 expression decreased 7.5-fold in healthy smokers and 12.9-fold in smokers with COPD compared to healthy nonsmokers (p&#x0003c;0.05). SOX9, another Wnt target gene, was also confirmed to be down-regulated in the small airway epithelium of healthy smokers and smokers with COPD compared to healthy nonsmokers (3.9-fold for smokers <italic>vs</italic> nonsmokers and 3.2-fold for smokers with COPD <italic>vs</italic> nonsmokers, both p&#x0003c;0.01).</p></sec><sec id="s3d"><title>Expression of SFRP2 in the Small Airway Epithelium of Healthy Nonsmokers, Healthy Smokers and Smoker with COPD</title><p>The <italic>in vivo</italic> gene expression data showed that Wnt signaling pathway was down-regulated in healthy smokers and smokers with COPD compared to healthy nonsmokers in the small airway epithelial cells. As a possible mechanism to explain this down-regulation, we hypothesized that there may be smoking-induced up-regulation of the SFRP and/or DKK family of extracellular Wnt pathway inhibitors. To assess this, we analyzed Wnt inhibitors expressed in human small airway epithelium including, SFRP2, DKK1, DKK3 and DKK4. Interestingly, among these 4 inhibitors, SFRP2 showed significant gene expression change between healthy smokers and healthy nonsmokers, with SFRP2 up-regulation 4.3-fold in healthy smokers and 4.9-fold in smokers with COPD compared with healthy nonsmokers (p&#x0003c;0.0001, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0014793-g003">Figure 3</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0014793-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0014793.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Comparison of the relative expression of the Wnt pathway inhibitors in healthy nonsmokers (n&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;47), healthy smokers (n&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;58), and smokers with COPD (n&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;22).</title><p>Analysis was carried out with HG-U133 plus 2.0 microarrays. Each bar represents mean expression with standard error&#x0003b; p values are represented in brackets above the bars.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0014793.g003"/></fig><p>To confirm the results obtained from microarrays, anti-SFRP2 immunofluorescence and Western analysis were utilized. First, anti-SFRP2 immunofluorescence was carried out on cytospin preparations of small airway epithelial cells obtained from healthy nonsmokers, healthy smokers and smokers with COPD. In all samples, SFRP2 protein expression was detected specifically in ciliated cells&#x0003b; other cell types, including secretory cells, undifferentiated cells and basal cells, did not show obvious staining (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0014793-g004">Figure 4</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0014793-g005">Figure 5</xref>). Consistent with the up-regulation of SFRP2 mRNA, qualitative immunofluorescence assessment suggested that SFRP2 protein was up-regulated in the healthy smokers and COPD smokers. Second, as further confirmation, SFRP2 expression was also observed to be up-regulated in ciliated cells of large airway biopsies (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0014793-g006">Figure 6</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0014793-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0014793.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Co-localization of SFRP2 and ciliated cell specific marker &#x003b2;-tubulin IV.</title><p>For <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0014793-g004">Figures 4<bold>A&#x02013;I</bold></xref>, Cytospin preparations of airway epithelium from a healthy smoker were stained with antibodies against SFRP2 (green), &#x003b2;-tubulin IV (red), Mucin 5AC (red) and chromogranin A (red). <bold>A&#x02013;C</bold>. Colocalization of SFRP2 and &#x003b2;-tubulin IV&#x0003b; <bold>D&#x02013;F</bold>. Colocalization of SFRP2 and mucin 5AC&#x0003b; <bold>G&#x02013;I</bold>. Colocalization of SFRP2 and chromogranin A. For <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0014793-g004">Figure 4<bold>J&#x02013;K</bold></xref>, biopsies from a healthy smoker were stained with antibodies against SFRP2 (red) &#x003b2;- tubulin IV (green). <bold>J</bold>. IgG controls of SFRP2 and &#x003b2;-tubulin IV&#x0003b; and <bold>K</bold>. SFRP2 and &#x003b2;-tubulin IV co-localization.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0014793.g004"/></fig><fig id="pone-0014793-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0014793.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Immunofluorescent assessment of SFRP2 expression in cytospin preparations of brushed small airway epithelium.</title><p>Small airway epithelial cell cytopreparations of healthy nonsmokers, healthy smokers and smokers with COPD were stained with anti-SFRP2 followed by a Cy3 conjugated secondary antibody (shown in red). Nuclei were stained with DAPI (shown in blue) <bold>A&#x02013;D</bold>. Healthy nonsmokers. <bold>A</bold>. IgG control&#x0003b; <bold>B&#x02013;D</bold>. Examples of anti-SFRP2. <bold>E&#x02013;H</bold>. Healthy smokers. <bold>E</bold>. IgG control&#x0003b; <bold>F&#x02013;H</bold>. Examples of anti-SFRP2. <bold>I&#x02013;L</bold>. Smokers with COPD&#x0003b; <bold>I</bold>. IgG Control. <bold>J&#x02013;L</bold>. Examples of anti-SFRP2. Bar&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;10 &#x000b5;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0014793.g005"/></fig><fig id="pone-0014793-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0014793.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Immunofluorescent assessment of SFRP2 expression in the endobronchial biopsies from large airway epithelium.</title><p>Endobronchial biopsies from large airway of healthy nonsmoker, healthy smokers and smokers with COPD were stained with anti-SFRP2 followed by a Cy3 conjugated secondary antibody (shown in red). Nuclei were stained with DAPI (shown in blue). <bold>A&#x02013;D</bold>. Healthy nonsmokers. <bold>A</bold>. IgG control&#x0003b; <bold>B&#x02013;D</bold>. Examples of anti-SFRP2. <bold>E&#x02013;H</bold>. Healthy smokers. <bold>E</bold>. IgG control&#x0003b; <bold>F&#x02013;H</bold>. Examples of anti-SFRP2. <bold>I&#x02013;L</bold>. Smokers with COPD. <bold>I</bold>. IgG Control, <bold>J&#x02013;L</bold>. Examples of anti-SFRP2. Bar&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;10 &#x000b5;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0014793.g006"/></fig><p>To quantify this observation, Western analysis of SFRP2 was carried out on small airway epithelial cell samples from healthy nonsmokers, healthy smokers and smokers with COPD. This analysis demonstrated increased SFRP2 protein expression in healthy smokers and smokers with established COPD compared to healthy nonsmokers in small airway epithelial cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0014793-g007">Figure 7</xref>, p&#x0003c;0.05).</p><fig id="pone-0014793-g007" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0014793.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>Western analysis of SFRP2 protein expression in small airway epithelial cells.</title><p><bold>A</bold>. Proteins were extracted from small airway epithelial cells of 3 healthy nonsmokers, 3 healthy smokers and 3 smokers with COPD. Shown is SFRP2 protein expression in healthy nonsmokers (lanes 1&#x02013;3), healthy smokers (lanes 4&#x02013;6) and smokers with COPD (lanes 7&#x02013;9). Lower panel - same membrane probed with anti &#x003b2;-actin antibody, a control for protein loading. <bold>B</bold>. Quantification by densitometry of SFRP2 to &#x003b2;-actin. The ratio for SFRP2 to &#x003b2;-actin based on panel A is represented on the ordinate for the nonsmoker, smoker and smoker with COPD. Error bars represent the standard error.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0014793.g007"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3e"><title>Down-regulation of the Wnt Signaling Pathway in Human Airway Epithelial Cells Exposed to Cigarette Smoke Extract <italic>In Vitro</italic></title><p>To assess whether the exposure of human airway epithelial cells to CSE would affect Wnt pathway gene expression, cultures of the human airway epithelial cell line 16HBE were exposed to freshly made CSE for 72 hr. Cell viability was analyzed with MTT assay and SFRP2, MMP7 and SOX9 gene expression was analyzed using TaqMan real-time PCR. Decreased cell viability compared to control cells was observed with concentrations of 5, 10 and 20&#x00025; CSE. Cell viability was 100&#x00025; with 0.1&#x00025; CSE and 92&#x00025; with 1&#x00025; CSE medium compared with controls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0014793-g008">Figure 8A</xref>). Based on this data, we chose 0.1&#x00025; and 1&#x00025; CSE for the CES <italic>in vitro</italic> exposure studies. Compared with controls, SFRP2 gene expression increased in a dose-dependent pattern, with 4.6-fold in 0.1&#x00025; CSE group (p&#x0003c;0.01) and 10.1-fold in 1&#x00025; CSE groups (p&#x0003c;0.001) compared to no CSE controls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0014793-g007">Figure 7B</xref>). The Wnt target gene MMP7 decreased 2.3-fold (p&#x0003c;0.05) and 4.0-fold (p&#x0003c;0.01) respectively in 0.1&#x00025; and 1&#x00025; CSE groups compared to the control. SOX9, another Wnt target gene, was not significant in 0.1&#x00025; CSE group, but significantly decreased in 1&#x00025; CSE group (1.8-fold, p&#x0003c;0.05) compared to the control (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0014793-g008">Figure 8B</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0014793-g008" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0014793.g008</object-id><label>Figure 8</label><caption><title><italic>In vitro</italic> cigarette smoke extract (CES) treatment of human 16HBE airway epithelial cells.</title><p>After 16HBE cells were exposed to different concentrations of CSE for 3 days, cell viability (MTT) and gene expression levels of Wnt signaling pathway inhibitor SFRP2 and target genes (MMP7, SOX9) were quantified using TaqMan real-time PCR. <bold>A</bold>. MTT assessment. <bold>B</bold>. Effect of CSE on gene expression of SFRP2, MMP7, SOX9 in 16HBE cells using 0.1 and 1&#x00025; CSE concentrations that do not affect viability. SFRP2 gene expression was up-regulated when treated with both 0.1 and 1&#x00025; CSE (4.6-fold and 10.1-fold, p&#x0003c;0.01 and p&#x0003c;0.001). Error bars represent the standard deviation. &#x0002a;p&#x0003c;0.05 compared to no CSE controls. For TaqMan real-time PCR, the average value of 0.1&#x00025; CSE treatment group for each gene is determined as the calibrator.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0014793.g008"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3f"><title>Wnt Reporter Assay</title><p>To demonstrate SFRP2-dependent suppression of Wnt signaling, HEK293 cells were transiently transfected with the reporter constructs. When luciferase expression was driven by a WNT1-dependent promoter, the co-transfection of SFRP2 in addition to the WNT1 plasmid decreased luciferase activity in HEK293 cells by two fold (p&#x0003c;0.0001, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0014793.s004">Figure S3</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>In healthy individuals, as airway epithelial cells are injured or reach senescence, there is ongoing cell regeneration, with basal cell proliferation and subsequent differentiation to ciliated and secretory cells that comprise the healthy pseudostratified epithelial barrier that lines the airways <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Knight1">&#x0005b;1&#x0005d;</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Bishop1">&#x0005b;3&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Stripp1">&#x0005b;5&#x0005d;</xref>. In cigarette smokers, the toxic components of smoke and the associated local persistent inflammatory host response to smoking place the epithelium under the constant stress of oxidants, apoptotic signals, and other mechanisms of injury <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Cosio1">&#x0005b;40&#x0005d;</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Rennard1">&#x0005b;43&#x0005d;</xref>. In response, the airway epithelium regenerates at a faster rate, attempting to maintain its healthy pseudostratified character <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Cosio1">&#x0005b;40&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Demoly1">&#x0005b;44&#x0005d;</xref>. To assess the role of the Wnt pathway in the context of the stress of cigarette smoking, whole-genome microarray was utilized to analyze expression of the Wnt pathway genes. The data demonstrate that the majority of genes involved in the Wnt signaling pathway, representing all functional categories in the pathway, are expressed in the normal adult human small airway epithelium of healthy nonsmokers, consistent with studies showing the Wnt pathway can regulate human lung morphogenesis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Pongracz1">&#x0005b;11&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Shu2">&#x0005b;24&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Li2">&#x0005b;25&#x0005d;</xref>. With the stress of smoking, the Wnt pathway intracellular modulators &#x003b2;-catenin and transcription factor TCF7L1, as well as Wnt target genes are down-regulated, suggesting the Wnt pathway is suppressed. Assessment of the known extracellular inhibitors of the Wnt pathway revealed that smoking is associated with up-regulation of SFRP2. The up-regulated SFRP2 expression occurred in the ciliated cell population, suggesting that the differentiated cells play a role in modulating the &#x0201c;on&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;off&#x0201d; status of the Wnt pathway. Finally, <italic>in vitro</italic> exposure of human airway epithelial cells to cigarette smoke extract recapitulated the <italic>in vivo</italic> observations, with increased SFRP2 gene expression and down-regulation of Wnt target gene expression, demonstrating that cigarette smoke can directly down-regulate Wnt signaling pathway in the airway epithelium.</p><sec id="s4a"><title>Wnt Signaling Pathway and Lung Development</title><p>Wnt pathway signaling is an important regulator of epithelial and mesenchymal cell biology <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-VanScoyk1">&#x0005b;26&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-vanAmerongen1">&#x0005b;27&#x0005d;</xref>. To date, there are at least 19 Wnt ligands and 10 Fz receptor proteins identified, with redundancy and multiplicity of the receptor interactions and the downstream signaling <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-VanScoyk1">&#x0005b;26&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-vanAmerongen1">&#x0005b;27&#x0005d;</xref>. Of the various Wnt mutant phenotypes in mice, loss of the ligands WNT7B and WNT5A results in an abnormal pulmonary phenotype <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Li1">&#x0005b;15&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Shu2">&#x0005b;24&#x0005d;</xref>. Wnt7B <sup>lacZ&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice exhibit lung hypoplasia and respiratory failure <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Shu2">&#x0005b;24&#x0005d;</xref>, and Wnt7B<sup>lacZ&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> embryos and newborn mice exhibit severe defects in the smooth muscle component of the major pulmonary vessels, suggesting that WNT7B signaling is required for proper lung mesenchymal growth and vascular development <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Shu2">&#x0005b;24&#x0005d;</xref>. Mice carrying a targeted disruption of the WNT5A locus show abnormalities in distal lung morphogenesis, as manifested by truncation of the trachea and overexpansion of the distal respiratory airways <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Li1">&#x0005b;15&#x0005d;</xref>. The overall architecture of these mutant lungs is characterized by overexpansion of the distal airways and inhibition of lung maturation, with a persistence of thickened intravascular interstitium <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Li1">&#x0005b;15&#x0005d;</xref>. Activation of &#x003b2;-catenin in mice causes ectopic differentiation of alveolar type II-like cells in conducting airways, goblet cell hyperplasia, and air space enlargement, suggesting a critical role for the Wnt/&#x003b2;-catenin signal transduction pathway in the differentiation of the respiratory epithelium in the postnatal lung <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Mucenski1">&#x0005b;12&#x0005d;</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title>Wnt Signaling Pathway and Lung Disease</title><p>Loss of regulation of Wnt signaling pathways has been linked to the pathogenesis of asthma, fibrotic lung disease, nitrogen-induced pulmonary hypoplasia and lung cancer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Morrisey1">&#x0005b;45&#x0005d;</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Konigshoff2">&#x0005b;50&#x0005d;</xref>. Konigshoff and colleagues <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Konigshoff1">&#x0005b;48&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Konigshoff2">&#x0005b;50&#x0005d;</xref> confirmed the up-regulation of WNT1, WNT7B and WNT10B, FZD2, FZD3, &#x003b2;-catenin, and LEF1 expression in the lungs of individuals with idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis compared to transplant donor lung. <italic>In vitro</italic> functional studies have indicated that Wnt ligands induce lung epithelial cell proliferation and (myo) fibroblast activation and collagen synthesis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Konigshoff1">&#x0005b;48&#x0005d;</xref>. Increased expression of Wnt ligands (WNT1, 2, 7A) along with decreased expression of Wnt inhibitors (DKK3 and SFRP3) was observed in non-small cell lung cancer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Huang1">&#x0005b;47&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Akiri1">&#x0005b;49&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-You1">&#x0005b;51&#x0005d;</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-He2">&#x0005b;53&#x0005d;</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title>Function of Wnt Signaling Pathway in Adult Human Airway Epithelium</title><p>In a previous study from our laboratory, the large airway epithelium of healthy individuals was denuded by bronchoscopy and brushing, and genome-wide microarrays were used to study the gene expression pattern in the same site at 0, 7 and 14 days after injury <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Heguy1">&#x0005b;54&#x0005d;</xref>. Histologically, the injured area was completely covered by a partially redifferentiated epithelial layer after 7 days, and at this time point, a Wnt pathway inhibitor DKK1 was found to be greatly up-regulated, suggesting that the Wnt/&#x003b2;-catenin pathway is inhibited at this stage of airway epithelial repair <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Heguy1">&#x0005b;54&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><p>In the present study, we found that the Wnt signaling pathway was also down-regulated in adult human airway epithelium under the stress of chronic smoking. Interestingly, using gene expression profiling with air/whole mainstream cigarette smoke to treat a three-dimensional air-liquid interface model of tracheobronchial epithelium that were grown from primary human lung epithelial cells, Maunders et al <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Maunders1">&#x0005b;55&#x0005d;</xref> showed that the Wnt signaling pathway was down-regulated at 1, 6, and 24 hr post-exposure. For example, at 1 hr post-treatment, 9 Wnt signaling pathway genes and 12 Wnt target genes, including AXIN2, CCND1, JAG1, RUNX2, were down-regulated, with no up-regulation of Wnt signaling pathway genes or Wnt target genes. This supports our <italic>in vivo</italic> data that smoking repressed the Wnt signaling pathway. We also showed that <italic>in vitro</italic> smokers have significant up-regulation of another Wnt pathway inhibitor, SFRP2, an extracellular mediator of the largest family of Wnt inhibitors. SFRP2 functions as a modulator of Wnt signaling through direct interaction with Wnt ligands, with consequent regulation of cell growth <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Kawano1">&#x0005b;28&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Yoshino1">&#x0005b;56&#x0005d;</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Matsuyama1">&#x0005b;64&#x0005d;</xref>. Inactivation of SFRP2 results in subtle limb defects in mice with mesomelic shortening and consistent shortening of all autopodal elements clinically manifested as brachydactyly <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Morello1">&#x0005b;65&#x0005d;</xref>. SFRP2 has been shown to repress canonical Wnt signaling activated by WNT1, WNT3A, WNT4, WNT7A, and WNT9A <italic>in vitro</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Morello1">&#x0005b;65&#x0005d;</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Hayashi2">&#x0005b;67&#x0005d;</xref>. Interestingly, SFRP1, another member of the SFRP family, is up-regulated in the distal epithelial cells of the mouse lung during development and in murine emphysema models <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Imai1">&#x0005b;68&#x0005d;</xref>. However, except for the function as the Wnt signaling pathway inhibitors, recent studies showed that SFRPs are not merely Wnt-binding proteins, but can also antagonize different SFRPs' activity, interfere with BMP signaling by acting as proteinase inhibitors, decrease susceptibility to UV-induced apoptosis in primary culture of canine mammary gland tumors by NF-&#x003ba;B activation or JNK suppression, and interact with other receptors or matrix molecules <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Bovolenta1">&#x0005b;69&#x0005d;</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0014793-Lee2">&#x0005b;74&#x0005d;</xref>. Because of the limitation of the primary human airway epithelial cells, which prohibits us from performing the functional assays of the Wnt signaling pathway in a condition similar to that <italic>in vivo</italic>, we could not be certain that the down-regulation of Wnt signaling in healthy smokers and COPD patients is the result of SFRP2 up-regulation, despite the fact that SFRP2 could decrease WNT1-induced activation of Wnt reporter luciferase activity in HEK293 cells (p&#x0003c;0.05, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0014793.s004">Figure S3</xref>). Another limitation of this study is, although the down-regulation of the Wnt signaling pathway might induce the human airway epithelial cells to differentiate in healthy smokers and COPD patients, in the current study, we found there were decreased ciliated cells and increased undifferentiated cells (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0014793-t001">Table 1</xref>). There are a number of reasons for this discrepancy. Although the down-regulation of the Wnt signaling pathway could promote the repair and differentiation of airway epithelial cells in healthy smokers and smokers with COPD, the effect of smoking undoubtedly has a complex effect on multiple pathways. The confirmation of this concept is limited by the lack of a proper <italic>in vitro</italic> model. Furthermore, because the airway epithelial cells <italic>in vivo</italic> are composed a mixed populations including ciliated cells, secretory cells, basal cells and other cell populations such as clara cells, the microarray data may solely reflect changes in cell populations from patient to patient. However, it is unlikely because of the up-regulation of SFRP2 (which is specifically expressed in ciliated cells) in healthy smokers and smokers with COPD as well as the fact that the healthy smokers and smokers with COPD have lower percentage of ciliated cells.</p><p>Our findings suggest there is a complex Wnt signaling system in the adult human airway epithelium, which is subjected to a tightly regulated pattern that can respond to stress. Together, the data show that smoking induces down-regulation of Wnt signaling pathway, consistent with the concept that in response to the stress of cigarette smoking, the small airway epithelium Wnt pathway is suppressed, allowing for epithelial repair and differentiation.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0014793.s001"><label>Table S1</label><caption><p>Expression of WNT Pathway Genes and Target Genes in Small Airway.</p><p>(0.12 MB DOC)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0014793.s001.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0014793.s002"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p>Ingenuity Pathway Analysis generated WNT/&#x003b2;-catenin gene network. A. IPA gene network of WNT/&#x003b2;-catenin signaling pathway genes that displayed 1.5-fold or greater changes between healthy smokers and healthy nonsmokers. B. IPA gene network of WNT/&#x003b2;-catenin signaling pathway genes that displayed 1.5-fold or greater changes between smokers with COPD and healthy nonsmokers. Additional information about the genes and the indicated interactions can be found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ingenuity.com">www.ingenuity.com</ext-link>.</p><p>(1.79 MB TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0014793.s002.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0014793.s003"><label>Figure S2</label><caption><p>TaqMan Real-time PCR confirmation of down-regulation of selected Wnt genes and Wnt target genes in healthy nonsmokers (NS), healthy smokers (S), and smokers with COPD (COPD). Each bar represents mean expression with standard error&#x0003b; p values are represented in brackets above the bars. The average value of healthy nonsmokers is determined as the calibrator for each gene.</p><p>(0.43 MB TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0014793.s003.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0014793.s004"><label>Figure S3</label><caption><p>The Wnt reporter assay in HEK293 cells. HEK293 cells were transiently transfected with Wnt reporter (Topflash) or Wnt reporter control (Fopflash) constructs, and stimulated with WNT1 plasmid or WNT1 plus SFRP2 plasmids, as indicated. The relative luciferase activity is plotted. The experiment was repeated three times and representative results are presented as mean &#x000b1; standard deviation.</p><p>(0.40 MB TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0014793.s004.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank D. Dang and M. Teater for expert technical assistance&#x0003b; and N Mohamed for help in preparing this manuscript.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="conflict"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding: </bold>These studies were supported, in part, by National Institutes of Health R01 HL074326, P50 HL084936&#x0003b; UL1-RR024996&#x0003b; and 1T32HL094284. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0014793-Knight1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Holgate</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name></person-group>
            <year>2003</year>
            <article-title>The airway epithelium: structural and functional properties in health and disease.</article-title>
            <source>Respirology</source>
            <volume>8</volume>
            <fpage>432</fpage>
            <lpage>446</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14708552</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Crystal1"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crystal</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Randell</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Engelhardt</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Voynow</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sunday</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group>
            <year>2008</year>
            <article-title>Airway epithelial cells: current concepts and challenges.</article-title>
            <source>Proc Am Thorac Soc</source>
            <volume>5</volume>
            <fpage>772</fpage>
            <lpage>777</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18757316</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Bishop1"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name></person-group>
            <year>2004</year>
            <article-title>Pulmonary epithelial stem cells.</article-title>
            <source>Cell Prolif</source>
            <volume>37</volume>
            <fpage>89</fpage>
            <lpage>96</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14871239</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Rawlins1"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rawlins</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ostrowski</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Randell</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hogan</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name></person-group>
            <year>2007</year>
            <article-title>Lung development and repair: contribution of the ciliated lineage.</article-title>
            <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
            <volume>104</volume>
            <fpage>410</fpage>
            <lpage>417</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17194755</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Stripp1"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stripp</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group>
            <year>2008</year>
            <article-title>Maintenance and repair of the bronchiolar epithelium.</article-title>
            <source>Proc Am Thorac Soc</source>
            <volume>5</volume>
            <fpage>328</fpage>
            <lpage>333</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18403328</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Zhang1"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Goss</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><name><surname>Kadzik</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lepore</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
            <year>2008</year>
            <article-title>A Gata6-Wnt pathway required for epithelial stem cell development and airway regeneration.</article-title>
            <source>Nat Genet</source>
            <volume>40</volume>
            <fpage>862</fpage>
            <lpage>870</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18536717</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Rock1"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rock</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Onaitis</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Rawlins</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
            <year>2009</year>
            <article-title>Basal cells as stem cells of the mouse trachea and human airway epithelium.</article-title>
            <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
            <volume>106</volume>
            <fpage>12771</fpage>
            <lpage>12775</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19625615</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Evans1"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Winkle</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Fanucchi</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Plopper</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name></person-group>
            <year>2001</year>
            <article-title>Cellular and molecular characteristics of basal cells in airway epithelium.</article-title>
            <source>Exp Lung Res</source>
            <volume>27</volume>
            <fpage>401</fpage>
            <lpage>415</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11480582</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Snyder1"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Teisanu</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Stripp</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name></person-group>
            <year>2009</year>
            <article-title>Endogenous lung stem cells and contribution to disease.</article-title>
            <source>J Pathol</source>
            <volume>217</volume>
            <fpage>254</fpage>
            <lpage>264</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19039828</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-DeLanghe1"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Langhe</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group>
            <year>2008</year>
            <article-title>Wnt signaling in lung organogenesis.</article-title>
            <source>Organogenesis</source>
            <volume>4</volume>
            <fpage>100</fpage>
            <lpage>108</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19279721</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Pongracz1"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pongracz</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Stockley</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group>
            <year>2006</year>
            <article-title>Wnt signalling in lung development and diseases.</article-title>
            <source>Respir Res</source>
            <volume>7</volume>
            <fpage>15</fpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16438732</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Mucenski1"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mucenski</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Nation</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Thitoff</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Besnard</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
            <year>2005</year>
            <article-title>Beta-catenin regulates differentiation of respiratory epithelial cells in vivo.</article-title>
            <source>Am J Physiol Lung Cell Mol Physiol</source>
            <volume>289</volume>
            <fpage>L971</fpage>
            <lpage>L979</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16040629</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Reynolds1"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Zemke</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Giangreco</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Brockway</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Teisanu</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
            <year>2008</year>
            <article-title>Conditional stabilization of beta-catenin expands the pool of lung stem cells.</article-title>
            <source>Stem Cells</source>
            <volume>26</volume>
            <fpage>1337</fpage>
            <lpage>1346</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18356571</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Shu1"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Guttentag</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Andl</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ballard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
            <year>2005</year>
            <article-title>Wnt/beta-catenin signaling acts upstream of N-myc, BMP4, and FGF signaling to regulate proximal-distal patterning in the lung.</article-title>
            <source>Dev Biol</source>
            <volume>283</volume>
            <fpage>226</fpage>
            <lpage>239</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15907834</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Li1"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hormi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Borok</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Minoo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
            <year>2002</year>
            <article-title>Wnt5a participates in distal lung morphogenesis.</article-title>
            <source>Dev Biol</source>
            <volume>248</volume>
            <fpage>68</fpage>
            <lpage>81</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12142021</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Wang1"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Shu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Morrisey</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name></person-group>
            <year>2005</year>
            <article-title>Wnt7b activates canonical signaling in epithelial and vascular smooth muscle cells through interactions with Fzd1, Fzd10, and LRP5.</article-title>
            <source>Mol Cell Biol</source>
            <volume>25</volume>
            <fpage>5022</fpage>
            <lpage>5030</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15923619</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Weidenfeld1"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weidenfeld</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Shu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Millar</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Morrisey</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name></person-group>
            <year>2002</year>
            <article-title>The WNT7b promoter is regulated by TTF-1, GATA6, and Foxa2 in lung epithelium.</article-title>
            <source>J Biol Chem</source>
            <volume>277</volume>
            <fpage>21061</fpage>
            <lpage>21070</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11914369</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Korinek1"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Korinek</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Moerer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>van</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Huls</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
            <year>1998</year>
            <article-title>Depletion of epithelial stem-cell compartments in the small intestine of mice lacking Tcf-4.</article-title>
            <source>Nat Genet</source>
            <volume>19</volume>
            <fpage>379</fpage>
            <lpage>383</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9697701</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Merrill1"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Merrill</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gat</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>DasGupta</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuchs</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>
            <year>2001</year>
            <article-title>Tcf3 and Lef1 regulate lineage differentiation of multipotent stem cells in skin.</article-title>
            <source>Genes Dev</source>
            <volume>15</volume>
            <fpage>1688</fpage>
            <lpage>1705</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11445543</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Chenn1"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chenn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group>
            <year>2002</year>
            <article-title>Regulation of cerebral cortical size by control of cell cycle exit in neural precursors.</article-title>
            <source>Science</source>
            <volume>297</volume>
            <fpage>365</fpage>
            <lpage>369</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12130776</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Kubo1"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kubo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeichi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakagawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
            <year>2003</year>
            <article-title>Wnt2b controls retinal cell differentiation at the ciliary marginal zone.</article-title>
            <source>Development</source>
            <volume>130</volume>
            <fpage>587</fpage>
            <lpage>598</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12490564</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Reya1"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Ailles</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Domen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Scherer</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
            <year>2003</year>
            <article-title>A role for Wnt signalling in self-renewal of haematopoietic stem cells.</article-title>
            <source>Nature</source>
            <volume>423</volume>
            <fpage>409</fpage>
            <lpage>414</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12717450</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Sato1"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Meijer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Skaltsounis</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Greengard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Brivanlou</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name></person-group>
            <year>2004</year>
            <article-title>Maintenance of pluripotency in human and mouse embryonic stem cells through activation of Wnt signaling by a pharmacological GSK-3-specific inhibitor.</article-title>
            <source>Nat Med</source>
            <volume>10</volume>
            <fpage>55</fpage>
            <lpage>63</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14702635</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Shu2"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>YQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Morrisey</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name></person-group>
            <year>2002</year>
            <article-title>Wnt7b regulates mesenchymal proliferation and vascular development in the lung.</article-title>
            <source>Development</source>
            <volume>129</volume>
            <fpage>4831</fpage>
            <lpage>4842</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12361974</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Li2"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
            <year>2005</year>
            <article-title>Wnt5a regulates Shh and Fgf10 signaling during lung development.</article-title>
            <source>Dev Biol</source>
            <volume>287</volume>
            <fpage>86</fpage>
            <lpage>97</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16169547</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-VanScoyk1"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Scoyk</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Randall</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sergew</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tennis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
            <year>2008</year>
            <article-title>Wnt signaling pathway and lung disease.</article-title>
            <source>Transl Res</source>
            <volume>151</volume>
            <fpage>175</fpage>
            <lpage>180</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18355764</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-vanAmerongen1"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Amerongen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Nusse</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
            <year>2009</year>
            <article-title>Towards an integrated view of Wnt signaling in development.</article-title>
            <source>Development</source>
            <volume>136</volume>
            <fpage>3205</fpage>
            <lpage>3214</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19736321</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Kawano1"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kawano</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kypta</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
            <year>2003</year>
            <article-title>Secreted antagonists of the Wnt signalling pathway.</article-title>
            <source>J Cell Sci</source>
            <volume>116</volume>
            <fpage>2627</fpage>
            <lpage>2634</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12775774</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Niehrs1"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Niehrs</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
            <year>2006</year>
            <article-title>Function and biological roles of the Dickkopf family of Wnt modulators.</article-title>
            <source>Oncogene</source>
            <volume>25</volume>
            <fpage>7469</fpage>
            <lpage>7481</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17143291</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Hogg1"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hogg</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Utokaparch</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
            <year>2004</year>
            <article-title>The nature of small-airway obstruction in chronic obstructive pulmonary disease.</article-title>
            <source>N Engl J Med</source>
            <volume>350</volume>
            <fpage>2645</fpage>
            <lpage>2653</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15215480</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Pauwels1"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pauwels</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Buist</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Calverley</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hurd</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name></person-group>
            <year>2001</year>
            <article-title>Global strategy for the diagnosis, management, and prevention of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease. NHLBI/WHO Global Initiative for Chronic Obstructive Lung Disease (GOLD) Workshop summary.</article-title>
            <source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source>
            <volume>163</volume>
            <fpage>1256</fpage>
            <lpage>1276</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11316667</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Rabe1"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rabe</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><name><surname>Hurd</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Anzueto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Buist</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
            <year>2007</year>
            <article-title>Global strategy for the diagnosis, management, and prevention of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease: GOLD executive summary.</article-title>
            <source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source>
            <volume>176</volume>
            <fpage>532</fpage>
            <lpage>555</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17507545</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Harvey1"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harvey</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><name><surname>Heguy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Leopold</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Carolan</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferris</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
            <year>2007</year>
            <article-title>Modification of gene expression of the small airway epithelium in response to cigarette smoking.</article-title>
            <source>J Mol Med</source>
            <volume>85</volume>
            <fpage>39</fpage>
            <lpage>53</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17115125</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Tilley1"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tilley</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Harvey</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><name><surname>Heguy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hackett</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
            <year>2009</year>
            <article-title>Down-regulation of the notch pathway in human airway epithelium in association with smoking and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease.</article-title>
            <source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source>
            <volume>179</volume>
            <fpage>457</fpage>
            <lpage>466</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19106307</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Raman1"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raman</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Connor</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name><surname>Hackett</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Harvey</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
            <year>2009</year>
            <article-title>Quality control in microarray assessment of gene expression in human airway epithelium.</article-title>
            <source>BMC Genomics</source>
            <volume>10</volume>
            <fpage>493</fpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19852842</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Ning1"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ning</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaminski</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Feghali-Bostwick</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Alber</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
            <year>2004</year>
            <article-title>Comprehensive gene expression profiles reveal pathways related to the pathogenesis of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease.</article-title>
            <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
            <volume>101</volume>
            <fpage>14895</fpage>
            <lpage>14900</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15469929</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Cozens1"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cozens</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Yezzi</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunzelmann</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohrui</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Chin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
            <year>1994</year>
            <article-title>CFTR expression and chloride secretion in polarized immortal human bronchial epithelial cells.</article-title>
            <source>Am J Respir Cell Mol Biol</source>
            <volume>10</volume>
            <fpage>38</fpage>
            <lpage>47</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7507342</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Berridge1"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berridge</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group>
            <year>1993</year>
            <article-title>Characterization of the cellular reduction of 3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyltetrazolium bromide (MTT): subcellular localization, substrate dependence, and involvement of mitochondrial electron transport in MTT reduction.</article-title>
            <source>Arch Biochem Biophys</source>
            <volume>303</volume>
            <fpage>474</fpage>
            <lpage>482</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8390225</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Jaluria1"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jaluria</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Betenbaugh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Konstantopoulos</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Shiloach</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
            <year>2007</year>
            <article-title>Enhancement of cell proliferation in various mammalian cell lines by gene insertion of a cyclin-dependent kinase homolog.</article-title>
            <source>BMC Biotechnol</source>
            <volume>7</volume>
            <fpage>71</fpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17945021</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Cosio1"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cosio</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Hale</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Niewoehner</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group>
            <year>1980</year>
            <article-title>Morphologic and morphometric effects of prolonged cigarette smoking on the small airways.</article-title>
            <source>Am Rev Respir Dis</source>
            <volume>122</volume>
            <fpage>265</fpage>
            <lpage>21</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7416603</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-vanderVaart1"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van der Vaart</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Postma</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Timens</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Ten Hacken</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name></person-group>
            <year>2004</year>
            <article-title>Acute effects of cigarette smoke on inflammation and oxidative stress: a review.</article-title>
            <source>Thorax</source>
            <volume>59</volume>
            <fpage>713</fpage>
            <lpage>721</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15282395</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Kinnula1"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kinnula</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name></person-group>
            <year>2005</year>
            <article-title>Focus on antioxidant enzymes and antioxidant strategies in smoking related airway diseases.</article-title>
            <source>Thorax</source>
            <volume>60</volume>
            <fpage>693</fpage>
            <lpage>700</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16061713</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Rennard1"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rennard</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name></person-group>
            <year>2007</year>
            <article-title>Inflammation in COPD: a link to systemic comorbidities.</article-title>
            <source>Eur Respir Rev</source>
            <volume>16</volume>
            <fpage>91</fpage>
            <lpage>97</lpage>
         </element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Demoly1"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Demoly</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Simony-Lafontaine</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chanez</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Pujol</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lequeux</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
            <year>1994</year>
            <article-title>Cell proliferation in the bronchial mucosa of asthmatics and chronic bronchitics.</article-title>
            <source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source>
            <volume>150</volume>
            <fpage>214</fpage>
            <lpage>217</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7912988</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Morrisey1"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morrisey</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name></person-group>
            <year>2003</year>
            <article-title>Wnt signaling and pulmonary fibrosis.</article-title>
            <source>Am J Pathol</source>
            <volume>162</volume>
            <fpage>1393</fpage>
            <lpage>1397</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12707021</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Takayasu1"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takayasu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakazawa</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Montedonico</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Puri</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
            <year>2007</year>
            <article-title>Down-regulation of Wnt signal pathway in nitrofen-induced hypoplastic lung.</article-title>
            <source>J Pediatr Surg</source>
            <volume>42</volume>
            <fpage>426</fpage>
            <lpage>430</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17270562</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Huang1"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishikawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakashima</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakashima</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
            <year>2008</year>
            <article-title>Wnt1 overexpression promotes tumour progression in non-small cell lung cancer.</article-title>
            <source>Eur J Cancer</source>
            <volume>44</volume>
            <fpage>2680</fpage>
            <lpage>2688</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18790633</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Konigshoff1"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Konigshoff</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Balsara</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Pfaff</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chrobak</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
            <year>2008</year>
            <article-title>Functional Wnt signaling is increased in idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis.</article-title>
            <source>PLoS One</source>
            <volume>3</volume>
            <fpage>e2142</fpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18478089</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Akiri1"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akiri</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Cherian</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Vijayakumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bafico</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
            <year>2009</year>
            <article-title>Wnt pathway aberrations including autocrine Wnt activation occur at high frequency in human non-small-cell lung carcinoma.</article-title>
            <source>Oncogene</source>
            <volume>28</volume>
            <fpage>2163</fpage>
            <lpage>2172</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19377513</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Konigshoff2"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Konigshoff</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Eickelberg</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>
            <year>2009</year>
            <article-title>WNT signaling in lung disease: a failure or a regeneration signal&#x0003f;</article-title>
            <source>Am J Respir Cell Mol Biol</source>
         </element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-You1"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>You</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Uematsu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazieres</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
            <year>2004</year>
            <article-title>Inhibition of Wnt-2-mediated signaling induces programmed cell death in non-small-cell lung cancer cells.</article-title>
            <source>Oncogene</source>
            <volume>23</volume>
            <fpage>6170</fpage>
            <lpage>6174</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15208662</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-He1"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Barg</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>You</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Reguart</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
            <year>2005</year>
            <article-title>Wnt signaling in stem cells and non-small-cell lung cancer.</article-title>
            <source>Clin Lung Cancer</source>
            <volume>7</volume>
            <fpage>54</fpage>
            <lpage>60</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16098245</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-He2"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Jablons</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group>
            <year>2006</year>
            <article-title>Wnt signaling in stem cells and lung cancer.</article-title>
            <source>Ernst Schering Found Symp Proc</source>
            <fpage>27</fpage>
            <lpage>58</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17939294</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Heguy1"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heguy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Harvey</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><name><surname>Leopold</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolgalev</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Raman</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
            <year>2007</year>
            <article-title>Responses of the human airway epithelium transcriptome to in vivo injury.</article-title>
            <source>Physiol Genomics</source>
            <volume>29</volume>
            <fpage>139</fpage>
            <lpage>148</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17164391</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Maunders1"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maunders</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Patwardhan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Clack</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Richter</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
            <year>2007</year>
            <article-title>Human bronchial epithelial cell transcriptome: gene expression changes following acute exposure to whole cigarette smoke in vitro.</article-title>
            <source>Am J Physiol Lung Cell Mol Physiol</source>
            <volume>292</volume>
            <fpage>L1248</fpage>
            <lpage>L1256</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17220372</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Yoshino1"><label>56</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoshino</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Higinbotham</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><name><surname>Uren</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Anest</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
            <year>2001</year>
            <article-title>Secreted Frizzled-related proteins can regulate metanephric development.</article-title>
            <source>Mech Dev</source>
            <volume>102</volume>
            <fpage>45</fpage>
            <lpage>55</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11287180</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Chen1"><label>57</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Stump</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lovicu</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>McAvoy</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group>
            <year>2004</year>
            <article-title>Expression of Frizzleds and secreted frizzled-related proteins (Sfrps) during mammalian lens development.</article-title>
            <source>Int J Dev Biol</source>
            <volume>48</volume>
            <fpage>867</fpage>
            <lpage>877</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15558478</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Hayashi1"><label>58</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Spencer</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name></person-group>
            <year>2006</year>
            <article-title>WNT pathways in the neonatal ovine uterus: potential specification of endometrial gland morphogenesis by SFRP2.</article-title>
            <source>Biol Reprod</source>
            <volume>74</volume>
            <fpage>721</fpage>
            <lpage>733</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16407498</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Wagatsuma1"><label>59</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wagatsuma</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
            <year>2007</year>
            <article-title>Adipogenic potential can be activated during muscle regeneration.</article-title>
            <source>Mol Cell Biochem</source>
            <volume>304</volume>
            <fpage>25</fpage>
            <lpage>33</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17487458</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Alfaro1"><label>60</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alfaro</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Pagni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vincent</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Atkinson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
            <year>2008</year>
            <article-title>The Wnt modulator sFRP2 enhances mesenchymal stem cell engraftment, granulation tissue formation and myocardial repair.</article-title>
            <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
            <volume>105</volume>
            <fpage>18366</fpage>
            <lpage>18371</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19017790</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Cho1"><label>61</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Her</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>OK</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
            <year>2008</year>
            <article-title>Differential effects of secreted frizzled-related proteins (sFRPs) on osteoblastic differentiation of mouse mesenchymal cells and apoptosis of osteoblasts.</article-title>
            <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source>
            <volume>367</volume>
            <fpage>399</fpage>
            <lpage>405</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18166153</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Das1"><label>62</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhattacharya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Hegde</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Mallya</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
            <year>2008</year>
            <article-title>The canonical Wnt pathway regulates retinal stem cells/progenitors in concert with Notch signaling.</article-title>
            <source>Dev Neurosci</source>
            <volume>30</volume>
            <fpage>389</fpage>
            <lpage>409</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19033687</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Descamps1"><label>63</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Descamps</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Arzouk</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Bacou</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernardi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Fedon</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
            <year>2008</year>
            <article-title>Inhibition of myoblast differentiation by Sfrp1 and Sfrp2.</article-title>
            <source>Cell Tissue Res</source>
            <volume>332</volume>
            <fpage>299</fpage>
            <lpage>306</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18322704</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Matsuyama1"><label>64</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matsuyama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Aizawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimono</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
            <year>2009</year>
            <article-title>Sfrp controls apicobasal polarity and oriented cell division in developing gut epithelium.</article-title>
            <source>PLoS Genet</source>
            <volume>5</volume>
            <fpage>e1000427</fpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19300477</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Morello1"><label>65</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morello</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bertin</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlaubitz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kakuru</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
            <year>2008</year>
            <article-title>Brachy-syndactyly caused by loss of Sfrp2 function.</article-title>
            <source>J Cell Physiol</source>
            <volume>217</volume>
            <fpage>127</fpage>
            <lpage>137</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18446812</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Deb1"><label>66</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deb</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
            <year>2008</year>
            <article-title>SFRP2 regulates cardiomyogenic differentiation by inhibiting a positive transcriptional autofeedback loop of Wnt3a.</article-title>
            <source>Stem Cells</source>
            <volume>26</volume>
            <fpage>35</fpage>
            <lpage>44</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17916803</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Hayashi2"><label>67</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Burghardt</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bazer</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name><name><surname>Spencer</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name></person-group>
            <year>2007</year>
            <article-title>WNTs in the ovine uterus: potential regulation of periimplantation ovine conceptus development.</article-title>
            <source>Endocrinology</source>
            <volume>148</volume>
            <fpage>3496</fpage>
            <lpage>3506</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17431004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Imai1"><label>68</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Imai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>D'Armiento</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
            <year>2002</year>
            <article-title>Differential gene expression of sFRP-1 and apoptosis in pulmonary emphysema.</article-title>
            <source>Chest</source>
            <volume>121</volume>
            <fpage>7S</fpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11893652</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Bovolenta1"><label>69</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bovolenta</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Esteve</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
            <year>2006</year>
            <article-title>Frizzled/RYK mediated signalling in axon guidance.</article-title>
            <source>Development</source>
            <volume>133</volume>
            <fpage>4399</fpage>
            <lpage>4408</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17035295</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Bovolenta2"><label>70</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bovolenta</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Esteve</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruiz</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cisneros</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopez-Rios</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
            <year>2008</year>
            <article-title>Beyond Wnt inhibition: new functions of secreted Frizzled-related proteins in development and disease.</article-title>
            <source>J Cell Sci</source>
            <volume>121</volume>
            <fpage>737</fpage>
            <lpage>746</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18322270</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Esteve1"><label>71</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Esteve</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Trousse</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bovolenta</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
            <year>2003</year>
            <article-title>SFRP1 modulates retina cell differentiation through a beta-catenin-independent mechanism.</article-title>
            <source>J Cell Sci</source>
            <volume>116</volume>
            <fpage>2471</fpage>
            <lpage>2481</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12724355</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Kim1"><label>72</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubenstein</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lowenstein</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Pleasure</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group>
            <year>2001</year>
            <article-title>Pax-6 regulates expression of SFRP-2 and Wnt-7b in the developing CNS.</article-title>
            <source>J Neurosci</source>
            <volume>21</volume>
            <fpage>RC132</fpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11222670</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Lee1"><label>73</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>HX</given-names></name><name><surname>Ambrosio</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Reversade</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>De Robertis</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group>
            <year>2006</year>
            <article-title>Embryonic dorsal-ventral signaling: secreted frizzled-related proteins as inhibitors of tolloid proteinases.</article-title>
            <source>Cell</source>
            <volume>124</volume>
            <fpage>147</fpage>
            <lpage>159</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16413488</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0014793-Lee2"><label>74</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chueh</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name></person-group>
            <year>2006</year>
            <article-title>Secreted frizzled related protein 2 (sFRP2) decreases susceptibility to UV-induced apoptosis in primary culture of canine mammary gland tumors by NF-kappaB activation or JNK suppression.</article-title>
            <source>Breast Cancer Res Treat</source>
            <volume>100</volume>
            <fpage>49</fpage>
            <lpage>58</lpage>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16791480</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>