<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26114868</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4483234</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0130703</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-52126</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Transcriptome Profile of the Response of Paracoccidioides spp. to a Camphene Thiosemicarbazide Derivative</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Response of Paracoccidioides to Camphene Thiosemicarbazide Derivative</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>do Carmo Silva</surname><given-names>L&#x000ed;via</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tamayo Ossa</surname><given-names>Diana Patr&#x000ed;cia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Castro</surname><given-names>Symone Vitoriano da Concei&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bringel Pires</surname><given-names>Ludmila</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Alves de Oliveira</surname><given-names>Cec&#x000ed;lia Maria</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Concei&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o da Silva</surname><given-names>Cleuza</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff004"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Coelho</surname><given-names>Narcim&#x000e1;rio Pereira</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff004"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bail&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>Alexandre Melo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Parente-Rocha</surname><given-names>Juliana Alves</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>C&#x000e9;lia Maria de Almeida</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ruiz</surname><given-names>Orville Hern&#x000e1;ndez</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ochoa</surname><given-names>Juan G. McEwen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>Maristela</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff001"><label>1</label><addr-line>Laborat&#x000f3;rio de Biologia Molecular, Instituto de Patologia Tropical e Sa&#x000fa;de P&#x000fa;blica Universidade Federal de Goi&#x000e1;s, Goi&#x000e2;nia, Brazil</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff002"><label>2</label><addr-line>Unidad de Biolog&#x000ed;a Celular y Molecular, Corporaci&#x000f3;n para Investigaciones Biol&#x000f3;gicas (CIB) and Facultad de Medicina Universidad de Antioquia, Medell&#x000ed;n, Colombia</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff003"><label>3</label><addr-line>Laborat&#x000f3;rio de Produtos Naturais, Instituto de Qu&#x000ed;mica, Universidade Federal de Goi&#x000e1;s, Goi&#x000e2;nia, Brazil</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff004"><label>4</label><addr-line>Laborat&#x000f3;rio de Fitoqu&#x000ed;mica e S&#x000ed;ntese Org&#x000e2;nica, Departamento de Qu&#x000ed;mica, Universidade Estadual de Maring&#x000e1;, Paran&#x000e1;, Brazil</addr-line></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Zaragoza</surname><given-names>Oscar</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Instituto de Salud Carlos III, SPAIN</addr-line></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: LCS MP OHR JGMO CMAO CCS. Performed the experiments: LCS DPTO SVCC LBP NPC. Analyzed the data: LCS CMAO AMB JAPR CMAS MP. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: CCS CMAS OHR MP. Wrote the paper: LCS DPTO CMAO AMB JAPR OHR JGMO MP.</p></fn><corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>maristelaufg@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>26</day><month>6</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue>6</issue><elocation-id>e0130703</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>3</day><month>2</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>5</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Silva et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="pone.0130703.pdf"/><abstract><p>Paracoccidioidomycosis (PCM) is a systemic granulomatous human mycosis caused by fungi of the genus <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic>, which is geographically restricted to Latin America. Inhalation of spores, the infectious particles of the fungus, is a common route of infection. The PCM treatment of choice is azoles such as itraconazole, but sulfonamides and amphotericin B are used in some cases despite their toxicity to mammalian cells. The current availability of treatments highlights the need to identify and characterize novel targets for antifungal treatment of PCM as well as the need to search for new antifungal compounds obtained from natural sources or by chemical synthesis. To this end, we evaluated the antifungal activity of a camphene thiosemicarbazide derivative (TSC-C) compound on <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> yeast. To determine the response of <italic>Paracoccidioides spp</italic>. to TSC-C, we analyzed the transcriptional profile of the fungus after 8 h of contact with the compound. The results demonstrate that <italic>Paracoccidioides lutzii</italic> induced the expression of genes related to metabolism; cell cycle and DNA processing; biogenesis of cellular components; cell transduction/signal; cell rescue, defense and virulence; cellular transport, transport facilities and transport routes; energy; protein synthesis; protein fate; transcription; and other proteins without classification. Additionally, we observed intensely inhibited genes related to protein synthesis. Analysis by fluorescence microscopy and flow cytometry revealed that the compound induced the production of reactive oxygen species. Using an isolate with down-regulated <italic>SOD1</italic> gene expression (<italic>SOD1</italic>-aRNA), we sought to determine the function of this gene in the defense of <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> yeast cells against the compound. Mutant cells were more susceptible to TSC-C, demonstrating the importance of this gene in response to the compound. The results presented herein suggest that TSC-C is a promising candidate for PCM treatment.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work performed at Universidade Federal de Goi&#x000e1;s was supported by MCTI/CNPq (Minist&#x000e9;rio da Ci&#x000ea;ncia e Tecnologia/Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Cient&#x000ed;fico e Tecnol&#x000f3;gico), FNDCT (Fundo Nacional de Desenvolvimento Cient&#x000ed;fico e Tecnol&#x000f3;gico), FAPEG (Funda&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o de Amparo &#x000e0; Pesquisa do Estado de Goi&#x000e1;s), CAPES (Coordena&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o de Aperfei&#x000e7;oamento de Pessoal de N&#x000ed;vel Superior), FINEP (Financiadora de Estudos e Projetos), and INCT-IF (Instituto Nacional de Ci&#x000ea;ncia e Tecnologia para Inova&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o Farmac&#x000ea;utica). Additionally, LCS was supported by fellowship from CNPq and SVCC, LBP, NPC from CAPES. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="9"/><table-count count="2"/><page-count count="25"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>The ESTs obtained were submitted to the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI) under accession numbers: LIBEST_028508 Paracoccidioides thiosemicarbazide Library.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><title>Data Availability</title><p>The ESTs obtained were submitted to the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI) under accession numbers: LIBEST_028508 Paracoccidioides thiosemicarbazide Library.</p></notes></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001"><title>Introduction</title><p>Paracoccidioidomycosis (PCM) is a systemic mycosis geographically restricted to Latin America caused by thermodimorphic fungi of the genus <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic>. The fungi usually infect the host through the respiratory tract by inhalation of conidia, which are the infectious propagules found in the environment. In the lungs, these propagules differentiate into the pathogenic form in a temperature-dependent manner, corresponding to the yeast phase of the fungus, and spreads to other organs through lymphohematogenous dissemination. Because this mycosis affects mainly rural males of working age between the ages of 30 and 50 years, the disease has socioeconomic repercussions due to its potential to debilitate. In addition to the lungs, PCM frequently compromises the mucous membranes, lymph nodes, liver, spleen and bone marrow [<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>].</p><p>Treating PCM remains a challenge due to the toxicity of the antifungals commonly used to treat this mycosis&#x02014;sulfonamides, azoles and polyenes [<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Additionally, despite the use of antifungals, individuals with PCM have persistent latent foci, which slow down treatment and may extend it over months or years depending on the severity of the disease and the site of injury [<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Thus, the need to research and develop new therapeutic approaches is increasingly evident. With this aim, our group has invested effort into identifying and characterizing novel targets for antifungal drugs against <italic>Paracoccidioides spp</italic>. [<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] and searching for new antifungal compounds obtained from natural sources or their synthetic derivatives [<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>].</p><p>The monoterpenoids are the components of essential oils, which are produced in large quantities by plants. These molecules are significant due to their therapeutic potential, low cost as well as the commercial availability, being used as starting material for synthesis of bioactive compounds [<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Following this approach a series of thiosemicarbazides and thiosemicarbazones deriving from bisabolol, kaurenoic acid, limonene and camphene were synthetized by our research group [<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Among them, the tiosemicarbazide camphene derivative (TSC-C) showed remarkable antifungal activity. The previous study showed that TSC-C inhibited the growth of <italic>Trichophyton mentagrophytes</italic> by damaging the cell wall structure or interfering with its formation during the process of cell division, growth or morphogenesis [<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Based on these results, we elected TSC-C to study its activity and mode of action on <italic>Paracoccidioides brasiliensis</italic>.</p><p>We constructed a cDNA library to obtain expressed sequences tags (ESTs) from <italic>P</italic>. <italic>lutzii</italic> in response to TSC-C with the ultimate aim to identify the likely mode of action of the compound in the fungus. We performed assays to confirm the transcriptome data to <italic>P</italic>. <italic>lutzii</italic> and <italic>Paracoccidioides brasiliensis</italic>, such as quantitative real-time PCR (qRT-PCR), fluorescence microscopy, DNA fragmentation, cell cycle analysis by flow cytometry and enzymatic assays.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec002"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="sec003"><title>General procedure for the preparation of compounds</title><p>The TSC-C was prepared as described by Yamaguchi [<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec004"><title>Microorganism and cell culture</title><p>The <italic>P</italic>. <italic>lutzii</italic> ATCC MYA 826 and <italic>P</italic>. <italic>brasiliensis</italic> ATCC 60855 strains were used in the assays. Yeast cells were maintained in Fava-Netto liquid medium [<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] for 3 days. The cells were then transferred and grown overnight in McVeigh Morton (MMcM) liquid medium overnight [<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] and subsequently used in experiments.</p></sec><sec id="sec005"><title>Determination of inhibitory concentration (IC<sub>50</sub>)</title><sec id="sec006"><title>Preparation of resazurin</title><p>Resazurin powder (Sigma Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA) was dissolved in sterile distilled water at a final concentration of 0.02%, sterilized by filtration and stored at 4&#x000b0;C until use.</p></sec><sec id="sec007"><title>Preparation of the camphene thiosemicarbazide derivative</title><p>The stock solution of TSC-C was prepared in dimethyl sulfoxide (10% DMSO) and diluted to obtain the evaluated concentrations (316 &#x003bc;M, 158 &#x003bc;M, 79 &#x003bc;M, 39.5 &#x003bc;M and 19.5 &#x003bc;M).</p><p>The determination of IC<sub>50</sub> was performed according to the micro-dilution method described in the Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute (CLSI) [<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] and De Paula et al. [<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Were inoculated 1x10<sup>6</sup> cells/mL of <italic>P</italic>. <italic>lutzii</italic> yeast cells per microplate well in MMcM liquid medium supplemented with 316 &#x003bc;M, 158 &#x003bc;M, 79 &#x003bc;M or 39.5 &#x003bc;M TSC-C. To determine the maximum growth rate (positive control), some wells received culture medium in place of the 100 mL of test compound dilution. The plates were incubated at 36&#x000b0;C with shaking at 150 rpm for 48 h. Each well then received 15 &#x003bc;L of the resazurin solution, and the plate was re-incubated for 24 h. The IC<sub>50</sub> was defined as the concentration of compound capable of inhibiting 50% of cell growth of the fungus according to the absorbance at 600 nm.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec008"><title>Determination of the susceptibility of <italic>P</italic>. <italic>lutzii</italic> to the camphene thiosemicarbazide derivative</title><p>The TSC-C sensitivity test was carried out on plates containing Fava-Netto semi-solid medium supplemented with TSC-C. The concentrations tested were 316 &#x003bc;M, 158 &#x003bc;M, 79 &#x003bc;M and 39.5 &#x003bc;M. Negative control plates were prepared in the absence of TSC-C. A total of 10<sup>5</sup>, 10<sup>6</sup> and 10<sup>7</sup> yeast cells were inoculated on each plate. The plates were incubated for 7 days at 36&#x000b0;C and photographed.</p></sec><sec id="sec009"><title>Viability curve</title><p>Cell viability was determined using trypan blue staining and standard cell count techniques in a Neubauer chamber. We inoculated 1x10<sup>6</sup> cells/mL of <italic>P</italic>. <italic>lutzii</italic> yeast cells in MMcM liquid medium supplemented with TSC-C at 79 &#x003bc;M&#x02014;the IC<sub>50</sub> concentration&#x02014;for 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 8 and 24 h of incubation. The negative control was performed in the absence of TSC-C. For counting, samples were collected at specific time points, and 10 &#x003bc;L of the cell solution was added to 190 &#x003bc;L trypan blue solution and diluted to a final volume of 1 mL. Yeast cells were observed under light microscopy with a 40X lens.</p></sec><sec id="sec010"><title>RNA extraction and purification of mRNA</title><p>Total RNA was extracted after the incubation of <italic>Paracoccidiodies spp</italic>. yeast with TSC-C at 79 &#x003bc;M for 8 h of cultivation. The RNA was extracted with Trizol reagent (Invitrogen), precipitated with isopropanol, and resuspended with diethyl pyrocarbonate- (DEPC-) treated water. The mRNA was purified using the GenElute mRNA kit (Sigma Aldrich).</p></sec><sec id="sec011"><title>cDNA library construction and DNA sequencing</title><p>The cDNA library was built using the SuperScript Plasmid System with Gateway Technology for cDNA Synthesis and Cloning kit (Invitrogen). The cDNA was cloned into the pCMV.SPORT6 plasmid vector and transformed into <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic> (XL1blue) cells. The cDNA library was plated at approximately 200 colonies per plate (150 mm Petri dish). The colonies were randomly selected and transferred to a 96-well polypropylene plate containing LB medium and grown overnight. Plasmid cDNA was isolated and purified.</p><p>cDNA inserts were sequenced from the 5&#x02019; end by employing standard fluorescence labeling with the DYEnamic ET dye terminator kit with an M13 flanking vector primer. Automated sequence analysis was performed in a MegaBACE 1000 DNA sequencer (GE Healthcare, Uppsala, Sweden).</p></sec><sec id="sec012"><title>Pipeline processing and annotation of ESTs</title><p>PHRED [<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>], Crossmatch (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.macvector.com/Assembler/trimmingwithcrossmatch.html">http://www.macvector.com/Assembler/trimmingwithcrossmatch.html</ext-link>) and CAP3 [<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] tools were integrated into a pipeline (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.lbm.icb.ufg.br/pipelineUFG/">http://www.lbm.icb.ufg.br/pipelineUFG/</ext-link>). Only sequences with at least 50 nucleotides and a PHRED quality greater or equal to 20 were considered for assembly and cluster formation. ESTs were screened for vector sequences against the UniVec data. All of the clustered sequences were queried for similarity using BLASTX (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/BLAST">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/BLAST</ext-link>) sequence comparison software against the nucleotide database generated from the <italic>P</italic>. <italic>lutzii Pb</italic>01 structural genome (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.broad.mit.edu/annotation/genome/paracoccidioides_brasiliensis/MulHome.html">http://www.broad.mit.edu/annotation/genome/paracoccidioides_brasiliensis/MulHome.html</ext-link>). Sequences were grouped into functional categories with the PEDANT3 database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pedant.helmholtz-muenchen.de/index.jsp">http://pedant.helmholtz-muenchen.de/index.jsp</ext-link>). Similarities with E-values &#x02264; 10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup> were considered significant. The Munich Information Center for Protein Sequences (MIPS) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mips.gsf.de/">http://mips.gsf.de/</ext-link>) database was used to assign functional categories. EC numbers were obtained by the Enzyme Database-Brenda (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.brenda-enzymes.info">http://www.brenda-enzymes.info</ext-link>)</p></sec><sec id="sec013"><title><italic>In silico</italic> determination of up-regulated genes</title><p>To assign a differential expression character, ESTs from contigs formed from yeast cells treated with TSC-C were statistically evaluated using the method by Audic and Claverie [<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Overexpressed genes, determined by comparison to the <italic>P</italic>. <italic>lutzii</italic> transcriptome database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://dna.biomol.unb.br/Pb/">https://dna.biomol.unb.br/Pb/</ext-link>), were determined with a 95% confidence rate.</p></sec><sec id="sec014"><title>Generation of <italic>P</italic>. <italic>brasiliensis SOD1</italic>-aRNA isolate</title><p>DNA from the <italic>P</italic>. <italic>brasiliensis</italic> wild-type strain ATCC 60855 (WT) was extracted from yeast cultures during exponential growth. We employed a high-fidelity Platinum Taq DNA polymerase (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA) to amplify aRNA oligonucleotides designed on the PABG_03954 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.broadinstitute.org">www.broadinstitute.org</ext-link>) sequence of the <italic>SOD1</italic> gene. <italic>P</italic>. <italic>brasiliensis</italic> plasmid construction for aRNA and <italic>Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic>-mediated transformation were performed as previously described [<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Briefly, the amplified <italic>SOD1</italic>-aRNA oligonucleotides were inserted into the pCR35 plasmid under the control of the Calcium Binding Protein 1 (CBP-1) promoter region from <italic>Histoplasma capsulatum</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. The pUR5750 plasmid was used as a parental binary vector to harbor the aRNA cassette within the transfer DNA (T-DNA). The constructed binary vectors were introduced into <italic>A</italic>. <italic>tumefaciens</italic> LBA1100 ultracompetent cells by electroporation as described previously [<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] and isolated by kanamycin selection (100 mg/mL).</p><p><italic>P</italic>. <italic>brasiliensis</italic> and <italic>A</italic>. <italic>tumefaciens</italic> were combined in a 1:10 ratio and incubated for 3 days of co-culture at 28&#x000b0;C. Selection of <italic>P</italic>. <italic>brasiliensis</italic> transformants was performed in BHI solid media containing hygromycin B (Hyg; 200 mg/mL) over a 15 day incubation period at 36&#x000b0;C. Randomly selected Hyg resistant transformants were tested for mitotic stability. <italic>P</italic>. <italic>brasiliensis</italic> yeast cells transformed with the empty parental vector pUR5750 (EV) were used as controls alongside the experimental yeast in the assays carried out in this study. The integration of the a-RNA cassette in the <italic>P</italic>. <italic>brasiliensis</italic> genome was confirmed by PCR analysis.</p></sec><sec id="sec015"><title>Determination of the susceptibility of <italic>P</italic>. <italic>brasiliensis</italic> and the <italic>SOD1</italic>-aRNA isolate to TSC-C</title><p>To evaluate the susceptibility of <italic>P</italic>. <italic>brasiliensis</italic> to TSC-C, the WT, EV and <italic>SOD1</italic>-aRNA isolate strains were grown in Fava-Netto liquid medium for 72 h under constant shaking at 150 rpm and 36&#x000b0;C. Yeast were then transferred into MMcM liquid medium and cultured overnight. Yeast cells were then washed with 1X PBS, and the assays were performed with 1x10<sup>6</sup> cells. The different isolates were distributed in solid BHI medium supplemented with 316 &#x003bc;M, 158 &#x003bc;M, 79 &#x003bc;M and 39.5 &#x003bc;M TSC-C. The controls were carried out in the same medium without the addition of TSC-C. The <italic>SOD1</italic>-aRNA isolated was growth in the presence of TSC-C added of ascorbic acid aiming to validate the influence of TSC-C as indutor agente of ROS. Initially, the concentrations from 0.08 to 100 mM ascorbic acid were used to determinate IC<sub>50</sub> (data not shown). So, 0.2 mM ascorbic acid was added at 316 &#x003bc;M, 158 &#x003bc;M, 79 &#x003bc;M and 39.5 &#x003bc;M TSC-C. All plates were incubated for 6 days at 36&#x000b0;C before being photographed.</p></sec><sec id="sec016"><title>Gene expression analysis by qRT-PCR</title><p>Total RNA was obtained from <italic>Paracoccidioides spp</italic>. yeast cells grown in the presence or absence of TSC-C for 8 h. After treatment with DNase, the cDNA was synthesized from total RNA using Superscript II reverse transcriptase (Invitrogen) according to the manufacturer's instructions. The primers for, ATP synthase, Superoxide dismutase (<italic>SOD1</italic>) [PABG_03954 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.broadinstitute.org">www.broadinstitute.org</ext-link>)], Heat shock protein 30 kDa (<italic>HSP30)</italic>, alcohol dehydrogenase (<italic>ADH</italic>), aldehyde dehydrogenase (<italic>ALDH</italic>) and &#x003b1;-tubulin genes were designed using the Primer Express software (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, USA). The sequences of the oligonucleotide primers are shown in <xref rid="pone.0130703.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. The qRT-PCR analyses were performed in triplicate with the StepOnePlus real-time PCR system (Applied Biosystems). The expression values were calculated using the alpha tubulin transcript (XM_002796593) as the endogenous control as reported previously [<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. For transcripts of interest, relative expression levels were calculated using the standard curve method for relative quantification [<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. The relative standard curve was generated by pooling cDNAs from all conditions and serially diluting them from 1:5 to 1:625.</p><table-wrap id="pone.0130703.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0130703.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Oligonucleotide primers used in qRT-PCR.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0130703.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0130703.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence Name</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward primer (5&#x02019;-3&#x02019;)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse primer (5&#x02019;-3&#x02019;)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tm (GC+AT)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Alpha-Tubulin</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACAGTGCTTGGGAACTATACC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGGACATATTTGCCACTGCC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Superoxide dismutase 1</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACTGCGCAAGTTATGATGGAA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CACGGGAAGGGTCCATTTTC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>ATP synthase</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAGCAGCGAAAATAATGGGATC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GCAAATAATCCTGTAGCTTCTG</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Heat shock protein 30 kDa</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGCCTTGACAGCATTCTGG</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CTGGCGATAAAGGGCAGAAG</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Alcohol dehydrogenase</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACCTTGTTGTGCTGGAGTAGA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGAGTCTGGAATCGGGGTG</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Aldehyde dehydrogenase</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCTCTTACGGCCTTGCTGC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CGGACGCCCTTGATCTGAG</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec017"><title>Preparation of protein extracts from <italic>P</italic>. <italic>lutzii</italic></title><p>Protein extracts were obtained after 8 h incubation in MMcM in the presence of 79 &#x003bc;M TSC-C or in its absence. Yeast cells were centrifuged at 10,000 x <italic>g</italic> for 10 min at 4&#x000b0;C, and the proteins were extracted using extraction buffer (20 mM Tris-HCl pH 8.8; 2 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>) with a mixture of protease inhibitors (GE Healthcare). After the addition of glass beads (0.45 mm), the cells were lysed in a bead-beater, followed by centrifugation at 10,000 x <italic>g</italic> for 15 min at 4&#x000b0;C. The supernatant was collected and used in enzyme activity assays. The protein concentrations were determined using the Bradford reagent (Sigma-Aldrich), as previously described [<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec018"><title>Determination of enzymatic activity</title><p>SOD activity was measured using a commercially available kit (SOD assay Kit Sigma-Aldrich) following the manufacturer's instructions. The SOD assay kit utilizes the water-soluble tetrazolium salt-WST-1 (2-[4- Iodophenyl]-3-[4-nitrophenyl]-5-[2,4-disulfophenyl]-2H-tetrazolium, monosodium salt), which produces a water-soluble formazan dye upon reduction with a superoxide anion, and the product can be detected by a colorimetric method at 440 nm. 1 &#x003bc;g/mL of proteins was used in assay, and the levels of SOD activity were quantified by measuring the decrease in absorbance.</p></sec><sec id="sec019"><title>Reactive oxygen species (ROS) detection</title><p>Intracellular H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> was measured by detecting the fluorescence intensity of 2`,7`-dichlorofluorescein, the oxidation product of 2`,7`-dichlorofluorescein diacetate. After treatment with 79 &#x003bc;M TSC-C for 4, 8 and 12 h, yeast cells were centrifuged and incubated with 20 &#x003bc;M 2`,7`- dichlorofluorescein diacetate for 30 min at 37&#x000b0;C. After washing with PBS, yeast cells were resuspended in 1 mL PBS and analyzed with a BD Accuri C6 flow cytometer (Accuri Cytometers, Ann Arbor, MI, USA). A total of 10,000 cells per sample were acquired with the FL1-H channel.</p></sec><sec id="sec020"><title>Fluorescence microscopy</title><p>Yeast cells were inoculated in 100 mL MMcM medium at 1x10<sup>6</sup> cells/mL. The cultures were incubated overnight at 36&#x000b0;C with gentle shaking. Cells were then centrifuged at 5,000 x <italic>g</italic> for 5 min and transferred into MMcM media containing 79 &#x003bc;M TSC-C for 4, 8 and 12 h. Control cells were incubated in MMcM without TSC-C. To detect ROS, cells were centrifuged and incubated with 20 &#x003bc;M 2`,7`- dichlorofluorescein diacetate for 30 min at 37&#x000b0;C. The specimens were analyzed with an Axio Scope A1 microscope and Axio Vison LE software (Carl Zeiss AG, Germany).</p></sec><sec id="sec021"><title>DNA fragmentation assay</title><p>Yeast cells were treated with 79 &#x003bc;M TSC-C for 4, 8 and 12 h. Samples were centrifuged, the cell pellet was resuspended in 300 mL of cell lysis buffer (10 mM Tris, 0.5% Triton X-100, pH 7.5), and the sample was incubated on ice for 30 min. The lysates were centrifuged at 12,000 x <italic>g</italic> for 10 min at 4&#x000b0;C, and the supernatants were extracted once with buffered phenol and once with chloroform. DNA was precipitated with 3 M sodium acetate and butanol. DNA samples were resuspended in 50 &#x003bc;L Tris-EDTA buffer (10 mM Tris, 1 mM EDTA, pH 7.5) treated with RNaseA. Extracted DNA was electrophoresed through a 2% agarose gel and stained with ethidium bromide.</p></sec><sec id="sec022"><title>Cell cycle analysis</title><p>The DNA content of yeast cells in the G0/G1, S and G2/M phases was measured using a BD Accuri C6 flow cytometer (Accuri Cytometers). Cells were incubated with 79 &#x003bc;M TSC-C for 4, 8 and 12 h. After treatment, the cells were collected, washed with PBS 1X, and 1x10<sup>6</sup> cells/mL were fixed with cold absolute ethanol overnight at 4&#x000b0;C. After two washes with PBS 1X, the cells were incubated with 1 mL propidium iodide staining solution (2 &#x003bc;g/mL) and 50 &#x003bc;L RNase (10 mg/mL) and incubated for 30 min at room temperature in the dark. A total of 10,000 cells per sample were acquired with the FL2-H channel. Data were collected using FCS Express 4 Plus Research Edition software (Denovo Software, Los Angeles, CA, USA).</p></sec><sec id="sec023"><title>Mitochondrial membrane potential measurement</title><p>The mitochondrial membrane potential was measured using rhodamine 123 (Rho123). Yeast cells were treated with 79 &#x003bc;M TSC-C for 4, 8 and 12 h. After treatment, the cells were collected by centrifugation and incubated with 20 &#x003bc;M Rho123 for 20 min at room temperature. After a PBS wash, the cells were resuspended in 1 mL PBS and analyzed using a BD Accuri C6 flow cytometer (Accuri Cytometers) with excitation and emission wavelengths of 488 and 530 nm, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="sec024"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Descriptive statistics were calculated from the results, and charts were created in Microsoft Office Excel 2003 (Microsoft, Redmond, WA, USA). In this study, all of the values were expressed as arithmetic means with S.D. of triplicates. The significant differences between the groups were analyzed by Student&#x02019;s t-test and <italic>p</italic>-values &#x02264;0.05 were considered statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec025"><title>Results and Discussion</title><sec id="sec026"><title>The camphene thiosemicarbazide derivative affects <italic>Paracoccidioides spp</italic>. growth and viability</title><p>Here, we aimed to evaluate the effect of TSC-C on <italic>P</italic>. <italic>lutzii</italic>. The cells were incubated in the presence of TSC-C. <xref rid="pone.0130703.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1A</xref> demonstrates that TSC-C inhibited yeast growth in a dose-dependent manner. TSC-C at a concentration of 79 &#x003bc;M inhibited the cellular growth by 50% and became the IC<sub>50</sub> value of TSC-C for <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> yeast. Additionally, the cellular viability of the fungus was monitored in the presence of 79 &#x003bc;M TSC-C for 24 h. <xref rid="pone.0130703.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1B</xref> reveals that the yeast cell viability drops to 85% after 8 h of exposure to TSC-C, time used for the transcriptomic analysis. The dose-dependent inhibition was also observed in yeast cells grown on the solid medium supplemented with different concentrations of TSC-C (<xref rid="pone.0130703.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>). TSC-C (79 &#x003bc;M) was not toxic to Balb 3T3 cells (data not shown), These results confirmed the antifungal activity of this compound.</p><fig id="pone.0130703.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0130703.g001</object-id><label>Fig 1</label><caption><title>Effect of TSC-C on <italic>P</italic>. <italic>lutzii</italic> yeast cell growth.</title><p><bold>(A)</bold> Inhibition of <italic>Paracoccidioide</italic>s cell growth after treatment with TSC-C. The inhibition was visualized by addition of resazurin reagent to culture and measuring the absorbance at 600 nm. To calculate the IC<sub>50</sub> value, two absorbance readings were performed; &#x02018;1&#x000b0; day&#x02019; refers to reading at the beginning of the experiment, &#x02018;3&#x000b0; days&#x02019; refers to reading after 3 days of incubation with 316 &#x003bc;M, 158 &#x003bc;M, 79 &#x003bc;M and 39.5 &#x003bc;M TSC-C. The positive control was performed in the absence of the compound. <bold>(B</bold>) Cell viability after 1, 2, 3, 4, 8 and 24 h exposure to TSC-C. The data are presented as percentage of cell viability. The Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic>-test was used for statistical comparisons, and the observed differences were statistically significant (<italic>p</italic> &#x02264; 0.05). The error bars represent the standard deviation of three biological replicates.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0130703.g001"/></fig><fig id="pone.0130703.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0130703.g002</object-id><label>Fig 2</label><caption><title>Susceptibility of <italic>P</italic>. <italic>lutzii</italic> yeast cells exposed to TSC-C.</title><p>Samples containing 1x10<sup>7</sup>, 1x10<sup>6</sup> and 1x10<sup>5</sup> yeast cells were spotted on Fava-Netto plates supplemented with TSC-C at the concentrations indicated above. The plates were incubated for 7 days at 36&#x000b0;C before photo documentation.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0130703.g002"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec027"><title>cDNA library construction and overview of ESTs from <italic>P</italic>. <italic>lutzii</italic> exposed to TSC-C</title><p>A cDNA library was constructed to determine the expression profile of <italic>Paracoccidioides spp</italic>. exposed to TSC-C. The dosage and duration of antifungal treatment are known to be critical steps in adaptive gene expression [<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]; thus, the choice of these parameters was necessary for the construction of a cDNA library. The concentration used in the experiments was 79 &#x003bc;M corresponding to IC<sub>50</sub> of TSC-C for <italic>P</italic>. <italic>lutzii</italic>. The fungus was exposed to TSC-C for 8 h, since exhibited 85% viability.</p><p>We obtained a total of 2,012 clones, and 1,844 of these were successfully sequenced. All sequences were arranged into 68 contigs and 686 singlets representing different transcripts. Of these, 33 genes were down-regulated and 84 genes were up-regulated when compared to the transcriptome <italic>P</italic>. <italic>lutzii</italic> yeast cells grown <italic>in vitro</italic>. A total of 64 genes were unique to TSC-C-treated <italic>P</italic>. <italic>lutzii</italic> yeast cells. The ESTs obtained were submitted to the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI) under accession numbers: LIBEST_028508 <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> thiosemicarbazide Library.</p></sec><sec id="sec028"><title>Functional annotation and analysis of sequences</title><p>All up- and down-regulated ESTs were compared to <italic>Paracoccidioides Pb</italic>01 genes in the Broad Institute database with the Blast X program. Only ESTs with e-value &#x0003c; 10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup> were considered in this analysis. All contigs and singlets were annotated with Blas2GO. The ESTs were grouped according to the MIPS functional annotation scheme (Munich Information Center for Protein Sequences) into general functional categories affected by TSC-C. The ESTs were related to metabolism; cell cycle and DNA processing; biogenesis of cellular components; cellular communication/signal transduction mechanism; cell rescue, defense and virulence; energy; protein synthesis; protein fate; translation; and unclassified proteins (<xref rid="pone.0130703.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="pone.0130703.t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0130703.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Functional classification of up and down-regulated genes from <italic>P</italic>. <italic>lutzii</italic> yeast cells in the presence TSC-C.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0130703.t002g" xlink:href="pone.0130703.t002"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Functional classification/ Accession number</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene product</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EC number</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of occurences ESTs</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1"><bold>Metabolism</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>Amino acid metabolism</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_00468.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4-aminobutyrate aminotransferase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6.1.19</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_04052.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Homoserine O-acetyltransferase</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3.1.31</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>C-compound and carbohydrate metabolism</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_00771.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Enolase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.2.1.11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_05580.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>NAD dependent epimerase/dehydratase family protein</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.1.3.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_08949.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>GPI Mannosyltransferase</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>Lipid</italic>, <italic>fatty acid and isoprenoid metabolism</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_05837.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Palmitoyl-protein thioesterase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1.2.22</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_06329.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3-hydroxybutyryl-CoA dehydrogenase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1.1.157</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_06215.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Hydroxymethylglutaryl-coa lyase</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.1.3.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_08410.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acyl-coenzyme A:6-aminopenicillanic-acid-acyltransferase 40 kDa form</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3.1.164</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_03203.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protoheme IX farnesyltransferase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>Nitrogen</italic>, <italic>sulfur and selenium metabolism</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_00954.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urease</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5.1.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>Nucleotide/nucleoside/nucleobase metabolism</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_04291.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nucleoside diphosphate kinase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7.4.6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-5</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1"><bold>Cell cycle and DNA processing</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>DNA recombination and DNA repair</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_04357.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>DNA mismatch repair protein</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_05988.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>DNA-repair protein rad2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_04646.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Mold-specific protein MS95</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>Cell cycle</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_02186.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Nuclear segregation protein Bfr1</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_00513.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Cell division control protein</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_07814.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Subunit of condensin complex</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_03188.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Nuclear movement protein NUDC</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1"><bold>Biogenesis of cellular componentes</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>Cytoskeleton/structural proteins</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_05855.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Ankyrin repeat domain containing protein</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1"><bold>Cellular communication/signal transduction mechanism</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>Cellular signalling</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_03783.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GAF domain nucleotide-binding protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_03386.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cAMP&#x02014;Dependent protein kinase catalytic subunit</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7.11.11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_03923.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>TRAF-type zinc finger protein</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_01861.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Membrane associated progesterone receptor component 1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6.2.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+5</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1"><bold>Cell rescue, defense and virulence</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>Stress response</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_00871.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heat shock protein 30 kDa</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_04164.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Superoxide dismutase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.15.1.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+5</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1"><bold>Cellular transport, transport facilities and transport routes</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>Transport routes</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_00782.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Small COPII coat GTPase sar</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_07328.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Transport protein SEC61 subunit alpha</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_09049.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>ENTH domain-containing protein</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_05643.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Endoplasmic reticulum and nuclear membrane proteinc Npl4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_08587.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GPR1/FUN34/yaaH family protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_05251.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High affinity copper transporter</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>Transported compounds (substrates)</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_00635.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>ABC transporter CDR4</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6.3.44</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+3</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1"><bold>Energy</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>Glycolysis and gluconeogenesis</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_00403.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alcohol dehydrogenase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1.1.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-4</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>Energy conversion and regeneration</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_04570.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATP synthase D chain, mitochondrial</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6.3.14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>Respiration</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_08901.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Glyoxylate reductase</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1.1.26</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_05249.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aldehyde dehydrogenase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2.1.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>Electron transport and membrane-associated energy conservation</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_06595.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3-demethylubiquinone-9 3-methyltransferase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_05031.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>NADH-ubiquinone oxidoreductase 40 kDa subunit</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6.5.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_01307.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>NADH dehydrogenase iron-sulfur protein</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6.99.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_07593.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cytochrome-c oxidase chain VIIc</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9.3.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1"><bold>Protein synthesis</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>Ribosome biogenesis</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_09043.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ribossomal protein 40S&#x02014;S2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_01785.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ribossomal protein 40S&#x02014;S3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_05017.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ribossomal protein 40S&#x02014;S10-A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_01433.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ribossomal protein 40S&#x02014;S14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_00088.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ribossomal protein 60S&#x02014;L3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_07955.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ribossomal protein 60S&#x02014;L18</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_00205.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ribossomal protein 60S&#x02014;L24</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_04965.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ribossomal protein 60S&#x02014;L31</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_07841.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ribossomal protein 60s&#x02014;P1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_03664.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ribossomal protein L28e</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_00206.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ribossomal protein S30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_07649.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ribossomal protein S36</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_03828.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ribossomal protein 40 S-S9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>Translation</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_02024.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elongation factor 1-alpha</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_07105.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Isoleucyl-tRNA synthetase</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1.1.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1"><bold>Protein fate (folding, modification, destination)</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>Assembly of protein complexes</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_05879.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Complex I intermediate-associated protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_02594.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Phosphoprotein phosphatase 2C</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1.3.16</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>Protein folding and stabilization</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_05788.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Peptidyl-prolyl cis-trans isomerase A2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.2.1.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>Protein/peptide degradation</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_05052.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>AAA Family ATPase</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>Protein modification</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_05777.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Dual specificity phosphatase catalytic domain containing protein</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1"><bold>Transcription</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>RNA synthesis</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_07098.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Histone H4.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_08917.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Histone H2a</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_08532.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Ribonuclease Z</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1.26.11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_00891.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>AT hook motif Family protein</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1"><bold>Unclassified Proteins</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_04823.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_03567.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Hypothetical protein</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_05112.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Hypothetical protein</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_04156.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Hypothetical protein</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_01567.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Hypothetical protein</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_03475.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Hypothetical protein</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_03684.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Hypothetical protein</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_03129.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Hypothetical protein</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_06864.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Hypothetical protein</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_01497.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Hypothetical protein</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_07875.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Hypothetical protein</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_04268.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_02546.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_08699.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Hypothetical protein</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_04869.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Hypothetical protein</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_02037.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Hypothetical protein</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_02676.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Hypothetical protein</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_07947.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Hypothetical protein</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_08808.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Hypothetical protein</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_00149.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Hypothetical protein</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_01940.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Hypothetical protein</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_07462.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Hypothetical protein</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_01216.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Hypothetical protein</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_02607.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_05412.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Hypothetical protein</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_05607.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Hypothetical protein</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_05415.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Hypothetical protein</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_07420.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Hypothetical protein</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_07885.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Hypothetical protein</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_00947.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Hypothetical protein</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_02407.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Hypothetical protein</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_08549.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Hypothetical protein</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_08355.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Hypothetical protein</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_02237.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Hypothetical protein</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_02996.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+18</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_07710.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_04455.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Hypothetical protein</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_06704.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Hypothetical protein</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_08976.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Hypothetical protein</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_04152.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Hypothetical protein</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_05097.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Hypothetical protein</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_06142.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Hypothetical protein</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_01456.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Hypothetical protein</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_04691.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_04913.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_04707.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_03385.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_07334.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_04431.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_08722.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_00415.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PAAG_03232.2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t002fn001"><p>Genes in bold correspond to single genes in condition TSC-C. The signs + and - represent induced and repressed genes, respectively.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Graphs were plotted to demonstrate the statistically enriched MIPS functions with up- or down-regulated genes after exposure to the compound. A total of 51% (161 ESTs) were associated with proteins of unknown function (<xref rid="pone.0130703.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3A</xref>). Transcriptome analysis revealed that ESTs associated with metabolism (9%) and protein synthesis (9%) were the most highly represented after 8 h of TSC-C exposure (<xref rid="pone.0130703.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3B</xref>). The TSC-C treatment resulted in the up- and down-regulation of genes involved in different biological processes (<xref rid="pone.0130703.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>; Fig <xref rid="pone.0130703.g003" ref-type="fig">3C</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0130703.g003" ref-type="fig">3D</xref>). The groups with the highest percentage of up-regulated genes were unclassified proteins (50%); metabolism (12%); cell cycle and DNA processing (8%); energy (6%); transcription (5%); protein fate (5%); cellular transport, transport facilities and transport routes (5%); biogenesis of cellular components (2%); protein synthesis (1%); and cell rescue, defense and virulence (1%) (<xref rid="pone.0130703.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3C</xref>). The highest percentage of down-regulated genes were grouped within protein synthesis (43%); unclassified proteins (27%); cellular transport, transport facilities and transport routes (9%); energy (6%); and cell rescue, defense and virulence (3%) (<xref rid="pone.0130703.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3D</xref>).</p><fig id="pone.0130703.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0130703.g003</object-id><label>Fig 3</label><caption><title>Statistically enriched MIPS functions.</title><p><bold>(A)</bold> Total ESTs represented by classified and unclassified categories. <bold>(B)</bold> Genes expressed differentially in the presence of camphene thiosemicarbazide derivate. Up- <bold>(C)</bold> or down- <bold>(D)</bold> regulated <italic>P</italic>. <italic>lutzii</italic> genes after exposure of yeast cells to TSC-C. The functional classification was based on the MIPS functional annotation scheme. Each functional class is represented as a color-coded segment and expressed as a percentage of the total number of ESTs.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0130703.g003"/></fig><p>We analyzed transcript occurrence by determining the number of ESTs found for each transcript. The transcripts with the highest occurrence of up-regulated ESTs were as follows: hypothetical protein PAAG_02996 (18 ESTs), histone H 4.1 (8 ESTs), hypothetical protein PAAG_03567 (6 ESTs), hypothetical protein PAAG_07875 (5 ESTs), histone H2a (5 ESTs), membrane-associated progesterone receptor component 1 (5 ESTs), 3-demethylquinone-9 3-methyltransferase (5 ESTs), hydroxymethylglutaryl-CoA lyase (5 ESTs) and superoxide dismutase (5 ESTs). For down-regulated ESTs, the highest abundance were as follows: hypothetical protein PAAG_04431 (7 ESTs), hypothetical protein PAAG_03385 (5 ESTs), nucleoside diphosphate kinase (5 ESTs) and ribosomal protein 60S &#x02013;L31 (5 ESTs).</p></sec><sec id="sec029"><title>Description of transcripts changed during exposure to TSC-C</title><p>ABC transporter <italic>CDR4</italic> was induced in TSC-C-treated <italic>P</italic>. <italic>lutzii</italic> yeast cells. These are transmembrane proteins that utilize energy generated by the hydrolysis of adenosine triphosphate (ATP) to carry out biological processes including the translocation of various substrates across membranes [<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. In addition, they are involved in multidrug resistance in other human pathogens such as <italic>Candida albicans</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] <italic>Aspergillus fumigatus</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>] and <italic>Cryptococcus neoformans</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Notably, its induction has been correlated with the protection of <italic>Aspergillus nidulans</italic> against cytotoxic agents [<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>].</p><p>Similarly, most genes related to protein fate were induced in the presence of TSC-C. Conversely, genes related to protein synthesis, mainly ribosomal proteins, were inhibited. It is well established that ribonuclease inhibitors such as the vanadyl ribonucleoside complex (VRC) can inhibit RNases involved in ribosomal subunit formation, resulting in a decreased rate of ribosomal subunit synthesis [<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>].</p><p>Another gene strongly repressed in the presence of TSC-C was the endoplasmic reticulum and nuclear membrane protein <italic>NPL4</italic>. In <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>, the Npl4p protein is part of a highly conserved protein complex required for the proteasome-mediated processing and activation of ER-membrane-bound transcription factors, resulting in proper membrane fluidity and organelle function. Furthermore, the perturbation of membrane composition in mutant npl4 cells leads to the loss of ER/nuclear envelope integrity, which in turn causes the observed defects in nuclear transport [<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>].</p><p>Here, we observed the down-regulation of a high affinity copper transporter (<xref rid="pone.0130703.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>), suggesting that TSC-C could interfere with copper homeostasis on <italic>Paracoccidioides spp</italic>. Copper is an essential cofactor for a wide variety of enzymes in crucial biological processes critical for cell growth, differentiation and survival [<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. Some studies suggest that copper acquisition plays an important role in the virulence of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>neoformans</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. However, at high intracellular concentrations, copper can be toxic due to the perturbation of the cellular redox potential, which increases production of reactive free radicals and indirectly increases oxidative stress [<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. In <italic>S</italic>. <italic>cerevisiae</italic>, the high-affinity copper transport proteins, which play an important role in regulating copper homeostasis, are induced by copper deprivation and repressed by copper excess [<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>].</p><p>The mitochondrial electron transport chain performs the transfer of electrons from glycolysis and the Krebs cycle and thereby creates an electrochemical gradient and energy, which is used for a variety of vital processes that include, ATP synthesis [<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>], ion homeostasis [<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>], protein import [<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>] and programmed cell death [<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. Because energy metabolism and redox state are potential targets, the development of drugs that specifically compromise the structural and functional integrity of mitochondria may provide novel opportunities to combat fungal infections [<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. Studies <italic>in vitro</italic> have demonstrated the interaction between drugs and mitochondria that may prove useful in several therapies [<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. In this sense, mitochondrial insult or failure can rapidly lead to the inhibition of cell survival and proliferation [<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. Furthermore, here we uncovered that genes related to electron transport, such as NADH-ubiquinone oxidoreductase 40 kDa subunit, NADH dehydrogenase iron-sulfur protein and cytochrome-c oxidase chain VII c, were induced in the presence of TSC-C; however, the expression of the ATP synthase D chain was inhibited (<xref rid="pone.0130703.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4A</xref>), suggesting that TSC-C could destabilize the electron transport chain and, as a consequence, decrease the production of ATP in <italic>P</italic>. <italic>lutzii</italic>.</p><fig id="pone.0130703.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0130703.g004</object-id><label>Fig 4</label><caption><p>Effect of TSC-C on the genes and <italic>SOD1</italic> activity of <italic>P</italic>. <italic>lutzii</italic>
<bold>(A)</bold> Gene expression profile of yeast cells exposed to TSC-C for 8 h. Changes in the gene expression levels were calculated by the relative standard curve method using the non-treated control samples to calibrate. Each error bar represents the standard error of the mean (&#x000b1;SD), and significant fold changes are denoted by asterisks in the figure (*<italic>p</italic>&#x02264;0.05). Data were normalized with the transcript encoding the &#x003b1;-tubulin protein. <bold>(B)</bold> SOD1 activity. Yeast cells were grown in the presence of TSC-C for 8 h, and total protein was extracted to measure SOD1 activity. The Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic>-test was used for statistical comparisons, and the observed differences were statistically significant (<italic>p</italic>&#x02264;0.05). Error bars represent the standard deviation of three biological replicates.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0130703.g004"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec030"><title>TSC-C induces <italic>SOD1</italic> up-regulation as a consequence of TSC-C-induced ROS</title><p>Superoxide dismutases (SODs) constitute the primary antioxidant defense against ROS, promoting dismutation of the superoxide radical (O<sup>2&#x02212;</sup>) into molecular oxygen and H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, which are less toxic for the cell. ROS-generating agents induce fungal SODs, among other proteins [<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. <italic>SOD3</italic> protects <italic>H</italic>. <italic>capsulatum</italic> yeast cells from host-derived oxidative stress by detoxifying ROS produced by macrophages and neutrophils, thereby enabling the survival of the fungus [<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. In the case of <italic>Paracoccidioides spp</italic>., the induction of <italic>SOD1</italic> protein is similarly observed in cells exposed to H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> [<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. In <italic>C</italic>. <italic>albicans</italic>, another fungal pathogen, the inactivation of ROS detoxifying enzymes has been shown to attenuate its virulence [<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>].</p><p>Here, we confirmed the up-regulation of <italic>SOD1</italic> in <italic>P</italic>. <italic>lutzii</italic> and <italic>P</italic>. <italic>brasiliensis</italic> by qRT-PCR (Figs <xref rid="pone.0130703.g004" ref-type="fig">4A</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0130703.g006" ref-type="fig">6D</xref>) and by enzymatic activity assay in <italic>P</italic>. <italic>lutzii</italic> (<xref rid="pone.0130703.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4B</xref>), suggesting that TSC-C could induce the formation of ROS leading to oxidative stress in <italic>Paracoccidioides spp</italic>. yeast cells. Thus, to confirm our hypothesis, we evaluated the production of ROS by means of fluorescence microscopy and flow cytometry. In yeast cells treated with TSC-C, we observed an increase in fluorescence in a time-dependent manner, indicating that this compound could be inducing the formation of ROS in <italic>P</italic>. <italic>lutzii</italic> (Fig <xref rid="pone.0130703.g005" ref-type="fig">5A</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0130703.g005" ref-type="fig">5B</xref>). The main classes of antifungal drugs used in the treatment of invasive fungal infections, such as azoles, polyenes and echinocandins, are also capable of inducing ROS production [<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>].</p><fig id="pone.0130703.g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0130703.g005</object-id><label>Fig 5</label><caption><title>Formation of ROS by TSC-C.</title><p>(A) Fluorescence microscopy of <italic>P</italic>. <italic>lutzii</italic> yeast cells stained with 2`,7`-dichlorofluorescein diacetate. Yeast cells were grown in the absence of TSC-C for <bold>i)</bold> 4 h, <bold>ii)</bold> 8 h and <bold>iii)</bold> 12 h and in the presence of TSC-C for <bold>iv)</bold> 4 h, <bold>v)</bold> 8 h and <bold>vi)</bold> 12 h. <bold>(B)</bold> Flow cytometry analysis of yeast cells grown in the absence or in the presence of TSC-C. The cells were monitored for <bold>i)</bold> 4 h, <bold>ii)</bold> 8 h and <bold>iii)</bold> 12 h stained with 2`,7`-dichlorofluorescein diacetate. Black histograms represent control yeast cells, and green histograms represent yeast cells treated with TSC-C.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0130703.g005"/></fig><fig id="pone.0130703.g006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0130703.g006</object-id><label>Fig 6</label><caption><title>Gene silencing of <italic>SOD1</italic> in <italic>P</italic>. <italic>brasiliensis</italic>.</title><p><bold>(A)</bold> Transfer DNA (T-DNA) inserted into the genome of <italic>P</italic>. <italic>brasiliensis</italic> yeast cells via ATMT in order to silence the <italic>SOD1</italic> gene. The antisense oligonucleotide was directed to exon 3 (black box) that amplify a length of 85 bp. This AS oligonucleotide was placed under the control of the calcium binding protein (<italic>CBP</italic>-1) with a terminator (<italic>CAT</italic>-B); the plasmid contained hygromycin B phosphotransferase (<italic>HPH</italic>) under the control of glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate of <italic>Aspergillus nidulans</italic> (<italic>PGPDA</italic>) with a terminator (<italic>TTRCP</italic>). <bold>(B)</bold>
<italic>PbSOD1</italic> gene expression levels obtained by RT-qPCR. The measurement was normalized with the housekeeping gene alpha-tubulin in WT, EV and <italic>SOD1</italic>-aRNA yeast cells growing in the exponential phase. Mitotic stability was confirmed by sub-culturing <italic>P</italic>. <italic>brasiliensis SOD1</italic>-aRNA yeast cells and testing for low expression levels in this isolate after successive sub-cultures. (C) Validation by PCR of the presence and integration of the Transfer DNA (T-DNA) into the genome of <italic>P</italic>. <italic>brasiliensis</italic> transformant. The genomic DNA from the <italic>SOD1</italic>-aRNA isolate was tested by PCR using specific primers for the alpha-tubulin gene <italic>TUB</italic> (Tub, lane 3), for the transformation constructs pCR35 (pCR, lane 4) and pUR5750 (pUR, lane 5) and for the hygromycin resistance gene (hph, lane 6). (D) <italic>SOD1</italic> expression profile in <italic>P</italic>. <italic>brasiliensis</italic> after exposure to TSC-C. RNA was extracted after 8 h of exposure of yeast cells to TSC-C. Changes in gene expression levels were calculated by the relative standard curve method using the non-treated control samples to calibrate.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0130703.g006"/></fig><p>Taking into account the above results, we inquired about the importance of <italic>SOD1</italic> during TSC-C treatment. To validate our assumption, we created a <italic>P</italic>. <italic>brasiliensis</italic> isolate (<italic>SOD1</italic>-aRNA) with down-regulated <italic>SOD1</italic> gene expression (Fig <xref rid="pone.0130703.g006" ref-type="fig">6A</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0130703.g006" ref-type="fig">6B</xref>). The PCR analysis was performed to confirm the integration of the a-RNA cassette in the <italic>P</italic>. <italic>brasiliensis</italic> genome (<xref rid="pone.0130703.g006" ref-type="fig">Fig 6C</xref>). <italic>SOD1</italic>-aRNA was obtained to ATCC 60855 isolate since <italic>SOD1</italic> was also induced in this isolate (<xref rid="pone.0130703.g006" ref-type="fig">Fig 6D</xref>) and the protocol to obtainment of mutant to <italic>P</italic>. <italic>brasiliensis</italic> has not yet standardized. The susceptibility of ATCC60855 and <italic>SOD1</italic>-aRNA to TSC-C was evaluated (<xref rid="pone.0130703.g007" ref-type="fig">Fig 7</xref>). When <italic>SOD1</italic>-aRNA isolate cells were exposed to TSC-C, we observed a reduced growth rate relative to WT and EV yeast cells. The growth was restored in the presence of antioxidant, ascorbic acid. This result corroborates our transcriptional data that indicate an up-regulation of <italic>SOD1</italic> during TSC-C treatment and suggests that the up-regulation of this gene is important for <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> survival in the presence of the compound.</p><fig id="pone.0130703.g007" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0130703.g007</object-id><label>Fig 7</label><caption><title>Susceptibility of <italic>P</italic>. <italic>brasiliensis SOD1</italic>-aRNA to TSC-C.</title><p>1x10<sup>6</sup> yeast cells of <italic>P</italic>. <italic>brasiliensis</italic> WT60855, EV60855 and <italic>SOD1</italic>-aRNA were spotted on solid BHI supplemented with 39.5, 79 and 158 &#x003bc;M TSC-C. Control cells were spotted on BHI without TSC-C or with 39.5, 79 and 158 &#x003bc;M TSC-C and ascorbic acid. The plates were incubated for 7 days at 36&#x000b0;C before photo documentation.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0130703.g007"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec031"><title>TSC-C-induced ROS leads to the collapse of the <italic>P</italic>. <italic>lutzii</italic> mitochondrial membrane</title><p>Mitochondrial ROS production can lead to the oxidative damage of mitochondrial proteins, membranes and DNA, thereby impairing the ability of this organelle to synthesize ATP and carry out its wide range of metabolic functions; such functions include the tricarboxylic acid cycle, fatty acid oxidation, the urea cycle and amino acid metabolism, which are pivotal for the normal function of most cells [<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. Furthermore, ROS also would cause a transition in mitochondrial permeability. This transition consists of the loss of the mitochondrial membrane potential, resulting from the formation of pores, and subsequent cell death [<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. Because TSC-C induces the production of ROS, we evaluated the mitochondrial membrane integrity by estimating the electric potential (&#x00394;&#x003a8;m) with fluorescence in yeast grown in the presence of TSC-C for 4, 8 and 12 h. Flow cytometry analysis revealed a &#x00394;&#x003a8;m decrease in the yeast cells exposed to the compound relative to control cells (<xref rid="pone.0130703.g008" ref-type="fig">Fig 8</xref>), suggesting that the TSC-C-induced ROS lead to the collapse of the mitochondrial membrane.</p><fig id="pone.0130703.g008" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0130703.g008</object-id><label>Fig 8</label><caption><title>Effect of TSC-C on the mitochondrial membrane potential of <italic>P</italic>. <italic>lutzii</italic>.</title><p>The mitochondrial membrane potential (&#x00394;&#x003a8;m) was determined by flow cytometry analysis of yeast cells treated with TSC-C for <bold>A)</bold> 4 h, <bold>B)</bold> 8 h and <bold>C)</bold> 12 h and stained with rodhamine123. Histograms in black represent the controls, and red histograms represent cells treated with TSC-C.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0130703.g008"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec032"><title>TSC-C inhibits cell proliferation by changing the expression profile of genes related to the cell cycle</title><p>Cell cycle and DNA processing were among the major classes of overexpressed genes in <italic>P</italic>. <italic>lutzii</italic> cells exposed to TSC-C. From these, 8 were unique to yeast cells grown in the presence of TSC-C, and these included DNA mismatch repair protein and DNA repair protein <italic>RAD2</italic>. Therefore, we explored the possibility that the induction of these genes was associated with DNA damage through a DNA fragmentation assay. In fact, we did not observe DNA fragmentation in the samples cultured in the presence of TSC-C for any of the times tested (<xref rid="pone.0130703.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Fig</xref>).</p><p>Considering the identity of the genes differentially regulated by the presence of the compound, we evaluated the <italic>P</italic>. <italic>lutzii</italic> cell cycle by analyzing DNA content by flow cytometry. The phase of the cell cycle was determined by the difference in DNA content between cells in the pre-replicative (G0 and G1) phases, the replicative (S) phase (DNA synthesis) and the post-replicative plus mitotic (G2+M) phases [<xref rid="pone.0130703.ref071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. The results showed that the percentage of yeast cells in the G1 phase increased in a time-dependent manner after exposure to TSC-C; furthermore, the number of cells in the S and G2 phases decreased (<xref rid="pone.0130703.g009" ref-type="fig">Fig 9</xref>). Altogether, these results indicate that TSC-C inhibits cell proliferation by changing the expression profile of genes related to the cell cycle.</p><fig id="pone.0130703.g009" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0130703.g009</object-id><label>Fig 9</label><caption><title>Effect of TSC-C on the <italic>P</italic>. <italic>lutzii</italic> cell cycle.</title><p>The DNA content of yeast in each cell cycle phase was analyzed by flow cytometry in the absence of TSC-C for <bold>A)</bold> 4 h, <bold>B)</bold> 8 h and <bold>C)</bold> 12 h or in the presence of TSC-C for <bold>D)</bold> 4 h, <bold>E)</bold> 8 h and <bold>F)</bold> 12 h and subsequently stained with ethidium iodide as represented by histograms.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0130703.g009"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec033"><title>Conclusion</title><p>TSC-C seems to induce the formation of ROS in <italic>Paracoccidioides spp</italic>., leading to the collapse of the mitochondrial membrane, and also to inhibit cell proliferation by changing the expression of genes related to the cell cycle. Relevant genes related to protein synthesis, copper homeostasis and cellular response induced by drugs or stress conditions were also observed in <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> yeast cells exposed to TSC-C. The high percentage of unclassified proteins found here indicates that further studies are needed in order to better understand how TSC-C affects <italic>Paracoccidioides spp</italic>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec034"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0130703.s001"><label>S1 Fig</label><caption><title>DNA fragmentation assay.</title><p>DNA fragmentation was carried out in P. lutzii yeast cells exposed to TSC-C at 79 &#x003bc;M for 4, 8 and 12 h. The controls were performed with yeast cells incubated in the absence of TSC-C.</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0130703.s001.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0130703.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bagagli</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Theodoro</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bosco</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McEwen</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>. <article-title><italic>Paracoccidioides brasiliensis</italic>: phylogenetic and ecological aspects</article-title>. <source>Mycopathologia</source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>165</volume>: <fpage>197</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2007</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18777629</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bocca</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Amaral</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Teixeira</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shikanai-Yasuda</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Soares Felipe</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Paracoccidioidomycosis: eco-epidemiology, taxonomy and clinical and therapeutic issues</article-title>. <source>Future Microbiol</source>. <year>2013</year>; <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>1177</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1179</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2217/fmb.13.68">10.2217/fmb.13.68</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24020744</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Marques</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Paracoccidioidomycosis: epidemiological, clinical, diagnostic and treatment up-dating</article-title>. <source>An Bras Dermatol</source>. <year>2013</year>; <volume>88</volume>: <fpage>700</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>711</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1590/abd1806-4841.20132463">10.1590/abd1806-4841.20132463</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24173174</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Travassos</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Taborda</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Colombo</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Treatment options for paracoccidioidomycosis and new strategies investigated</article-title>. <source>Expert Rev Anti Infect Ther</source>. <year>2008</year>; <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>251</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>262</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1586/14787210.6.2.251">10.1586/14787210.6.2.251</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18380607</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Borges</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chambela Mda</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oliveira Rde</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wanke</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Itraconazole vs. trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole: A comparative cohort study of 200 patients with paracoccidioidomycosis</article-title>. <source>Med Mycol</source>. <year>2014</year>; <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>303</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>310</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/mmy/myt012">10.1093/mmy/myt012</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24577007</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bocca</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Amaral</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Teixeira</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shikanai-Yasuda</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Soares Felipe</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Paracoccidioidomycosis: eco-epidemiology, taxonomy and clinical and therapeutic issues</article-title>. <source>Future Microbiol</source>. <year>2013</year>; <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>1177</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1191</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2217/fmb.13.68">10.2217/fmb.13.68</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24020744</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yasuda</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Pharmacological management of paracoccidioidomycosis</article-title>. <source>Expert Opin Pharmacother</source>. <year>2005</year>; <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>385</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>397</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15794730</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>De Oliveira</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>da Silva Neto</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Parente</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>da Silva</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Quintino</surname><given-names>GO</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Voltan</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Intermolecular interactions of the malate synthase of <italic>Paracoccidioides spp</italic></article-title>. <source>BMC Microbiol</source>. <year>2013</year>; <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>107</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2180-13-107">10.1186/1471-2180-13-107</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23672539</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Santana</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vainstein</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tomazett</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Santos-Silva</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>G&#x000f3;es</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schrank</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Distinct chitinases are expressed during various growth phases of the human pathogen <italic>Paracoccidioides brasiliensis</italic></article-title>. <source>Mem Inst Oswaldo Cruz</source>. <year>2012</year>; <volume>107</volume>: <fpage>310</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>316</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22510825</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cruz</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brock</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zambuzzi-Carvalho</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Santos-Silva</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Troian</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>G&#x000f3;es</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Phosphorylation is the major mechanism regulating isocitrate lyase activity in <italic>Paracoccidioides brasiliensis</italic> yeast cells</article-title>. <source>FEBS J</source>. <year>2011</year>; <volume>278</volume>: <fpage>2318</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2332</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1742-4658.2011.08150.x">10.1111/j.1742-4658.2011.08150.x</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21535474</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tomazett</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Castro Nda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lenzi</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>de Almeida Soares</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Response of <italic>Paracoccidioides brasiliensis</italic> Pb01 to stressor agents and cell wall osmoregulators</article-title>. <source>Fungal Biol</source>. <year>2011</year>; <volume>115</volume>: <fpage>62</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>69</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.funbio.2010.10.005">10.1016/j.funbio.2010.10.005</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21215956</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tomazett</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>F&#x000e9;lix</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lenzi</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>de Paula Faria</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>de Almeida Soares</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>1,3-&#x003b2;-d-Glucan synthase of <italic>Paracoccidioides brasiliensis</italic>: recombinant protein, expression and cytolocalization in the yeast and mycelium phases</article-title>. <source>Fungal Biol</source>. <year>2010</year>; <volume>114</volume>: <fpage>809</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>816</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.funbio.2010.07.007">10.1016/j.funbio.2010.07.007</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20943190</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Santos-Silva</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Cloning, mechanistic and functional analysis of a fungal sterol C24-methyltransferase implicated in brassicasterol biosynthesis</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source>. <year>2010</year>; <volume>1801</volume>: <fpage>1163</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1174</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.bbalip.2010.06.007">10.1016/j.bbalip.2010.06.007</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20624480</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zambuzzi-Carvalho</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cruz</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Santos-Silva</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goes</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>The malate synthase of <italic>Paracoccidioides brasiliensis</italic> Pb01 is required in the glyoxylate cycle and in the allantoin degradation pathway</article-title>. <source>Med Mycol</source>. <year>2009</year>; <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>734</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>744</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3109/13693780802609620">10.3109/13693780802609620</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19888806</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>da Silva Neto</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>de F&#x000e1;tima da Silva</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mendes-Giannini</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lenzi</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>de Almeida Soares</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>.<article-title>The malate synthase of <italic>Paracoccidioides brasiliensis</italic> is a linked surface protein that behaves as an anchorless adhesin</article-title>. <source>BMC Microbiol</source>. <year>2009</year>; <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>272</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2180-9-272">10.1186/1471-2180-9-272</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20034376</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bonfim</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cruz</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jesuino</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ulhoa</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Molinari-Madlum</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Chitinase from Paracoccidioides brasiliensis: molecular cloning, structural, phylogenetic, expression and activity analysis</article-title>. <source>FEMS Immunol Med Microbiol</source>. <year>2006</year>; <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>269</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>283</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16487309</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zambuzzi-Carvalho</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tomazett</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ferri</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Borges</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Transcriptional profile of <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> induced by oenothein B, a potential antifungal agent from the Brazilian Cerrado plant <italic>Eugenia uniflora</italic></article-title>. <source>BMC Microbiol</source>. <year>2013</year>; <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>227</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2180-13-227">10.1186/1471-2180-13-227</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24119145</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ferri</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Oenothein B inhibits the expression of PbFKS1 transcript and induces morphological changes in <italic>Paracoccidioides brasiliensis</italic></article-title>. <source>Med Mycol</source>. <year>2007</year>; <volume>45</volume>: <fpage>609</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>618</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18033615</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Prado</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>CMA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Quintino</surname><given-names>GO</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Inhibition of <italic>Paracoccidioides lutzii Pb</italic>01 isocitrate lyase by the natural compound argentilactone and its semisynthetic derivatives</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2014</year>; <day>21</day>; <volume>9</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>e94832</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0094832">10.1371/journal.pone.0094832</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24752170</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Figueiredo</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>LV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sacoman</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kohn</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sarragiotto</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>. <article-title>Synthesis and Antiproliferative Activity of Novel Limonene Derivates with a Substituted Thiourea Moiety</article-title>. <source>Braz. J. Chem</source>. <year>2006</year>; <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>954</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>960</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Piochon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Legault</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gauthier</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pichette</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Synthesis and cytotoxicity evaluation of natural alpha-bisabolol beta-D-fucopyranoside and analogues</article-title>. <source>Phytochem</source>. <year>2009</year>; <volume>70</volume>: <fpage>228</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>236</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2008.11.013">10.1016/j.phytochem.2008.11.013</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19136127</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Da Silva</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Martini</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>de Oliveira</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cunha</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>de Carvalho</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ruiz</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>da Silva</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Antitumor activity of (-)-alpha-bisabolol- based thiosemicarbazones agains human tumor cell lines</article-title>. <source>Eur J Med Chem</source>. <year>2010</year>; <volume>45</volume>: <fpage>2987</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2993</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ejmech.2010.03.026">10.1016/j.ejmech.2010.03.026</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20413188</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Haraguchi</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vidotti</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>dos Santos</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>FP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pedroso</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>CV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>de Oliveira</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>da Silva</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Antitrypanasomal activity of novel benzaldehyde-thiosemicarbazone derivates from kaurenoic acid</article-title>. <source>Molecules</source>. <year>2011</year>; <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>1166</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1180</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3390/molecules16021166">10.3390/molecules16021166</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21270733</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>UM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>APB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>TU</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Filho</surname><given-names>BPD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>CV</given-names></name>. <article-title>Effects of a thiosemcarbazide camphene derivative on <italic>Trichophyton mentagrophytes</italic></article-title>. <source>Molecules</source>. <year>2009</year>; <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>1796</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1807</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3390/molecules14051796">10.3390/molecules14051796</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19471200</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fava-Netto</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>Estudos quantitativos sobre a fixa&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o de complemento na blastomicose sul-americana, com antigeno polissacar&#x000ed;dico</article-title>. <source>Arq Cir Clin Exp</source>.<year>1955</year>; <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>197</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>254</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13363721</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Restrepo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jim&#x000e9;nez</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name>. <article-title>Growth of <italic>Paracoccidioides brasiliensis</italic> yeast phase in a chemically defined culture medium</article-title>. <source>J Clin Microbiol</source>. <year>1980</year>; <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>279</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>281</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7229010</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Clinical Laboratory Standards Institute. Reference method for broth dilution antifungal susceptibility testing of filamentous fungi: Approved Standards 2nd Edition M27-A2. 2002.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>De Paula e Silva</surname><given-names>ACA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sangalli-Leite</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Scorzoni</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fusco-Almeida</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Microplate alamar Blue Assay for <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> Susceptibility Testing</article-title>. <source>J Clin Microbiol</source>. <year>2013</year>; <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>1250</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1252</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1128/JCM.02914-12">10.1128/JCM.02914-12</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23345296</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ewing</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hillier</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wendl</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>Base-calling of automated sequencer traces using phred. I. Accuracy assessment</article-title>. <source>Genome Res</source>. <year>1998</year>; <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>175</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>185</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9521921</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Madan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>CAP3: a DNA sequence assembly program</article-title>. <source>Genome Res</source>. <year>1999</year>; <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>868</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>877</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10508846</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Audic</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Claverie</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>. <article-title>The significance of digital gene expression profiles</article-title>. <source>Genome Res</source>. <year>1997</year>; <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>986</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>995</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9331369</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Almeida</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carmona</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cunha</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rappleye</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goldman</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Towards a molecular genetic system for the pathogenic fungus <italic>Paracoccidioides brasiliensis</italic></article-title>. <source>Fungal Genet Biol</source>. <year>2007</year>; <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>1387</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1398</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17512227</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rappleye</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Engle</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goldman</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name>. <article-title>RNA interference in Histoplasma capsulatum demonstrates a role for alpha-(1,3)-glucan in virulence</article-title>. <source>Mol microbiol</source>. <year>2004</year>; <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>153</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>165</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15225311</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Den Dulk-Ras</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hooykaas</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Electroporation of Agrobacterium tumefaciens</article-title>. <source>Methods Mol Biol</source>. <year>1995</year>; <volume>55</volume>: <fpage>63</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>72</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8528423</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bail&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nogueira</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rondon Caixeta Bonfim</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>de Castro</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>de Fatima da Silva</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mendes Giannini</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Comparative transcriptome analysis of <italic>Paracoccidioides brasiliensis</italic> during in vitro adhesion to type I collagen and fibronectin: identification of potential adhesins</article-title>. <source>Res Microbiol</source>. <year>2012</year>; <volume>163</volume>: <fpage>182</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>191</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.resmic.2012.01.004">10.1016/j.resmic.2012.01.004</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22306611</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bookout</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cummins</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mangelsdorf</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pesola</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>. <article-title>High-throughput real-time quantitative reverse transcription PCR</article-title>. <source>Curr Protoc Mol Biol</source>. <year>2006</year>; <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>8</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/0471142727.mb1508s73">10.1002/0471142727.mb1508s73</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18265376</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bradford</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>. <article-title>A rapid and sensitive method for the quantitation of microgram quantities of protein utilizing the principle of protein-dye binding</article-title>. <source>Anal Biochem</source>. <year>1976</year>; <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>248</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>254</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">942051</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Freiberg</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brotz-Oesterhelt</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Functional genomics in antibacterial drug discovery</article-title>. <source>Drug Discov Today</source>. <year>2005</year>; <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>927</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>935</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15993812</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Goffeau</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>de Hertogh</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baret</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name>. <article-title>ABC transportadores</article-title>. <source>In: Enciclop&#x000e9;dia of Biol. Chemistry</source>. <year>2004</year>; <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Franz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Michel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Morschhauser</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>A fourth gene from the <italic>Candida albicans</italic> CDR family of ABC transporters</article-title>. <source>Gene</source>. <year>1998</year>; <volume>220</volume>: <fpage>91</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>98</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9767132</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Prasad</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>De</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goffeau</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Balzi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>. <article-title>Molecular cloning and characterization of a novel gene of <italic>Candida albicans</italic>, CDR1, conferring multiple resistance to drugs and antifungals</article-title>. <source>Curr Genet</source>. <year>1995</year>; <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>320</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>329</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7614555</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Slaven</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sanglard</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bille</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Increased expression of a novel <italic>Aspergillus fumigatus</italic> ABC transporter gene, atrF, in the presence of itraconazole in an itraconazole resistant clinical isolate</article-title>. <source>Fungal Genet Biol</source>. <year>2002</year>; <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>199</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>206</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12135575</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tobin</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peery</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Skatrud</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Genes encoding multiple drug resistance-like proteins in <italic>Aspergillus fumigatus</italic> and <italic>Aspergillus flavus</italic></article-title>. <source>Gene</source>. <year>1997</year>; <volume>200</volume>: <fpage>11</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>23</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9373135</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Posteraro</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sanguinetti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sanglard</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>La</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Boccia</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Romano</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Identification and characterization of a <italic>Cryptococcus neoformans</italic> ATP binding cassette (ABC) transporter-encoding gene, CnAFR1, involved in the resistance to fluconazole</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>. <year>2003</year>; <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>357</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>371</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12519188</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Andrade</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Van Nistelrooy</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peery</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Skatrud</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>de Waard</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>. <article-title>The role of ABC transporters from <italic>Aspergillus nidulans</italic> in protection against cytotoxic agents and in antibiotic production</article-title>. <source>Mol Gen Genet</source>. <year>2000</year>; <volume>263</volume>: <fpage>966</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>977</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10954082</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref046"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Frazier</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Champney</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Inhibition of ribosomal subunit synthesis in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> by the vanadyl ribonucleoside complex</article-title>. <source>Curr Microbiol</source>. <year>2013</year>; <volume>67</volume>: <fpage>226</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>223</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00284-013-0350-5">10.1007/s00284-013-0350-5</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23512123</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref047"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hitchcock</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Krebber</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Frietze</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Latterich</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Silver</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>.<article-title>The conserved npl4 protein complex mediates proteasome-dependent membrane-bound transcription factor activation</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Cell</source>. <year>2001</year>; <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>3226</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3241</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11598205</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref048"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nevitt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thiele</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Mechanisms for copper acquisition, distribution and regulation</article-title>. <source>Nat Chem Biol</source>. <year>2008</year>; <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>176</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>185</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nchembio.72">10.1038/nchembio.72</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18277979</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref049"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Samanovic</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thiele</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Darwin</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name>. <article-title>Copper in microbial pathogenesis: meddling with the metal</article-title>. <source>Cell Host Microbe</source>. <year>2012</year>; <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>106</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>115</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.chom.2012.01.009">10.1016/j.chom.2012.01.009</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22341460</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref050"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Waterman</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hacham</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>YD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Role of a CUF1/CTR4 copper regulatory axis in the virulence of <italic>Cryptococcus neoformans</italic></article-title>. <source>J Clin Invest</source>. <year>2007</year>; <volume>117</volume>: <fpage>794</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>802</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17290306</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref051"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>Role of reactive oxygen species in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> inactivation by cupricion</article-title>. <source>Environ Sci Technol</source>. <year>2012</year>; <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>11299</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11304</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1021/es302379q">10.1021/es302379q</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22998466</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref052"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dancis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Haile</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Klausner</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>. <article-title>The Saccharomyces cerevisiae copper transport protein(Ctr1p). Biochemical characterization, regulation bycopper, and physiologic role in copper uptake</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>. <year>1994</year>; <volume>269</volume>: <fpage>25660</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>25667</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7929270</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref053"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pena</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Puig</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thiele</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Characterization of the <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> high affinity copper transporter Ctr3</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>. <year>2000</year>; <volume>275</volume>: <fpage>33244</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>33251</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10924521</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref054"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dimroth</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kaim</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Matthey</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>. <article-title>Crucial role of the membrane potential for ATP synthesis by F(1)F(o) ATP synthases</article-title>. <source>J Exp Biol J</source>. <year>2000</year>; <volume>203</volume>: <fpage>51</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>59</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10600673</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref055"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nicholls</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>. <article-title>Mitochondria and calcium signaling</article-title>. <source>Cell Calcium</source>. <year>2005</year>; <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>311</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>317</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16087232</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref056"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mahlke</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pfanner</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>. <article-title>Role of an energized inner membrane in mitochondrial protein import. Delta psi drives the movement of presequences</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>.<year>1991</year>; <volume>266</volume>: <fpage>18051</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>18057</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1833391</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref057"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ly</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Grubb</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lawen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>The mitochondrial membrane potential (deltapsi(m)) in apoptosis; an update</article-title>. <source>Apoptosis</source>. <year>2003</year>; <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>115</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>128</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12766472</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref058"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ghannoum</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name>. <article-title>Antifungal agents: mode of action, mechanisms of resistance, and correlation of these mechanisms with bacterial resistance</article-title>. <source>Clin Microbiol Rev</source>. <year>1999</year>; <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>501</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>517</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10515900</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref059"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dias</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bailly</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>Drugs targeting mitochondrial functions to control tumor cell growth</article-title>. <source>Biochem Pharmacol</source>. <year>2005</year>; <volume>70</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15907809</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref060"><label>60</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Grivicich</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Regner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>da Rocha</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Grass</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kayser</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Irinotecan/5-fluorouracil combination induces alterations in mitochondrial membrane potential and caspases on colon cancer cell lines</article-title>. <source>Oncol Res</source>. <year>2005</year>; <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>385</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>392</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16491956</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref061"><label>61</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Moreno-Sanchez</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bravo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vasquez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ayala</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Silveira</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez-Lav&#x000ed;n</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Inhibition and uncoupling of oxidative phosphorylation by nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs: study in mitochondria, submitochondrial particles, cells, and whole heart</article-title>. <source>Biochem Pharmacol</source>. <year>1999</year>; <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>743</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>752</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10075080</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref062"><label>62</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ruy</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vercesi</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kowaltowski</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Inhibition of specific electron transport pathways leads to oxidative stress and decreased <italic>Candida albicans</italic> proliferation</article-title>. <source>J Bioenerg Biomembr</source>. <year>2006</year>; <volume>38</volume>:<fpage>129</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>135</lpage>.<fpage>63</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17053999</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref063"><label>63</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Angelova</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pashova</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Spasova</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vassilev</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Slokoska</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Oxidative stress response of filamentous fungi induced by hydrogen peroxide and paraquat</article-title>. <source>Mycol Res</source>. <year>2005</year>; <volume>109</volume>: <fpage>150</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>158</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15839099</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref064"><label>64</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Youseff</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Holbrook</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Smolnycki</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rappleye</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Extracellular superoxide dismutase protects Histoplasma yeast cells from host-derived oxidative stress</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog</source>. <year>2012</year>; <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e1002713</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1002713">10.1371/journal.ppat.1002713</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22615571</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref065"><label>65</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>De Arruda Grossklaus</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bail&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vieira Rezende</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Borges</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>de Oliveira</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Parente</surname><given-names>J&#x000c1;</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Response to oxidative stress in Paracoccidioides yeast cells as determined by proteomic analysis</article-title>. <source>Microbes Infect</source>. <year>2013</year>; <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>347</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>364</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.micinf.2012.12.002">10.1016/j.micinf.2012.12.002</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23421979</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref066"><label>66</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rhie</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huh</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yim</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>SO</given-names></name>. <article-title>Copper- and zinc-containing superoxide dismutase (Cu/ZnSOD) is required for the protection of <italic>Candida albicans</italic> against oxidative stresses and the expression of its full virulence</article-title>. <source>Microbiol</source>. <year>2002</year>; <volume>148</volume>: <fpage>3705</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3713</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12427960</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref067"><label>67</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Delattin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cammue</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thevissen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>Reactive oxygen species-inducing antifungal agents and their activity against fungal biofilms</article-title>. <source>Future Med Chem</source>. <year>2014</year>; <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>77</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>90</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.4155/fmc.13.189">10.4155/fmc.13.189</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24358949</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref068"><label>68</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vandenbosch</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Braeckmans</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nelis</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Coenye</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>Fungicidal activity of miconazole against Candida <italic>spp</italic>. Biofilms</article-title>. <source>J Antimicrob Chemother</source>. <year>2010</year>; <volume>65</volume>: <fpage>694</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>700</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/jac/dkq019">10.1093/jac/dkq019</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20130024</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref069"><label>69</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>. <article-title>How mitochondria produce reactive oxygen species</article-title>. <source>Biochem J</source>. <year>2009</year>; <volume>417</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>13</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1042/BJ20081386">10.1042/BJ20081386</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19061483</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref070"><label>70</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vercesi</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kowaltowski</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Grijalba</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Meinicke</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Castilho</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name>. <article-title>The role of reactive oxygen species in mitochondrial permeability transition</article-title>. <source>Biosci Rep</source>. <year>1997</year>; <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>43</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>52</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9171920</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0130703.ref071"><label>71</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Delobel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tesni&#x000e8;re</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>A simple FCM method to avoid misinterpretation in Saccharomyces cerevisiae cell cycle assessment between G0 and sub-G1</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2014</year>; <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>e84645</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0084645">10.1371/journal.pone.0084645</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24392149</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>