<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Saudi J Gastroenterol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Saudi J Gastroenterol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SJG</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Saudi Journal of Gastroenterology : Official Journal of the Saudi Gastroenterology Association</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1319-3767</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1998-4049</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Medknow Publications &#x00026; Media Pvt Ltd</publisher-name><publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23319034</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3603485</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">SJG-19-23</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/1319-3767.105916</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Immunohistochemical Expression of Matrix Metalloproteinase-7 in Human Colorectal Adenomas Using Specified Automated Cellular Image Analysis System: A Clinicopathological Study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Qasim</surname><given-names>Ban J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>Hussam H.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hussein</surname><given-names>Alaa G.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">Department of Pathology and Forensic Medicine, College of Medicine, Al-Nahrain University, Baghdad, Iraq</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold>Address for correspondence:</bold> Dr. Ban J. Qasim, Department of Pathology and Forensic Medicine, College of Medicine, Al-Nahrain University, Baghdad, Iraq. E-mail: <email xlink:href="dr.banqasim@yahoo.com">dr.banqasim@yahoo.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>Jan-Feb</season><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>19</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>19</day><month>5</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>31</day><month>7</month><year>2012</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; Saudi Journal of Gastroenterology</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec id="st1"><title>Background/Aim:</title><p>To evaluate the immunohistochemical expression of matrix metalloproteinase-7 (MMP-7) in colorectal adenomas, and to correlate this expression with different clinicopathological parameters.</p></sec><sec id="st2"><title>Patients and Methods:</title><p>The study was retrospectively designed. Thirty three paraffin blocks from patients with colorectal adenoma and 20 samples of non-tumerous colonic tissue taken as control group were included in the study. MMP-7 expression was assessed by immunohistochemistry method. The scoring of immunohistochemical staining was conducted utilizing a specified automated cellular image analysis system (Digimizer).</p></sec><sec id="st3"><title>Results:</title><p>The frequency of positive immunohistochemical expression of MMP-7 was significantly higher in adenoma than control group (45.45% versus 10%) (<italic>P</italic> value &#x0003c; 0.001). Strong MMP-7 staining was mainly seen in adenoma cases (30.30%) in comparison with control (0%) the difference is significant (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001). The three digital parameters of MMP-7 immunohistochemical expression (Area (A), Number of objects (N), and intensity (I)) were significantly higher in adenoma than control. Mean (A and I) of MMP-7 showed a significant correlation with large sized adenoma (&#x02265; 1cm) (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05), also a significant positive correlation of the three digital parameters (A, N, and I) of MMP-7 expression with villous configuration and severe dysplasia in colorectal adenoma had been identified (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05).</p></sec><sec id="st4"><title>Conclusion:</title><p>MMP-7 plays an important role in the growth and malignant conversion of colorectal adenomas as it is more likely to be expressed in advanced colorectal adenomatous polyps with large size, severe dysplasia and villous histology. The use of automated cellular image analysis system (Digmizer) to quantify immunohistochemical staining yields more consistent assay results, converts semi-quantitative assay to a truly quantitative assay, and improves assay objectivity and reproducibility.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Colorectal adenoma</kwd><kwd>digimizer</kwd><kwd>matrix metalloproteinase-7</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Colorectal cancer (CRC) is a major public health problem and there is renewed interest in understanding the basic principles of its molecular biology.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>] Surrogate endpoint markers provide opportunities to understand cancer development and also to evaluate the efficacy of intervention. Based on epidemiologic, therapeutic, pathophysiological, clinical and cost benefit, adenomas are considered to be surrogate endpoints in CRC because removal of adenomatous polyps (adenomas) has been shown to reduce the risk of development of CRC.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>] There is currently a multitiered approach to reducing the burden of colorectal cancer through both the earlier diagnosis of cancer and the detection and removal of benign polyp precursors. These clinical strategies have been informed by our understanding of the molecular pathology underpinning colorectal carcinogenesis.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>] Multiple factors including alterations in matrix metalloproteinases (MMPs) seem to be associated with polyp development. MMPs are a family of zinc-dependent and calcium-dependent endopeptidases that degrade matrix glycoproteins, play an important role in tumor invasion and metastases, and are inhibited by tissue inhibitors of metalloproteinases (TIMPs). MMP-7, matrilysin, appears to be expressed by neoplastic cells and may function in the early phase of neoplastic growth.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref>] Up-regulation of MMP-7 occurs very early in colonic epithelial cells as a result of mutation of adenomatous polyposis coli (APC) gene. Mutation of APC is the putative &#x0201c;gatekeeping&#x0201d; event in colorectal carcinogenesis, leading to translocation of &#x003b2;-catenin to the nucleus. Over expression of MMP-7 has been found in 85% of colorectal adenocarcinomas and associated with a poor prognosis.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref>]</p><p>The aim of the present study is to evaluate the immunohistochemical expression of MMP-7 in colorectal adenoma using specified automated cellular image analysis system and to correlate this expression with different clinicopathological parameters &#x0201c;Age and gender of the patients, number, size, site, histopathological type and degree of dysplasia&#x0201d;.</p><sec sec-type="methods" id="sec1-1"><title>PATIENTS AND METHODS</title><p>The study was retrospectively designed. A total of 53 tissue samples (paraffin blocks and tissue biopsies) were included in the study.</p><p>Out of the total number of tissue samples, 33 paraffin blocks from patients with colorectal adenomas were collected from Gastroenterology and Hepatology Center, Gastroenterology unit at Al-Khadhmiya Teaching Hospital and private laboratories in Baghdad, Iraq, for the period 2006-2010. The control group included 20 samples of non-tumerous colonic tissue taken from autopsy cases from the Institute of Forensic Medicine. These specimens were processed and paraffin embedded in the same center. The clinicopathological parameters were obtained from patients&#x02019; admission case sheets and pathology reports. An absolute confidentiality of the patients&#x02019; vital information was maintained for ethical purposes and an ethical approval was obtained from institutions in which the study was carried out.</p><p>From each block, 2 sections of 5&#x003bc;m thickness were taken, one section was stained with Hematoxylin and Eosin (H and E) and slides were revised for the histopathological type and grade of dysplasia. The other section was stained immunohistochemically using three steps- indirect streptavidin method for Monoclonal Mouse Anti-Human Matrix Metalloproteinase-7 (MMP-7, Matrilysin), clone 3F264, manufactured by US Biological. Brown cytoplasmic and membranous staining is considered positive reaction. Positive control is breast carcinoma tissue. Technical negative control was obtained by omission of primary antibody.</p><sec id="sec2-1"><title>Scoring of immunohistochemical staining</title><p>Scoring of immunohistochemical staining was performed using specialized automated cellular image analysis system, Digimizer software, version 3.7.0.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref>]</p><p>Each immunohistochemically stained slide was scanned by alight microscope (Proway, China) for the positive brown immunostaining and three fields that reflect the best of the overall immunostaining were chosen and captured using a Sony digital camera (digital still camera DSH-H55).</p></sec><sec id="sec2-2"><title>Determination of staining intensity cut-off value</title><p>To obtain a cut-off value for intensity of immunostaining, photomicrographs presented at the website of NordiCQ showing different grades of brown color intensity (strong (+3) for dark brown, moderate (+2) for brown, weak (+1) for light brown to yellow) were analyzed by digimizer software, and the digital value of intensity was classed into three categories: weak, moderate and strong, taking into consideration that the digital value of intensity of staining is inversely proportional to digital number in the digimizer color scale [<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>].[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref>]</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Determination of staining intensity cut-off value[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref>]</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="SJG-19-23-g001"/></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec2-3"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Data was analyzed using SPSS program (Statistical Package for Social Sciences) version 16 and Microsoft Office Excel 2007. Numeric data were expressed as mean + SEM, frequency was used to express discrete data. ANOVA was used to analyze numeric data while Chi-square was used to analyze discrete data, and benferroni test was used for multiple comparisons. Scattered graph was used to show relation between various markers. <italic>P</italic> Value of less than 0.05 was considered significant. For Digimizer software, the integrated statistics window displays statistics (n, mean of area, mean of average intensity, Standard deviation (SD), minimum and maximum) of the measurements in the measurements list; these measurements were saved as Excel 2007 spreadsheet file.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec1-2"><title>RESULTS</title><sec id="sec2-4"><title>Clinicopathological parameters</title><p>The results concerning clinicopathological parameters assessed in patients studied are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Clinicopathological parameters of patients studied</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="SJG-19-23-g002"/></table-wrap><p>Comparison of MMP-7 immunohistochemical expressions in colorectal adenoma and control group.</p><p>The frequency of MMP-7 &#x02013; positive cases was significantly higher in adenoma than control group (45.45% versus 10%) (<italic>P</italic> value &#x0003c; 0.001). The classification of the MMP-7 positive cases of adenoma and control groups into different grades of intensity (negative, weak, moderate, and strong) according to the tabulated values of NordiCQ laboratories showed that strong MMP-7 staining was mainly seen in adenoma cases 10 (30.30%) in comparison with control 0 (0%), the difference is significant (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001) [Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>] [<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>].</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Normal colonic tissue with negative MMP-7 immunohistochemical expression (&#x000d7;40)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="SJG-19-23-g003"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Tubular colonic adenoma with mild dysplasia showing MMP-7- positive brown cytoplasmic staining with moderate intensity (&#x000d7;40)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="SJG-19-23-g004"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Tubulo-villous colonic adenoma with severe dysplasia showing MMP-7-positive brown cytoplasmic and membranous staining with strong intensity (&#x000d7;40)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="SJG-19-23-g005"/></fig><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Immunohistochemical expression of matrix metalloproteinase-7 in patients and control groups</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="SJG-19-23-g006"/></table-wrap><p>The three digital parameters of MMP-7 immunohistochemical expression (Area (A), Number of objects (N), and intensity (I)) were significantly higher in adenoma than control group (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05).</p><p>Correlation of MMP-7 immunohistochemical expression with different clinicopathological parameters in colorectal adenomas.</p><p>Mean (A and I) of MMP-7 showed a significant correlation with large sized adenoma (&#x02265; 1cm) (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05), also a significant correlation of the three digital parameters (A, N, and I) of MMP-7 expression with villous configuration (tubulovillous and villous) and severe dysplasia in colorectal adenoma had been identified (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05). There was no significant correlation between age, gender, site, and number of adenomas with the mean (A, N, and I) of MMP-7 [<xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">Table 4</xref>].</p><table-wrap id="T4" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Correlations of matrix metalloproteinase-7 immunohistochemical expression with different clinicopathological parameters in patients with colorectal adenomas</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="SJG-19-23-g007"/></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec1-3"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>It has been proposed that aberrant crypt foci (small areas of epithelium with irregular glandular architecture without any evidence of dysplasia) are precursor lesions which give rise to adenomas. Adenomas can gradually grow in size and change from a tubular to a villous architecture. In general, colonic adenomas comprise tubular, tubulovillous, and villous adenomas, each of which has a different potential for malignancy, depending on its size. They are considered to play an important role as normal mucosa progresses to adenoma.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref>]</p><p>MMPs are over expressed in a variety of premalignant tumor tissues, including colorectal adenoma and MMP-7 has been shown to be important in the growth of early colonic adenomas and their transformation into invasive cancer.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref>]</p><p>The present study found that the frequency of the positive cases of MMP-7 expression was significantly higher in adenoma than in control (45.45% versus 10%, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001) and the three digital parameters of MMP-7 immunohistochemical expression (A, N, and I) were also significantly higher in adenoma than in normal colonic mucosa. Strong MMP-7 staining was mainly seen in adenoma cases 10 (30.30%) in comparison with control 0 (0%), the difference is significant (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001). Several published studies are in accordance with these data, Kirimlioglu <italic>et al</italic>., found that immunohistochemical staining for MMP-7 was identified in the cytoplasm of all types of adenoma cells and it was not expressed either in any of the control colorectal epithelia studied or in non tumoral epithelial cells next to adenomas.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref>] Clapper <italic>et al</italic>., showed that strong MMP-7 expression is restricted to the neoplastic cells of small and large adenomas and is absent in the non-neoplastic colonic epithelium.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref>] Nosho <italic>et al</italic>., observed a progressive increase in the expression of MMP-7 during the transition from normal to adenomatous to carcinomatous colonic mucosa.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref>] Heslin <italic>et al</italic>. and Fingleton <italic>et al</italic>., recorded that MMP-7 over expression is an early event in the carcinogenetic cascade as normal colonic mucosa progresses to adenoma.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>] Newell <italic>et al</italic>., had shown that MMP-7 is focally over expressed in 50% of benign adenomas.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref>]</p><p>Advanced colorectal adenomatous polyps are identified based on size &#x02265; 10 mm, high-grade dysplasia, and/or villous histology.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref>] The current work found that MMP-7 over expression was significantly correlated with severe degree of dysplasia, villous configuration and large size (&#x02265; 1cm). In keeping with these results, Kirimlioglu <italic>et al</italic>., revealed that the degree of MMP-7 over expression was significantly higher in villous type and high grade dysplasia.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref>] Ishikawa <italic>et al</italic>., and Takeuchi <italic>et al</italic>., found that Matrilysin mRNA expression in adenomas was correlated with the degree of dysplasia and the size of the mass.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref>] Hai-yan <italic>et al</italic>., also demonstrated that immunohistochemical expression of MMP-7 in colorectal adenomas was significantly correlated with the degree of epithelial dysplasia and can be used as an indicator of risk of malignant transformation in adenoma.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref>]</p><p>The foregoing data suggest that MMP-7 over expression is an early event in the adenoma-carcinoma pathway and because MMP-7 is more likely to be expressed in adenomas with a potential for malignancy, this enzyme may play a role in the malignant conversion of colorectal adenomas.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref>]</p><p>Ougolkov <italic>et al</italic>., suggested that MMP-7 could be considered to function as an oncogene since colorectal tumourigenesis is suppressed in mice lacking matrilysin and tumourigenic potential is enhanced in cell lines over expressing MMP-7.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref>]</p><p>In the early stages of colorectal tumorogenesis, there is direct interaction of individual MMPs, particularly MMP-7, with the genes involved in the pathways of colorectal cancer development,[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref>] and as adenomas progress to invasive carcinomas, MMP-7 moreover remains elevated as detected immunohistochemically and zymographically. MMP-7 protein and mRNA are consistently expressed in liver metastasis too.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref>] The accumulation of beta-catenin leads to the up-regulation of MMP-7 gene transcription in colorectal adenomas. This indicates that the transcriptional upregulation of MMP-7 is under the control of genes that have been identified as being important in the early stages of colorectal tumourigenesis.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref>]</p><p>To the best of our knowledge, this is the first clinicopatholgical study conducted in Iraq on the immunohistochemical MMP-7 expression in colorectaladenomas, and using automated cellular image analysis system. Compared with the manual immunohistochemical scoring method, there are major benefits of using an image analyzer (Digimizer) to quantify immunohistochemical staining. First, it converts a qualitative or semi-quantitative assay into a truly quantitative assay. Second, it can improve assay objectivity and reproducibility. Third, such image analyzer-assisted immunohistochemical quantification does not require much additional training and is simple to perform. Instead of adding a totally new assay to laboratory operation, it modifies only the quantifying step while keeping the previous immunohistochemical assay steps unchanged.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref>]</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusion" id="sec1-4"><title>CONCLUSION</title><p>In conclusion, MMP-7 plays an important role in the growth and malignant conversion of colorectal adenomas as it is more likely to be expressed in advanced colorectal adenomatous polyps with large size, severe dysplasia and villous histology. The use of automated cellular image analysis system (Digmizer) to quantify immunohistochemical staining yields more consistent assay results, converts semiquantitative assay to a truly quantitative assay, and improves assay objectivity and reproducibility.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="supported-by"><p><bold>Source of Support:</bold> College of Medicine/Al-Nahrain University Especially the Department of Pathology and Forensic Medicine, and Teaching Laboratories at Al-Khadhmiya Teaching Hospital</p></fn><fn fn-type="conflict"><p><bold>Conflict of Interest:</bold> None declared</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mor&#x000e1;n</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ortega</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>de Juan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez-Marcelo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fr&#x000ed;as</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>S&#x000e1;nchez-Pernaute</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Differential colorectal carcinogenesis: Molecular basis and clinical relevance</article-title><source>World J Gastrointest Oncol</source><year>2010</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>151</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21160823</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Colorectal carcinogenesis: Review of human and experimental animal studies</article-title><source>J Carcinog</source><year>2009</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>5</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19332896</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Worthley</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Leggett</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Colorectal Cancer: Molecular features and clinical opportunities</article-title><source>Clin Biochem Rev</source><year>2010</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20498827</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kirimlioglu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirimlioglu</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Yilmaz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sagir</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Coban</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Turkmen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Role of matrix metalloproteinase-7 in colorectal adenomas</article-title><source>Dig Dis Sci</source><year>2006</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>2068</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17009118</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clapper</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Hensley</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name><surname>Devarajan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detection of colorectal adenomas using a bioactivatable probe specific for matrix metalloproteinase activity</article-title><source>Neoplasia</source><year>2011</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>685</fpage><lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21847360</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qasim</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hussein</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immunohistochemical expression of estrogen and progesterone receptors in human colorectal adenoma and carcinoma using specified automated cellular image analysis system: Aclinicopathological study</article-title><source>Oman Med J</source><year>2011</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>307</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22125723</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li&#x000e8;vre</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Milet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Carayol</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Corre</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Milan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pariente</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genetic polymorphisms of MMP-1, MMP-3 and MMP-7 gene promoter and risk of colorectal adenoma</article-title><source>BMC Cancer</source><year>2006</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>270</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17125518</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nosho</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Taniguchi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Adachi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Arimura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Interplay of insulin-like growth factor-II, insulin-like growth factor-I, insulin-like growth factor-I receptor, COX-2, and matrix metalloproteinase-7, play key roles in the early stage of colorectal carcinogenesis</article-title><source>Clin Cancer Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>7950</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15585629</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heslin</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Diasio</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Urist</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of matrix metalloproteinases in colorectal carcinogenesis</article-title><source>Ann Surg</source><year>2001</year><volume>233</volume><fpage>786</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11371737</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fingleton</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Heppner Goss</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Matrisian</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Matrilysin in early stage intestinal tumorigenesis</article-title><source>APMIS</source><year>1999</year><volume>107</volume><fpage>102</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10190286</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Newell</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Witty</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodgers</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Matrisian</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression and localization of matrix-degrading metalloproteinases during colorectal tumorigenesis</article-title><source>Mol Carcinog</source><year>1994</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>199</fpage><lpage>206</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8068180</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ishii</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Notohara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Umapathy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mallitt</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Chikuba</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Moritani</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Tubular adenomas with minor villous changes show molecular features characteristic of tubulovillous adenomas</article-title><source>Am J Surg Pathol</source><year>2011</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>212</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21263241</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ishikawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ichikawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitsuhashi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Momiyama</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Chishima</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Matrilysin is associated with progression of colorectal tumor</article-title><source>Cancer Lett</source><year>1996</year><volume>107</volume><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8913260</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takeuchi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ichikawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishikawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Momiyama</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasegawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagashima</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Matrilysin gene expression in sporadic and familial colorectal adenomas</article-title><source>Mol Carcinog</source><year>1997</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9290698</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hai-yan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao-dong</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ying-bin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression and significance of matrilysin in human colorectal adenoma</article-title><source>J Int Med Health Guid News</source><year>2009</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>20</fpage><lpage>2</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ougolkov</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamashita</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Mai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Minamoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oncogenic beta-catenin and MMP-7 (matrilysin) cosegregate in late-stage clinical colon cancer</article-title><source>Gastroenterology</source><year>2002</year><volume>122</volume><fpage>60</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11781281</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leeman</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Curran</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>GI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New insights into the roles of matrix metalloproteinases in colorectal cancer development and progression</article-title><source>J Pathol</source><year>2003</year><volume>201</volume><fpage>528</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14648655</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>ZS</given-names></name><name><surname>Shu</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Guillem</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Matrix metalloproteinase-7 expression in colorectal cancer liver metastases: Evidence for involvement of MMP-7 activation in human cancer metastases</article-title><source>Clin Cancer Res</source><year>2002</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>144</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11801551</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>