<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="abstract"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Springerplus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Springerplus</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>SpringerPlus</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2193-1801</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer International Publishing</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Cham</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4796443</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1728</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/2193-1801-4-S2-P4</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Poster Presentation</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Facilitating students' project work with online collaborative support: A case from Business Administration Discipline at Hong Kong Institute of Vocational Education (Lee Wai Lee)</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>Janet Man-wai</given-names></name><address><email>janet@vtc.edu.hk</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>Emma Yim-ha</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>Candy Mei-ting</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label/>Research Support Unit, Vocational Training Council, Hong Kong </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label/>Department of Business Administration, Hong Kong Institute of Vocational Education (Lee Wai Lee), Hong Kong </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label/>Web-based VEP Development Project Office, Languages Planning and Development Unit, Vocational Training Council, Hong Kong </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>11</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>27</day><month>11</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>4</volume><issue>Suppl 2</issue><issue-sponsor>Publication of this supplement was funded by the Vocational Training Council. The Supplement Editors declare that they have no competing interests.</issue-sponsor><elocation-id>P4</elocation-id><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; Cheung et al.; 2015</copyright-statement><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This article is published under license to BioMed Central Ltd. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><conference><conf-name>Practical Social and Industrial Research (PSIR) Symposium 2015</conf-name><conf-loc>Wan Chai, Hong Kong</conf-loc><conf-date>27 November 2015</conf-date><string-conf><uri>https://rsu.vtc.edu.hk/conferences_symposiums_detail.php?consymid=19</uri></string-conf></conference><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2015</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p>'Generation Z' [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>] students are immersed in digital technology, which has 'a profound impact on their personalities, including their attitudes and approach to learning' [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. This 'forces a change in the model of pedagogy... based on collaboration' [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>].</p><p>Collaborative learning is a social act through which learning occurs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Over 90% of students in a survey found group work with peers was the most engaging [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>].</p><p>To facilitate collaborative learning, online drives and communication tools are useful for matters such as time-saving, flexible access, and ease of sharing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>].</p><p>Moodle, the official learning management platform of the VTC, facilitates sharing of learning materials. Its discussion forum can support asynchronous exchange of ideas.</p><p>The aim of the study is to explore whether online collaborative support is an effective means of facilitating students' project work.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><p>Four classes studying Business Administration Discipline at the Hong Kong Institute of Vocational Education (Lee Wai Lee) took a module on 'Crisis Management' in semester 2 of the academic year 2014-2015. They needed to share preliminary research findings in a Moodle forum, and save project reports and presentation slides to an online drive. In addition to tracking anonymous data from the online platforms, a questionnaire survey was given to 91 students and an interview was conducted with 22 students. The teacher was also interviewed. The aim of the surveys was to collect respondents' reflections on their online participation, reasons for participation, and the usefulness of the technology.</p></sec><sec id="Sec3"><title>Results</title><p>The results of this pilot study are summarised in two parts: students' online engagement and feedback from the perception survey.</p><p><italic>Part 1: Students' Online Engagement</italic></p><p>As reflected by the learning analytics, 352.78 page views per day were recorded during the semester, equivalent to 10 page views per visit. On average, students spent 4 minutes 17 seconds on each visit.</p><p>The three days when the highest numbers of users were recorded were in the last weeks of the semester. Another peak was recorded at the beginning of the semester, when the online platforms were introduced to the classes.</p><p>The top three most popular Moodle activities recorded 1394 views, covering a quarter of the total. 152 posts were shared in the discussion forums, in which different perspectives on the case studies were raised.</p><p><italic>Part 2: Feedback from the Perception Survey</italic></p><p>A perception survey in the form of a questionnaire was disseminated immediately after the students' presentations. The survey results indicate that 'course requirement' and 'interest to learn' were students' main motivations to complete the online activities (roughly 40%). The convenience of the technology was an attraction for 23.6% of the respondents.</p><p>The most frequent online work was discussion via WhatsApp (over 60%), followed by other project related work such as web searches and Moodle discussion (38%).</p><p>More than half the respondents reflected that WhatsApp and the readings in Moodle were useful for their study. The online drive was the third most useful feature (44.4%).</p><p>The interviewees were positive about using technology in their studies: WhatsApp was used for daily communication such as project reminders; the Moodle forum was used for cross-class and cross-team exchange; the online drive was the working platform for project documents. They found this learning mode time-saving, and some aspects, such as different views collected from forums, were helpful for comprehension. However, they found Moodle was not user-friendly when logging in or sending large files.</p><p>The teacher shared strategies in the interview: planning online activities well and demonstrating the use of technologies at the beginning of the semester, and giving feedback in the online platforms during the project period. Overall, this teaching method was found to be effective for project-based modules.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Teachers' demonstrations and setting online work as a module requirement are important in engaging students online. The inclusion of communication tools such as WhatsApp and Moodle was essential and well-liked for collaborative project work. When ranking the usefulness of the technologies for study, WhatsApp, readings in Moodle and the online drive were the three most popular choices.</p><p>In summary, incorporating an online drive and online communication tools into daily learning is useful for project-based tasks.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Strauss and Howe. Millenials Rising: the Next Great Generation. 2000, New York: Vintage Books</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tapscott</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The net generation and the school. International Society of the Learning Sciences; 1998 In Jones and Ramanau</article-title><source>Collaboration and the Net Generation: the Changing Characteristics of First Year University Students</source><year>2009</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tapscott</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><source>Grown Up Digital: How the Net Generation is Changing Your World</source><year>2008</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>McGraw-Hill</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gerlach</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Bosworth</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>JS.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Is this collaboration?</article-title><source>Collaborative Learning: Underlying Processes and Effective Techniques</source><year>1994</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nichol</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyle</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Peer instruction versus classwide discussion in large classes: A comparison of two interaction methods in the wired classroom</article-title><source>Studies in Higher Education</source><year>2008</year><volume>28</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>457</fpage><lpage>473</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/0307507032000122297</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Siegal</collab></person-group><source>Cloud computing: a free technology option to promote collaborative learning [Online] c</source><year>2015</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seaman</surname><given-names>Moran</given-names></name><name><surname>Tinti-Kane</surname></name></person-group><source>Teaching, learning, and sharing: How today's higher education faculty use social media [Online] c</source><year>2011</year></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>