<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="abstract" xml:lang="en"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Proc</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Proc</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Proceedings</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1753-6561</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4306045</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1753-6561-9-S1-A38</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1753-6561-9-S1-A38</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Poster Presentation</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The efficacy of the current adult observation chart: audit of compliance with trust guidelines at City Hospital, Birmingham, UK</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A1"><name><surname>Connelly</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A2"><name><surname>Bleasdale</surname></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>The University of Birmingham, Birmingham, UK</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Sandwell and West Birmingham Hospitals, NHS Trust, UK</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>1</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue>Suppl 1</issue><supplement><named-content content-type="supplement-title">International Conference for Healthcare and Medical Students (ICHAMS) 2013</named-content><named-content content-type="supplement-sponsor">This supplement has been funded by the ICHAMS conference.</named-content></supplement><fpage>A38</fpage><lpage>A38</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2015 Connelly and Bleasdale; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Connelly and Bleasdale; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1753-6561/9/S1/A38"/><conference><conf-date>11-12 October 2013</conf-date><conf-name>International Conference for Healthcare and Medical Students (ICHAMS) 2013</conf-name><conf-loc>Dublin, Ireland</conf-loc></conference></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>The Royal College Of Physicians (RCP) has shown that the multiplicity of locally developed Early Warning Scores (EWS) used throughout the UK is causing a &#x02018;lack of consistency in detecting the deterioration of patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. The RCP therefore produced a report in July 2012 proposing a National Early Warning Score (NEWS), a point based system, with the aim of standardisation across the UK. However, there is concern that if locally developed systems are working well why &#x0201c;fix what isn&#x02019;t broken&#x0201d;. The current system used at Sandwell &#x00026; West Birmingham Hospitals (SWBH) NHS Trust, UK is a simple colour coded observation chart. As observations become more abnormal they are documented in amber or red zones on the chart. Instructions on the chart explain that single &#x0201c;amber&#x0201d;, double &#x0201c;amber&#x0201d; or &#x0201c;red&#x0201d; observation should trigger a specified action, to be documented in the clinical notes, and increased frequency of observations. Previous audits of patients admitted to the Intensive Care Units of SWBH indicated that even this simple colour coded system was not accurately followed and could indicate that the NEWS, a more complicated point based system, may worsen compliance. The aims of this audit were to evaluate adherence to the current colour-coded EWS adult observation chart across a variety of wards.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><p>194 patients charts were reviewed during the 2012 winter period. For each patient, all observations over the preceding 24hrs were assessed. If they indicated that further action should be taken, the nursing and medical notes were consulted.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p>25% of patients had an incomplete set of observation parameters recorded. For single &#x0201c;amber&#x0201d; observations only 21% had any subsequent action recorded and 67% had their frequency of observations increased. For double &#x0201c;amber&#x0201d; observations the results were 33% and 83%. Of the 11 red observations, only 3 had actions documented.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>The results highlight that the current chart does not appear to be as effective or utilised in the way that it was designed. To re-establish effective use of the current chart will require a massive trustwide education programme. The proposed RCP NEWS system has been tested and demonstrated to be an effective system for identifying at risk patients. It may make more sense to concentrate education efforts on the introduction of the RCP NEWS system rather than re-launching the old one.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>National Institute for Health and Care Excellence</collab><article-title>&#x02018;Management of Acutely ill patients in Hospital&#x02019;</article-title><source>CG50</source><year>2007</year><publisher-name>London: National Institute for Health and Care Excellence</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>