<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="article-commentary"><?properties open_access?><?properties manuscript?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">0372741</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">3058</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Clin Pharmacol Ther</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Clin. Pharmacol. Ther.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Clinical pharmacology and therapeutics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0009-9236</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1532-6535</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23085878</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3837384</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/clpt.2012.99</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS524146</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Models of Excellence: Improving Oncology Drug
Development</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>Manish R.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Maitland</surname><given-names>Michael L.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ratain</surname><given-names>Mark J.</given-names></name></contrib><aff id="A1">Department of Medicine (MRS, MLM, MJR), Comprehensive Cancer Center
(MLM, MJR), and Committee on Clinical Pharmacology and Pharmacogenomics (MRS,
MLM, MJR), University of Chicago, Chicago, IL</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="FN1">Corresponding author: Mark J. Ratain, MD,
<email>mratain@medicine.bsd.uchicago.edu</email>, 5841 S. Maryland Avenue,
MC 2115, Chicago, IL 60637-1470, Phone: (773) 702-4400, Fax: (773)
702-3969</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>8</day><month>11</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>11</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>22</day><month>11</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>92</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>548</fpage><lpage>550</lpage><!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1038/clpt.2012.99--><permissions><license xlink:href="http://www.nature.com/authors/editorial_policies/license.html#terms"><license-p>Users may view, print, copy, and download text and data-mine the content in such documents, for the purposes of academic research, subject always to the full Conditions of use:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nature.com/authors/editorial_policies/license.html#terms">http://www.nature.com/authors/editorial_policies/license.html#terms</ext-link></license-p></license></permissions></article-meta><notes notes-type="related-article"><p>This is a commentary on article Claret L, Lu JF, Bruno R, Hsu CP, Hei YJ, Sun YN. Simulations using a drug-disease modeling framework and
phase II data predict phase III survival outcome in first-line
non-small-cell lung cancer. Clin Pharmacol
Ther.
2012;92(5):631-4.
</p></notes></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="S1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="P1">Simulations based on disease progression models and phase II trial results
can predict phase III results and have the potential to improve oncology drug
development by informing end-of-phase II decisions (EOP2D). Many barriers impede
effective use of modeling and simulation (M&#x00026;S) for EOP2D in oncology: concerns
about model validity, lack of access to M&#x00026;S results and patient-level data,
limited awareness of M&#x00026;S among academic oncologists, and inexperience fitting
M&#x00026;S into the drug development timeline.</p><p id="P2">The statistician George E.P. Box famously wrote that &#x0201c;essentially,
all models are wrong, but some are useful&#x0201d;.<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> He was making the point that, while models
make predictions that never perfectly reflect reality, they can still be powerful
tools for guiding decisions. Modeling and simulation (M&#x00026;S) have been used to
guide decision-making for non-oncology drugs in development, and have the potential
to do the same for the largest active area of development, oncology drugs.</p><p id="P3">Disease progression models are mixed effects mathematical models that
describe the relationship between a quantitative measure of disease status and time.
These models support use of M&#x00026;S to guide decision-making in drug development.
The potential of this approach was recently demonstrated in studies of
Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease and rheumatoid arthritis, in which models based on
validated scales of symptom severity enabled efficacy comparisons to existing
drugs.<sup><xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> In both examples, M&#x00026;S was used not only
to support a go/no-go decision regarding further development, but also to guide the
optimal design of the subsequent trial, saving resources and enhancing the
probability of success.</p><p id="P4">In 2009, two landmark studies introduced disease progression models in
oncology. In solid tumor oncology, the usual measure of disease status is tumor
size, conventionally defined as the sum of longest diameters of target lesions
measured on routinely performed cross-sectional imaging studies. Wang (and his FDA
colleagues) used data from four registration trials in advanced non-small cell lung
cancer (NSCLC) to develop drug-specific models of tumor size, as well as a
drug-independent model linking overall survival (OS) to baseline prognostic factors
and early change in tumor size.<sup><xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup>
Similarly, Claret et al used data from a phase II trial of capecitabine and a phase
III trial of 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin in metastatic colorectal cancer to develop
drug-specific models of tumor size, as well as a drug-independent model linking OS
to baseline prognostic factors and early change in tumor size.<sup><xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> These studies implied that data from phase II
trials could be used to predict accurately a range of outcomes for hypothetical
phase III trials, and inform the design of potential phase III trials, providing
valuable information for end-of-phase II decisions (EOP2D).</p><p id="P5">In the article by Claret et al<sup><xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> published in this issue of <italic>Clinical Pharmacology &#x00026;
Therapeutics</italic>, the authors present results of phase III trial
simulations based on the aforementioned models of tumor size and overall survival in
advanced NSCLC. They utilized data from a previously completed, 3-arm, randomized,
open-label, phase II trial of carboplatin/paclitaxel (C/P) plus motesanib (an oral
anti-angiogenic drug, administered on either a continuous or intermittent schedule)
or bevacizumab in patients with advanced NSCLC. They simulated OS data for 700
patients receiving each of the following: C/P plus continuous motesanib (median OS
11.0 months); C/P plus intermittent motesanib (median OS 11.0 months); C/P plus
bevacizumab (median OS 10.8 months); and C/P alone (median OS 9.3 months). The
predicted hazard ratio (HR) for OS in hypothetical trials of C/P plus continuous
motesanib versus C/P alone was 0.87 (95% CI, 0.71&#x02013;1.1), with
60% of hypothetical trials having a statistically significant survival
advantage for the motesanib arm (P&#x0003c;0.05). The actual phase III trial of C/P plus
continuous motesanib versus C/P plus placebo (MONET1) demonstrated median OS of 13.0
vs. 11.0 months with an HR of 0.90 (95% CI, 0.78&#x02013;1.04;
P=0.14).</p><p id="P6">The authors conclude that &#x0201c;the results of our simulations&#x02026;are
consistent with the MONET1 results&#x0201d;. While this is certainly true if one
uses the HR as the criteria for consistency, it is not necessarily true if one
examines the OS data. The median OS for C/P plus motesanib in MONET1 (13.0 months)
is greater than the upper bound of the 95% prediction interval (12.3 months)
for the simulated results. Similarly, the median OS for C/P plus bevacizumab in the
registration trial for bevacizumab (12.3 months) is greater than the upper bound of
the 95% prediction interval (12.1 months) for the simulated
results.<sup><xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> Thus, the model
underestimates survival in patients treated with motesanib or bevacizumab in
combination with chemotherapy. Since these anti-angiogenic drugs inhibit tumor
growth by different mechanisms than cytotoxic chemotherapy, it is perhaps not
surprising that the model may need to be refined to reflect more accurately their
different treatment effects. As the authors point out, the disparity between
observed and predicted survival might also result from known prognostic factors that
are absent from the original model (e.g., histologic subtype, presence of brain
metastases, age) and/or differences in covariate distributions between the phase II
and phase III trials.</p><p id="P7">The authors should be commended for demonstrating the potential value of
M&#x00026;S to support EOP2D in oncology. Nonetheless, there is an important detail in
this example that prevented M&#x00026;S from being used to its maximum potential. The
authors acknowledge that the simulations were performed &#x0201c;while MONET1 was
ongoing&#x0201d;, which means that the decision to move forward with phase III
development was made without these results available. MONET1 had a target accrual of
1,060 patients (530 per arm) based on having 80% power to detect an HR of
0.80 with a Type I error rate of 0.03.<sup><xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> However, the simulation results demonstrate a power of only
60% with 1,400 patients (700 per arm) and a Type I error rate of 0.05. In
MONET1, the motesanib arm had a median OS that was two months longer than the
placebo arm (13.0 vs. 11.0 months) with an HR of 0.90 but the results did not reach
statistical significance, suggesting that the study was underpowered. A
simulation-based power calculation prior to launching the phase III trial could have
been used to predict the number of patients necessary to achieve 80% power,
which would have substantially exceeded 1,400 patients. It is unclear whether the
sponsor would have spent the resources necessary to complete the trial in these
circumstances, especially since bevacizumab was already commercially available for
use in combination with C/P.</p><p id="P8">What are the barriers to more successful applications of M&#x00026;S to improve
oncology drug development? One barrier is the accuracy and precision of the models,
although the published models are an excellent starting point for future
investigation. As models are applied to novel settings and performance is
continually re-evaluated, opportunities to incorporate previously unrecognized
covariates arise and the models improve. A second barrier is the paucity of publicly
available information about M&#x00026;S done in the private sector. The study by Claret
et al was the result of collaboration between quantitative pharmacologists at a
large pharmaceutical company and their external consultants. In the current drug
development climate, divisions dedicated to &#x0201c;quantitative
pharmacology&#x0201d; or &#x0201c;modeling and simulation&#x0201d; exist at most
large pharmaceutical companies, and a multitude of consulting companies have sprung
up to support their efforts as well as those of their smaller counterparts. Given
the large number of individuals employed to conduct these sorts of analyses, the
absence of more examples in the literature is striking. It is understandable that
sponsors have little incentive to publish results from M&#x00026;S prior to a potential
registration application, but results should be published eventually.</p><p id="P9">A third barrier is the lack of public access to patient-level data from
completed trials. To partially solve this problem, we propose the creation of a new
public database for federally funded clinical trials data with submission required
by NIH policy. The goal of this database would be to create a resource for M&#x00026;S,
as well as for re-analysis of completed trials. A model for how to do this
successfully could be the dbGAP database of genotypes and phenotypes, which was
established in 2007 by the National Center for Biotechnology Information to
facilitate the progress of clinical applications of genetics research.<sup><xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup></p><p id="P10">A fourth barrier is the limited awareness of M&#x00026;S in the academic
oncology community. Non-industry sponsored oncology clinical trials around the world
are typically government-funded and conducted through cooperative groups, with lead
investigators at academic institutions. M&#x00026;S could be used to prioritize proposed
studies, as well as to improve the efficiency of such studies. A professional
campaign to increase awareness of M&#x00026;S in the academic oncology community and
foster collaboration between oncologists and pharmacometricians would be a good
first step, but resources to support the collection and verification of quantitative
data will also be required.</p><p id="P11">A final barrier is inexperience with fitting M&#x00026;S into the conventional
drug development timeline. EOP2D are typically made very quickly after phase II
results become available, while results of M&#x00026;S based on these data might take
several months to become available. One potential solution to this dilemma is the
increased use of combined Phase II/III trials, in which an interim analysis is
planned and conducted at the end of the phase II portion while accrual continues on
the phase III portion. In this setting, M&#x00026;S could be undertaken side-by-side
with conventional statistical analyses and used to guide the decision about whether
to continue forward with the phase III trial. These analyses could even be repeated
at intervals with preliminary phase III data in order to inform changes to target
accrual and possible decisions about early termination, similar to adaptive designs
that are increasingly used in oncology trials.<sup><xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup>
<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref> schematically illustrates this
proposed paradigm.</p><p id="P12">Given the high failure rate of phase III trials in oncology and the current
economic climate for funding new trials, it is more important than ever to use all
tools available to optimize the efficiency and success rate of drug development. As
Claret et al shows, M&#x00026;S has the potential to enhance oncology drug development
by informing EOP2D. However, M&#x00026;S in oncology drug development will not fulfill
its potential if we we do not recognize and overcome the significant but remediable
barriers to success.</p></sec></body><back><ack id="S2"><p><bold><underline>Grant support:</underline></bold> NIH training grant T32GM007019 for
Clinical Therapeutics (MRS), National Cancer Institute Mentored Career Development
Award K23CA124802 (MLM), and a Conquer Cancer Foundation Translational Research
Professorship Award (MJR).</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="FN2" fn-type="conflict"><p><bold><underline>Conflicts of interest:</underline></bold> MRS and MJR have no
relevant conflicts to disclose. MLM has received confidential data and
reimbursement for travel expenses from GlaxoSmithKline for related research.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Box</surname><given-names>GEP</given-names></name><name><surname>Draper</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name></person-group><source>Empirical Model-Building and Response Surfaces</source><publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name><publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc><year>1987</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lockwood</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Application of clinical trial simulation to compare
proof-of-concept study designs for drugs with slow onset of effect; an
example in Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease</article-title><source>Pharm Res</source><volume>23</volume><fpage>2050</fpage><lpage>2059</lpage><year>2006</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16906456</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nixon</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Rheumatoid Arthritis Drug Development Model: a case study in
Bayesian clinical trial simulation</article-title><source>Pharmaceut Statist</source><volume>8</volume><fpage>371</fpage><lpage>389</lpage><year>2009</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Elucidation of relationship between tumor size and survival in
non-small-cell lung cancer patients can aid early decision making in
clinical drug development</article-title><source>Clin Pharmacol Ther</source><volume>86</volume><fpage>167</fpage><lpage>174</lpage><year>2009</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19440187</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Claret</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Model-based prediction of phase III overall survival in
colorectal cancer on the basis of phase II tumor dynamics</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><volume>27</volume><fpage>4103</fpage><lpage>4108</lpage><year>2009</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19636014</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Claret</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Simulations using a drug-disease modeling framework and phase II
data predict phase III survival outcome in first-line non-small-cell lung
cancer</article-title><source>Clin Pharmacol Ther</source><comment>volume, page numbers</comment><year>2012</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sandler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Paclitaxel-carboplatin alone or with bevacizumab for
non-small-cell lung cancer</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><volume>355</volume><fpage>2542</fpage><lpage>2550</lpage><year>2006</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17167137</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scagliotti</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>An international, randomized, placebo-controlled, double-blind
phase III study (MONET1) of motesanib plus carboplatin/paclitaxel (C/P) in
patients with advanced nonsquamous non-small cell lung cancer
(NSCLC)</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><volume>29</volume><comment>abstr LAB7512</comment><year>2011</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mailman</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The NCBI dbGaP database of genotypes and
phenotypes</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><volume>39</volume><fpage>1181</fpage><lpage>1186</lpage><year>2007</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17898773</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adaptive clinical trials in oncology</article-title><source>Nat Rev Clin Oncol</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>199</fpage><lpage>207</lpage><year>2011</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22064459</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Phase II/III trials with an adaptive component during phase III. M&#x00026;S:
modeling and simulation.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms524146f1"/></fig></floats-group></article>