<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">HIV Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">HIV Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">hiv</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>HIV Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1464-2662</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1468-1293</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BlackWell Publishing Ltd</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23731450</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4231999</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/hiv.12047</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Short Communications</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Total and unbound darunavir pharmacokinetics in pregnant women infected with HIV-1: results of a study of darunavir/ritonavir 600/100&#x02009;mg administered twice daily</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zorrilla</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Osiyemi</surname><given-names>OO</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yasin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Baugh</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Coate</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Verboven</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au7">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mrus</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Falcon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kakuda</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au6">6</xref></contrib><aff id="au1"><label>1</label><institution>University of Puerto Rico School of Medicine</institution><addr-line>San Juan, Puerto Rico</addr-line></aff><aff id="au2"><label>2</label><institution>Montefiore Medical Center/Albert Einstein College of Medicine</institution><addr-line>Bronx, NY, USA</addr-line></aff><aff id="au3"><label>3</label><institution>Triple O Research Institute PA</institution><addr-line>West Palm Beach, FL, USA</addr-line></aff><aff id="au4"><label>4</label><institution>University of Miami School of Medicine</institution><addr-line>Miami, FL, USA</addr-line></aff><aff id="au5"><label>5</label><institution>Janssen Therapeutics</institution><addr-line>Titusville, NJ, USA</addr-line></aff><aff id="au6"><label>6</label><institution>Janssen Research &#x00026; Development</institution><addr-line>Titusville, NJ, USA</addr-line></aff><aff id="au7"><label>7</label><institution>Janssen Research &#x00026; Development</institution><addr-line>Beerse, Belgium</addr-line></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Correspondence: Dr Carmen D. Zorrilla, University of Puerto Rico School of Medicine, Obstetrics and Gynecology Department, Maternal-Infant Studies Center (CEMI), PO Box 365067, San Juan 00936-5067, Puerto Rico. Tel: 787&#x02009;771&#x02009;4740; fax: 787&#x02009;771&#x02009;4739; e-mail: <email>carmen.zorrilla@upr.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>1</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>03</day><month>6</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>50</fpage><lpage>56</lpage><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>12</day><month>4</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2013 The Authors. HIV Medicine published by John Wiley &#x00026; Sons Ltd on behalf of British HIV Association.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs License, which permits use and distribution in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited, the use is non-commercial and no modifications or adaptations are made.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Objectives</title><p>Antiretroviral therapy during pregnancy is recommended to reduce the risk of mother-to-child transmission of HIV and for maternal care management. Physiological changes during pregnancy can affect pharmacokinetics, potentially altering pharmacological activity. We therefore evaluated the pharmacokinetics of twice-daily (bid) darunavir in HIV-1-infected pregnant women.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>HIV-1-infected pregnant women receiving an antiretroviral regimen containing darunavir/ritonavir 600/100&#x02009;mg bid were enrolled in this study. Total and unbound darunavir and total ritonavir plasma concentrations were obtained over 12&#x02009;h during the second and third trimesters and postpartum. Total darunavir and ritonavir plasma concentrations were determined using a validated high-performance liquid chromatography tandem mass spectrometry assay and unbound darunavir was determined using <sup>14</sup>C-darunavir-fortified plasma. Pharmacokinetic parameters were derived using noncompartmental analysis.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Data were available for 14 women. The area under the plasma concentration&#x02013;time curve from 0 to 12&#x02009;h (AUC<sub>12h</sub>) for total darunavir was 17&#x02013;24% lower during pregnancy than postpartum. The AUC<sub>12h</sub> for unbound darunavir was minimally reduced during pregnancy <italic>vs.</italic> postpartum. The minimum plasma concentration (<italic>C</italic><sub>min</sub>) of total and unbound darunavir was on average 43&#x02013;86% and 10&#x02013;14% higher, respectively, during pregnancy <italic>vs.</italic> postpartum. The antiviral response (&#x0003c;&#x02009;50 HIV-1 RNA copies/mL) was 33% at baseline and increased to 73&#x02013;90% during treatment; the percentage CD4 count increased over time. One serious adverse event was reported (increased transaminase). All 12 infants born to women remaining in the study at delivery were HIV-1-negative; four of these infants were premature.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Total darunavir exposure decreased during pregnancy. No clinically relevant change in unbound (active) darunavir occurred during pregnancy, suggesting that no dose adjustment is required for darunavir/ritonavir 600/100&#x02009;mg bid in pregnant women.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>darunavir</kwd><kwd>HIV</kwd><kwd>pharmacokinetics</kwd><kwd>pregnancy</kwd><kwd>ritonavir</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Data on the pharmacology of darunavir/ritonavir during pregnancy are limited to case reports <xref rid="b1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="b8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, few of which examined pharmacokinetics <xref rid="b1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="b3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="b5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="b7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="b9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>. The effects of pregnancy on the pharmacokinetics of darunavir remain unclear; therefore, further pharmacokinetic studies are needed.</p><p>Maternal physiological changes during pregnancy (e.g. blood volume expansion, increased glomerular filtration rate and alterations in hepatic metabolism) may result in altered pharmacokinetics <xref rid="b10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>. Data support the conclusion that the pharmacokinetic parameters of HIV protease inhibitors (PIs) are changed during pregnancy, leading to lower exposure in pregnant women <xref rid="b3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="b5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="b6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="b11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="b12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>. Studying darunavir/ritonavir in HIV-infected pregnant women may provide insights into population-specific pharmacokinetics that could inform treatment strategies and dosing recommendations.</p><p>This nonrandomized study was designed to investigate the pharmacokinetic profile, antiviral activity and safety of darunavir/ritonavir [600/100&#x02009;mg twice daily (bid) or 800/100&#x02009;mg once daily (qd)], etravirine (200&#x02009;mg bid) and rilpivirine (25&#x02009;mg qd) in HIV-infected pregnant women. Here we report only on the group that received darunavir/ritonavir 600/100&#x02009;mg bid.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Study design and treatment</title><p>HIV-1-infected pregnant women, aged 18 years or older, with pregnancies between 18 and 26 weeks of gestation were included in this multicentre, single-arm, open-label trial. Subjects had to be on the study drug before screening and enrolment, and had to undergo an obstetric examination and have a normal level II ultrasound. The study was approved by a centralized ethics committee [Western institutional review board (IRB)] or a site-specific IRB.</p><p>Subjects with any obstetric complications, any neurological conditions requiring medication or any active disease that may have compromised patient safety or study outcomes were excluded from the study. All subjects agreed to comply with protocol requirements and provided written informed consent.</p></sec><sec><title>Objectives</title><p>The primary objective was to assess the effect of pregnancy on the pharmacokinetics of darunavir/ritonavir administered bid during the second and third trimesters of gestation and postpartum. The secondary objectives were to document antiviral activity, safety and tolerability of darunavir/ritonavir-based regimens during pregnancy and postpartum, to compare darunavir/ritonavir concentrations between maternal serum and cord blood at delivery and to assess the outcomes for infants of women treated with darunavir/ritonavir bid during pregnancy.</p></sec><sec><title>Evaluations</title><p>Intensive pharmacokinetic samplings over 12&#x02009;h were performed at three study visits: during the second trimester (24&#x02013;28 weeks), during the third trimester (34&#x02013;38 weeks) and 6&#x02013;12 weeks postpartum. Eight blood draws were performed during each visit: predose and 1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 9 and 12&#x02009;h postdose. Darunavir (total and unbound) and ritonavir (total) plasma concentrations were measured. Cord blood and maternal plasma concentrations of total darunavir and ritonavir were also measured on the day of delivery. Total darunavir and ritonavir plasma concentrations were determined using a previously validated high-performance liquid chromatography tandem mass spectrometry assay with a lower limit of quantification of 5.00&#x02009;ng/mL for both compounds <xref rid="b13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>. The unbound darunavir concentration was determined by fortifying plasma samples with <sup>14</sup>C-darunavir. The unbound <sup>14</sup>C-darunavir was separated using ultrafiltration. Total and unbound <sup>14</sup>C-darunavir concentrations were measured using liquid scintillation counting. The unbound fraction of darunavir was calculated as the ratio of the unbound concentration in the filtrate to the total concentration in the plasma before centrifugation.</p><p>Human serum albumin and &#x003b1;<sub>1</sub>-acid glycoprotein (AAG) were measured because darunavir is highly protein bound and the concentration of these proteins usually decreases during pregnancy as a result of haemodilution <xref rid="b14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>. Efficacy and safety assessments were completed at each visit. Adherence was self-reported and based on the 4 days preceding the visit. Infants' HIV-1 statuses were determined by polymerase chain reaction testing, reported within 16 weeks postpartum.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Total and unbound pharmacokinetic parameters were derived from the plasma concentration&#x02013;actual time data using noncompartmental analysis (W<sc>in</sc>N<sc>onlin</sc> Professional&#x02122; 4.1; Pharsight, Mountain View, CA). The minimum and maximum plasma concentrations (<italic>C</italic><sub>min</sub> and <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub>, respectively) along with time to reach <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub> (<italic>t</italic><sub>max</sub>) were obtained by inspection of the plasma concentration&#x02013;time profiles. The area under the plasma concentration&#x02013;time curve from 0 to 12&#x02009;h (AUC<sub>12h</sub>) was determined using the linear trapezoidal rule. The primary pharmacokinetic parameters used in the statistical analysis were AUC<sub>12h</sub>, <italic>C</italic><sub>min</sub> and <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub> on the logarithmic scale. The least squares means (LSMs) of the primary parameters for each treatment were estimated with a linear mixed-effects model, controlling for period as a fixed effect and subject as a random effect. A 90% confidence interval (CI) was constructed around the difference between the LSMs of test and reference. Both the difference between the LSMs and the 90% CI were retransformed to the original scale. Period effects were considered significant at the 5% level. Safety and antiviral activity were summarized using descriptive statistics (<sc>sas/stat</sc><sup>&#x000ae;</sup> version 9.2; SAS Institute Inc., Cary, NC).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Population and baseline characteristics</title><p>Sixteen women were enrolled in this part of the trial and received darunavir/ritonavir 600/100&#x02009;mg bid (Supplementary Table&#x02009;S1). The median age was 24 years (range 18&#x02013;35 years), and 63% were Black or African American. Most (80%) subjects had a CD4 count &#x02265;&#x02009;350 cells/&#x003bc;L, 33% had a viral load &#x0003c;&#x02009;50 HIV-1 RNA copies/mL, 53% had a viral load between 50 and 400 copies/mL and 14% had a viral load &#x02265;&#x02009;400 copies/mL. Sixty-three per cent were previously treated with one protease inhibitor (PI)-based regimen.</p></sec><sec><title>Disposition</title><p>Of 16 subjects, 14 had at least one intensive pharmacokinetic visit and were included in the pharmacokinetic analysis, and 12 completed the treatment phase of the study. A total of five subjects discontinued (four during treatment before delivery; one during follow-up) (Table&#x02009;S1). Two subjects discontinued because of adverse events (AEs): one for increased transaminases related to study drugs and one for unrelated premature delivery (premature delivery led to an inability to fulfill protocol requirements as the patient missed the postpartum visit). Two subjects discontinued because of virological failure related to suboptimal adherence as documented by the principal investigator [one patient reported 87.5% adherence (AUC<sub>12h</sub> 69&#x02009;970&#x02009;ng/h/mL; <italic>C</italic><sub>min</sub> 4140&#x02009;ng/mL) in the 4 days prior to the second trimester visit and 75% adherence in the 4 days prior to the third trimester visit (no pharmacokinetic data were available), and the other patient reported 62.5% adherence in the 4 days prior to the second trimester visit; third trimester adherence rate and pharmacokinetic data were not available]. One subject was ineligible to continue the trial because of a failed drug screening.</p></sec><sec><title>Pharmacokinetics of total and unbound darunavir</title><p>Mean total and unbound darunavir plasma concentrations were higher during the postpartum period compared with the second and third trimesters of pregnancy (Fig.&#x02009;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">1</xref>a,b).</p><fig id="fig01" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Mean (standard deviation) plasma concentration&#x02013;time curves for total darunavir (a), unbound darunavir (b) and total ritonavir (c) after administration of darunavir/ritonavir 600/100&#x02009;mg twice daily (bid), during the second and third trimesters and postpartum.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="hiv0015-0050-f1"/></fig><p>Pharmacokinetic parameters for total and unbound darunavir are provided in Table&#x02009;<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">1</xref>. Data for unbound darunavir were not available for all patients as not all plasma samples were available for plasma protein binding analysis. The maximum plasma concentration of total darunavir during the second and third trimesters was 28 and 19% lower, respectively, <italic>vs.</italic> postpartum based on the LSM ratios. The median <italic>t</italic><sub>max</sub> for total darunavir was 3&#x02009;h in all periods examined. Total darunavir <italic>C</italic><sub>min</sub> was on average 43 and 86% higher during the second and third trimesters, respectively, <italic>vs.</italic> postpartum. Individual <italic>C</italic><sub>min</sub> values for total darunavir are provided in Figure&#x02009;S1a. Total darunavir AUC<sub>12h</sub> during pregnancy was 24 and 17% lower in the second and third trimesters, respectively, <italic>vs.</italic> postpartum. Unbound darunavir <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub> was 22 and 18% lower during the second and third trimesters, respectively, <italic>vs.</italic> postpartum. The median <italic>t</italic><sub>max</sub> of unbound darunavir was approximately 3&#x02009;h during pregnancy and 2&#x02009;h postpartum. Unbound darunavir <italic>C</italic><sub>min</sub> was 10 and 14% higher during the second and third trimesters, respectively, <italic>vs.</italic> postpartum. Individual <italic>C</italic><sub>min</sub> values for unbound darunavir are provided in Figure&#x02009;S1b. Unbound darunavir AUC<sub>12h</sub> was 8 and 7% lower during the second and third trimesters, respectively, <italic>vs.</italic> postpartum. The free fraction of darunavir (ratio of unbound plasma concentration <italic>vs.</italic> total plasma concentration) was slightly higher during pregnancy <italic>vs.</italic> postpartum (data not shown).</p><table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Mean (&#x000b1;&#x02009;standard deviation)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf1-2">*</xref> pharmacokinetic parameters and statistical results for total and unbound darunavir and total ritonavir, after administration of darunavir/ritonavir 600/100&#x02009;mg twice daily (bid), during the second and third trimesters and postpartum</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Postpartum (6&#x02013;12 weeks) (reference)</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Second trimester of pregnancy</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Third trimester of pregnancy</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">LSM ratio (90% CI)<hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Second trimester <italic>vs.</italic> reference</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Third trimester <italic>vs.</italic> reference</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Pharmacokinetics of total darunavir</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>n</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf1-3">&#x02020;</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf1-3">&#x02020;</xref>:11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11:11</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C<sub>0h</sub> (ng/mL)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3&#x02009;497&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2&#x02009;922</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2&#x02009;403&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1&#x02009;161</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3&#x02009;028&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1&#x02009;236</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C<sub>min</sub> (ng/mL)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2&#x02009;711&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2&#x02009;268</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02009;980&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;840</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2&#x02009;498&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1&#x02009;193</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.43 (0.39&#x02013;5.22)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.86 (0.49&#x02013;7.04)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C<sub>max</sub> (ng/mL)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6&#x02009;499&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2&#x02009;411</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4&#x02009;601&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1&#x02009;125</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5&#x02009;111&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1&#x02009;517</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72 (0.61&#x02013;0.86)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81 (0.69&#x02013;0.96)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C<sub>12h</sub> (ng/mL)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3&#x02009;194&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1&#x02009;847</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2&#x02009;268&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;624</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2&#x02009;807&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1&#x02009;446</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">t<sub>max</sub> (h)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00 (1.00&#x02013;6.00)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00 (0.93&#x02013;5.83)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00 (2.00&#x02013;11.88)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUC<sub>12h</sub> (ng/h/mL)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55&#x02009;300&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;27&#x02009;020</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38&#x02009;950&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;10&#x02009;010</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43&#x02009;700&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;16&#x02009;400</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76 (0.63&#x02013;0.90)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83 (0.72&#x02013;0.97)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CL/F (L/h)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.79&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.19</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.45&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.65</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.60&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.73</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Pharmacokinetics of unbound darunavir<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf1-4">&#x02021;</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>n</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf1-5">&#x000a7;</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf1-6">&#x000b6;</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf1-7">#</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf1-8">**</xref>:11<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf1-9">&#x02020;&#x02020;</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf1-10">&#x02021;&#x02021;</xref>:11<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf1-9">&#x02020;&#x02020;</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C<sub>0h</sub> (ng/mL)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">592.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;446.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">526.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;281.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">504.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;270.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C<sub>min</sub> (ng/mL)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">420.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;293.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">413.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;243.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">414.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;243.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10 (0.59&#x02013;2.06)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14 (0.59&#x02013;2.20)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C<sub>max</sub> (ng/mL)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02009;173&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;481.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">933.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;371.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">923.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;286.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78 (0.52&#x02013;1.18)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82 (0.57&#x02013;1.16)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C<sub>12h</sub> (ng/mL)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">464&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;241</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">456&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;209</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">519&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;336</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">t<sub>max</sub> (h)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.03 (1.00&#x02013;4.00)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.92 (0.93&#x02013;8.83)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00 (1.00&#x02013;11.88)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUC<sub>12h</sub> (ng/h/mL)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9&#x02009;178&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3&#x02009;956</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7&#x02009;425&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2&#x02009;999</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7&#x02009;294&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2&#x02009;408</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92 (0.66&#x02013;1.30)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93 (0.69&#x02013;1.24)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CL/F (L/h)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.66&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;35.46</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.63&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;33.86</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.20&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;32.72</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Pharmacokinetics of total ritonavir</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>n</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf1-11">&#x000a7;&#x000a7;</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf1-12">&#x000b6;&#x000b6;</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf1-13">##</xref>:11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf1-14">***</xref>:11</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C<sub>0h</sub> (ng/mL)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">418.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;419.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">241.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;120.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">210.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;63.64</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C<sub>min</sub> (ng/mL)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">232.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;246.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">149.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;69.92</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">137.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;39.47</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08 (0.31&#x02013;3.81)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.22 (0.41&#x02013;3.59)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C<sub>max</sub> (ng/mL)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02009;016&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;881.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">569.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;245.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">515.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;206.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.66 (0.41&#x02013;1.08)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63 (0.40&#x02013;0.98)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C<sub>12h</sub> (ng/mL)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">309&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;224</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">177&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;53</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">179&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;99</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">t<sub>max</sub> (h)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.00 (2.02&#x02013;12.08)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.14 (0.93&#x02013;6.08)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.05 (1.00&#x02013;9.10)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUC<sub>12h</sub> (ng/h/mL)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6&#x02009;746&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;6&#x02009;032</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3&#x02009;929&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1&#x02009;203</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3&#x02009;532&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1&#x02009;130</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72 (0.44&#x02013;1.17)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67 (0.43&#x02013;1.04)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CL/F (L/h)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.98&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;24.95</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.80&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;8.754</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.05&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;9.715</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>LSM, least squares mean; CI, confidence interval; <italic>C</italic><sub>0h</sub>, predose plasma concentration; ND, not determined; <italic>C</italic><sub>min</sub>, minimum plasma concentration; <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub>, maximum plasma concentration; C<sub>12h</sub>, plasma concentration at 12 hours; <italic>t</italic><sub>max</sub>, time to reach the maximum plasma concentration; AUC<sub>12h</sub>, area under the plasma concentration&#x02013;time curve over 12&#x02009;h; CL/F, apparent clearance.</p></fn><fn id="tf1-2"><label>*</label><p>Median (range) for <italic>t</italic><sub>max</sub>.</p></fn><fn id="tf1-3"><label>&#x02020;</label><p><italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;10 for AUC<sub>12h</sub>.</p></fn><fn id="tf1-4"><label>&#x02021;</label><p>Data for unbound darunavir were not available for all patients because of poor sample quality (protein in the filtrate) or low sample volume.</p></fn><fn id="tf1-5"><label>&#x000a7;</label><p><italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;10 for <italic>C</italic><sub>0h</sub> and <italic>C</italic><sub>min</sub>.</p></fn><fn id="tf1-6"><label>&#x000b6;</label><p><italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;10 for <italic>C</italic><sub>0h</sub>, <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;9 for <italic>C</italic><sub>min</sub>, and <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;7 for <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub> and <italic>t</italic><sub>max</sub>.</p></fn><fn id="tf1-7"><label>#</label><p><italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;11 for <italic>C</italic><sub>0h</sub>, and <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;8 for <italic>C</italic><sub>min</sub>, <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub> and <italic>t</italic><sub>max</sub>.</p></fn><fn id="tf1-8"><label>**</label><p><italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;9 for <italic>C</italic><sub>min</sub>, and <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;7 for <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub>.</p></fn><fn id="tf1-9"><label>&#x02020;&#x02020;</label><p><italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;10 for <italic>C</italic><sub>min</sub>.</p></fn><fn id="tf1-10"><label>&#x02021;&#x02021;</label><p><italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;8 for <italic>C</italic><sub>min</sub> and <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub>.</p></fn><fn id="tf1-11"><label>&#x000a7;&#x000a7;</label><p><italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;12 for <italic>C</italic><sub>0h</sub>, <italic>C</italic><sub>min</sub>, <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub> and <italic>t</italic><sub>max</sub>.</p></fn><fn id="tf1-12"><label>&#x000b6;&#x000b6;</label><p><italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;10 for <italic>C</italic><sub>min</sub>.</p></fn><fn id="tf1-13"><label>##</label><p><italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;12 for <italic>C</italic><sub>min</sub> and <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub>.</p></fn><fn id="tf1-14"><label>***</label><p><italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;10 for <italic>C</italic><sub>min</sub>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Matched maternal and cord plasma concentrations were available for 10 subjects. Excluding one outlier resulting from a possible switch of the samples, the mean [standard deviation (SD)] total darunavir concentrations were higher in maternal plasma <italic>vs.</italic> cord plasma [2324 (1056) ng/mL <italic>vs.</italic> 383 (322) ng/mL, respectively] when assessed in nine women and their infants. The median cord&#x02009;:&#x02009;maternal plasma ratio was 0.1455 (range 0.01407&#x02013;0.3621).</p></sec><sec><title>Pharmacokinetics of ritonavir</title><p>Mean total ritonavir plasma concentrations were higher during the postpartum period compared with the second and third trimesters of pregnancy (Fig.&#x02009;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">1</xref>c). Median total ritonavir plasma concentrations peaked 4&#x02009;h after drug administration during pregnancy and at 6&#x02009;h in the postpartum period (Table&#x02009;<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">1</xref>). Total ritonavir <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub> during the second and third trimesters of pregnancy was 34 and 37% lower, respectively, <italic>vs.</italic> postpartum based on the LSM ratios. Total ritonavir <italic>C</italic><sub>min</sub> was on average 8 and 22% higher during the second and third trimesters, respectively, <italic>vs.</italic> postpartum. Individual <italic>C</italic><sub>min</sub> values for total ritonavir are provided in Figure&#x02009;S1c. Total ritonavir AUC<sub>12h</sub> during pregnancy was 28 and 33% lower in the second and third trimesters, respectively, <italic>vs.</italic> postpartum.</p><p>Matched maternal and cord plasma concentrations were available for eight subjects. Excluding one outlier resulting from a possible switch of the samples, the mean (SD) total ritonavir concentrations were higher in maternal plasma <italic>vs.</italic> cord plasma [429 [428] ng/mL <italic>vs.</italic> 17 [24] ng/mL, respectively) when assessed in seven women and their infants. The median cord&#x02009;:&#x02009;maternal plasma ratio was 0.1076 (range 0.04432&#x02013;0.114).</p></sec><sec><title>Albumin and &#x003b1;<sub>1</sub>-acid glycoprotein concentrations</title><p>Mean baseline albumin and AAG concentrations were 31 and 617&#x02009;g/L and postpartum concentrations were 38 and 790&#x02009;g/L, respectively, resulting in a 22 to 28% decrease during pregnancy <italic>vs.</italic> postpartum (Fig.&#x02009;S2).</p></sec><sec><title>Antiviral activity</title><p>The response rate (&#x0003c;&#x02009;50 copies/mL) increased significantly from 33% (five of 15) at baseline (Table&#x02009;S1) to 73% (eight of 11) and 90% (nine of 10) during the second and third trimesters, respectively, and was 80% (eight of 10) at 12 weeks postpartum (Fig.&#x02009;S3a). Three patients had detectable viral loads during pregnancy; two patients had detectable viral load during the second but not the third trimester [72 copies/mL in one patient (100% reported adherence in both trimesters) and 123 copies/mL in the other (87.5% reported adherence in the second trimester, and 100% reported adherence in the third)]. The third patient had detectable viral load during both trimesters (813 copies/mL in the second trimester and 59 copies/mL in the third trimester), with 100% reported adherence for both trimesters. Of these three patients with detectable viral load during pregnancy, two had undetectable viral load in the postpartum and follow-up periods. CD4 count is significantly lower in HIV-1-negative women during pregnancy compared with the 12-week postdelivery period <xref rid="b15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>; therefore, the percentage of CD4 cells was plotted instead of absolute CD4 count. The percentage of CD4 cells increased from 30% at baseline to 35% at 2&#x02013;5 weeks postpartum (Fig.&#x02009;S3b). All 12 infants born to women who stayed on treatment until delivery were HIV negative. One of these infants was born to a patient who discontinued the study but remained on study treatment during follow-up.</p></sec><sec><title>Safety</title><p>The most common AEs, occurring with an incidence of &#x02265;&#x02009;25%, were infections and infestations (44%), gastrointestinal disorders (25%) and premature labour (25%). Of 12 infants, four were born prematurely (at weeks 30, 36, 36 and 37) and no congenital abnormalities occurred. One serious AE possibly related to study medication was reported (increased transaminase).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Lower exposures of total darunavir/ritonavir 600/100&#x02009;mg bid were observed during pregnancy compared with postpartum. Total darunavir <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub> was 28 and 19% lower, and AUC<sub>12h</sub> was 24 and 17% lower during the second and third trimesters, respectively, <italic>vs.</italic> postpartum. These data are consistent with published reports demonstrating a decrease in total drug exposure (AUC) of darunavir/ritonavir 600/100&#x02009;mg bid during pregnancy ranging from 29 <xref rid="b1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> to 36% <xref rid="b9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>. Lower levels of drug exposure during pregnancy <italic>vs.</italic> postpartum have been observed with other HIV PIs <xref rid="b11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="b12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="b16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="b19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>. However, unlike previous reports, the current study also assessed free plasma darunavir levels, which were higher during pregnancy <italic>vs.</italic> postpartum. As a result, the difference in unbound <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub> and AUC<sub>12h</sub> at postpartum compared with values found during pregnancy was minimal. The small number of patients with pharmacokinetic data for unbound darunavir, six in the second trimester and seven in the third trimester, limited the ability to draw definitive conclusions; however, we hypothesize that the lower total drug exposure of darunavir during pregnancy might be partially compensated for by higher free drug, resulting from lower protein binding to darunavir. The antiviral activity of darunavir/ritonavir in HIV-infected pregnant women was effective in preventing mother-to-child transmission and in suppressing HIV in pregnant women, consistent with findings in pregnant <xref rid="b1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="b3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="b5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="b9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> and nonpregnant HIV-infected individuals <xref rid="b20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>. Despite lower total PI levels in studies in pregnant women, subjects achieved desired immunovirological responses and protection from transmission of HIV to their infants <xref rid="b3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="b5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="b6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="b9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="b11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="b12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>. Taken together, the findings that unbound concentrations of darunavir remained nearly unchanged during pregnancy relative to postpartum and that clinical responses were maintained suggest that no <italic>a priori</italic> dose adjustment is needed in darunavir/ritonavir when dosed bid in pregnant women.</p><p>Total ritonavir <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub> was 34 and 37% lower, and AUC<sub>12h</sub> was 28 and 33% lower during the second and third trimesters, respectively, <italic>vs.</italic> postpartum, similar to findings in previously published reports <xref rid="b11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>. The levels of darunavir/ritonavir transferred from maternal to cord plasma were low, with median cord&#x02009;:&#x02009;maternal ratios of 0.1455 and 0.1076, respectively, consistent with other reports demonstrating low transplacental passage of PIs <xref rid="b3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="b7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="b9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>.</p><p>It is interesting to note that <italic>C</italic><sub>min</sub> values were on average higher during the second and third trimesters, respectively, <italic>vs.</italic> postpartum for both darunavir (43 and 86% higher, respectively) and ritonavir (8 and 22% higher, respectively). This is a novel observation and further investigation is warranted. Plasma concentration values at 12 hours have also been presented in Table&#x02009;<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">1</xref> in order to provide additional context to these data.</p><p>In this study, darunavir/ritonavir bid treatment was generally well tolerated in HIV-infected pregnant women, with few discontinuations because of AEs (12%). The observed AE profile partially overlaps with that found previously in nonpregnant adults <xref rid="b20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, and it is unclear how many AEs may actually have been associated with pregnancy independent of darunavir/ritonavir bid treatment.</p><p>A limitation of this study may be the use of the 6- to 12-week postpartum levels as the reference. Darunavir/ritonavir pharmacokinetic parameters after administration of darunavir/ritonavir 600/100&#x02009;mg bid &#x02013; as part of an antiretroviral regimen during pregnancy and postpartum &#x02013; were not clinically different compared with historical controls.</p><p>Darunavir/ritonavir 600/100&#x02009;mg bid administered with other antiretrovirals during pregnancy resulted in consistent unbound (active) drug exposure during pregnancy and postpartum, was effective in preventing mother-to-child transmission and in suppressing HIV and was generally well tolerated, with few discontinuations because of AEs. Data from this small pharmacokinetic study, while not definitive, suggest that darunavir/ritonavir 600/100&#x02009;mg bid may be a treatment option for pregnant women in need of highly active antiretroviral therapy.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank the subjects, staff at the study sites and principal investigators for their participation in the trial. The authors also acknowledge internal study support staff, and Francesca Balordi, PhD, and Jennifer Granit, PhD, Medicus International New York, for editorial assistance. Funding for the study and for editorial support was provided by Janssen Services LLC.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="b1"><element-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Capparelli</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name><name><surname>Best</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Stek</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pharmacokinetics of darunavir once or twice daily during and after pregnancy</article-title><comment>Rome, Italy, July 15&#x02013;16, 2011. Poster P72 <italic>3rd International Workshop on HIV Pediatrics</italic></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="b2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Furco</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gosrani</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicholas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Successful use of darunavir, etravirine, enfuvirtide and tenofovir/emtricitabine in pregnant woman with multiclass HIV resistance</article-title><source>AIDS</source><year>2009</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>434</fpage><lpage>435</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19188762</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ivanovic</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bellagamba</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicastri</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Use of darunavir/ritonavir once daily in treatment-naive pregnant woman: pharmacokinetics, compartmental exposure, efficacy and safety</article-title><source>AIDS</source><year>2010</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>1083</fpage><lpage>1084</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20386380</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jaworsky</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Yudin</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Use of newer antiretroviral agents, darunavir and etravirine with or without raltegravir, in pregnancy: a report of two cases</article-title><source>Antivir Ther</source><year>2010</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>677</fpage><lpage>680</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20587860</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pacanowski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bollens</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Poirier</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Efficacy of darunavir despite low plasma trough levels during late pregnancy in an HIV-hepatitis C virus-infected patient</article-title><source>AIDS</source><year>2009</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>1923</fpage><lpage>1924</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19710560</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pinnetti</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamburrini</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ragazzoni</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>De Luca</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Navarra</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Decreased plasma levels of darunavir/ritonavir in a vertically infected pregnant woman carrying multiclass-resistant HIV type-1</article-title><source>Antivir Ther</source><year>2010</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>129</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20167999</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ripamonti</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Cattaneo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Cortinovis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Maggiolo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Suter</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transplacental passage of ritonavir-boosted darunavir in two pregnant women</article-title><source>Int J STD AIDS</source><year>2009</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>215</fpage><lpage>216</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19255280</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sued</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Lattner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gun</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Use of darunavir and enfuvirtide in a pregnant woman</article-title><source>Int J STD AIDS</source><year>2008</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>866</fpage><lpage>867</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19050223</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b9"><element-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Colbers</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Molt&#x000f3;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ivanovic</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A comparison of the pharmacokinetics of darunavir, atazanavir and ritonavir during pregnancy and post-partum</article-title><comment>Seattle, WA, USA, March, 2012 [Poster 1013] <italic>19th Conference on Retroviruses and Opportunistic Infections</italic></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="b10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pregnancy-induced changes in pharmacokinetics: a mechanistic-based approach</article-title><source>Clin Pharmacokinet</source><year>2005</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>989</fpage><lpage>1008</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16176115</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Acosta</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><name><surname>Bardeguez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zorrilla</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pharmacokinetics of saquinavir plus low-dose ritonavir in human immunodeficiency virus-infected pregnant women</article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>2004</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>430</fpage><lpage>436</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14742191</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stek</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mirochnick</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Capparelli</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Reduced lopinavir exposure during pregnancy</article-title><source>AIDS</source><year>2006</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>1931</fpage><lpage>1939</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16988514</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scholler-Gyure</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kakuda</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name><name><surname>Sekar</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pharmacokinetics of darunavir/ritonavir and TMC125 alone and coadministered in HIV-negative volunteers</article-title><source>Antivir Ther</source><year>2007</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>789</fpage><lpage>796</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17713162</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Notarianni</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plasma protein binding of drugs in pregnancy and in neonates</article-title><source>Clin Pharmacokinet</source><year>1990</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>20</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2178848</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Towers</surname><given-names>CV</given-names></name><name><surname>Rumney</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghamsary</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Longitudinal study of CD4+ cell counts in HIV-negative pregnant patients</article-title><source>J Matern Fetal Neonatal Med</source><year>2010</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>1091</fpage><lpage>1096</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20121393</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cespedes</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Castor</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Steady-state pharmacokinetics, cord blood concentrations, and safety of ritonavir-boosted fosamprenavir in pregnancy</article-title><source>J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr</source><year>2013</year><comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1097/QAI.0b013e318285">10.1097/QAI.0b013e318285</ext-link> [Epub ahead of print]</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="b17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Conradie</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Zorrilla</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Josipovic</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Safety and exposure of once-daily ritonavir-boosted atazanavir in HIV-infected pregnant women</article-title><source>HIV Med</source><year>2011</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>570</fpage><lpage>579</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21569187</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mirochnick</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Best</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Stek</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Atazanavir pharmacokinetics with and without tenofovir during pregnancy</article-title><source>J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr</source><year>2011</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>412</fpage><lpage>419</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21283017</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name><name><surname>Dumond</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Prince</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Protein binding of lopinavir and ritonavir during four phases of pregnancy: implications for treatment guidelines</article-title><source>J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr</source><year>2013</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>51</fpage><lpage>58</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23221983</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Madruga</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>McMurchie</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Efficacy and safety of darunavir-ritonavir compared with that of lopinavir-ritonavir at 48 weeks in treatment-experienced, HIV-infected patients in TITAN: a randomised controlled phase III trial</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2007</year><volume>370</volume><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>58</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17617272</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supporting Information</title><p>Additional Supporting Information may be found in the online version of this article at the publisher's web-site:</p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sd1"><caption><p><bold>Fig.&#x02009;S1</bold>&#x02002;Individual minimum plasma concentrations of total darunavir (A), unbound darunavir (B) and total ritonavir (C) after administration of darunavir/ritonavir 600/100&#x02009;mg twice daily (bid), during the second and third trimesters and postpartum.</p></caption><media mimetype="tif" mime-subtype="tif" xlink:href="hiv0015-0050-sd1.tif" xlink:type="simple" id="d35e2053" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sd2"><caption><p><bold>Fig.&#x02009;S2</bold>&#x02002;Mean (standard error) plasma concentration&#x02013;time curves for albumin (A) and &#x003b1;<sub>1</sub>-acid glycoprotein (AAG) (B) assessed at various time-points throughout the study.</p></caption><media mimetype="pdf" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="hiv0015-0050-sd2.pdf" xlink:type="simple" id="d35e2063" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sd3"><caption><p><bold>Fig.&#x02009;S3</bold>&#x02002;Antiviral activity expressed as percentage response rate (A) (only patients who completed the study in its entirety are included) and status of the immune system expressed as median percentage CD4 count (B) assessed at various time-points throughout the study.</p></caption><media mimetype="pdf" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="hiv0015-0050-sd3.pdf" xlink:type="simple" id="d35e2070" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sd4"><caption><p><bold>Table&#x02009;S1</bold>&#x02002;Baseline demographics, disease characteristics and study discontinuations.</p></caption><media mimetype="doc" mime-subtype="doc" xlink:href="hiv0015-0050-sd4.doc" xlink:type="simple" id="d35e2077" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></back></article>