<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Fertil Steril</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Int J Fertil Steril</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Royan Institute</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>International Journal of Fertility &#x00026; Sterility</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2008-076X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2008-0778</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Royan Institute</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27441060</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4948079</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="other">Int-J-Fertil-Steril-10-253</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject><subj-group><subject>Andrology</subject><subject>Biotechnology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Zeta Sperm Selection Improves Pregnancy Rate and Alters
Sex Ratio in Male Factor Infertility Patients:
A Double-Blind, Randomized Clinical Trial </article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nasr Esfahani</surname><given-names>Mohammad Hossein</given-names></name><degrees>Ph.D</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Deemeh</surname><given-names>Mohammad Reza</given-names></name><degrees>M.Sc</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tavalaee</surname><given-names>Marziyeh</given-names></name><degrees>M.Sc</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sekhavati</surname><given-names>Mohammad Hadi</given-names></name><degrees>Ph.D</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gourabi</surname><given-names>Hamid</given-names></name><degrees>Ph.D</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref></contrib><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Reproductive Biotechnology, Reproductive Biomedicine Research Center, Royan Institute for
Biotechnology, ACECR, Isfahan, Iran</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Isfahan Fertility and Infertility Center, Isfahan, Iran</aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Department of Animal Science, Ferdowsi University of Mashhad, Mashhad, Iran</aff><aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Embryonic and Stem Cell Biotechnology Research Group, Institute of Biotechnology,
Ferdowsi University of Mashhad, Mashhad, Iran</aff><aff id="A5"><label>5</label>Department of Genetics, Reproductive Biomedicine Research Center,
Royan Institute for Reproductive Biomedicine, ACECR, Tehran, Iran</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*Corresponding Address:</label><addr-line>P.O. Box</addr-line><addr-line>8165131378</addr-line><addr-line>Department of
Reproductive Biotechnology</addr-line><addr-line>Reproductive Biomedicine Research
Center</addr-line><institution>Royan Institute for Biotechnology</institution><addr-line>ACECR</addr-line><addr-line>Isfahan</addr-line><country>Iran</country>
Email:<email>mh.nasr-esfahani@royaninstitute.org</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>Jul-Sep</season><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>1</day><month>6</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>253</fpage><lpage>260</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>25</day><month>6</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>1</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Any use, distribution, reproduction or abstract of this publication in any medium, with the exception of commercial purposes, is permitted provided the original work is properly cited</copyright-statement><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the
Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use,
distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.
</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Selection of sperm for intra-cytoplasmic sperm injection (ICSI) is usually
considered as the ultimate technique to alleviate male-factor infertility. In routine ICSI,
selection is based on morphology and viability which does not necessarily preclude the
chance injection of DNA-damaged or apoptotic sperm into the oocyte. Sperm with high
negative surface electrical charge, named &#x0201c;Zeta potential&#x0201d;, are mature and more likely to
have intact chromatin. In addition, X-bearing spermatozoa carry more negative charge.
Therefore, we aimed to compare the clinical outcomes of Zeta procedure with routine
sperm selection in infertile men candidate for ICSI.</p></sec><sec><title>Materials and Methods</title><p>From a total of 203 ICSI cycles studied, 101 cycles were
allocated to density gradient centrifugation (DGC)/Zeta group and the remaining 102
were included in the DGC group in this prospective study. Clinical outcomes were com-
pared between the two groups. The ratios of Xand Y bearing sperm were assessed
by fluorescence <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization (FISH) and quantitative polymerase chain reaction
(qPCR) methods in 17 independent semen samples.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>In the present double-blind randomized clinical trial, a significant increase in
top quality embryos and pregnancy rate were observed in DGC/Zeta group compared
to DGC group. Moreover, sex ratio (XY/XX) at birth significantly was lower in the
DGC/Zeta group compared to DGC group despite similar ratio of X/Y bearings sper-
matozoa following Zeta selection.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Zeta method not only improves the percentage of top embryo quality and
pregnancy outcome but also alters the sex ratio compared to the conventional DGC
method, despite no significant change in the ratio of Xand Ybearing sperm population
(Registration number: IRCT201108047223N1).</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Zeta Potential</kwd><kwd>Density Gradient Centrifugation</kwd><kwd>Sex Ratio</kwd><kwd>Embryo Quality</kwd><kwd>Pregnancy</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>Citation</meta-name><meta-value>Nasr Esfahani MH, Deemeh MR, Tavalaee M, Sekhavati MH, Gourabi H. Zeta sperm selection improves
pregnancy rate and alters sex ratio in male factor infertility patients: a double-blind, randomized clinical trial. Int J
Fertil Steril. 2016; 10(2): 253-260.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Intra-cytoplasmic sperm injection (ICSI) is usually considered as the ultimate technique to alleviate male-factor infertility when other assisted reproductive technologies (ART) fail to help a couple conceive. During ICSI, a single sperm is directly deposited into the cytoplasm of a mature oocyte, thereby bypassing all natural selection barriers to fertilization (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). </p><p>Accordingly, studies demonstrate that selection of sperm based on viability and morphology does not necessarily preclude the chance of oocyte injection with a DNA-damaged or apoptotic sperm when there are no other criteria for selection of sperm in conventional ICSI procedure (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). </p><p>To address this obstacle, a series of advanced strategies for non-invasive selection of intact sperm based on cellular and molecular principles have been implemented ( for more detail see review by Nasr-Esfahani et al. (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>), and Simon L et al. (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). In this regard, Chan et al. (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>) and our group (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>) proposed that sperm population selected based on the membrane Zeta potential represent lower degrees of DNA fragmentation. Zeta potential is a negative electro-kinetic potential of around -16 to -20 mV which is acquired by sperm-membrane during spermatogenesis and epididymal maturation as a result of sperm surface coating with sialic acids (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). </p><p>Our recent study has provided preliminary data on the capacity of Zeta potential to improve the ICSI outcomes on small population (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). Therefore, we aimed to compare clinical outcomes of ICSI using sperm selected by using of Zeta potential or routine density gradient centrifugation (DGC) methods. Moreover, considering differential Zeta-potential of Xand Ybearing sperm (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>), we designed to understand whether Zeta method of sperm selection has any bearing influence on the sex ratio of developed pregnancies developed by ICSI. In the present double-blind randomized clinical trial, we showed that Zeta procedure not only improves the pregnancy outcome but also alters the sex ratio of developed pregnancies, despite no significant change in the ratio of Xand Ybearing sperm. </p></sec><sec sec-type="materials-methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Patients</title><p>This prospective study was approved by the Research Ethics Committee involving human subjects at Royan Institute and Isfahan Fertility and Infertility Center. A total of independent 228 ICSI cycles were included in a parallel double-blind randomized clinical trial spanning the period between September 2010 and March 2014. The power of sample size was calculated to be around 200 based on a previous study (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). Furthermore, we assessed the ratio of Xand Ybearing sperm by fluorescence <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization (FISH) and quantitative polymerase chain reaction (qPCR) methods in 17 independent samples of all 228 semen samples subjected to DGC/Zeta and DGC procedures. </p></sec><sec><title>Inclusion criteria</title><p>A trained nurse was asked to assess the last ultrasound and semen analysis of ICSI candidates on the day of human chorionic gonadotropin (hCG) injection. Accordingly, women below 40 years who had adequate number of follicle in their last ultrasound scan (at least 4 dominate follicle greater 16 mm) and at least one semen parameter (volume, total motility, progressive motility, concentration and morphology) of their partner was below normal threshold based on World Health Organization (WHO 2010) (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). The verified couples were randomly allocated using block designed between the control (DGC) or treatment (DGC/Zeta) trial groups by one of the staff who was unaware of the experimental study. On the day of ICSI, semen samples from men were assessed according to WHO (2010) (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>) and only this data for semen samples are provided in this study. </p></sec><sec><title>Exclusion criteria</title><p>Women with poor quality oocyte (abnormal zona pellucida, large perivitelline space, refractile bodies, increased cytoplasmic granularity, smooth endoplasmic reticulum clusters, and abnormal, fragmented, or degenerated polar bodies) and endometrial thickness greater than 7 mm (type C) were excluded from this study. </p></sec><sec><title>Semen processing by density gradient centrifugation</title><p>All procedures were conducted under sterile conditions. Semen processing was carried out using Ham&#x02019;s F-10 supplemented with 10% human serum albumin (HAS, Octalbin, Switzerland). Liquefied semen samples were placed on PureSperm column (80% lower, 40% upper) and centrifuged at 300 g for 20 minutes. Sperm pellets were suspended in Ham&#x02019;s-F10 plus albumin and washed twice in the same medium. The pellet was finally resuspended in 1 ml of the Ham&#x02019;s-F10 plus albumin for ICSI. </p></sec><sec><title>Sperm selection based on combined density gradient and Zeta</title><p>The Zeta method was carried out according to modified protocol of Chan et al. (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). For DGC/ Zeta, Ham&#x02019;s-F10 was used without serum supplementation, unless otherwise stated. Immediately after DGC, sperm pellets were washed with Ham&#x02019;s-F10, re-suspended and diluted in 4 ml Ham&#x02019;s -F10 in 5 ml Falcon plastic tubes. The prepared sperm suspension was subsequently exposed to the positive charge which was induced by placing the tube inside a latex glove up to the cap. For induction of the charge, the glove was rotated or twisted two or three turns around the tube which was grasped by its cap. Finally, the tube was rapidly removed from the glove and kept at room temperature for 1 minute to allow adherence of the "intact" sperm to the charged tube wall. The medium then was dispensed from the tube to eliminate any non-adhering sperm and the tube wall was washed with 4 ml Ham&#x02019;sF10 plus albumin to neutralize the charge on the tube wall and to detach adhering sperm. The tube was centrifuged and the pellet was re-suspended in 1 ml of Ham&#x02019;s-F10 plus albumin to be used for ICSI. The entire centrifugation step was carried out at 300 g for 5 minutes. For verification of Zeta procedure, an electrostatic voltmeter (Alpha lab, Salt Lake City, USA) was used (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). To minimize variation, a trained individual carried out all procedures and the tubes were labeled by codes. In addition, the embryologist who performed the ICSI procedure was unaware of the individual allocation to the groups (DGC or DGC/Zeta) or the type of sperm preparation implemented. </p></sec><sec><title>Intra-cytoplasmic sperm injection</title><p>A single standard stimulation and ovulation induction protocol, and ICSI procedure were performed for all the cases (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). </p><p>Fertilization rate was calculated from the ratio of fertilized oocytes (2PN) by the total number of injected metaphase II oocytes, multiplied by 100. Embryo quality was assessed by a certain staff who was not involved and aware of trail on day 3 post-oocyte retrieval and a top quality embryo was defined as an embryo between 6-8 cells with equal blastomere size and less than 25% fragmentation (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). Percentage of top quality embryos was assessed by dividing number of top quality embryo by the total number of embryos, multiplied by 100. Chemical pregnancy was defined when &#x003b2;-hCG level was higher than 10 IU and clinical pregnancy rate was defined by ultrasonography findings showing at least one embryo with a fetal heart beat, 5 weeks after transfer. Implantation rate was defined by the number of observed gestational sacs per number of transferred embryos. </p></sec><sec><title>Assessing Xand Ybearing sperm ratio</title><p>Ratio of Xand Ybearing sperm was determined by FISH technique according to Aleahmad et al. (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). Quantitative PCR was also conducted according to Ainsworth et al. (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>) 2011 for determining the ratio of X and Y bearing sperm. </p></sec><sec><title>Quantitative polymerase chain reaction method</title><p>Genomic DNA was extracted using the DNeasy&#x000ae; Blood &#x00026; Tissue Kit (Qiagen<sup>TM</sup>, Germany), according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions with some modifications. In brief, semen and blood samples were centrifuged at 3000 g for 3 minutes. The sperm pellet was re-suspended in 200 &#x003bc;l phosphatebuffered saline (PBS) and the samples were treated with proteinase K (40 mAU/mg protein, supported by DNeasy&#x000ae; Blood &#x00026; Tissue Kit) and incubated at 56&#x000b0;C for 30 minutes. Genomic DNA was harvested by Mini spin column and stored at -20&#x000b0;C. Sex determining region Y (<italic>SRY</italic>) and <italic>Amelogenin</italic> genes were candidate as Y and X chromosome determinations, respectively. SRY gene located on p11.3 region of the Y chromosome encodes a transcription factor that belongs to the high mobility group (HMG) box that has a DNA binding domain and was used as a dominant gene in mammalian male sex determination (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). <italic>Amelogenin</italic> gene is located on the X and Y chromosomes at X p22.1X p22.3 and Y p11.2. This gene could be used as a sequence for mammalian female sex determination because it has a 177-bp fragment which inserted just in X-sequence (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). To amplify Y and X specific chromosome fragments by PCR, two pairs of primers were designed (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). </p><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label> Table 1</label><caption><p> The list of primers used in this study </p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><th colspan="5" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Primer</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Sequence (5'-3')</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Size</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Gene</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Accession no.</td></tr><tr><th colspan="5" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1"> SRY</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> F: CGTCGGAAGGCGAAGATGC </td><td align="left" rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1"> 167-bp</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1">SRY</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1">NW_001842360.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R: TTGATGGGCGGTAAGTGGC</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1"> Amel</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F: GTGTCTCTTGCTTGCCTCTGC </td><td align="left" rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1"> 107-bp</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1">Amelogenin</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1"> NW_001842422.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R: GGAGAACCTCAAACCCGACG</td></tr><tr><th colspan="5" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>SRY-forward/reverse primers were designed to amplify a 167-bp fragment from SRY gene. For amplification of an X chromosome specific fragment, Amel-reverse primer was designed to anneal to inserted 177-bp fragment in X-sequence. Amel-forward/reverse primers amplified a specific 107-bp fragment for X chromosome (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig .1</xref>). Sex ratio was quantified by quantitative real-time PCR (RT-qPCR) using the Rotorgene 2000 Real Time Cycler (Corbett Research, Sydney, Australia). For each sample, RT-qPCR was performed in triplicate. PCR was conducted by adding 1 &#x000b5;L genomic DNA to the 20 &#x000b5;L of PCR mixture that contained 1 &#x000d7;SYBR&#x000ae; Premix Ex Taq<sup>TM</sup>(Takara Bio Inc., Otsu, Japan), 0.4 &#x000b5;M of each specific primer, and DNase-free water. The PCR protocol included an initial step of 94&#x000b0;C (4 minutes), followed by 40 cycles of 94&#x000b0;C (30 seconds), 60&#x000b0;C (30 seconds), and 72&#x000b0;C (30 seconds). Primer efficiency was evaluated by making a 5-fold serial dilution of each samples reaction for each primer pairs and was calculated by 10-1/slope equation. The sex ratio in each reaction was calculated by the ratio of threshold cycle (CT) of X to Y (X/Y). </p></sec><sec><title>Fluorescence in situ hybridization technique</title><p>Mixture of X (DXZ1) red and Y (DYZ3) green (Abbott) labeled probes were prepared for detection of X and Y chromosomes in sperm nuclei. Under a cover slip, ten microliter of probe mixture was added and sealed with rubber cement. For hybridization of the DNA probes, spermatozoa and probe DNA were concomitantly denatured for 5 minutes at 75&#x000ba;C. Then, slides were incubated in a moist chamber at 37&#x000ba;C for 4 hours. After washing with 0.4&#x000d7; SSC/0.3% NP40 at 73&#x000ba;C for 2 minutes and then in 2&#x000d7; SSC/0.1% NP40 at room temperature for 1 minute, slides were counterstained with 10 ml of 4(6-diamidino-2-phenylindole) (DAPI) mixed with antifade (Cytocell Technologies Ltd, UK) using a fluorescence microscope (Nikon E800, Japan) equipped with a triple-band 476 pass filter for DAPI/ spectrum green/spectrum orange. At least 1000 spermatozoa with intact nuclei were counted and green or orange fluorescent spot were considered as X and Y chromosomes in sperm, respectively (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). </p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>For statistical analysis, the Chi-square, Student&#x02019;s t test, one-way analysis of variance
(ANOVA) and logistic regression model were
carried out using the Statistical Package for
the Social Sciences software (SPSS 18, Chicago, IL, USA). All data were presented as
means &#x000b1; SEM, and differences were considered
significant at P&#x0003c;0.05.</p><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig.1</label><caption><p> PCR amplicons of the <italic>Amelogenin</italic> and <italic>Sex</italic> determining region Y (SRY) gene from sperm genomic DNA. A. Schematic illustration of
annealing of primers for specific amplification of X and Y chromosome in PCR reaction and B. A 167-bp and 107-bp fragment was
amplified in PCR reaction from <italic>SRY</italic> and <italic>Amelogenin</italic> gene as indicators for sex determination. PCR; Polymerase chain reaction.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="Int-J-Fertil-Steril-10-253-g01"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Patient cohorts</title><p>251 couples were informed about the trial and 228 accepted to participate in the trail. Due to technical limitation, two cases were included per day (one for DGC and one for DGC/Zeta) and therefore, 20 cases which had the inclusion criteria were excluded from the study. Of the 208 remaining cases, 5 cases (3 from DGC/Zeta and 2 from control group) were excluded from the study based on the exclusion criteria. Of the 203 ICSI cycles included in this study, 101 cases were designated to the DGC/Zeta group while 102 were allocated to DGC group. </p></sec><sec><title>Confounding factors</title><p><xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref> compares possible confounding factors between DGC/Zeta and DGC groups. As shown, no significant difference in term of semen parameters, number of oocyte retrieved (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>), female and male ages were observed between the two groups. </p><table-wrap id="T2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Comparison of possible confounding factors between
DGC/Zeta and DGC groups</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tr><th colspan="4" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">DGC/Zeta
group
Mean (SE)
n=102</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">DGC group
Mean (SE)
n=101</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th></tr><tr><th colspan="4" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male age (Y)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.76 &#x000b1; 5.91</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.79 &#x000b1; 6.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sperm concentration (10<sup>6</sup>/ml)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.27 &#x000b1; 3.42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.14 &#x000b1; 3.43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.41</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total sperm motility(%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.84 &#x000b1; 1.20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.09 &#x000b1; 1.45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Progressive motility (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.86 &#x000b1; 1.05 </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.21 &#x000b1; 1.24 </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sperm normal morphology (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.78 &#x000b1; 0.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.13 &#x000b1; 0.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female age (Y) </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.73 &#x000b1; 0.48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.34 &#x000b1; 0.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26</td></tr><tr><th colspan="4" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>DGC; Density gradient centrifugation.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Intra-cytoplasmic sperm injection outcomes</title><p>Table 3 shows ICSI outcome between the two
groups. No difference in fertilization rates was observed between the DGC/Zeta and DGC groups
(77.89 &#x000b1; 1.87 vs. 76.91 &#x000b1; 2.08%, respectively).
Even though, the respective percentages of top
quality embryos (45.83 &#x000b1; 3.11 vs. 35.38 &#x000b1; 4.64%),
chemical pregnancy (43.13 vs. 23.7%), clinical
pregnancy (39.2 vs. 21.8%) and abortion (7.5 vs.
18.2%) were significantly improved in DGC/Zeta
group when compared with DGC group. The implantation rate was similar between the two groups
(21.01 vs. 12.75% in DGC/Zeta and DGC group,
respectively). The mean numbers of embryos
transferred were 2.51 &#x000b1; 0.08 vs. 2.48 &#x000b1; 0.09 in
DGC/Zeta and DGC group, respectively without
any significant difference. </p><table-wrap id="T3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Comparison of ICSI outcome between DGC/Zeta and
DGC groups</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tr><th colspan="4" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">DGC/Zeta group n=102</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">DGC group n=101</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th></tr><tr><th colspan="4" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of oocyte retrieved</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.65 &#x000b1; 0.40 </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.06 &#x000b1; 0.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fertilization rate (%) </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.89 &#x000b1; 1.87</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.91 &#x000b1; 2.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Top quality embryo (%) </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.83 &#x000b1; 3.11 </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.38 &#x000b1; 4.64 </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04*</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean of transferred embryos</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.51 &#x000b1; 0.08 </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.48 &#x000b1; 0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean of vitrified embryos</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.06 &#x000b1; 0.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.78 &#x000b1; 0.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chemical pregnancy rate (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44/102 (43.13%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24/101 (23.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004*</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical pregnancy rate (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 40/102 (39.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 22/101n(21.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009*</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abortion rate (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/40 (7.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/22 (18.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03*</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stillbirth rate (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0(0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2(18.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00*</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">%Implantation rate (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54/257 (21.01%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32/251 (12.75%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td></tr><tr><th colspan="4" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Independent student&#x002bc;s t test and Chi-square carried out for
statically analyzing. ICSI; Intra cytoplasmic sperm injection, DGC;
Density gradient centrifugation, and *; Indicates significant dif-
ference (P&#x0003c;0.05). </p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Confounding factors of intra-cytoplasmic sperm
injection outcomes</title><p>To compare the clinical pregnancy rate between
the two groups and evaluate the possible con-
founding factors on ICSI outcomes, we applied
binary regression model (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">Table 4</xref>). Results showed
the odds ratio of clinical pregnancy between DGC/
Zeta versus DGC group was 2.304 with P=0.01.
Therefore, the chance of clinical pregnancy rate in
DGC/Zeta group was 2.3 fold higher than DGC
group. These data revealed that confounding fac-
tors which had significant influence on the ICSI
outcome were male smoking, female age, total
oocyte retrieved and injected, ovarian factor and
polycystic ovarian syndrome.</p><table-wrap id="T4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label> Table 4</label><caption><p> Multiple regression analysis for DGC vs. DGC/Zeta </p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><th colspan="5" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1"> Parameters</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1"> P value</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1"> Odds ratio</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">95% CI for EXP(B)</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Lower</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Upper</th></tr><tr><th colspan="5" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Male smoking</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.042<sup>*</sup></td><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.383</th><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.152</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.965</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Female age</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.012<sup>*</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.903</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.834</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.978</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Total oocyte retrieved</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.019<sup>*</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.795</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.656</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.963</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Injected oocyte</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.020<sup>*</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.290</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 1.040</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 1.601</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Tubal factor</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.608 </td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.238</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.547</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 2.805</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Endometriosis</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.248</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 2.075</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.601</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 7.165</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Uterine factor</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.798</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 1.143</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.410</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 3.185</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Polycystic ovarian Syn.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.005 *</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 5.618</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 1.699</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 18.577</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Ovarian factor</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.049<sup>*</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.352</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.124</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 1.002</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Duration of infertility</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.293</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.743</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.427</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 1.292</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No. Previous ART</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.994</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 1.000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.914</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 1.093</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Clinical pregnancy (DGC/Zeta vs. DGC)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.018 *</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 2.304</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 1.154</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 4.601</td></tr><tr><th colspan="5" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Binary logistic regression carried out for statically analyzing.
<sup>*</sup>; Indicates statistical significance (P&#x0003c;0.05), CI; Confidence interval, DGC;
Density gradient centrifugation, and ART; Assisted reproduction technique.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Sex ratios</title><p>Figure 2 compares the percentage of girl baby
delivery to total baby delivery between DGC
and DGC/Zeta groups. As shown, the percentage of girls delivered after DGC/Zeta sperm
selection procedure was significantly higher than
DGC procedure with a P&#x0003c;0.001. In addition, we
observed statistical significance in sex ratio between DGC and DGC/Zeta groups. Sex ratio was
significantly lower in the DGC/Zeta group compared to DGC group (P=0.04). Therefore, the
number of girl birth was higher in the DGC/Zeta
group compared to DGC group.</p><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig.2</label><caption><p> A. Comparison percentage of girl baby delivery to total
baby delivery and B. Number of male and female births.
<sup>*</sup>; Indicates statistical significance in sex ratio between two groups. Chi-
square carried out for statically analyzing, F; Female, M; Male,
and DGC; Density gradient centrifugation.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="Int-J-Fertil-Steril-10-253-g02"/></fig></sec><sec><title>X- and Y- bearing sperm ratios</title><p>We assessed and compared the ratio of X- and
Y- bearing sperm by FISH and RT-qPCR methods
in the DGC and DGC/Zeta groups. As depicted in
Table 5, the ratios of X- and Y- chromosome bearing sperm population were not significantly different between the two groups. </p><table-wrap id="T5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Comparison of X and Y chromosome-bearing sperm
populations between washed sperm, DGC and DGC/Zeta groups&#x02019;
by real-time PCR</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tr><th colspan="5" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Groups</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Sample number</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Replicate per sample</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ct<sub>SRY</sub>/Ct<sub>Amelo</sub>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th></tr><tr><th colspan="5" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Male blood</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.99 &#x000b1; 0.01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.21</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> washed sperm</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.99 &#x000b1; 0.01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.22</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> DGC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.99 &#x000b1; 0.01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.20</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> DGC/Zeta</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 1.00 &#x000b1; 0.01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.17</td></tr><tr><th colspan="5" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>One-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) carried out for statically analyzing. DGC; Density gradient centrifugation , Ct; Cycle
threshold and PCR; Polymerase chain reaction.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>The association between sperm maturation and
chromatin integrity with ICSI outcome is well
established in several studies (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>-<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). Moreover,
intensive studies on sperm morphology and chromatin status have revealed that that spermatozoa
with apparently normal morphology may have
fragmented DNA. Therefore, a simple selection
of ICSI sperm based on viability and morphology
does not necessarily preclude the chance of oocyte
injection with a DNA-damaged or apoptotic sperm
(<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). This notion has been supported by inverse as-
sociation observed between the increased proportion of normal spermatozoa with damaged DNA with embryo quality and also pregnancy outcome after ICSI (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). There are evidence that sperm selected based on their Zeta capacity represent lower degree of DNA damage (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). A recent study by Simon et al. (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>) showed that selection of negatively-charged sperm through micro-electrophoresis decreased the degree of DNA damage. Therefore, to reduce the chance of selection of morphologically normal spermatozoa with damaged DNA during ICSI, we carried out a double-blind randomized clinical trial to investigate the efficiency of Zeta sperm selection method to distinguish between intact and damaged sperm. </p><p>The results of this study revealed that selection of sperm based on Zeta method increases embryo quality, and chemical and clinical pregnancy rates taking into account all the possible confounding factors which may affect the ICSI outcomes. The confounding factors which had significant influence on the ICSI outcome were male smoking, female age, total numbers of oocyte retrieved and injected, ovarian factors and polycystic ovarian syndrome. These findings are in agreement with the available studies (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). Furthermore, the improved ICSI outcomes are consistent with our previous study which suggested that selection of sperm based on sperm functional characteristics reduces the possibility of insemination of DNA damaged sperm during ICSI (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). These results are also in concordance with previous preliminary studies which have implemented SpermSep&#x000ae; CS-10 technique based on sperm surface negative charge (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). To our knowledge, this is the first clinical trial on a large cohort patient group that evaluates the outcome of novel sperm selection based on Zeta potential after ICSI procedure. </p><p>The Zeta potential of human Ybearing sperm has been estimated to be around -16 mV, while the corresponding value for the X-bearing sperm is around -20 mV. The higher negative charge of Xbearing sperm has been attributed to 25% more densely charge sialated proteins residues on their plasma membrane (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). Based on these reports, we compared the sex ratio of children born in DGC and DGC/Zeta groups which was significantly in favor of higher females born in the DGC/Zeta procedure. Subsequently, we analyzed the ratio of Xand Y-bearing sperm using quantitative PCR and FISH analysis. The results revealed no significant difference between the ratios of Xand Y -bearing sperm between the two groups. These results are consistent with previous report of Ainsworth et al. (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>) using electrophoretic chamber designed based on sperm Zeta potential to separate sperm with intact DNA. They also reported no significant difference in the ratio of X and Y bearing sperm using quantitative PCR. </p><p>Considering the fact that the study was a doubleblind trial in which the individuals who carried out the ICSI procedure were unaware of sperm selection procedure (DGC or DGC/Zeta), the tentative difference or the skewed sex ratio of children born through Zeta procedure may be attributed to other possible unknown factors. It seems that the difference could be due to higher resistance of Xbearing sperm to stressful conditions. We had previously shown that during Zeta procedure, sperm with negative Zeta potential attached to the positive surface of the tube and the selected sperm underwent a capacitation-like process. This was confirmed by Chlortetracycline (CTC) staining for detection of capacitated sperm and also externalization of phosphatidyl serine (EPS) as an early marker of apoptosis by annexin V staining (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). EPS is attributed to early apoptosis and part of natural process of capacitation and acrosome reaction when two membranes (inner acrosome and sperm lemma) are in the process of fusion. Based on the present data, we proposed that Y -bearing sperm may be less resistant to this process and become immotile during the Zeta procedure. Therefore, following Zeta procedure, we might be selecting Xbearing sperm which may have resisted the Zeta procedure. This proposition is consistent with a previous report which showed that X-bearing sperm are more resistant to stressful conditions like thermal stress (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). </p><p>Literature background regarding changes in sex ratio from fertilization to birth in ART cycles suggest that &#x0201c;In-vitro-culture-induced precocious Xchromosome inactivation together with ICSI-induced decrease in number of trophectoderm cells in female blastocysts may account for preferential female mortality at early post-implantation stages and thereby variations in sex ratios at birth in ART cycles&#x0201d;. Whether selection of normal sperm, by procedures like Zeta or Time-lapse, may help to overcome these <italic>in vitro</italic> induced defects, remains to be explored (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). </p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Selection of sperm based on Zeta potential improves ICSI outcome. Furthermore, the sex ratio is tentatively affected in favor of female sex. However, further studies are required to confirm this possibility and the mechanism by which Zeta selection may alters the sex ratio. </p></sec></body><back><ack><p>This study was support by Royan institute and we would like to express our gratitude to staff of Isfahan Fertility and Infertility for their full support. None of the authors has any conflicts of interest to disclose and all authors support submission to this journal.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Palermo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Joris</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Devroey</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Steirteghem</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pregnancies after intracytoplasmic injection of single spermatozoon into an oocyte</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>1992</year><volume>340</volume><issue>8810</issue><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1351601</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Celik-Ozenci</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Jakab</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kovacs</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Catalanotti</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Demir</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bray-Ward</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sperm selection for ICSI: shape properties do not predict the absence or presence of numerical chromosomal aberrations</article-title><source>Hum Reprod</source><year>2004</year><volume>19</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>2052</fpage><lpage>2059</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15205404</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Avenda&#x000f1;o</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Franchi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Morshedi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bocca</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Oehninger</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fragmentation of DNA in morphologically normal human spermatozoa</article-title><source>Fertil Steril</source><year>2009</year><volume>91</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1077</fpage><lpage>1084</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18440529</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nasr-Esfahani</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Deemeh</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Tavalaee</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New era in sperm selection for ICSI</article-title><source>Int J Androl</source><year>2012</year><volume>35</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>475</fpage><lpage>484</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22804455</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>SQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Carrell</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sperm selection based on electrostatic charge</article-title><source>Methods Mol Biol</source><year>2013</year><volume>927</volume><fpage>269</fpage><lpage>278</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22992922</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobson</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Corselli</surname><given-names>JU</given-names></name><name><surname>Patton</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A simple zeta method for sperm selection based on membrane charge</article-title><source>Fertil Steril</source><year>2006</year><volume>85</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>481</fpage><lpage>486</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16595231</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Razavi</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Nasr-Esfahani</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Deemeh</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Shayesteh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tavalaee</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of zeta and HA-binding methods for selection of spermatozoa with normal morphology, protamine content and DNA integrity</article-title><source>Andrologia</source><year>2010</year><volume>42</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20078511</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kirchhoff</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hale</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cell-to-cell transfer of glycosylphosphatidylinositol-anchored membrane proteins during sperm maturation</article-title><source>Mol Hum Reprod</source><year>1996</year><volume>2</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>184</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9238677</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kheirollahi-Kouhestani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Razavi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tavalaee</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Deemeh</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Mardani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Moshtaghian</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Selection of sperm based on combined density gradient and Zeta method may improve ICSI outcome</article-title><source>Hum Reprod</source><year>2009</year><volume>24</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>2409</fpage><lpage>24016</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19553239</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ishijima</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Okuno</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohri</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Zeta potential of human Xand Y-bearing sperm</article-title><source>Int J Androl</source><year>1991</year><volume>14</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>340</fpage><lpage>347</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1794918</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>World Health Organization </collab><source>WHO Laboratory Manual for the examination and processing of human semen</source><edition>5th ed</edition><publisher-loc>Geneva, Switzerland</publisher-loc><publisher-name>WHO Press</publisher-name><year>2010</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>271</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giorgetti</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Terriou</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Auquier</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hans</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Spach</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Salzmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Embryo score to predict implantation after in-vitro fertilization: based on 957 single embryo transfers</article-title><source>Hum Reprod</source><year>1995</year><volume>10</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>2427</fpage><lpage>2431</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8530679</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Terriou</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Giorgetti</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hans</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Salzmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Charles</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Cignetti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Relationship between even early cleavage and day 2 embryo score and assessment of their predictive value for pregnancy</article-title><source>Reprod Biomed Online</source><year>2007</year><volume>14</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>294</fpage><lpage>299</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17359580</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aleahmad</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Gourabi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeinali</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kazemi Ashtiani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Baharvand</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Separation of Xand Y-bearing human spermatozoa by sperm isolation medium gradients evaluated by FISH</article-title><source>Reprod Biomed Online</source><year>2009</year><volume>18</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>475</fpage><lpage>478</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19400987</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ainsworth</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Nixon</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Aitken</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The electrophoretic separation of spermatozoa: an analysis of genotype, surface carbohydrate composition and potential for capacitation</article-title><source>Int J Androl</source><year>2011</year><volume>34</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>e422</fpage><lpage>434</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21564134</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gubbay</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Collignon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Koopman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Capel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Economou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000fc;nsterberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A gene mapping to the sex-determining region of the mouse Y chromosome is a member of a novel family of embryonically expressed genes</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1990</year><volume>346</volume><issue>6281</issue><fpage>245</fpage><lpage>250</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2374589</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Acharyya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanjilal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhattacharyya</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Does human sperm nuclear DNA integrity affect embryo quality?</article-title><source>Indian J Exp Biol</source><year>2005</year><volume>43</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1016</fpage><lpage>1022</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16313064</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Meriano</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kader</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Jarvi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Laskin</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cadesky</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Potential adverse effect of sperm DNA damage on embryo quality after ICSI</article-title><source>Hum Reprod</source><year>2005</year><volume>20</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>3476</fpage><lpage>3480</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16123087</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Shamsi</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Emery</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Aston</surname><given-names>KI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Paternal influence of sperm DNA integrity on early embryonic development</article-title><source>Hum Reprod</source><year>2014</year><volume>29</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>2402</fpage><lpage>2412</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25205757</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Avenda&#x000f1;o</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Franchi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Duran</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Oehninger</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DNA fragmentation of normal spermatozoa negatively impacts embryo quality and intracytoplasmic sperm injection outcome</article-title><source>Fertil Steril</source><year>2010</year><volume>94</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>549</fpage><lpage>557</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19339003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fleming</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Ilad</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffin</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ong</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prospective controlled trial of an electrophoretic method of sperm preparation for assisted reproduction: comparison with density gradient centrifugation</article-title><source>Hum Reprod</source><year>2008</year><volume>23</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>2646</fpage><lpage>2651</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18765400</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Aston</surname><given-names>KI</given-names></name><name><surname>Emery</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hotaling</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Carrell</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Micro-electrophoresis: a noninvasive method of sperm selection based on membrane charge</article-title><source>Fertil Steril</source><year>2015</year><volume>103</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>361</fpage><lpage>366</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25500020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name><name><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Loh</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Female ageing and reproductive outcome in assisted reproduction cycles</article-title><source>Singapore Med J</source><year>2014</year><volume>55</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>305</fpage><lpage>303</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25017405</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wissing</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Bjerge</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Olesen</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoest</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mikkelsen</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of PCOS on early embryo cleavage kinetics</article-title><source>Reprod Biomed Online</source><year>2014</year><volume>28</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>508</fpage><lpage>514</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24581983</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Briggs</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kovacs</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>MacLachlan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Motteram</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Can you ever collect too many oocytes?</article-title><source>Hum Reprod</source><year>2015</year><volume>30</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>87</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25362088</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zarei-Kheirabadi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shayegan Nia</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Tavalaee</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Deemeh</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Arabi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Forouzanfar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of ubiquitin and annexin V in sperm population selected based on density gradient centrifugation and zeta potential (DGC-Zeta)</article-title><source>J Assist Reprod Genet</source><year>2012</year><volume>29</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>365</fpage><lpage>371</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22183502</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>P&#x000e9;rez-Crespo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pintado</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Guti&#x000e9;rrez-Ad&#x000e1;n</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Scrotal heat stress effects on sperm viability, sperm DNA integrity, and the offspring sex ratio in mice</article-title><source>Mol Reprod Dev</source><year>2008</year><volume>75</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>40</fpage><lpage>47</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17474098</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kovacs</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Embryo selection: the role of time-lapse monitoring</article-title><source>Reprod Biol Endocrinol</source><year>2014</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>124</fpage><lpage>124</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25510244</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tar&#x000ed;n</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a-P&#x000e9;rez</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hermenegildo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Cano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changes in sex ratio from fertilization to birth in assistedreproductive-treatment cycles</article-title><source>Reprod Biol Endocrinol</source><year>2014</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>56</fpage><lpage>56</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24957129</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>