<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Iran Red Crescent Med J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Iran Red Crescent Med J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.5812/ircmj</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Kowsar</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Iranian Red Crescent Medical Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2074-1804</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2074-1812</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Kowsar</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23984009</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3745758</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5812/ircmj.7975</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Lateral Traumatic Esophago-Cutaneous fistula in a Child; Platelet-Rich Fibrin Glue Challenge</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="short">Esophago-Cutaneous Fistula and PRFG</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Joudi</surname><given-names>Marjan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff11627">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hamidi Alamdari</surname><given-names>Daryoush</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff11628">2</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor11629">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hyradfar</surname><given-names>Mehran</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff11627">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rahimi</surname><given-names>Hamid Reza</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff11630">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Saremi</surname><given-names>Elena</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff11627">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fathi</surname><given-names>Mahdi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff11631">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shojaeian</surname><given-names>Reza</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff11627">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Koliakos</surname><given-names>George</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff11632">5</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff11627"><label>1</label>Pediatric Surgery Department, Sheikh Academic Hospital, Mashhad University of Medical Sciences, Mashhad, IR Iran</aff><aff id="aff11628"><label>2</label>Stem Cell and Regenerative Medicine Research Group, Department of Biochemistry, Mashhad University of Medical Sciences, Mashhad, IR Iran</aff><aff id="aff11630"><label>3</label>Department of Modern Sciences and Technologies, Faculty of Medicine, Mashhad University of Medical Sciences, Mashhad, IR Iran</aff><aff id="aff11631"><label>4</label>Heart Surgery Departments, Imam Reza Academic Hospital, Mashhad University of Medical Sciences, Mashhad, IR Iran</aff><aff id="aff11632"><label>5</label>Departments of Biochemistry, Medical School, Aristotle University of Thessaloniki, Thessaloniki, Greece</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor11629"><label>*</label>Corresponding author: Daryoush Hamidi Alamdari, Stem Cell and Regenerative Medicine Research Group, Department of Biochemistry, Mashhad University of Medical Sciences, Mashhad, IR Iran. Tel: +98-5118457406, Fax: +98-5118457406, E-mail: <email>dhamidialam@yahoo.com</email>.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>05</day><month>3</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>3</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>256</fpage><lpage>259</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>8</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>13</day><month>1</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>20</day><month>1</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2013, Iranian Red Crescent Medical Journal</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>The endoscopic fibrin glue or platelet-rich fibrin glue (PRFG) injection is an easy, safe and effective technique for the fistula. So far, the use of fibrin glue has been limited to selected cases.</p></sec><sec><title>Case report</title><p>Our case is a three years old male child with a neck trauma resulting in a Esophago-Cutaneous fistula after a 3 month period of follow up we decided to use PRFG for this lesion after fine debridement of the fistula tract, and the surrounding fibrosed tissue twice with a one week interval. Our visit after two weeks showed complete recovery and normal general condition. A contrast study revealed complete disappearance of the lesion.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>In our case the PRFG completely resolved a long-standing fistula resistant to exhaustive conservative management. The treatment with PRFG has been proved to be effective in the selected cases and it seems that traumatic esophago-cutaneous fistula may be one of these selections. Application of fibrin sealant should be considered early in the management of these difficult clinical problems.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>Fistula</kwd><kwd>Wounds and Injuries</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec8135"><title>1. Introduction</title><p>Fibrin sealants were first reported in 1909; their usages adapted extensively in Europe for 20 years, and have received increased interest over the last decade in this country. The sealant functions by imitating the final stages of the coagulation cascade. There are many commercial preparations but most involve two solutions, fibrinogen and thrombin. These are applied to the tissue site and in the presence of calcium ions the thrombin cleaves the fibrinogen into fibrin monomers which then polymerize to produce the fibrin clot independent of the patient's own coagulation cascade. The sealant has been used to aid hemostasis or to enhance tissue sealing and has found use in a wide variety of circumstances in plastic, orthopedic, vascular and general surgery (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="A7975R1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="A7975R2">2</xref>).The endoscopic fibrin glue or platelet-rich fibrin glue (PRFG) injection is an easy, safe and effective technique for the fistula even caused by malignancies, and contributes to the quality of life of these patients (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="A7975R3">3</xref>). The constituents of the sealant are either bovine in origin or more commonly isolated from blood bank samples, however, although adverse events (allergic reactions) have rarely been reported there are no documented cases of viral transmission as a result of the use of fibrin sealant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="A7975R1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="A7975R2">2</xref>). So far, the use of fibrin glue has been limited to the treatment of anal, recto-vaginal and enter cutaneous fistula (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="A7975R4">4</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec8136"><title>2. Case Study</title><p>Our case is a 3 years old male child with a neck trauma resulting in a large tissue defect in the right cervical region plus other minor injuries. Primary assessment was done, the patient was stabilized. Early surgical approach was conducted. On exploration, no major vascular or neurologic defect was found. Soft tissue repair was performed. On the third postoperative day after beginning of oral feeding, the surgeon noticed discharge from the wound. An esophago-Cutaneous fistula that wet clothes were found, the discharged fluid revealed saliva, remaining food ingestion also bubble-making (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2077">Figure 1</xref>). As the fistula was a low output one and patient&#x02019;s general condition was acceptable, greatest inlet diameter was 4 mm and length of the fistula was 5 mm, other complication of this fistula was perioutlet erythema and irritation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2077">Figure 1</xref>), Due to possible damage to the cervical vessels and nerves further surgical exploration was cancel and our primary plan was conservative management and observation. At the first step of conservative management a rigid esophagoscopy was done and in right lateral cervical esophagus inlet of fistula was seen. Output decreased but never ceased during a 3 month period of follow up. After this period we decided to use PRFG for this lesion primarily used for some other esophageal fistulas successfully by the author. A home-made PRFG was prepared apportioning was not used for avoiding probable anaphylactic shock (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="A7975R1">1</xref>) and viral inactivation also was done in process of PRFG preparation. After taking 400 ml peripheral blood from ABO match donor into commercial 450-ml triple blood donation bags and passing all viral tests safety according to blood transfusion regulation; PRFG were prepared according to standard procedures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="A7975R5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="A7975R6">6</xref>). The platelets were prepared by first centrifugation at 2000g for 2 min and then second centrifugation at 4000g for 8 min and the supernatant plasma was separated and 10 ml platelet rich plasma was left. The fibrinogen concentrate was prepared from separated plasma by cryoprecipitating method. Following a -70 &#x000ba;C freeze and a 4 &#x000ba;C thaw, plasma were centrifuged at 6500 x g for 5 minutes. The supernatant plasma was removed to a final volume of 10 ml, and 15 ml concentrated fibrinogen mixed with platelets (final volume 20ml). 1 ml thrombin was prepared from removed plasma by adding 10% calcium gluconate. In each application to 5 ml mixture of fibrinogen &#x00026; platelets was added 250 &#x000b5;l mixture of thrombin &#x00026; calcium gluconate. PRFG was applied topically onto the wounds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="A7975R7">7</xref>). So after fine debridement of the fistula tract, and the surrounding fibrosed tissue by freshening the edges of the lesion, we applied PRFG around the esophageal opening twice with a one week interval. Observation during the treatment showed that the external orifice was treated after the first procedure. Our visit after 2 weeks showed complete recovery and normal general condition. A contrast study revealed complete disappearance of the lesion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2078">Figure 2</xref>). After 1 year follow up there are no complication or any problem with surgery site.
</p><fig id="fig2077" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><title>Bubble Making and Discharge for Outlet of Fistula (before Platelet-Rich Fibrin Glue injection)</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="ircmj-15-256-g001"/></fig><fig id="fig2078" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><title>Outlet Closure by Platelet-Rich Fibrin Glue injection (after treatment)</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="ircmj-15-256-g002"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec8137"><title>3. Discussion</title><p>This is an extremely rare condition in which a traumatic fistula has been formed connecting skin and esophagus in the lateral neck area. We searched the media using several medical search machines but we did not succeed in finding a similar case in the literature. After third operation the conservative management was disappointing, also some physicians believe that for same situation &#x0201c;conservative treatment should not be prolonged beyond 14 days and that endoscopic treatment should be performed at that stage with 2 - 4 ml of reconstituted fibrin glue&#x0201d; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="A7975R8">8</xref>). There were cases of esophageal traumatic fistula but all of them connected the esophagus to the nearby trachea and none of them used PRFG as treatment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="A7975R9">9-12</xref>). There is commercial fibrin glue without platelets (because of platelets elimination during fibrinogen preparation) which is used in clinic. In this treatment, home-made fibrin glue is prepared which contain platelets. Platelets, in addition their role in hemostasis, contain a number of growth factors such as platelet-derived growth factor (PDGF), transforming growth factor-&#x003b2; (TGF-&#x003b2;), vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF), epidermal growth factor (EGF), insulin-like growth factor (IGF), and basic fibroblast growth factor (bFGF) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="A7975R13">13-17</xref>) that stimulate cells to regenerate tissue. There are several reports that cytokines or growth factors are critical to wound healing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="A7975R18">18</xref>). These growth factors play major roles in local inflammation, re-epithelialization, granulation tissue formation, neovascularization and extracellular matrix production from various cell sources and through diverse mechanisms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="A7975R19">19</xref>). The child&#x02019;s treatment was a great challenge but as we had the experience of using PRFG in the treatment of congenital trachea esophageal fistulas in our medical center, we decided to use it for this special case as well. In the upper gastrointestinal tract, fibrin sealant has been used in the management of acute hemorrhage, to support suture lines after resection, to aid resolution of anastomotic leaks after resection and in the treatment of esophagotracheal and gastro-colic fistulae (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="A7975R1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="A7975R2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="A7975R20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="A7975R21">21</xref>). Between 1991 and 2003 the treatment of anastomotic leaks of the upper and lower gastro-intestinal tract was performed with fibrin glue in 13 selected patients (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="A7975R4">4</xref>). Recurrent tracheo-oesophageal fistula (TEF) is the most common and serious complication of the treatment of oesophageal atresia with TEF. Following this complication, the patient might need several operations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="A7975R22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="A7975R23">23</xref>). The mortality rate is high (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="A7975R22">22</xref>). The treatment of recurrent TEF has been done using bronchoscopic application of fibrin glue (FG) to the fistula tract (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="A7975R23">23</xref>). Fibrin glue has also been shown to be a suitable delivery vehicle for exogenous growth factors that may in the future be used to accelerate wound healing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="A7975R24">24</xref>). Some authors suggest that if the gastro-intestinal fistulae clinically occurred 7 days after surgery a higher number of endoscopic sessions were necessary than in patients with earlier appearance of anastomotic leakage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="A7975R4">4</xref>). We used the sealant in our case twice with a time interval of one week. Delayed treatment with endoscopic placement of fibrin glue in a persistent esophago-bronchial fistula from spontaneous rupture of the esophagus (Boerhaave's syndrome a resistant to extended conservative management was performed successfully (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="A7975R1">1</xref>). The history of failed conservative management and immediate success of the intervention leave no doubt that the fibrin treatment was responsible for the resolution of the fistula (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="A7975R1">1</xref>). In our case the fibrin glue completely resolved a long-standing fistula resistant to exhaustive conservative management. Fibrin glue has been widely used as an adhesive in plastic and reconstructive surgery (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="A7975R24">24</xref>). The treatment with PRFG has been proved to be effective in the selected cases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="A7975R4">4</xref>) and it seems that traumatic esophago-cutaneous fistula may be one of these selections. Application of fibrin sealant should be considered early in the management of these difficult clinical problems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="A7975R1">1</xref>).</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>This research project was supported by the Mashhad University of Medical Science Research Council. Finally, written informed consent was obtained from the patient&#x02019;s parents for publication of this case report, these procedures and any accompanying.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="afn5968" fn-type="other"><p><bold>Implication for health policy/practice/research/medical education</bold> In our case the fibrin glue completely resolved a long-standing fistula resistant to exhaustive conservative management. The treatment with PRFG has been proved to be effective in the selected cases</p></fn><fn id="afn5969" fn-type="other"><p><bold>Please cite this paper as</bold> Joudi M, Hamidi Alamdari D, Hyradfar M, Rahimi HR, Saremi E, Fathi M, Shojaeian R, Koliakos G. Lateral Traumatic Esophago-Cutaneous fistula in a Child; Platelet-Rich Fibrin Glue Challenge. Iran Red Cres J. 2013; 15(3): 256-9. DOI: 10.5812/ircmj.7975</p></fn><fn id="afn5970" fn-type="other"><p><bold>Authors&#x02019; Contribution</bold> None declared.</p></fn><fn id="afn5971" fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Financial Disclosure</bold> The authors indicate no potential conflicts of interest. The study protocol and informed-consent forms were reviewed and approved by the Human Research Ethics Committee of Mashhad University of Medical Sciences; the patient&#x02019;s parents signed that form also one of the surgery team has explained all procedures and processes for them.</p></fn><fn id="afn5972" fn-type="other"><p><bold>Funding Support</bold> None declared.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="A7975R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harries</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Masoud</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Endoscopic placement of fibrin sealant as a treatment for a long-standing Boerhaave's fistula.</article-title><source>Dis Esophagus.</source><year>2004</year><volume>17</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>348</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1442-2050.2004.00421.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15569376</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A7975R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spotnitz</surname><given-names>William D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Commercial fibrin sealants in surgical care.</article-title><source>American journal of surgery.</source><year>2001</year><volume>182</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>S8</fpage><lpage>S14</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="A7975R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hirao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaneko</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mizunoya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Okagawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>[Two cases of esophageal fistula, in which a fibrin glue preparation was effective].</article-title><source>Nihon Kyobu Geka Gakkai Zasshi.</source><year>1994</year><volume>42</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>2144</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7836832</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A7975R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Del Rio</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Dell'Abate</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Soliani</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ziegler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Arcuri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sianesi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Endoscopic treatment of esophageal and colo-rectal fistulas with fibrin glue.</article-title><source>Acta Biomed.</source><year>2005</year><volume>76</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16350554</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A7975R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valbonesi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fibrin glues of human origin.</article-title><source>Best Pract Res Clin Haematol.</source><year>2006</year><volume>19</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>191</fpage><lpage>203</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.beha.2005.01.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16377550</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A7975R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whitman</surname><given-names>Dean H</given-names></name><name><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>Ronald L</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>David M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Platelet gel: An autologous alternative to fibrin glue with applications in oral and maxillofacial surgery.</article-title><source>Journal of oral and maxillofacial surgery : official journal of the American Association of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgeons.</source><year>1997</year><volume>55</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1294</fpage><lpage>1299</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9371122</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A7975R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ravari</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamidi-Almadari</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Salimifar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonakdaran</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Parizadeh</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Koliakos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Treatment of non-healing wounds with autologous bone marrow cells, platelets, fibrin glue and collagen matrix.</article-title><source>Cytotherapy.</source><year>2011</year><volume>13</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>705</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/14653249.2011.553594</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21284564</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A7975R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rabago</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ventosa</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Castro</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Marco</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Herrera</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Gea</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Endoscopic treatment of postoperative fistulas resistant to conservative management using biological fibrin glue.</article-title><source>Endoscopy.</source><year>2002</year><volume>34</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>632</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-2002-33237</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12173084</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A7975R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Antkowiak</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Kyllonen</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tracheoesophageal fistula following blunt trauma.</article-title><source>Arch Surg.</source><year>1974</year><volume>109</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>529</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4416684</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A7975R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Braun</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldware</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cervical tracheal transsection with esophageal fistula.</article-title><source>Arch Otolaryngol.</source><year>1972</year><volume>96</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5032059</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A7975R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Braun</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The management of traumatic tracheo-esophageal fistula caused by blunt chest trauma.</article-title><source>Arch Surg.</source><year>1970</year><volume>100</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>681</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5444486</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A7975R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gerwat</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bryce</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Management of traumatic tracheoesophageal fistula.</article-title><source>Arch Otolaryngol.</source><year>1975</year><volume>101</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1119995</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A7975R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Assoian</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Komoriya</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyers</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sporn</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transforming growth factor-beta in human platelets. Identification of a major storage site, purification, and characterization.</article-title><source>J Biol Chem.</source><year>1983</year><volume>258</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>7155</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6602130</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A7975R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eppley</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Woodell</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Platelet quantification and growth factor analysis from platelet-rich plasma: implications for wound healing.</article-title><source>Plast Reconstr Surg.</source><year>2004</year><volume>114</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1502</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15509939</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A7975R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>Russell</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Platelets: Cell proliferation and atherosclerosis.</article-title><source>Metabolism.</source><year>1979</year><volume>28</volume><issue>4, Supplement 1</issue><fpage>410</fpage><lpage>414</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0026-0495(79)90047-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">122294</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A7975R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Slater</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Patava</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kingham</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Involvement of platelets in stimulating osteogenic activity.</article-title><source>J Orthop Res.</source><year>1995</year><volume>13</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>655</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jor.1100130504</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7472743</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A7975R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spencer</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tokunaga</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Insulin-like growth factor binding protein-3 is present in the alpha-granules of platelets.</article-title><source>Endocrinology.</source><year>1993</year><volume>132</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>996</fpage><lpage>1001</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7679986</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A7975R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gharaee-Kermani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Phan</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of cytokines and cytokine therapy in wound healing and fibrotic diseases.</article-title><source>Curr Pharm Des.</source><year>2001</year><volume>7</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1083</fpage><lpage>103</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11472255</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A7975R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singer</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cutaneous wound healing.</article-title><source>N Engl J Med.</source><year>1999</year><volume>341</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>738</fpage><lpage>46</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJM199909023411006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10471461</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A7975R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bardaxoglou</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Manganas</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Meunier</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Landen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Maddern</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Campion</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>New approach to surgical management of early esophageal thoracic perforation: primary suture repair reinforced with absorbable mesh and fibrin glue.</article-title><source>World J Surg.</source><year>1997</year><volume>21</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>618</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9230659</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A7975R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cellier</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Landi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Faye</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wind</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Frileux</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Cugnenc</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Upper gastrointestinal tract fistulae: endoscopic obliteration with fibrin sealant.</article-title><source>Gastrointest Endosc.</source><year>1996</year><volume>44</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>731</fpage><lpage>3</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8979068</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A7975R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gutierrez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Barrios</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Lluna</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Vila</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia-Sala</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Roca</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Recurrent tracheoesophageal fistula treated with fibrin glue.</article-title><source>J Pediatr Surg.</source><year>1994</year><volume>29</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1567</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7877030</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A7975R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kili&#x000e7;</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x000fc;rpinar</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiristio&#x0011d;lu</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Turkel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Dogruyol</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Treatment of recurrent tracheo-oesophageal fistula in an infant using bronchoscopic I application of fibrin glue.</article-title><source>Minimally Invasive Therapy and Allied Technologies.</source><year>1999</year><volume>8</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/13645709909153143</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A7975R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Currie</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharpe</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The use of fibrin glue in skin grafts and tissue-engineered skin replacements: a review.</article-title><source>Plast Reconstr Surg.</source><year>2001</year><volume>108</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1713</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11711954</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>