<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Biol Chem</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jbc</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Journal of Biological Chemistry</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0021-9258</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1083-351X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Society for Biochemistry and Molecular Biology</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18308722</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3259572</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">13225</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M704532200</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Membrane Transport, Structure, Function, and Biogenesis</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Regulation of the Epithelial Na<sup>+</sup> Channel by the Protein Kinase
 CK2<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">*</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2">&#x00053;&#x020de;</xref></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bachhuber</surname><given-names>Tanja</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="d31e115">&#x02021;</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Alma&#x000e7;a</surname><given-names>Joana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="d31e115">&#x02021;</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="d31e115">&#x000a7;</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Aldehni</surname><given-names>Fadi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="d31e115">&#x02021;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>Anil</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="d31e115">&#x000b6;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Amaral</surname><given-names>Margarida D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="d31e115">&#x000b6;</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="d31e115">&#x02225;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schreiber</surname><given-names>Rainer</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="d31e115">&#x02021;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kunzelmann</surname><given-names>Karl</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="d31e115">&#x02021;</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">3</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="d31e115"><label><sup>&#x02021;</sup></label>Institut f&#x000fc;r Physiologie,
 Universit&#x000e4;t Regensburg, Universit&#x000e4;tsstra&#x003b2;e 31, D-93053
 Regensburg, Germany, the <label><sup>&#x000b6;</sup></label>Department
 of Maternal and Child Health Sciences, University of Dundee, Ninewells
 Hospital, Dundee DD1 9SY, United Kingdom, the
 <label><sup>&#x000a7;</sup></label>Faculdade de Ci&#x000ea;ncias,
 Universidade de Lisboa, 1749-016 Lisboa, Portugal, and the
 <label><sup>&#x02225;</sup></label>Centre of Human Genetics, National
 Institute of Health, 1649-016 Lisboa, Portugal</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>3</label>
 To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel.: 49-0-941-943-4302; Fax:
 49-0-941-943-4315; E-mail:
 <email>uqkkunze@mailbox.uq.edu.au</email>.
 </corresp><fn id="fn3"><label>1</label><p>Both authors contributed equally to the present work.</p></fn><fn id="fn4"><label>2</label><p>Recipient of the SFRH/BD/29134/2006 PhD fellowship from FCT (Portugal).</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>9</day><month>5</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>9</day><month>5</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on 
			/art/copyright. --><volume>283</volume><issue>19</issue><fpage>13225</fpage><lpage>13232</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>1</day><month>6</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>7</day><month>2</month><year>2008</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2008, The American Society for Biochemistry and
 Molecular Biology, Inc.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><license-p><italic>Author's Choice</italic></license-p><license-p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License</ext-link> applies to Author Choice Articles</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="zbc01908013225.pdf"/><abstract><p>CK2 is a ubiquitous, pleiotropic, and constitutively active Ser/Thr protein
 kinase that controls protein expression, cell signaling, and ion channel
 activity. Phosphorylation sites for CK2 are located in the C terminus of both
 &#x003b2;- and &#x003b3;-subunits of the epithelial Na<sup>+</sup> channel (ENaC).
 We examined the role of CK2 on the regulation of both endogenous ENaC in
 native murine epithelia and in <italic>Xenopus</italic> oocytes expressing rENaC. In
 Ussing chamber experiments with mouse airways, colon, and cultured
 M1-collecting duct cells, amiloride-sensitive Na<sup>+</sup> transport was
 inhibited dose-dependently by the selective CK2 inhibitor
 4,5,6,7-tetrabromobenzotriazole (TBB). In oocytes, ENaC currents were also
 inhibited by TBB and by the structurally unrelated inhibitors heparin and
 poly(E:Y). Expression of a trimeric channel lacking both CK2 sites
 (&#x003b1;&#x003b2;<sub>S631A</sub>&#x003b3;<sub>T599A</sub>) produced a largely
 attenuated amiloride-sensitive whole cell conductance and rendered the mutant
 channel insensitive to CK2. In <italic>Xenopus</italic> oocytes, CK2 was translocated
 to the cell membrane upon expression of wt-ENaC but not of
 &#x003b1;&#x003b2;<sub>S631A</sub>&#x003b3;<sub>T599A</sub>-ENaC. Phosphorylation by
 CK2 is essential for ENaC activation, and to a lesser degree, it also controls
 membrane expression of &#x003b1;&#x003b2;&#x003b3;-ENaC. Channels lacking the Nedd4-2
 binding motif in &#x003b2;-ENaC (R561X, Y618A) no longer required the CK2 site
 for channel activity and siRNA-knockdown of Nedd4-2 eliminated the effects of
 TBB. This implies a role for CK2 in inhibiting the Nedd4-2 pathway. We propose
 that the C terminus of &#x003b2;-ENaC is targeted by this essential, conserved
 pleiotropic kinase that directs its constitutive activity toward many cellular
 protein complexes.</p></abstract></article-meta><notes><fn-group><fn id="fn1"><label>*</label><p>This work was supported in part by <funding-source>Deutsche
 Forschungsgemeinschaft</funding-source> <award-id>SFB699 A6</award-id>, the
 <funding-source>Wellcome Trust</funding-source> (to A. M.),
 and <funding-source>Fundacao para a Ciencia e a Tecnologia</funding-source>
 grants (Portugal) (to M. D. A.). The costs of publication of this article were
 defrayed in part by the payment of page charges. This article must therefore
 be hereby marked &#x0201c;<italic>advertisement</italic>&#x0201d; in accordance with 18
 U.S.C. Section 1734 solely to indicate this fact.</p></fn><fn id="fn2"><label/><p>The on-line version of this article (available at
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jbc.org">http://www.jbc.org</ext-link>)
 contains supplemental Fig. S1.</p></fn></fn-group></notes></front><body><p>Electrogenic Na<sup>+</sup> absorption across the apical membrane of
 epithelia utilizes an amiloride-sensitive channel
 (ENaC)<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5">4</xref> composed of
 three (&#x003b1;&#x003b2;&#x003b3;) subunits produced from different genes
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref>). In kidney-collecting duct,
 distal colon, airway, secretory ducts from a variety of organs, and the
 absorptive sweat duct, ENaC is regulated by an interaction between the &#x003b2;-
 and &#x003b3;-subunits (at their C terminus) and the E3-ubiquitin ligase
 Nedd4-2. The WW domains of Nedd4-2 bind proline-rich PY (P<italic>XX</italic>Y) motifs
 in each ENaC subunit leading to channel ubiquitination, internalization, and
 degradation and hence channel inactivation
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref>). Nedd4-2 interaction with
 ENaC is positively and negatively controlled by phosphorylation of either
 Nedd4-2, or the C termini of both &#x003b2;- and &#x003b3;-ENaC. Accordingly, the
 aldosterone-induced serum and glucocorticoid-dependent kinase, Sgk-1,
 phosphorylates Nedd4-2 on serines (Ser) 444 and 338, thereby reducing its
 interaction with the channel and causing enhanced ENaC activity
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref23">23</xref>). Apart from this, Sgk-1
 also phosphorylates &#x003b1;-ENaC directly at Ser-621, causing a stimulatory
 effect on the channel, which appears to be Nedd-4-2-independent
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref>). Protein kinase A (PKA),
 which is known to activate ENaC in alveolar epithelial cells, sweat duct, and
 kidney, was also shown to phosphorylate Nedd4-2 (at serine residues 221, 246,
 and 327) and to reduce binding to ENaC
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref22">22</xref>). Moreover, PKA prevents
 inhibition of ENaC by preventing &#x003b2;-ENaC phosphorylation at threonine
 (Thr) 613 by the extracellular-regulated kinase (Erk)
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref26">26</xref>). Indeed, phosphorylation
 of Thr-613 in &#x003b2;-ENaC and Thr-623 in &#x003b3;-ENaC were previously shown to
 increase channel affinity toward Nedd4-2, thereby down-regulating channel
 activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">20</xref>).</p><p>Thus, differential phosphorylation of both &#x003b2;- and &#x003b3;-ENaC
 subunits can either enhance or reduce its affinity for Nedd4-2, thereby
 controlling its degradation and hence the channel activity. Along this line,
 the G protein-coupled receptor kinase 2 (Grk2) was found recently to
 upregulate the activity of ENaC in salivary duct cells
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref>). Grk2 acts at the C
 terminus of &#x003b2;-ENaC phosphorylating Ser-633, <italic>i.e.</italic> twenty amino
 acids downstream of Erk. Grk2 increases the activity of ENaC by rendering the
 channel insensitive to Nedd4-2
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref>). Notably, an increased Grk2
 activity has been reported to be associated with hypertension in humans and in
 animal models (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref>). Therefore,
 imbalance in ENaC channel regulation by activatory or inhibitory pathways may
 lead to inappropriate Na<sup>+</sup> absorption, hypertension, or cystic
 fibrosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref>).</p><p>Additional phosphorylation sites at the C terminus of the &#x003b2;- and
 &#x003b3;-subunits of ENaC include those for the pleiotropic but essential
 protein casein kinase 2 (CK2)
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">21</xref>). It has been demonstrated
 that CK2 specifically binds to and phosphorylates the C termini of both these
 ENaC subunits. As found for the Grk2 site (Ser-633) in &#x003b2;-ENaC, a pair of
 CK2 phosphorylation sites (&#x003b2;Ser-631 and &#x003b3;Thr-599) are located in
 close proximity to their respective PY motifs. CK2 is not easy to study, as
 siRNA approaches invariably impact on a number of targets in multiple
 pathways, some of which coupled to its essential function for cell survival.
 In a previous study, no contribution of CK2 to regulation of ENaC was observed
 following the mutation of single putative CK2 sites
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">21</xref>). Notwithstanding, we
 investigated a role for CK2 on ENaC function in native epithelia from airway
 and colon as well as in <italic>Xenopus</italic> oocytes expressing rat ENaC. We found
 that constitutive CK2 phosphorylation not only maintains ENaC active, but it
 also controls the membrane expression of its subunits.</p><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><p><italic>Ussing Chamber Experiments</italic>&#x02014;Tracheas and distal colon were
 removed from mice euthanized by ethically approved institutional procedures
 (C57BL/6, Charles Rivers, Germany). Tissues were put immediately into ice-cold
 buffer solution of the following composition (mmol/liter): NaCl 145, KCI 3.8,
 <sc>d</sc>-glucose 5, MgCI<sub>2</sub> 1, HEPES 5, Ca<sup>2+</sup> gluconate
 1.3. After stripping the colonic mucosa and opening tracheas by a longitudinal
 cut, tissues were mounted into a micro Ussing chamber with a circular aperture
 of 0.95 mm<sup>2</sup>. Mouse M-1 kidney cortex-collecting duct cells (kindly
 provided by C. Korbmacher, Physiologisches Institut, Universit&#x000e4;t
 Erlangen, Germany) were grown to confluence on permeable supports and mounted
 into the Ussing chamber (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>).
 Luminal and basolateral sides of the epithelium were perfused continuously at
 a rate of 5 ml/min. The bath solution containing (mmol/liter) NaCl 145,
 KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub> 0.4, K<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub> 1.6,
 <sc>d</sc>-glucose 5, MgCI<sub>2</sub> 1, HEPES 5, and calcium gluconate
 1.3, was heated to 37 &#x000b0;C, and the pH was adjusted to 7.4. Experiments were
 carried out under open circuit conditions. Values for transepithelial voltages
 (V<sub>te</sub>) were referred to the serosal side of the epithelium.
 Transepithelial resistance (R<sub>te</sub>) was determined by applying short
 (1 s) current pulses (&#x00394;l = 0.5 &#x003bc;A) and after subtracting the
 resistance of the empty chamber, using Ohm's law (R<sub>te</sub>
 =&#x00394;V<sub>te</sub>/&#x00394;I). Transepithelial resistances were 63 &#x000b1;
 3.8 &#x003a9;cm<sup>2</sup>; <italic>n</italic> = 12 (trachea), 31 &#x000b1; 2.1;
 <italic>n</italic> = 13 (colon), and 669 &#x000b1; 45 &#x003a9;cm<sup>2</sup>; <italic>n</italic>
 = 38 (M1).</p><p><italic>cRNAs for ENaC Subunits and CFTR</italic>&#x02014;cDNAs-encoding rat
 (FLAG-tagged or non-tagged) &#x003b1;&#x003b2;&#x003b3;-ENaC (kindly provided by
 Prof. Dr. B. Rossier, Pharmacological Institute of Lausanne, Switzerland, Ref.
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref>) and the Cl<sup>-</sup>
 channels CFTR were linearized in pBluescript with Notl or Mlul, and <italic>in
 vitro</italic> transcribed using T7, T3, or SP6 promotor and polymerase (Promega).
 Isolation and microinjection of oocytes have been described in detail
 elsewhere (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>). The ENaC mutants
 &#x003b2;<sub>S631A</sub>, &#x003b3;<sub>T599A</sub>, &#x003b2;<sub>R561X</sub>,
 &#x003b2;<sub>Y618A</sub>, and &#x003b2;<sub>S633A</sub> were generated by PCR, and
 correct sequences were verified by sequencing.</p><p><italic>Double Electrode Voltage Clamp</italic>&#x02014;Oocytes were injected with
 cRNA (10 ng, 47 nl double-distilled water). Water-injected oocytes served as
 controls. 2-4 days after injection, oocytes were impaled with two electrodes
 (Clark Instruments Ltd, Salisbury, UK), which had a resistance of &#x0003c;1
 <sc>m</sc>&#x003a9; when filled with 2.7 mol/liter KCI. Using two bath
 electrodes and a virtual ground head stage, the voltage drop across
 R<sub>serial</sub> was effectively zero. Membrane currents were measured by
 voltage clamping (oocyte clamp amplifier, Warner Instruments LLC, Hamden CT)
 in intervals from -90 to +30 mV, in steps of 10 mV, each 1 s. The bath was
 continuously perfused at a rate of 5 ml/min. All experiments were conducted at
 room temperature (22 &#x000b0;C).</p><p><italic>Chemiluminescence Measurements</italic>&#x02014;Oocytes were fixed for 60 min
 at room temperature with 3% paraformaldehyde (in Tris-buffered saline (TBS),
 pH 8.0) and washed with TBS; (m<sc>m</sc>) 50 Tris, 138 NaCl, 2.7 KCl, pH
 8.0 at room temperature. Then oocytes were incubated for 60 min in TBS with 1%
 (w/v) bovine serum albumin (BSA), another 60 min with 1 &#x003bc;g/ml mouse
 monoclonal anti-FLAG M2 antibody in 1% BSA/TBS at 4 &#x000b0;C (Sigma-Aldrich),
 washed at 4 &#x000b0;C with 1% BSA/TBS and incubated with sheep anti-mouse IgG
 peroxidase-linked whole antibody (Amersham Biosciences) diluted 1:20,000 in 1%
 BSA/TBS for 40 min at 4 &#x000b0;C. Afterward oocytes were washed for 60 min at 4
 &#x000b0;C in 1% BSA/TBS and finally in TBS (60 min, 4 &#x000b0;C). Oocytes were
 placed separately in 50 &#x003bc;l of ECL Plus Western blotting detection reagents
 (Amersham Biosciences). After incubation for 5 min at room temperature,
 chemiluminescence was measured in a BioOrbit 1250 Luminometer (Turku,
 Finland), and an integration period of 1 s was allowed.</p><p><italic>Oocyte Staining</italic>&#x02014;Oocytes were incubated for 60 min in ND96
 solution (in m<sc>m</sc>: 96 NaCl, 2.0 KCl, 1.8 CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 1.0
 MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 5.0 HEPES, pH 7.4), fixed for 60 min with 3%
 paraformaldehyde (in TBS, pH 8.0) and washed in TBS. After embedding in
 optimum cutting temperature compound (Sakura Finetek Europe, Zoeterwoude, NL),
 oocytes were cut to 20-&#x003bc;m slices with a cryostat (Leica CM3050 S, Wetzlar,
 Germany). Sections were put in either TBS or phosphate-buffered saline (PBS;
 (m<sc>m</sc>) 137 NaCl, 1.8 KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, 10.3
 Na<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub>, pH 7.4), incubated for 5 min in 0.1% (w/v) SDS
 in PBS and washed two times with either TBS or PBS. Sections were incubated
 for 60 min in TBS or PBS (5% BSA) and for 60 min at 37 &#x000b0;C with the
 anti-FLAG M2 antibody diluted 1:50 in 2% BSA/TBS or a goat polyclonal casein
 kinase II&#x003b1; antibody (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Heidelberg, Germany)
 diluted 1:25 in 2% BSA/PBS. Afterward sections were washed twice in PBS and
 incubated for 1 h with secondary antibodies (donkey anti-mouse IgG-Alexa Fluor
 488 conjugated and donkey anti-goat IgG-Alexa Fluor 546 conjugated; Molecular
 Probes, Eugene, OR) at a dilution of 1:1000 in 2% BSA/PBS. Sections were
 washed two times with PBS for 5 min and covered with DakoCytomation
 fluorescent mounting medium (DakoCytomation, Inc., Carpinteria, CA). Images
 were obtained using a Zeiss Axiovert 200 m microscope with a &#x000d7;63
 objective (Carl Zeiss, Inc., Jena, Germany).</p><p><italic>Materials and Statistical Analysis</italic>&#x02014;All compounds used were
 of highest available grade of purity. Amiloride,
 2-dimethylamino-4,5,6,7-tetrabromo-1<italic>H</italic>-benzimidazole (DMAT),
 forskolin, IBMX (3-isobutyl-1-methylxanthine), heparin, okadaic acid,
 poly(E:Y) peptide, and poly(K) were from Sigma. TBB was a generous gift from
 Prof. L. Pinna (Department of Biological Chemistry, University of Padua,
 Italy). The Nedd4-2 antibody was a generous gift from Prof. Dr. J. Loffing
 (University of Z&#x000fc;rich, Switzerland). mNedd4-2-RNAi (5&#x02032;-CCA UUU GUC
 CUA UUU CAC CUU CAU U-3&#x02032;), xNedd4-2-RNAi (5&#x02032;-GCG UGC CUA UGA AUG
 GAU U-3&#x02032;), and mCK2-RNAi (5&#x02032;-UUG UCA AGA AGA UCU AGG GCC UCC
 G-3&#x02032;) were from Invitrogen (Paisley, UK). Scrambled RNA is a mixture of
 double-stranded RNA sequences that has no match to any of the known
 <italic>Xenopus</italic> mRNA sequences. Student's <italic>t</italic> test was used for
 statistical analysis. A <italic>p</italic> value of &#x0003c;0.05 was regarded as
 significant.</p><p><fig position="float" id="fig1"><label>FIGURE 1.</label><caption><p><bold>CK2 activates ENaC in native epithelia and in epithelial cells.</bold>
 Original Ussing chamber recordings of the transepithelial voltages
 V<sub>te</sub> detected in mouse trachea (<italic>A</italic>), mouse colon
 (<italic>C</italic>), and M1 cells (<italic>E</italic>). Effects of amiloride (<italic>A</italic>, 10
 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>) and the CK2 inhibitor TBB (10 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>).
 Concentration-dependence of the effects of TBB on amiloride-sensitive
 transport in trachea (<italic>B</italic>), colon (<italic>D</italic>), and M1 cells
 (<italic>F</italic>). The <italic>asterisk</italic> (<sup>*</sup>) indicates significant
 effects of TBB (paired <italic>t</italic>-tests, number of experiments: 9-13 for each
 series).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zbc0200835040001"/></fig></p><p><fig position="float" id="fig2"><label>FIGURE 2.</label><caption><p><bold>CK2 activates ENaC in Xenopus oocytes.</bold> <italic>A</italic>, current recording
 from a <italic>Xenopus</italic> oocyte expressing &#x003b1;&#x003b2;&#x003b3;-ENaC and
 effects of amiloride (10 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>) and TBB (10 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>).
 Oocytes were voltage-clamped from -90 mV to +10 mV in steps of 10 mV, and the
 resulting currents were recorded. <italic>B</italic>, summary of the effects of
 amiloride and TBB on whole cell conductance in ENaC-expressing oocytes.
 <italic>C</italic>, summary of the change of amiloride-sensitive conductance
 (<italic>G</italic><sub>amil</sub>) after injection of water, the CK2 inhibitor
 poly(E:Y) (50 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>) and CK2 activator poly(K) (50
 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>), respectively. <italic>D</italic>, current recording of an
 ENaC-expressing oocyte and the effects of amiloride (<italic>A</italic>, 10
 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>) and okadaic acid (100 n<sc>m</sc>). <italic>E</italic>, summary of
 the effect of okadaic acid on the amiloride-sensitive whole cell conductance
 measured in oocytes. The <italic>asterisk</italic> (<sup>*</sup>) indicates
 significant effects (paired <italic>t</italic>-test). The <italic>number sign</italic> (#)
 indicates a significant difference for the effects of amiloride before and
 after incubation with TBB (paired <italic>t</italic>-test, 6-25 experiments for each
 series).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zbc0200835040002"/></fig></p></sec><sec><title>RESULTS</title><p><italic>CK2 Blocker Inhibits ENaC Activity</italic>&#x02014;We examined the
 contribution of CK2 to the regulation of epithelial Na<sup>+</sup> channels in
 native epithelia from mouse trachea and colon. In Ussing chamber experiments,
 we explored CK2-selective concentrations of the specific inhibitor TBB, which
 was shown to have no effect on over 30 other kinases. TBB selectivity depends
 on its ability to bind an unusual hydrophobic ATP binding site that differs
 from the equivalent in conventional kinases. Electrogenic Na<sup>+</sup>
 transport in mouse trachea was assessed by inhibition of ENaC with amiloride
 (10 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig.
 1<italic>A</italic></xref>). TBB (10 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>) reduced the
 transepithelial voltage V<sub>te</sub> and attenuated amiloride-sensitive
 short-circuit currents (I<sub>sc-amil</sub>) in a dose-dependent manner
 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1, <italic>A</italic> and
 <italic>B</italic></xref>). Similarly, TBB significantly blocked
 amiloride-sensitive Na<sup>+</sup> transport in mouse distal colon
 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1, <italic>C</italic> and
 <italic>D</italic></xref>). This effect could be reproduced in cultured mouse
 M1-collecting duct cells, grown on permeable supports
 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1, <italic>E</italic> and
 <italic>F</italic></xref>). These combined results suggest that endogenous
 epithelial Na<sup>+</sup> channels expressed in epithelial tissues are
 maintained in an active state by constitutively active CK2.</p><p>To further confirm regulation of epithelial Na<sup>+</sup> channels by CK2,
 the three (&#x003b1;&#x003b2;&#x003b3;)-ENaC subunits were expressed in
 <italic>Xenopus</italic> oocytes and examined in double electrode voltage clamp
 experiments. As shown in the original recording in
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2<italic>A</italic></xref>, the
 simultaneous expression of the three ENaC subunits produced a large current,
 which was inhibited by amiloride (A, 10 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>). The CK2 structure
 is virtually identical in <italic>Xenopus</italic> compared with mammals. Thus, TBB
 (10 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>) also significantly reduced amiloride-sensitive whole
 cell currents and conductance (<italic>G</italic><sub>amil</sub>), respectively
 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2, <italic>A</italic> and
 <italic>B</italic></xref>) in oocytes. Another compound, DMAT, has recently been
 shown to inhibit CK2 with higher inhibitory potency, but it has limited
 efficacy <italic>in vivo</italic> due to its rapid
 turnover.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6">5</xref> At 2
 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>, we did not observe inhibition of ENaC currents by DMAT in
 <italic>Xenopus</italic> oocytes; however, 5 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc> reduced
 amiloride-sensitive ENaC conductance significantly from 31.9 &#x000b1; 6.8 to
 25.7 &#x000b1; 4.1 &#x003bc;S(<italic>n</italic> = 5). Regulation of ENaC by CK2 was further
 validated using the structurally unrelated peptide inhibitor of CK2, poly(E:Y)
 and conversely, by activating CK2 with polylysine (poly(K))
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref24">24</xref>). The peptides were
 injected into oocytes at final concentrations between 10 and 100
 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>, and amiloride-sensitive Na<sup>+</sup> conductances were
 compared before and 1-5 h after injection. During these few hours, ENaC
 conductance increased, almost doubling initial values in water-injected
 controls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2</xref>), This
 time-enhanced Na<sup>+</sup> conductance was nevertheless inhibited by
 poly(E:Y) and was further activated through stimulation of CK2 by poly(K)
 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2<italic>C</italic></xref>). CK2 is
 known to associate with protein phosphatase 2A (PP2A). To confirm
 phosphorylation-dependent activation of ENaC, ooctyes were exposed to okadaic
 acid at a PP2A-specific concentration (10 n<sc>m</sc>), which further
 increased amiloride-sensitive Na<sup>+</sup> transport
 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2, <italic>D</italic> and
 <italic>E</italic></xref>). Thus ENaC appears to be stimulated by constitutively
 active CK2 with counter-regulation by PP2A-like inhibition. To further confirm
 this activation by CK2, injection of the nonspecific CK2 inhibitor heparin (10
 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>) also reduced Na<sup>+</sup> conductance in <italic>Xenopus</italic>
 oocytes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4<italic>C</italic></xref>).</p><p><fig position="float" id="fig3"><label>FIGURE 3.</label><caption><p><bold>Elimination of CK2 phosphorylation sites on ENaC inhibits channel
 activity.</bold> <italic>A</italic>, current recording from a <italic>Xenopus</italic> oocyte
 expressing &#x003b1;&#x003b2;&#x003b3;-ENaC and effects of amiloride
 (10&#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>) and TBB (10&#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>). Oocytes were
 voltage-clamped from -90 mV to +10 mV in steps of 10 mV, and the resulting
 currents were recorded. <italic>B</italic>, current recording from a <italic>Xenopus</italic>
 oocyte expressing &#x003b1;&#x003b2;<sub>S631A</sub>&#x003b3;<sub>T559A</sub>-ENaC
 and effects of amiloride (10 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>) and TBB (10 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>).
 <italic>C</italic> and <italic>D</italic>, summaries of the effects of amiloride and TBB on
 <italic>G</italic><sub>amil</sub> generated by &#x003b1;&#x003b2;&#x003b3;-ENaC and
 &#x003b1;&#x003b2;<sub>S631A</sub>&#x003b3;<sub>T559A</sub>-ENaC. <italic>E</italic>,
 comparison of <italic>G</italic><sub>amil</sub> produced by
 wt-(&#x003b1;&#x003b2;&#x003b3;)-, single mutants
 (&#x003b1;&#x003b2;<sub>S631A</sub>&#x003b3;, &#x003b1;&#x003b2;&#x003b3;<sub>T559A</sub>)-,
 and a doublemutant
 (&#x003b1;&#x003b2;<sub>S631A</sub>&#x003b3;<sub>T559A</sub>)-ENaC.<italic>F</italic>,
 summaries of <italic>G</italic><sub>amil</sub> produced by dimeric wt-(&#x003b1;&#x003b2;,
 &#x003b1;&#x003b3;)- and mutant (&#x003b1;&#x003b2;<sub>S631A</sub>,
 &#x003b1;&#x003b3;<sub>T559</sub>)-ENaC channels. The <italic>asterisk</italic>
 (<sup>*</sup>) and <italic>number sign</italic> (#) indicate a significant difference
 (paired <italic>t</italic>-test, 13-25 experiments for each series).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zbc0200835040003"/></fig></p><p><fig position="float" id="fig4"><label>FIGURE 4.</label><caption><p><bold>CK2 controls membrane expression of ENaC in <italic>Xenopus</italic>
 oocytes.</bold> Time course for <italic>G</italic><sub>amil</sub> (<italic>A, C, E</italic>) and
 membrane expression of &#x003b1;<sub>Flag</sub>-ENaC (<italic>B, D, F</italic>). Ooctyes
 were kept in ND97 or in ND97 containing TBB (10 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>), or were
 injected with heparin (10 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>), poly(E:Y) (50 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>),
 or equal amounts (30 nl) of water. The <italic>asterisk</italic> (<sup>*</sup>)
 indicates significant differences when compared with ND96 or water (unpaired
 <italic>t</italic>-tests, 6-13 experiments for each series).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zbc0200835040004"/></fig></p><p><italic>Removal of CK2 Sites from</italic> &#x003b2;<italic>- and</italic> &#x003b3;<italic>-ENaC
 Inhibits Amiloride-sensitive Na</italic><sup>+</sup> <italic>Conductance and Renders
 It Insensitive to TBB</italic>&#x02014;Similar to endogenous Na<sup>+</sup> currents
 present in epithelial tissues (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig.
 1</xref>), ENaC expressed exogenously in <italic>Xenopus</italic> oocytes was
 inhibited by TBB in a dose-dependent manner
 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3, <italic>A</italic> and
 <italic>C</italic></xref>). ENaC contains two phosphorylation sites for CK2, in
 &#x003b2;-ENaC (serine 631) and &#x003b3;-ENaC (threonine 599). Changing both CK2
 sites to alanines (&#x003b1;&#x003b2;<sub>S631A</sub>&#x003b3;<sub>T599A</sub>)
 virtually eliminated Na<sup>+</sup> conductance and rendered residual
 conductance of the double mutant channel insensitive to TBB
 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3, <italic>B</italic> and
 <italic>D</italic></xref>). Trimeric Na<sup>+</sup> channels carrying only one
 mutation in either &#x003b2;-ENaC (&#x003b1;&#x003b2;<sub>S631A</sub>&#x003b3;) or
 &#x003b3;-ENaC (&#x003b1;&#x003b2;&#x003b3;<sub>T599A</sub>), produced more measurable
 but still significantly attenuated Na<sup>+</sup> conductances when compared
 with wt-ENaC (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig.
 3<italic>E</italic></xref>). Moreover, the remaining amiloride-sensitive
 Na<sup>+</sup> conductances formed by dimeric &#x003b1;&#x003b2;-ENaC and
 &#x003b1;&#x003b3;-ENaC channels were further reduced by &#x003b2;<sub>S631A</sub>
 and &#x003b3;<sub>T599A</sub>, respectively
 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3<italic>F</italic></xref>). Finally,
 coexpression of hCK2 together with wt-ENaC increased <italic>G</italic><sub>amil</sub>
 (65.9 &#x000b1; 9.0 &#x003bc;S; <italic>n</italic> = 7), when compared with injection of
 wt-ENaC alone (47.2 &#x000b1; 8.1 &#x003bc;S; <italic>n</italic> = 7). Co-expression of hCK2
 did not augment <italic>G</italic><sub>amil</sub> of
 &#x003b1;&#x003b2;<sub>S631A</sub>&#x003b3;<sub>T599A</sub>-ENaC (3.3 &#x000b1; 0.7
 &#x003bc;S; <italic>n</italic> = 11 <italic>versus</italic> 3.4 &#x000b1; 0.5 &#x003bc;S; <italic>n</italic> =
 11). Taken together, these results demonstrate that phosphorylation of
 &#x003b2;<sub>S631</sub> and &#x003b3;<sub>T599</sub> is essential for ENaC.</p><p><italic>CK2 Controls ENaC Activity and Membrane Expression of</italic>
 &#x003b1;<italic>-ENaC</italic>&#x02014;To examine whether CK2 phosphorylation controls
 membrane expression of ENaC, FLAG-tagged &#x003b1;-ENaC was co-expressed with
 non-flagged &#x003b2;&#x003b3;-ENaC in <italic>Xenopus</italic> oocytes. The appearance of
 &#x003b1;<sub>Flag</sub>-ENaC in the cell membrane was monitored by
 chemiluminescence, during an observation period of 40-48 h
 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4, <italic>B, D</italic>, and
 <italic>F</italic></xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig.
 5<italic>A</italic></xref>, see &#x0201c;Materials and Methods&#x0201d;). Control
 injection with non-flagged ENaC did not produce a chemiluminescence different
 from background (data not shown). In parallel, amiloride-sensitive
 Na<sup>+</sup> conductance was assessed at corresponding intervals
 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4, <italic>A, C</italic>, and
 <italic>E</italic></xref>). When &#x003b1;<sub>Flag</sub>&#x003b2;&#x003b3;-ENaC was
 expressed in control oocytes, both <italic>G</italic><sub>amil</sub> and membrane
 expression continuously increased (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4,
 <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic></xref>). In contrast, when oocytes were kept in
 10 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc> TBB-containing buffer, amiloride-sensitive Na<sup>+</sup>
 conductance was completely abolished, and membrane expression was
 significantly reduced, albeit not completely. Moreover, co-injection of
 &#x003b1;&#x003b2;&#x003b3;-ENaC-cRNAs together with the CK2 inhibitors heparin
 (final concentration 10 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>) or the peptide inhibitor poly(E:Y)
 (final concentration 50 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>) also inhibited Na<sup>+</sup>
 conductance along with membrane expression of &#x003b1;-ENaC
 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4, <italic>C-F</italic></xref>).
 Finally, M1 cells were grown on permeable supports, in the absence or presence
 of 10 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc> TBB. As observed in oocytes, TBB reduced
 amiloride-sensitive transport from 2.05 &#x000b1; 0.35 &#x003bc;A/cm<sup>2</sup>
 (<italic>n</italic> = 19) to 1.52 &#x000b1; 0.25 &#x003bc;A/cm<sup>2</sup> (<italic>n</italic> =
 16). Thus, CK2 phosphorylation differentially controls membrane expression of
 &#x003b1;-ENaC and ENaC activity. Of note, the inhibitory effect on conductance
 (3-5-fold) was significantly greater than on membrane expression (typically
 2-fold).</p><p><fig position="float" id="fig5"><label>FIGURE 5.</label><caption><p><bold>CK2 is essential for ENaC activity and antagonizes the inhibitory effect
 of Nedd4-2 on ENaC.</bold> <italic>A</italic>, summary of &#x003b1;-ENaC membrane
 expression and <italic>G</italic><sub>amil</sub> after 40 h. TBB inhibited membrane
 expression of &#x003b1;-ENaC via single mutants
 (&#x003b1;&#x003b2;<sub>S631A</sub>&#x003b3;,&#x003b1;&#x003b2;&#x003b3;<sub>T559A</sub>)
 but not that of the double mutant
 (&#x003b1;&#x003b2;<sub>S631A</sub>&#x003b3;<sub>T559A</sub>).
 <italic>G</italic><sub>amil</sub> was largely reduced for all mutants, and
 <italic>G</italic><sub>amil</sub> produced by the double mutant was no longer
 inhibited by TBB. <italic>Dashed lines</italic> indicate membrane expression and
 <italic>G</italic><sub>amil</sub> of wt-ENaC. <italic>B</italic>, whole cell conductances
 relative to wt-ENaC. A mutation in the PY motif (Y618A) of &#x003b2;-ENaC
 increased Na<sup>+</sup> conductance, and S631A no longer inhibited ENaC
 conductance. The Grk2 mutant S633A inhibited ENaC, but not as a double mutant
 S631A/S633A. <italic>C</italic>, inhibition of xNedd4-2 expression by siRNA-xNedd4-2
 but not scrambled siRNA. The abundant poly(A)-binding protein indicates equal
 loading. Summary of ENaC whole cell conductances measured in the absence or
 presence of siRNA-xNedd4-2 or scrambled siRNA (see &#x0201c;Materials and
 Methods&#x0201d;). <italic>D</italic>, summary of the amiloride-sensitive short-circuit
 current and effects of TBB (10 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>) in control M1 cells and M1
 cell treated with scrambled RNAi, mNedd4-2-RNAi, and mCK2-RNAi (see
 &#x0201c;Materials and Methods&#x0201d;). The <italic>asterisk</italic> (<sup>*</sup>)
 indicates significant effects of TBB (paired <italic>t</italic>-tests). The <italic>number
 sign</italic> (#) indicates a significant difference compared with control
 (unpaired <italic>t</italic>-test, 6-24 experiments for each series).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zbc0200835040005"/></fig></p><p><italic>CK2 Is Essential for ENaC Activity, but Has a Small Effect on Membrane
 Expression of</italic> &#x003b1;<italic>-ENaC</italic>&#x02014;The contribution of both CK2
 phosphorylation sites in &#x003b2;-ENaC and &#x003b3;-ENaC, to membrane expression
 of &#x003b1;-ENaC was further examined by expressing single mutants
 (&#x003b1;<sub>Flag</sub>&#x003b2;<sub>S631A</sub>&#x003b3;-ENaC or
 &#x003b1;<sub>Flag</sub>&#x003b2;&#x003b3;<sub>T599A</sub>-ENaC) or the double mutant
 (&#x003b1;<sub>Flag</sub>&#x003b2;<sub>S631A</sub>&#x003b3;<sub>T599A</sub>-ENaC) in
 oocytes. For the sake of simplicity, we only show a summary of the data
 obtained for membrane expression and ENaC conductance after 40 h of expression
 of those ENaC variants (relative to wild type). Importantly, single mutations
 in &#x003b2;-ENaC or &#x003b3;-ENaC largely reduced the Na<sup>+</sup> conductance
 but had only a small effect on membrane expression. Elimination of both CK2
 sites in &#x003b2;-ENaC and &#x003b3;-ENaC also strongly reduced
 <italic>G</italic><sub>amil</sub>, with a minor effect on membrane expression
 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5<italic>A</italic></xref>). Of note,
 TBB reduced &#x003b1;-ENaC expression only when one CK2 site was intact.</p><p>The nearby located Grk2 phosphorylation site Ser-633 was reported to
 control Nedd4-2 binding to ENaC
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref>). We explored whether the
 same might hold true for CK2 phosphorylation sites. To this end, we compared
 whole cell conductances of several ENaC mutants to that of wt-ENaC. A mutation
 in the Nedd4-2 binding site (&#x003b2;<sub>Y618A</sub>) increased ENaC whole cell
 conductance relative to the wild type and eliminated the inhibitory effect of
 S631A on ENaC conductance (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig.
 5<italic>B</italic></xref>). This strongly suggests that CK2 phosphorylation at
 Ser-631 antagonizes the inhibitory action of Nedd4-2 in ENaC
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">20</xref>)
 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8</xref>). Similarly, when we
 expressed the truncated &#x003b1;&#x003b2;<sub>R561X</sub>&#x003b3;-ENaC channel, we
 found that amiloride-sensitive whole cell conductance was largely increased
 (64.5 &#x000b1; 5.9 &#x003bc;S; <italic>n</italic> = 14) when compared with
 &#x003b1;&#x003b2;&#x003b3;-ENaC, and was now unaffected by 10 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc> TBB
 (64.1 &#x000b1; 6.1 &#x003bc;S). Interestingly, mutating the Grk2 site also reduced
 ENaC conductance; however, eliminating both CK2 and Grk2 sites in &#x003b2;-ENaC
 produced a channel with similar activity to that of wt-ENaC
 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5<italic>B</italic></xref>). This
 suggests that the closely located phosphorylation sites of CK2 and Grk2
 (Ser-631, Ser-633) influence each other.</p><p>The role of Nedd4-2 on CK2 regulation of ENaC was further examined by
 siRNA-knockdown of xNedd4-2, similar to a recent study
 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5<italic>C</italic></xref>)
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref>). Two remarkable results
 were obtained, namely: (i) wt-ENaC was no longer inhibited by TBB. (ii)
 &#x003b1;&#x003b2;<sub>S631A</sub>&#x003b3;-rENaC, which normally produced only small
 amiloride-sensitive Na<sup>+</sup> conductance, generated a whole cell
 conductance that was indistinguishable to that obtained for wt
 &#x003b1;&#x003b2;&#x003b3;-rENaC (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig.
 5<italic>C</italic></xref>). These effects were not observed when scrambled RNAi
 was injected. The contribution of Nedd4-2 to CK2 regulation of ENaC was
 further examined in mammalian cells. M1 cells were grown on permeable supports
 after treatment with RNAi for mCK2, mNedd4-2, or scrambled RNAi, or as
 nontransfected control cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig.
 5<italic>D</italic></xref>). Knockdown of CK2 and Nedd4-2 was verified by Western
 blotting (supplemental Fig. S1). I<sub>sc-amil</sub> was enhanced in M1 cells
 following Nedd4-2 knockdown, and inhibition by TBB was largely reduced
 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5<italic>D</italic></xref>). In
 contrast, CK2 knockdown reduced I<sub>sc-amil</sub> and also abolished the
 effect of TBB on I<sub>sc-amil</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig.
 5<italic>D</italic></xref>). Taken together, these results suggest that CK2
 phosphorylation of ENaC antagonizes the inhibitory effects of Nedd4-2.</p><p><fig position="float" id="fig6"><label>FIGURE 6.</label><caption><p><bold>CK2 is not essential for membrane expression of</bold> &#x003b2;<bold>-ENaC
 and</bold> &#x003b3;<bold>-ENaC.</bold> <italic>A</italic>, inhibition of membrane expression of
 &#x003b2;<sub>Flag</sub>-ENaC and &#x003b3;<sub>Flag</sub>-ENaC and
 <italic>G</italic><sub>amil</sub> by 10 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc> TBB. <italic>B</italic> and
 <italic>C</italic>, TBB inhibited membrane expression of &#x003b2;<sub>Flag</sub>-ENaC
 and &#x003b3;<sub>Flag</sub>-ENaC in single mutants
 (&#x003b1;&#x003b2;<sub>S631A</sub>&#x003b3;, &#x003b1;&#x003b2;&#x003b3;<sub>T559A</sub>),
 but not in double mutants
 (&#x003b1;&#x003b2;<sub>S631A</sub>&#x003b3;<sub>T559A</sub>).
 <italic>G</italic><sub>amil</sub> was largely reduced for all mutants, and
 <italic>G</italic><sub>amil</sub> produced by the double mutants was no longer
 inhibited by TBB. <italic>Dashed lines</italic> indicate membrane expression and
 <italic>G</italic><sub>amil</sub> of wt-ENaC. The <italic>asterisk</italic> (<sup>*</sup>)
 indicates a significant effect of TBB (paired <italic>t</italic>-tests, 6-12
 experiments for each series).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zbc0200835040006"/></fig></p><p><italic>CK2 Controls Membrane Expression of</italic> &#x003b2;<italic>-ENaC and</italic>
 &#x003b3;<italic>-ENaC</italic>&#x02014;The activity of epithelial Na<sup>+</sup> channels
 largely depends on co-expression of both &#x003b2;- and &#x003b3;-subunits.
 Membrane expression of &#x003b2;-ENaC and &#x003b3;-ENaC was monitored by injecting
 &#x003b1;&#x003b2;<sub>Flag</sub>&#x003b3;-ENaC or
 &#x003b1;&#x003b2;&#x003b3;<sub>Flag</sub>-ENaC, respectively, and Na<sup>+</sup>
 conductances were measured in parallel. Na<sup>+</sup> conductances generated
 by either &#x003b1;&#x003b2;<sub>Flag</sub>&#x003b3;-ENaC or
 &#x003b1;&#x003b2;&#x003b3;<sub>Flag</sub>-ENaC, respectively, were almost completely
 abolished when oocytes were exposed to 10 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc> TBB, while membrane
 expression of &#x003b2;<sub>Flag</sub> and &#x003b3;<sub>Flag</sub> were reduced by
 about 50% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6<italic>A</italic></xref>).
 We further examined whether &#x003b2;<sub>Flag</sub> and &#x003b3;<sub>Flag</sub>
 behave in a similar fashion in the absence of &#x003b1;-ENaC. Dimeric channels
 formed by &#x003b2;<sub>Flag</sub>&#x003b3;-ENaC or
 &#x003b2;&#x003b3;<sub>Flag</sub>-ENaC produced small but detectable
 amiloride-sensitive whole cell conductances (0.74 &#x000b1; 0.2 &#x003bc;S;
 <italic>n</italic> = 8 and 0.2 &#x000b1; 0.1 &#x003bc;S; <italic>n</italic> = 7, respectively).
 Interestingly expression of &#x003b2;<sub>Flag</sub>-ENaC and
 &#x003b3;<sub>Flag</sub>-ENaC in dimeric and trimeric channels was similar, but
 expression of both subunits in the dimeric channel was not affected by TBB
 (data not shown). This suggests a complex role of &#x003b1;-ENaC for expression
 of &#x003b2;&#x003b3;-ENaC.</p><p>To further assess the impact of CK2 phosphorylation on membrane expression
 of &#x003b2;-ENaC and &#x003b3;-ENaC in trimeric
 (&#x003b1;&#x003b2;<sub>Flag</sub>&#x003b3;-ENaC and
 &#x003b1;&#x003b2;&#x003b3;<sub>Flag</sub>-ENaC) channels, we expressed single
 mutants (&#x003b1;&#x003b2;<sub>S631A-Flag</sub>&#x003b3;-ENaC or
 &#x003b1;&#x003b2;&#x003b3;<sub>T599A-Flag</sub>-ENaC) and double mutants
 (&#x003b1;&#x003b2;<sub>S631A-Flag</sub>&#x003b3;<sub>T599A</sub>-ENaC or
 &#x003b1;&#x003b2;<sub>S631A</sub>&#x003b3;<sub>T599A-Flag</sub>-ENaC) in the absence
 or presence of 10 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc> TBB. For all mutant combinations,
 Na<sup>+</sup> conductances were largely reduced in comparison to that of
 wt-ENaC, and residual conductances generated by the double mutants were
 insensitive to TBB (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6, <italic>B</italic> and
 <italic>C</italic></xref>). In contrast, the membrane expression of &#x003b2;-ENaC
 and &#x003b3;-ENaC was not affected by any of the mutations individually, and
 membrane expression of the double mutants
 (&#x003b1;&#x003b2;<sub>S631A-Flag</sub>&#x003b3;<sub>T599A</sub>-ENaC;
 &#x003b1;&#x003b2;<sub>S631A</sub>&#x003b3;<sub>T599A-Flag</sub>-ENaC) was no longer
 inhibited by TBB (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6, <italic>B</italic> and
 <italic>C</italic></xref>). These data suggest that when CK2 sites are present in
 &#x003b2;-ENaC and &#x003b3;-ENaC, they need to be phosphorylated to allow proper
 membrane expression of all three subunits.</p><p><italic>ENaC Translocates CK2 to the Cell Membrane</italic>&#x02014;It has been
 reported that CK2 binds directly to ENaC
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">21</xref>). This suggests that CK2
 may be translocated by ENaC to the cell membrane as found for CFTR
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref24">24</xref>). Oocytes expressing ENaC
 and non-injected control oocytes were immunolabeled, after embedding and
 cutting into 20-&#x003bc;m sections. Using an anti-FLAG antibody, &#x003b1;-ENaC
 could be visualized in membranes of <italic>Xenopus</italic> oocytes expressing
 &#x003b1;<sub>Flag</sub>&#x003b2;&#x003b3;-ENaC
 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7<italic>A</italic></xref>). Moreover,
 upon expression of &#x003b1;&#x003b2;<sub>Flag</sub>&#x003b3;-ENaC or
 &#x003b1;&#x003b2;&#x003b3;<sub>Flag</sub>-ENaC, &#x003b2;- and &#x003b3;-subunits could
 be immunolabeled in the oocyte membrane
 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7<italic>B</italic></xref>, <italic>left
 panels</italic>). Expression of the three subunits was similar in
 &#x003b1;&#x003b2;<sub>S631A</sub>&#x003b3;<sub>T559A</sub>-ENaC-injected oocytes
 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7<italic>B</italic></xref>, <italic>right
 panels</italic>). However, while CK2 was detected in membranes of oocytes
 expressing wt-ENaC, no membrane staining of CK2 was detectable in
 &#x003b1;&#x003b2;<sub>S631A</sub>&#x003b3;<sub>T559A</sub>-ENaC-injected oocytes
 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7<italic>B</italic></xref>, <italic>lower
 panels</italic>). These results suggest that CK2 may be translocated to oocyte
 membranes by binding to ENaC &#x003b2;- and &#x003b3;-subunits.</p></sec><sec><title>DISCUSSION</title><p><italic>CK2 Regulates Ion Channels</italic>&#x02014;CK2 is an essential,
 constitutively regulated multifunctional protein kinase whose functions are
 not fully understood (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">21</xref>). CK2
 is believed to insert into protein complexes bringing its constitutive
 activity to many signaling complexes (p53, ion channels, actin capping at
 membranes, lipid flippases, etc). Notably, CK2 controls trafficking and
 sorting of trans-Golgi proteins. CK2 affects a number of membrane channels and
 pumps, among them is polycystin-2 (PC2), a divalent cation-selective channel.
 CK2 was shown to maintain the Ca<sup>2+</sup> sensitivity of PC2. Elimination
 of a CK2 site in PC2 reduced its Ca<sup>2+</sup> sensitivity, without changing
 membrane expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref>). Others
 reported the importance of phosphorylation of PC2 by CK2, for proper ciliary
 localization of the channel
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref>). CK2 also phosphorylates
 three critical serine residues within nephrocystin, another ciliary protein.
 CK2 phosphorylation is essential for co-localization of nephrocystin with the
 sorting protein PACS-1 at the base of cilia. Inhibition of CK2 was shown to
 eliminate interaction of PACS-1 and nephrocystin and to induce defective
 nephrocystin targeting (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19">19</xref>).
 CK2 may thus be relevant to the common autosomal form of polycystic kidney
 disease.</p><p><fig position="float" id="fig7"><label>FIGURE 7.</label><caption><p><bold>wt-ENaC translocates CK2 to the cell membrane.</bold> <italic>A</italic>, DIC image
 of the oocyte membrane (<italic>left panels</italic>) and immunostaining of
 &#x003b1;<sub>Flag</sub>-ENaC in an ENaC-expressing (<italic>right upper panel</italic>)
 and a non-injected (<italic>right lower panel</italic>) oocyte. <italic>B</italic>,
 immunostaining of the three ENaC subunits (<italic>green</italic>) and CK2
 (<italic>red</italic>) in wt-ENaC (<italic>left panel</italic>) and
 &#x003b1;&#x003b2;<sub>S631A</sub>&#x003b3;<sub>T559A</sub>-ENaC (<italic>right
 panel</italic>)-expressing oocytes. <italic>Bars</italic> indicate 10 &#x003bc;m. Experiments
 were performed in at least triplicates.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zbc0200835040007"/></fig></p><p>We found here that ENaC is regulated by CK2 in a related manner,
 <italic>i.e.</italic> CK2 regulates ENaC activity as well as membrane expression. Lack
 of CK2 phosphorylation appears to reduce Nedd4-2 binding to ENaC, thereby
 enhancing channel activity and membrane expression. Notably, phosphorylation
 of ENaC by ERK inhibits both channel activity and membrane expression, and
 both effects are mediated by Nedd4-2 binding to ENaC
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>).</p><p>CK2 has also been described to influence other ion channels, namely by
 regulating the current amplitude of voltage-dependent Ca<sup>2+</sup> channels
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref>), as well as the
 Ca<sup>2+</sup>-dependent gating of small conductance
 Ca<sup>2+</sup>-activated K<sup>+</sup> channels
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref>). SK channels are organized
 in multiprotein complexes together with CK2 and PP2A, located in the
 postsynaptic pole of cochlear outer hair cells
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref>). Furthermore, CK2 has
 recently been found to regulate CFTR, the chloride channel that is defective
 in cystic fibrosis and, as in this study, CK2 becomes membrane-associated with
 CFTR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref24">24</xref>). Once again both CK2
 and PP2A co-localize with different domains of CFTR
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref24">24</xref>). Importantly, CK2 binding
 may be disease relevant because phenylalanine 508 (F508), the common missing
 residue in most patients with CF, is critical in promoting the interaction
 with CFTR. In both CFTR-expressing <italic>Xenopus</italic> oocytes and cell-attached
 mammalian cells, inhibition of CK2 induced prompt closure of CFTR in less than
 80 s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref24">24</xref>). However, direct
 phosphorylation of CFTR by CK2 at Ser-511 close to F508 has not been confirmed
 by radiolabeling cells and direct phosphopeptide mapping, and the exact
 mechanism remains unknown. Moreover, CFTR expression determines the cellular
 localization of CK2, which in turn could affect other membrane conductances
 such as amiloride-sensitive Na<sup>+</sup> absorption. It is interesting to
 note that the effect of CK2 is not stimulatory of the function of all proteins
 studied to date. Indeed, CK2 is inhibitory of another ABC family member,
 ABCA1; thus, constitutively suppressing the lipid flippase activity of this
 CFTR-related protein.</p><p><italic>C Terminus of</italic> &#x003b2;<italic>-ENaC, a Target for Kinase Regulation of
 ENaC</italic>&#x02014;Phosphorylation-dependent regulation of ENaC by CK2 is
 demonstrated in the present study by several agents, namely, heparin, a
 nonspecific inhibitor of CK2 directed against acidic motifs; the peptide
 inhibitor of CK2; poly(E:Y); and the specific CK2 inhibitors TBB and DMAT.
 Inhibition of protein phosphatases with okadaic acid further increased
 Na<sup>+</sup> conductance, indicating the importance of basal CK2-dependent
 phosphorylation for ENaC regulation
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>). Furthermore, elimination
 of CK2 phosphorylation sites (Ser-6331) abrogated Na<sup>+</sup> conductance
 in <italic>Xenopus</italic> oocytes. Thus, together with results obtained in native
 epithelia and in epithelial cells, these data show that ENaC is compellingly
 regulated by CK2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8</xref>).
 Notably, CK1 was shown recently to control intracellular trafficking of ENaC
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref25">25</xref>). Yet, in a previous
 report such regulation could not be detected in salivary duct cells
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref>). Instead, activation of
 ENaC by the G protein-coupled receptor kinase 2 Grk2 was found. Because of
 phosphorylation of Ser-633 by Grk2 in the C terminus of &#x003b2;-ENaC, the
 affinity of Nedd4-2 binding to ENaC is apparently reduced, thus enhancing ENaC
 currents. According to the present data
 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5<italic>B</italic></xref>), a similar
 scenario may hold true for CK2-dependent regulation of ENaC, because both
 phosphorylation sites for Grk2 and CK2 are located in close proximity to one
 other. Because CK2 classically engages in hierarchical phosphorylation with
 other kinases, phosphorylation through either Grk2 or CK2 could control EnaC
 activity and membrane expression depending on the cell type and expression
 levels of the kinases involved. Moreover, phosphorylation by CK2 is likely to
 affect regulation by Grk2 and <italic>vice versa</italic>
 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5<italic>B</italic></xref>). Further
 experiments will be needed to unravel this complex regulatory network and
 should focus on the inhibitory phosphorylation by Erk and its counteraction by
 activation through PKA, Grk2, and CK2, with Nedd4-2 as the central control
 switch (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">20</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref26">26</xref>). As suggested in a
 previous report and supported by the present data, acute and chronic
 regulation may be different, inasmuch as acute regulation is changing the open
 probability of the channel, while chronic regulation by Nedd4-2 controls
 membrane expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>).</p><p><fig position="float" id="fig8"><label>FIGURE 8.</label><caption><p><bold>Model for CK2 action on ENaC.</bold> Binding of the ubiquitin ligase
 Nedd4-2 leads to ubiquitination of ENaC and subsequent degradation of the
 channel and/or channel inactivation. Phosphorylation of ENaC at Ser-631
 reduces affinity of ENaC for Nedd4-2, thereby maintaining membrane
 localization and ENaC activity.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zbc0200835040008"/></fig></p></sec>
      <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
         <title>Supplementary Material</title>
         <supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
            <caption>
               <title>[Supplemental Data]</title>
            </caption>
            <media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="M704532200_index.html"/>
            <media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"
                   xlink:href="M704532200_1.pdf"/>
         </supplementary-material>
      </sec>
   </body><back><ack><p>We thank E. Tartler and A. Paech for expert technical assistance. TBB and
 DMAT were generous gifts from Prof. Dr. L. Pinna (Dept. of Biological
 Chemistry, University of Padova, Italy).</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Awayda, M. S., Ismailov, I. I., Berdiev, B. K., Fuller, C. M., and
 Benos, D. J. (<year>1996</year>) <source>J. Gen. Physiol.</source>
 <volume>108</volume> <fpage>49</fpage>-65<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8817384</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Bachhuber, T., K&#x000f6;nig, J., Voelcker, T., M&#x000fc;rle, B.,
 Schreiber, R., and Kunzelmann, K. (<year>2005</year>) <source>J. Biol.
 Chem.</source> <volume>280</volume>
 <fpage>31587</fpage>-31594<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16027156</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Becchetti, A., Malik, B., Yue, G., Duchatelle, P., Al Khalili, O.,
 Kleyman, T. R., and Eaton, D. C. (<year>2002</year>) <source>Am. J.
 Physiol. Renal Physiol.</source> <volume>283</volume>
 <fpage>F1030</fpage>-F1045<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12372779</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Bildl, W., Strassmaier, T., Thurm, H., Andersen, J., Eble, S.,
 Oliver, D., Knipper, M., Mann, M., Schulte, U., Adelman, J. P., and Fakler, B.
 (<year>2004</year>) <source>Neuron</source>
 <volume>43</volume> <fpage>847</fpage>-858<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15363395</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Cai, Y., Anyatonwu, G., Okuhara, D., Lee, K. B., Yu, Z., Onoe, T.,
 Mei, C. L., Qian, Q., Geng, L., Wiztgall, R., Ehrlich, B. E., and Somlo, S.
 (<year>2004</year>) <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
 <volume>279</volume>
 <fpage>19987</fpage>-19995<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14742446</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Canessa, C. M., Schild, L., Buell, G., Thorens, B., Gautschl, I.,
 Horisberger, J. D., and Rossier, B. C. (<year>1994</year>)
 <source>Nature</source> <volume>367</volume>
 <fpage>463</fpage>-467<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8107805</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Debonneville, C., Flores, S. Y., Kamynina, E., Plant, P. J., Tauxe,
 C., Thomas, M. A., Munster, C., Chraibi, A., Pratt, J. H., Horisberger, J. D.,
 Pearce, D., Loffing, J., and Staub, O. (<year>2001</year>) <source>EMBO
 J.</source> <volume>20</volume>
 <fpage>7052</fpage>-7059<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11742982</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Diakov, A., and Korbmacher, C. (<year>2004</year>). <source>J.
 Biol. Chem.</source> <volume>279</volume>
 <fpage>38134</fpage>-38142<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15234985</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Dinudom, A., Fotia, A. B., Lefkowitz, R. J., Young, J. A., Kumar,
 S., and Cook, D. I. (<year>2004</year>) <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.
 S. A.</source> <volume>101</volume>
 <fpage>11886</fpage>-11890<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15284439</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Falin, R. A., and Cotton, C. U. (<year>2007</year>) <source>J.
 Gen. Physiol.</source> <volume>130</volume>
 <fpage>313</fpage>-328<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17724164</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Feldman, R. D. (<year>2002</year>) <source>Mol.
 Pharmacol.</source> <volume>61</volume>
 <fpage>707</fpage>-709<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11901207</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Firsov, D., Schild, L., Gautschi, I., Merillat, A. M.,
 Schneeberger, E., and Rossier, B. C. (<year>1996</year>) <source>Proc.
 Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.</source> <volume>93</volume>
 <fpage>15370</fpage>-15375<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8986818</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Hu, J., Bae, Y. K., Knobel, K. M., and Barr, M. M.
 (<year>2006</year>) <source>Mol. Biol. Cell</source>
 <volume>17</volume>
 <fpage>2200</fpage>-2211<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16481400</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Kimura, T., and Kubo, T. (<year>2003</year>) <source>Neurosci.
 Res.</source> <volume>46</volume>
 <fpage>105</fpage>-117<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12725917</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Kunzelmann, K., Schreiber, R., Nitschke, R., and Mall, M.
 (<year>2000</year>) <source>Pfl&#x000fc;gers Arch.</source>
 <volume>440</volume>
 <fpage>193</fpage>-201</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Meggio, F., Boldyreff, B., Issinger, O. G., and Pinna, L. A.
 (<year>1994</year>) <source>Biochemistry</source>
 <volume>33</volume>
 <fpage>4336</fpage>-4342<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8155651</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Michlig, S., Harris, M., Loffing, J., Rossier, B. C., and Firsov,
 D. (<year>2005</year>) <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
 <volume>280</volume>
 <fpage>38264</fpage>-38270<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16172119</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Rajamanickam, J., Palmada, M., Lang, F., and Boehmer, C.
 (<year>2007</year>) <source>J. Neurochem.</source>
 <volume>102</volume>
 <fpage>858</fpage>-866<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17442044</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Schermer, B., Hopker, K., Omran, H., Ghenoiu, C., Fliegauf, M.,
 Fekete, A., Horvath, J., Kottgen, M., Hackl, M., Zschiedrich, S., Huber, T.
 B., Kramer-Zucker, A., Zentgraf, H., Blaukat, A., Walz, G., and Benzing, T.
 (<year>2005</year>) <source>EMBO J.</source>
 <volume>24</volume>
 <fpage>4415</fpage>-4424<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16308564</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Shi, H., Asher, C., Chigaev, A., Yung, Y., Reuveny, E., Seger, R.,
 and Garty, H. (<year>2002</year>) <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
 <volume>277</volume>
 <fpage>13539</fpage>-13547<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11805112</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Shi, H., Asher, C., Yung, Y., Kligman, L., Reuveny, E., Seger, R.,
 and Garty, H. (<year>2002</year>) <source>Eur. J. Biochem.</source>
 <volume>269</volume>
 <fpage>4551</fpage>-4558<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12230567</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Snyder, P. M., Olson, D. R., Kabra, R., Zhou, R., and Steines, J.
 C. (<year>2004</year>) <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
 <volume>279</volume>
 <fpage>45753</fpage>-45758<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15328345</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Snyder, P. M., Olson, D. R., and Thomas, B. C. (<year>2002</year>)
 <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source> <volume>277</volume>
 <fpage>5</fpage>-8<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11696533</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Treharne, K. J., Crawford, R. M., Best, O. G., Schulte, E. A.,
 Chen, J.-H., Gruenert, D. C., Wilson, S. M., Kunzelmann, K., Sheppard, D. N.,
 and Mehta, A. (<year>2007</year>) <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
 <volume>282</volume>
 <fpage>10804</fpage>-10813<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17289674</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Yan, W., Spruce, L., Rosenblatt, M. M., Kleyman, T. R., and
 Rubenstein, R. C. (<year>2007</year>) <source>Am. J. Physiol. Renal
 Physiol.</source> <volume>293</volume>
 <fpage>F868</fpage>-F876<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17596527</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Yang, L. M., Rinke, R., and Korbmacher, C. (<year>2006</year>)
 <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source> <volume>281</volume>
 <fpage>9859</fpage>-9868<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16476738</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list><fn-group><fn id="fn5"><label>4</label><p>The abbreviations used are: ENaC, epithelial Na<sup>+</sup> channel; ERK,
 extracellular signal-regulated kinase; CK, casein kinase; BSA, bovine serum
 albumin; PBS, phosphate-buffered saline; wt, wild type; TBB,
 4,5,6,7-tetrabromobenzotriazole; DMAT,
 2-dimethylamino-4,5,6,7-tetrabromo-1<italic>H</italic>-benzimidazole; Grk2, G
 protein-coupled receptor kinase 2; siRNA, small interfering RNA.</p></fn><fn id="fn6"><label>5</label><p>L. A. Pinna, personal communication.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>