<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Cell Biol</journal-id><journal-title>The Journal of Cell Biology</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0021-9525</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1540-8140</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Rockefeller University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">5459003</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2108060</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>THE NATURE AND PROCESSING OF RIBOSOMAL RIBONUCLEIC ACID IN A DINOFLAGELLATE</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rae</surname><given-names>Peter M. M.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="N0x3802550N0x3784540">From the Whitman Laboratory, Department of Biology, The University of Chicago, Chicago, Illinois 60637</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>1</day><month>7</month><year>1970</year></pub-date><volume>46</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>106</fpage><lpage>113</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>12</month><year>1969</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>12</day><month>1</month><year>1970</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 1970 by The Rockefeller University Press</copyright-statement></permissions><abstract><p> Certain features of the dinoflagellate nucleus suggest that it represents a primitive form of eukaryotic nucleus. For this reason, it was of interest to characterize dinoflagellate ribosomal RNA (rRNA) and its mode of synthesis to determine if it also deviated from typical eukaryotic patterns. <italic>Gyrodinium cohnii</italic> was chosen for this examination. <italic>Gyrodinium</italic> ribosomal RNA species are 16 and 25s as judged by their sedimentation velocities in isokinetic sucrose gradients. These values are typical of higher plants. In addition, the RNA cosedimented precisely with rRNA from the ciliate <italic>Tetrahymena</italic>. Nucleotide ratio analyses revealed a GMP + CMP content of 46% for both species of rRNA. The kinetics of incorporation of a radioactive precursor into ribosomal RNA have also been studied, and it seems likely that the maturation of rRNA starts with the synthesis of a 38s molecule. This serves as precursor to the 16s species, and, after a 27s intermediate, the 25s ribosomal component. The process is similar to that in other eukaryotes. The structure of the nucleolus has also been examined, and is seen to be typically eukaryotic. </p></abstract></article-meta></front></article>


