<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Exp Med</journal-id><journal-title>The Journal of Experimental Medicine</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0022-1007</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1540-9538</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Rockefeller University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">12070282</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2193552</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">020369</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.20020369</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Interleukin 15 Is Required for Proliferative Renewal of Virus-specific Memory CD8 T Cells</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>Todd C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wherry</surname><given-names>E. John</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Boone</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Murali-Krishna</surname><given-names>Kaja</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Antia</surname><given-names>Rustom</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Averil</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>Rafi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Emory Vaccine Center and Department of Microbiology and Immunology, Emory University School of Medicine, Atlanta, GA 30322</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Biology, Emory University School of Medicine, Atlanta, GA 30322</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Department of Medicine, University of Chicago, Chicago, IL 60637</aff><author-notes><fn><p>Address correspondence to R. Ahmed, Emory Vaccine Center, G211 Rollins Research Bldg., 1510 Clinton Rd., Atlanta, GA 30322. Phone: 404-727-4700&#x0003b; Fax: 404-727-3722&#x0003b; E-mail: <email>ra@microbio.emory.edu</email></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>17</day><month>6</month><year>2002</year></pub-date><volume>195</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1541</fpage><lpage>1548</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>6</day><month>3</month><year>2002</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>17</day><month>5</month><year>2002</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2002, The Rockefeller University Press</copyright-statement></permissions><abstract><p>The generation and efficient maintenance of antigen-specific memory T cells is essential for long-lasting immunological protection. In this study, we examined the role of interleukin (IL)-15 in the generation and maintenance of virus-specific memory CD8 T cells using mice deficient in either IL-15 or the IL-15 receptor &#x003b1; chain. Both cytokine- and receptor-deficient mice made potent primary CD8 T cell responses to infection with lymphocytic choriomeningitis virus (LCMV), effectively cleared the virus and generated a pool of antigen-specific memory CD8 T cells that were phenotypically and functionally similar to memory CD8 T cells present in IL-15<sup>+/+</sup> mice. However, longitudinal analysis revealed a slow attrition of virus-specific memory CD8 T cells in the absence of IL-15 signals.This loss of CD8 T cells was due to a severe defect in the proliferative renewal of antigen-specific memory CD8 T cells in IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice. Taken together, these results show that IL-15 is not essential for the generation of memory CD8 T cells, but is required for homeostatic proliferation to maintain populations of memory cells over long periods of time.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>CD8 T cell</kwd><kwd>immunological memory</kwd><kwd>IL-15</kwd><kwd>homeostasis</kwd><kwd>viral immunity</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta><notes><fn-group><fn><p>T.C. Becker, E.J. Wherry, D. Boone, and K. Murali-Krishna contributed equally to this paper.</p></fn><fn><p>K. Murali-Krishna's current address is Dept. of Immunology, University of Washington, Seattle, WA 98195.</p></fn></fn-group></notes></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Long-term CD8 T cell memory, as determined by faster recall responses in vivo, is a characteristic feature of most acute viral infections (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">1</xref>). These rapid anamnestic responses to reinfection are the result of both qualitative and quantitative changes in virus-specific T cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">2</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">6</xref>). During primary infection there is extensive expansion of antigen-specific CD8 T cells and, even though the vast majority of these activated effector CD8 T cells undergo apoptosis, the end result is a net increase in the numbers of virus-specific T cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">7</xref>). For example, after infection of mice with lymphocytic choriomeningitis virus (LCMV)<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">*</xref>there is up to a 1,000-fold increase in the precursor frequency of virus-specific CD8 T cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">8</xref>). Substantial increases (200&#x02013;500-fold) in the numbers of antigen-specific CD8 T cells are also seen after clearance of acute vaccinia virus or vesicular stomatitis virus infections (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">10</xref>). This numerical advantage alone can account for the faster recall response, but several recent studies have shown that upon reexposure to antigen, memory T cells can also elaborate effector functions such as cytotoxicity and cytokine production much more quickly than naive T cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">2</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">6</xref>). Thus, it is this combination of increased numbers and faster responsiveness that forms the cellular basis of long-term T cell immunity.</p><p>A central question of immunological memory is understanding how memory T cells are maintained. The availability of TCR transgenic T cells, the development of sensitive techniques for assessing T cell function at the single cell level, and perhaps most importantly, the ability to physically identify antigen-specific CD8 T cells using MHC class I tetramers, has greatly facilitated studies addressing the important question of memory T cell maintenance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">11</xref>). Several studies using a variety of antigenic systems have now clearly established that memory CD8 T cells can persist in the absence of specific antigen (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">12</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">24</xref>). It has also been shown that memory CD8 T cells undergo homeostatic proliferation to replenish their numbers and that this proliferative renewal does not require stimulation with specific antigen (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">15</xref>), or even MHC class I (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">24</xref>). It also appears that costimulatory signals including B7-CD28 are not essential for maintaining memory CD8 T cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">26</xref>). Recently, attention has turned toward the possible role of cytokines in this process and in particular to the role of IL-15 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">27</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">29</xref>). Knockout mice lacking IL-15 or the high affinity IL-15R&#x003b1; contain reduced numbers of memory phenotype CD8 CD44<sup>hi</sup> T cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">29</xref>). Also, exogenous IL-15 or IL-15&#x02013;inducing agents selectively stimulate the division of CD44<sup>hi</sup> CD8 T cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">30</xref>) and IL-15 overexpressing transgenic animals contain increased numbers of memory phenotype CD8 T cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">31</xref>). Despite these elegant studies implicating IL-15 in the development of memory CD8 T cells, several important questions remain unanswered. First, it is not precisely known whether IL-15 is needed for the generation of memory CD8 T cells or for their maintenance. Second, and perhaps more importantly, all studies done so far using the cytokine (IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup>) or the receptor (IL-15R&#x003b1;<sup>2/&#x02212;</sup>) knockout mice have been confined to the analysis of memory phenotype CD44<sup>hi</sup> CD8 T cells whose antigenic specificity is not known, and so far no studies have examined the generation and maintenance of antigen-specific CD8 T cells. While the study of memory phenotype CD44<sup>hi</sup> CD8 T cells is certainly of value, the antigenic stimuli and signals that result in their generation are not known. It is also not clear whether these CD44<sup>hi</sup> CD8 T cells present in &#x0201c;clean&#x0201d; (specific pathogen-free) mice truly represent the functional characteristics of antigen-specific memory CD8 T cells induced after infection or vaccination.</p><p>In this study, we have investigated the role of IL-15 in the generation and maintenance of virus-specific CD8 T cells. Our results show that after infection with LCMV mice deficient in either IL-15 or IL-15R&#x003b1; mount robust primary CD8 T cell responses, clear the virus, and generate a pool of virus-specific memory CD8 T cells. These memory CD8 T cells appear phenotypically and functionally normal and can make potent recall responses in vivo upon viral rechallenge. However, homeostatic proliferation of LCMV-specific memory CD8 T cells is almost completely lost in IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice and memory CD8 T cell numbers undergo a slow attrition in the absence of IL-15. Thus, IL-15 is not required to generate a virus-specific CD8 T cell response or to develop a pool of antigen-specific memory CD8 T cells, but IL-15 signals appear crucial for homeostatic proliferation and long-term maintenance of memory CD8 T cells.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Mice.</title><p>4&#x02013;6-wk-old female C57Bl/6 were purchased from The National Cancer Institute (Frederick, MD). The generation and description of IL-15R&#x003b1;<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> and IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> have been described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">29</xref>). IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice were obtained from Michael Caligiuri (Ohio State University, Columbus, OH). Both IL-15&#x003b1;<sup>2/&#x02212;</sup> and IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice and littermate controls were backcrossed to B6 mice for &#x0003e;10 generations.</p></sec><sec><title>Viral Infections.</title><p>Stocks of the Armstrong strain of LCMV were plaque purified on Vero cells and grown in BHK-21 cells as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">32</xref>). Mice were infected by intraperitoneal injection with 2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> PFU of LCMV. For rechallenge experiments, mice were infected intravenously with 2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup> PFU of LCMV clone 13, a strain that causes chronic infection in naive adult mice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">32</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Antibodies and MHC Class I Tetramers.</title><p>All antibodies were purchased from BD PharMingen. MHC class I/peptide tetramers were prepared and used as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">7</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Cell Preparation and Staining.</title><p>Mice were bled retroorbitally into 4% sodium citrate under isofluorane anesthesia. PBMCs were purified on a histopaque density gradient (Sigma-Aldrich). Single cell suspensions were prepared from spleens and red blood cells were lysed using 0.83% ammonium chloride. Cells were washed and stained for four-color flow cytometry on a FACSCalibur&#x02122; Flow Cytometer (Becton Dickinson).</p></sec><sec><title>Isolation of Hepatic Lymphocytes.</title><p>Mice were killed and the liver was perfused with 5 ml ice cold PBS via the hepatic artery. Liver tissue was homogenized using a wire screen and incubated with 0.25 mg/ml collagenase B (Boehringer Mannheim) and 1 U/ml DNase (Sigma-Aldrich) at 37&#x000b0;C for 45 min. Digested liver was centrifuged and the pellet was resuspended in 5&#x02013;10 ml 44% Percoll (Sigma-Aldrich). This solution was underlaid with 56% Percoll and spun for 20 min at 20&#x000b0;C. The interface was harvested, RBCs were lysed using 0.83% ammonium chloride, washed, and counted. This procedure was found to have little impact on the expression of most cell surface molecules, including TCR (data not shown).</p></sec><sec><title>Intracellular Cytokine Staining.</title><p>Intracellular cytokine staining was performed as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">7</xref>). Briefly, 10<sup>6</sup> splenocytes were incubated in 96-well, flat-bottomed plates in the presence of 1 &#x003bc;l/ml Golgistop (BD PharMingen) with or without 0.1 &#x003bc;g/ml of the indicated peptides. After 5 h at 37&#x000b0;C, cells were washed 1&#x000d7; in FACS<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> buffer (0.5% FCS, 0.2% sodium azide in PBS) and stained for surface markers for 30 min on ice. After two washes in FACS<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> buffer, cells were fixed and permeabilized using the BD PharMingen Cytofix/Cytoperm kit, according to the manufacturer's instructions, and stained for intracellular cytokines. After two washes in perm/wash and two washes in FACS<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> buffer, cells were fixed in 2% PFA and samples acquired as described previously.</p></sec><sec><title>CFSE Labeling and Adoptive Transfer.</title><p>B6 or IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice that had been infected with LCMV 140 d previously were killed. Spleens were removed, RBCs lysed, and single cell suspensions were generated. Splenocytes were labeled with CFSE (Molecular Probes) as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">33</xref>) and 3 &#x000d7; 10<sup>7</sup> labeled splenocytes were transferred by intravenous injection into naive recipients. After 30 d, recipients were killed and splenocytes were prepared and analyzed as described above.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results and Discussion</title><sec><title>IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> and IL-15R&#x003b1;<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> Mice Generate Robust Primary CD8 T Cell Responses to LCMV Infection, but Virus-specific Memory CD8 T Cell Numbers Slowly Decline Over Time.</title><p>Previous reports have demonstrated that mice lacking either IL-15 or IL-15R&#x003b1; have reduced CD8 T cell numbers, particularly those of a CD44<sup>hi</sup> memory phenotype (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">29</xref>). To investigate the induction and maintenance of virus-specific memory CD8 T cells in the absence of IL-15 signals, groups of IL-15R&#x003b1;<sup>2/&#x02212;</sup> and IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice and their respective controls were infected with LCMV, and virus-specific CD8 T cell responses were monitored longitudinally in the PBMCs of individual mice. <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>   A shows staining with MHC class I/peptide tetramers for a dominant (NP396) and a subdominant (GP276) LCMV epitope from representative IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> and IL-15<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> mice. At the peak of the response, day 8, the frequency of tetramer-positive cells was similar between IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> and IL-15<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> mice, whether expressed as a percentage of total PBMCs (in bold) or as a percentage of the total CD8 T cells (in parentheses). This demonstrates that potent virus-specific CD8 T cell responses can be generated in the absence of IL-15. Indeed, functional virus-specific responses were not affected by the absence of IL-15 signals since effector CD8 T cells from IL-15<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> and IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice were equally proficient at eliminating the viral infection and exhibited similar effector responses (data not shown). Also, the persistence of readily detectable numbers of tetramer-positive cells at days 30, 50, and 140 demonstrates that memory CD8 T cells were generated in the absence of IL-15 (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). However, it became evident during longitudinal tracking that LCMV-specific memory T cells were inefficiently maintained in IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> B). This is illustrated by examining the magnitude of the response in IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice as a percentage of the response in IL-15<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> mice. While only slightly reduced (in most cases) or not affected at day 8, the responses in IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice fell to &#x0003c;25&#x02013;50% of that in controls by 140 d after infection for all epitopes that were examined (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> B). This longitudinal analysis examining virus-specific CD8 T cells in the PBMCs of the same animals over time is an excellent way of monitoring memory T cell maintenance. A similar trend was seen in both lymphoid and nonlymphoid tissues as was observed in the longitudinal PBMC analysis&#x0003b; fewer virus-specific memory CD8 T cells were present in both lymphoid and nonlymphoid tissues of IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice compared with IL-15<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> littermates. Data from a representative experiment quantitating the number of LCMV-specific CD8 T cells for four different epitopes in the spleens at day 80 after infection are shown in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> C.</p><fig position="float" id="fig1"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice mount a substantial CD8 T cell response to LCMV infection but memory CD8 T cell numbers gradually decline. (A) Longitudinal PBMC analysis was performed by serially bleeding individual mice on the indicated days after infection with LCMV. PBMCs were stained with MHC tetra-mers of two LCMV epitopes (NP396 and GP276). Plots are gated on CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells, and the numbers represent the number of MHC tetramer binding cells as a percentage of total PBMCs (bold) and as a percentage of CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells (parentheses). Staining is representative of four to seven mice per group. (B) The numbers of epitope-specific cells/10<sup>6</sup> PBMCs in IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice are expressed as a percentage of the number/10<sup>6</sup> PBMC in control mice. Staining was performed as in A. Numbers are averages of four to seven mice. (C) At 80 d after infection, IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> and IL-15<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> littermate control mice were killed and single cell suspensions from spleens were stained with MHC tetramers as above. Absolute numbers of LCMV-specific memory CD8 T cells in the spleen were calculated. LCMV-specific CD4 responses were similar in both IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> and IL-15<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> control mice (data not shown).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="020369f1a"></graphic><graphic xlink:href="020369f1b"></graphic><graphic xlink:href="020369f1c"></graphic></fig><p>In addition to analyzing CD8 T cell responses in the cytokine knockout mice, we also examined the ability of IL-15R&#x003b1;<sup>2/&#x02212;</sup> mice to generate virus-specific CD8 T cell responses. The receptor knockout mice exhibited a phenotype very similar to the cytokine-deficient mice&#x0003b; virus-specific CD8 T cell responses of IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice were comparable to IL-15<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> mice at day 8 but then slowly declined over time. A representative set of data quantitating antigen-specific CD8 T cells in the spleen and liver are shown in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>   A and B. Taken together the results of <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> and <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> show that both IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> and IL-15R&#x003b1;<sup>2/&#x02212;</sup> mice mount potent primary antiviral CD8 T cell responses, but the magnitude of the LCMV-specific memory population declines in lymphoid as well as nonlymphoid tissues over time in the absence of IL-15 signals.</p><fig position="float" id="fig2"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>IL-15R&#x003b1;<sup>2/&#x02212;</sup> mice generate a potent LCMV-specific CD8 T cell response but memory CD8 T cell numbers are reduced relative to controls at day 70 after infection. (A) NP396-specific CD8 T cells from the PBMCs were stained as in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>. Staining is representative of five mice per group. (B) Total numbers of memory LCMV-specific CD8 T cells were determined in the spleen and liver by tetramer staining as described in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> C. Numbers indicate the average of three to four mice per group. LCMV-specific CD4 responses were similar in both IL-15R&#x003b1;<sup>2/&#x02212;</sup> and IL-15R&#x003b1;<sup>1/&#x02212;</sup> control mice (data not shown).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="020369f2a"></graphic><graphic xlink:href="020369f2b"></graphic></fig><p>Since virus-specific memory CD8 T cell numbers declined in IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice, we next examined whether these cells were qualitatively similar to those induced and maintained in normal mice. First, IFN-&#x003b3; production by memory CD8 T cells from IL-15<sup>+/+</sup> and IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice was assessed after a 5-h stimulation with peptides corresponding to a dominant and a subdominant LCMV epitope. <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>   A shows MHC tetramer staining along with intracellular cytokine staining. The frequencies obtained by IFN-&#x003b3; production were similar to those obtained by MHC tetramer staining, indicating that antigen-specific CD8 T cells from IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice were capable of rapidly synthesizing the effector cytokine IFN-&#x003b3; in this short term assay. In addition, LCMV-specific memory CD8 T cells from IL-15<sup>+/+</sup> and IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice were also similar with respect to TNF-&#x003b1; production (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> A). Similar results were obtained for IL-15R&#x003b1;<sup>2/&#x02212;</sup> and IL-15R&#x003b1;<sup>1/+</sup> mice 80 d after infection (data not shown). <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> B shows that expression of two surface markers characteristic of memory CD8 T cells is comparable. Despite the deficiency in CD44<sup>hi</sup> CD8 T cells in naive IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice, &#x0201c;true&#x0201d; LCMV-specific tetramer positive memory CD8 T cells induced in IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice by viral infection expressed levels of CD44 similar to those observed in +/+ LCMV immune mice (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> B). In addition, cells generated in IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice showed an equivalent increase in their expression of CD122, the IL-2/15R&#x003b2; chain (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> B). The latter is significant, since CD122 is thought to facilitate the response of these cells to IL-15. Staining with an additional panel of antibodies to surface markers, including CD132, Ly6C, and CD62L, and adhesion molecules including CD49b, CD54, and CD103, showed no differences between IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> and wild-type antigen-specific cells (data not shown).</p><fig position="float" id="fig3"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Antigen-specific memory CD8 T cells in IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice are functionally and phenotypically similar to memory CD8 T cells in IL-15<sup>+/+</sup> mice. (A) Splenocytes from IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> or IL-15<sup>+/+</sup> control mice were prepared 40 d after infection. Cells were stimulated in vitro for 5 h with NP396 or GP276 peptides, then intracellular cytokine staining was performed for IFN-&#x003b3; and TNF-&#x003b1;. The percentage of CD8 T cells producing either cytokine is essentially equivalent to the percentage of tetramer-binding cells in all cases. Tetramer staining and IFN-&#x003b3;/TNF-&#x003b1; dual staining is shown gated on CD8 T cells. Numbers in the top right represent the percentage of CD8 T cells (B) LCMV-specific GP33 tetramer<sup>+</sup> CD8 T cells from the spleens of IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice or IL-15<sup>+/+</sup> controls were stained for CD44 and CD122 at 40 d after infection. The dark line indicates GP33 tetramer<sup>+</sup> cells from a IL-15<sup>+/+</sup> mouse while the dashed line represents GP33 tetramer<sup>+</sup> CD8 T cells from an IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mouse. Naive controls are shown in light gray&#x0003b; all CD8s from a naive mouse for the CD44 plot and CD44<sup>lo</sup>CD8s for the CD122 plot.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="020369f3a"></graphic><graphic xlink:href="020369f3b"></graphic></fig><p>To determine whether memory CD8 T cells maintained in an IL-15&#x02013;deficient environment were competent to respond to a viral challenge in vivo, mice that had been immunized 3 mo previously with the Armstrong strain of LCMV were infected intravenously with the more virulent LCMV clone 13 strain. The memory CD8 T cells in both IL-15<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> and IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice expanded rapidly after reinfection and made potent secondary responses (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>)  . By 8 d after infection, virus was undetectable in the sera, spleens, and livers of immunized IL-15<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> and IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> animals (&#x0003c;50 PFU/ml) while naive (unimmunized) animals had high levels of virus in the sera (3.5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>4</sup> PFU/ml), liver (5.5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>7</sup> PFU/g), and spleen (10<sup>8</sup> PFU/g).</p><fig position="float" id="fig4"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Memory CD8 T cells in IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice generate a potent recall response. IL-15<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> and IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice were immunized with the Armstrong strain of LCMV. 3 mo later, mice were challenged with the virulent LCMV clone 13 strain intravenously. PBMCs were stained using MHC class I tetramers at days 0, 3, and 8 after rechallenge. Plots are gated on CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells, and the numbers indicate the percentages of MHC tetramer positive cells as a percentage of total PBMCs (top number) and as a percentage of CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells (bottom number).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="020369f4"></graphic></fig><p>Together these results demonstrate that virus-specific memory CD8 T cells can be generated in the absence of IL-15 signals and these cells are phenotypically and functionally similar to memory T cells generated in IL-15<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> mice. However, LCMV-specific CD8 T cell numbers decline over time in receptor and cytokine knockout mice, suggesting a defect in memory maintenance.</p></sec><sec><title>Memory CD8 T Cells Are Unable to Undergo Homeostatic Proliferation in an IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> Environment.</title><p>Based on the gradual decline in antigen-specific memory CD8 T cell numbers in the absence of IL-15 signals, we hypothesized that ineffective memory CD8 T cell maintenance might reflect a defect in proliferative renewal. To test this hypothesis memory CD8 T cells from B6 mice were labeled with CFSE and adoptively transferred into intact, nonirradiated, B6 or IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> hosts. Homeostatic proliferation of these memory CD8 T cell populations was assessed by the loss of CFSE fluorescence 30 d after transfer. When antigen-specific CD8 T cells generated in B6<sup>+/+</sup> animals were transferred into B6<sup>+/+</sup> recipient mice, their numbers were maintained and they underwent normal homeostatic proliferation (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>   A). A large proportion of the transferred LCMV NP396 and GP33-specific CD8 T cells had divided between one and four times. In striking contrast, when memory CD8 T cells from B6 mice were transferred into IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice little division of antigen-specific memory CD8 T cells was detected (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref> A). Similar observations were made for total CD44<sup>hi</sup> &#x0201c;memory phenotype&#x0201d; CD8 T cells&#x0003b; CD44<sup>hi</sup> CD8 T cells divided in a +/+ environment but showed minimal to no division in IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> recipients. These transfer experiments clearly demonstrate that efficient homeostatic proliferation of antigen-specific memory CD8 T cells is compromised in an IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> environment.</p><fig position="float" id="fig5"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Memory CD8 T cells do not undergo homeostatic proliferation, but undivided cells are maintained in an IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> environment. (A) Splenocytes from LCMV immune mice were labeled with CFSE and transferred into naive recipients. 30 d after transfer, spleens were removed from recipient animals and cells were stained using MHC class I tetramers to identify antigen specific memory CD8 T cells. Transferred antigen-specific cells proliferated in IL-15<sup>+/+</sup> but not IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice over a 30-d period. In the right column, the same experiment was performed using splenocytes from immune IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice and similar results were observed. Homeostatic proliferation of CD4 T cells occurred and was normal in all environments (data not shown) (B) Labeled cells recovered from the recipient spleens at 30 d after transfer were quantified. In addition, the number of undivided cells (i.e., zero division CFSE peak) and the number of divided cells (sum of cells in divisions 1&#x02013;4) are graphed. Results are similar for transfers of memory cells from +/+ mice (left panel) and IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice (right).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="020369f5a"></graphic><graphic xlink:href="020369f5b"></graphic></fig><p>The above experiments show that memory CD8 T cells generated in IL-15<sup>+/+</sup> mice required IL-15 for homeostatic proliferation. However, it is possible that memory CD8 T cells generated in IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice might adopt a partially or fully IL-15&#x02013;independent phenotype that allows them to undergo homeostatic proliferation in an IL-15&#x02013;deficient environment. To test this, memory CD8 T cells from LCMV immune IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice were CFSE-labeled and transferred into IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> or normal IL-15<sup>+/+</sup> hosts. Under these conditions, virtually no proliferation was detectable at 1 mo after transfer into IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref> A). Thus, the LCMV-specific memory CD8 T cells generated in IL-15&#x02013;deficient animals had not adapted to undergo IL-15&#x02013;independent homeostatic proliferation. Moreover, antigen-specific memory CD8 T cells from IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice underwent substantial proliferation when transferred to normal B6<sup>+/+</sup> recipients, indicating that memory cells generated in IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice were still competent to respond to the IL-15 signals for homeostatic proliferation.</p><p>The total numbers of memory CD8 T cells recovered from the spleen at 30 d after adoptive transfer into +/+ or &#x02212;/&#x02212; mice are shown in <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref> B. In all instances (+/+ memory CD8 T cells into +/+ or &#x02212;/&#x02212; mice or &#x02212;/&#x02212; memory cells into +/+ or &#x02212;/&#x02212; mice) there were fewer memory CD8 T cells present in IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> recipients. This is consistent with the data obtained from the longitudinal analysis of memory CD8 T cells shown in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>. However, a particularly interesting pattern emerged when we analyzed the number of memory CD8 T cells present in the &#x0201c;divided&#x0201d; versus &#x0201c;undivided&#x0201d; cell populations. There was no loss in the number of undivided memory CD8 T cells present in IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> recipients compared with IL-15<sup>+/+</sup>. In fact, in most cases the number was slightly higher in IL-15&#x02013;deficient mice. This suggests that memory CD8 T cells that are in G<sub>0</sub>/G<sub>1</sub> can survive in the absence of IL-15. In striking contrast to the persistence of undivided memory CD8 T cells in IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice, very few memory cells had undergone division in the absence of IL-15. The decrease in total numbers of memory CD8 T cells after adoptive transfer into IL-15<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice was solely due to the absence of this divided population of memory cells. These results show that IL-15 plays an important role in cell cycle progression of memory CD8 T cells. Alternatively, it is equally plausible that IL-15 is essential for the survival of &#x0201c;dividing&#x0201d; memory CD8 T cells. These two are not mutually exclusive and it is possible that IL-15 is needed for initiating entry into the cell cycle and also for the survival of memory CD8 T cells in cycle.</p><p>T cells undergo two distinct types of proliferation&#x0003b; antigen-driven and homeostatic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">34</xref>). After antigenic stimulation, both naive and memory CD8 T cells undergo rapid cell division (6&#x02013;8 h doubling time) and also initiate a program that results in at least seven consecutive divisions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">23</xref>). This proliferation results in substantial increases in the number of antigen-specific T cells. Thus, the primary function of antigen-driven proliferation is clonal expansion. The results of our study show that IL-15 does not play a major role in this process and that at least after a viral infection antigen-driven proliferation of CD8 T cells appeared to proceed normally in the absence of IL-15. In striking contrast, the second type of T cell proliferation termed &#x0201c;homeostatic&#x0201d; proliferation was dependent on IL-15. Only memory T cells undergo homeostatic proliferation under normal physiological conditions, naive cells do not. Also, in contrast to antigen-driven proliferation, homeostatic proliferation does not result in a net increase in the number of memory T cells and the primary function of this proliferation is maintaining the pool of memory T cells&#x0003b; hence the term &#x0201c;homeostatic&#x0201d; proliferation accurately describes this type of cell division. Our study not only identifies a key cytokine involved in memory CD8 T cell proliferation, but also shows that this proliferative renewal is critical for maintaining memory T cell numbers. In the absence of IL-15 signals, memory CD8 T cells in G<sub>0</sub>/G<sub>1</sub> were able to survive as well as in IL-15<sup>+/+</sup> mice, but homeostatic proliferation was severely compromised, and this resulted in a net decrease in the total number of memory CD8 T cells. It will be interesting to determine whether the loss of T cell memory that is seen during aging and in certain other conditions is related to IL-15 deficiency and whether treatment with IL-15 can restore CD8 T cell memory. Also, it will be of interest to address in future studies which are the critical cell types that produce IL-15, how IL-15 regulates the proliferation and survival of memory CD8 T cells, whether IL-15 is acting directly on memory CD8 T cells or mediating its effects by acting on non-T cells, and, in particular, to determine how IL-15 effects the expression and function of genes involved in cell cycle regulation.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank S. Kaech for helpful discussions and P. Yeiser, K. Madhavi-Krishna, and S. Jenkins for their technical assistance.</p><p>This work was supported by National Institutes of Health grants AI30048 (to R. Ahmed) and RO1AI45860 (to A. Ma) and a Cancer Research Institute postdoctoral fellowship (to E.J. Wherry). A. Ma is a Cancer Research Institute Scholar.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal">Ahmed, R., and D. Gray. <year>1996</year>. Immunological memory and protective immunity: understanding their relation. <source>Science.</source> <volume>272</volume>:<fpage>54</fpage>&#x02013;60.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8600537</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal">Bachmann, M.F., M. Barner, A. Viola, and M. Kopf. <year>1999</year>. Distinct kinetics of cytokine production and cytolysis in effector and memory T cells after viral infection. <source>Eur. J. Immunol.</source> <volume>29</volume>:<fpage>291</fpage>&#x02013;299.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9933111</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal">Harrington, L.E., M. Galvan, L.G. Baum, J.D. Altman, and R. Ahmed. <year>2000</year>. Differentiating between memory and effector CD8 T cells by altered expression of cell surface <italic>O</italic>-glycans. <source>J. Exp. Med.</source> <volume>191</volume>:<fpage>1241</fpage>&#x02013;1246.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10748241</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal">Veiga-Fernandes, H., U. Walter, C. Bourgeois, A. McLean, and B. Rocha. <year>2000</year>. Response of naive and memory CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells to antigen stimulation in vivo. <source>Nat. Immunol.</source> <volume>1</volume>:<fpage>47</fpage>&#x02013;53.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10881174</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal">Kaech, S.M., and R. Ahmed. <year>2001</year>. Memory CD8<sup>+</sup> T cell differentiation: initial antigen encounter triggers a developmental program in naive cells. <source>Nat. Immunol.</source> <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>415</fpage>&#x02013;422.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11323695</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal">Zimmermann, C., A. Prevost-Blondel, C. Blaser, and H. Pircher. <year>1999</year>. Kinetics of the response of naive and memory CD8 T cells to antigen: similarities and differences. <source>Eur. J. Immunol.</source> <volume>29</volume>:<fpage>284</fpage>&#x02013;290.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9933110</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal">Murali-Krishna, K., J.D. Altman, M. Suresh, D.J. Sourdive, A.J. Zajac, J.D. Miller, J. Slansky, and R. Ahmed. <year>1998</year>. Counting antigen-specific CD8 T cells: a reevaluation of bystander activation during viral infection. <source>Immunity.</source> <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>177</fpage>&#x02013;187.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9491999</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal">Blattman, J.N., R. Antia, D.J.D. Sourdive, X. Wang, S.M. Kaech, K. Murali-Krishna, J.D. Altman, and R. Ahmed. <year>2002</year>. Estimating the precursor frequency of naive antigen-specific CD8 T cells. <source>J. Exp. Med.</source> <volume>195</volume>:<fpage>657</fpage>&#x02013;664.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11877489</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal">Masopust, D., V. Vezys, A.L. Marzo, and L. Lefrancois. <year>2001</year>. Preferential localization of effector memory cells in nonlymphoid tissue. <source>Science.</source> <volume>291</volume>:<fpage>2413</fpage>&#x02013;2417.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11264538</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="other">Harrington, L.E., R. van der Most, J.L. Whitton, R. Ahmed. <year>2002</year>. Recombinant vaccina virus induced T cell immunity: quantitation of the response to the virus vector and the foreign epitope. <source>J. Vir.</source> <volume>In press</volume>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal">Altman, J.D., P.A. Moss, P.J. Goulder, D.H. Barouch, M.G. McHeyzer-Williams, J.I. Bell, A.J. McMichael, and M.M. Davis. <year>1996</year>. Phenotypic analysis of antigen-specific T lymphocytes. <source>Science.</source> <volume>274</volume>:<fpage>94</fpage>&#x02013;96.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8810254</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal">Mullbacher, A. <year>1994</year>. The long-term maintenance of cytotoxic T cell memory does not require persistence of antigen. <source>J. Exp. Med.</source> <volume>17</volume>:<fpage>317</fpage>&#x02013;321.</citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal">Hou, S., L. Hyland, K.W. Ryan, A. Portner, and P.C. Doherty. <year>1994</year>. Virus-specific CD8<sup>+</sup> T-cell memory determined by clonal burst size. <source>Nature.</source> <volume>369</volume>:<fpage>652</fpage>&#x02013;654.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7516039</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal">Tanchot, C., F. Lemonnier, B. Perarnau, A. Freitas, and B. Rocha. <year>1997</year>. Differential requirements for survival and proliferation of CD8 naive or memory cells. <source>Science.</source> <volume>276</volume>:<fpage>2057</fpage>&#x02013;2064.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9197272</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="journal">Markiewicz, M.A., C. Girao, J.T. Opferman, J. Sun, Q. Hu, A.A. Agulnik, C.E. Bishop, C.B. Thompson, and P.G. Ashton-Rickardt. <year>1998</year>. Long-term T cell memory requires the surface expression of self-peptide/major histocompatibility complex molecules. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA.</source> <volume>95</volume>:<fpage>3065</fpage>&#x02013;3070.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9501216</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="journal">Murali-Krishna, K., L.L. Lau, S. Sambhara, F. Lemonnier, J. Altman, and R. Ahmed. <year>1999</year>. Persistence of memory CD8 T cells in MHC class I-deficient mice. <source>Science.</source> <volume>286</volume>:<fpage>1377</fpage>&#x02013;1381.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10558996</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal">Sprent, J., and C.D. Surh. <year>2001</year>. Generation and maintenance of memory T cells. <source>Curr. Opin. Immunol.</source> <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>248</fpage>&#x02013;254.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11228420</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal">Swain, S.L., H. Hu, and G. Huston. <year>1999</year>. Class II-independent generation of CD4 memory T cells from effectors. <source>Science.</source> <volume>286</volume>:<fpage>1381</fpage>&#x02013;1383.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10558997</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="journal">Freitas, A.A., and B. Rocha. <year>1999</year>. Peripheral T cell survival. <source>Curr. Opin. Immunol.</source> <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>152</fpage>&#x02013;156.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10322146</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="journal">Ku, C.C., M. Murakami, A. Sakamoto, J. Kappler, and P. Marrack. <year>2000</year>. Control of homeostasis of CD8<sup>+</sup> memory T cells by opposing cytokines. <source>Science.</source> <volume>288</volume>:<fpage>675</fpage>&#x02013;678.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10784451</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="journal">Marshall, D.R., S.J. Turner, G.T. Belz, S. Wingo, S. Andreansky, M.Y. Sangster, J.M. Riberdy, T. Liu, M. Tan, and P.C. Doherty. <year>2001</year>. Measuring the diaspora for virus-specific CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA.</source> <volume>98</volume>:<fpage>6313</fpage>&#x02013;6318.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11344265</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="journal">Doherty, P.C., D.J. Topham, and R.A. Tripp. <year>1996</year>. Establishment and persistence of virus-specific CD4<sup>+</sup> and CD8<sup>+</sup> T cell memory. <source>Immunol. Rev.</source> <volume>150</volume>:<fpage>23</fpage>&#x02013;44.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8782700</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><label>23</label><citation citation-type="journal">van Stipdonk, M.J., E.E. Lemmens, and S.P. Schoenberger. <year>2001</year>. Naive CTLs require a single brief period of antigenic stimulation for clonal expansion and differentiation. <source>Nat. Immunol.</source> <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>423</fpage>&#x02013;429.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11323696</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><label>24</label><citation citation-type="journal">Schluns, K.S., W.C. Kieper, S.C. Jameson, and L. Lefrancois. <year>2000</year>. Interleukin-7 mediates the homeostasis of naive and memory CD8 T cells in vivo. <source>Nat. Immunol.</source> <volume>1</volume>:<fpage>426</fpage>&#x02013;432.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11062503</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><label>25</label><citation citation-type="journal">Suresh, M., J.K. Whitmire, L.E. Harrington, C.P. Larsen, T.C. Pearson, J.D. Altman, and R. Ahmed. <year>2001</year>. Role of CD28-B7 interactions in generation and maintenance of CD8 T cell memory. <source>J. Immunol</source>. <volume>167</volume>:<fpage>5565</fpage>&#x02013;5573.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11698427</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><label>26</label><citation citation-type="journal">Prlic, M., B.R. Blazar, A. Khoruts, T. Zell, and S.C. Jameson. <year>2001</year>. Homeostatic expansion occurs independently of costimulatory signals. <source>J. Immunol</source>. <volume>167</volume>:<fpage>5664</fpage>&#x02013;5668.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11698438</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><label>27</label><citation citation-type="journal">Zhang, X., S. Sun, I. Hwang, D.F. Tough, and J. Sprent. <year>1998</year>. Potent and selective stimulation of memory-phenotype CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells in vivo by IL-15. <source>Immunity.</source> <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>591</fpage>&#x02013;599.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9620680</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><label>28</label><citation citation-type="journal">Lodolce, J.P., D.L. Boone, S. Chai, R.E. Swain, T. Dassopoulos, S. Trettin, and A. Ma. <year>1998</year>. IL-15 receptor maintains lymphoid homeostasis by supporting lymphocyte homing and proliferation. <source>Immunity.</source> <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>669</fpage>&#x02013;676.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9846488</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><label>29</label><citation citation-type="journal">Kennedy, M.K., M. Glaccum, S.N. Brown, E.A. Butz, J.L. Viney, M. Embers, N. Matsuki, K. Charrier, L. Sedger, C.R. Willis, et al. <year>2000</year>. Reversible defects in natural killer and memory CD8 T cell lineages in interleukin 15-deficient mice. <source>J. Exp. Med.</source> <volume>191</volume>:<fpage>771</fpage>&#x02013;780.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10704459</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><label>30</label><citation citation-type="journal">Tough, D.F., P. Borrow, and J. Sprent. <year>1996</year>. Induction of bystander T cell proliferation by viruses and type I interferon in vivo. <source>Science.</source> <volume>272</volume>:<fpage>1947</fpage>&#x02013;1950.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8658169</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><label>31</label><citation citation-type="journal">Fehniger, T.A., K. Suzuki, A. Ponnappan, J.B. VanDeusen, M.A. Cooper, S.M. Florea, A.G. Freud, M.L. Robinson, J. Durbin, and M.A. Caligiuri. <year>2001</year>. Fatal leukemia in interleukin 15 transgenic mice follows early expansions in natural killer and memory phenotype CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells. <source>J. Exp. Med.</source> <volume>193</volume>:<fpage>219</fpage>&#x02013;231.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11208862</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><label>32</label><citation citation-type="journal">Ahmed, R., A. Salmi, L.D. Butler, J.M. Chiller, and M.B. Oldstone. <year>1984</year>. Selection of genetic variants of lymphocytic choriomeningitis virus in spleens of persistently infected mice. Role in suppression of cytotoxic T lymphocyte response and viral persistence. <source>J. Exp. Med.</source> <volume>160</volume>:<fpage>521</fpage>&#x02013;540.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6332167</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><label>33</label><citation citation-type="journal">Murali-Krishna, K., and R. Ahmed. <year>2000</year>. Cutting edge: naive T cells masquerading as memory cells. <source>J. Immunol.</source> <volume>165</volume>:<fpage>1733</fpage>&#x02013;1737.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10925249</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><label>34</label><citation citation-type="journal">Dutton, R.W., S.L. Swain, and L.M. Bradley. <year>1999</year>. The generation and maintenance of memory T and B cells. <source>Immunol. Today.</source> <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>291</fpage>&#x02013;293.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10475676</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list><fn-group><fn id="fn1"><label>*</label><p><italic>Abbreviation used in this paper:</italic> LCMV, lymphocytic choriomeningitis virus.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>


