<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Gen Physiol</journal-id><journal-title>The Journal of General Physiology</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0022-1295</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1540-7748</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Rockefeller University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">11158166</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2217243</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">8209</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Cooperative Mechanisms in the Activation Dependence of the Rate of Force Development in Rabbit Skinned Skeletal Muscle Fibers</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fitzsimons</surname><given-names>Daniel P.</given-names></name><address><addr-line>Department of Physiology, University of Wisconsin School of Medicine, 1300 University Avenue, Madison, WI 53706.</addr-line><fax>(608) 265-5512</fax></address><email>fitzsimons@physiology.wisc.edu</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>Jitandrakumar R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>Kenneth S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>Richard L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a">a</xref></contrib><aff id="a"><label>a</label>Department of Physiology, University of Wisconsin School of Medicine, Madison, Wisconsin 53706</aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>1</day><month>2</month><year>2001</year></pub-date><volume>117</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>148</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>29</day><month>3</month><year>2000</year></date><date date-type="rev-request"><day>18</day><month>12</month><year>2000</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>20</day><month>12</month><year>2000</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2001 The Rockefeller University Press</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2001</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Rockefeller University Press</copyright-holder></permissions><abstract><p>Regulation of contraction in skeletal muscle is a highly cooperative process involving Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding to troponin C (TnC) and strong binding of myosin cross-bridges to actin. To further investigate the role(s) of cooperation in activating the kinetics of cross-bridge cycling, we measured the Ca<sup>2+</sup> dependence of the rate constant of force redevelopment (<italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub>) in skinned single fibers in which cross-bridge and Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding were also perturbed. Ca<sup>2+</sup> sensitivity of tension, the steepness of the force-pCa relationship, and Ca<sup>2+</sup> dependence of <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> were measured in skinned fibers that were (1) treated with NEM-S1, a strong-binding, non&#x02013;force-generating derivative of myosin subfragment 1, to promote cooperative strong binding of endogenous cross-bridges to actin&#x0003b; (2) subjected to partial extraction of TnC to disrupt the spread of activation along the thin filament&#x0003b; or (3) both, partial extraction of TnC and treatment with NEM-S1. The steepness of the force-pCa relationship was consistently reduced by treatment with NEM-S1, by partial extraction of TnC, or by a combination of TnC extraction and NEM-S1, indicating a decrease in the apparent cooperativity of activation. Partial extraction of TnC or NEM-S1 treatment accelerated the rate of force redevelopment at each submaximal force, but had no effect on kinetics of force development in maximally activated preparations. At low levels of Ca<sup>2+</sup>, 3 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1 increased <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> to maximal values, and higher concentrations of NEM-S1 (6 or 10 &#x003bc;M) increased <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> to greater than maximal values. NEM-S1 also accelerated <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> at intermediate levels of activation, but to values that were submaximal. However, the combination of partial TnC extraction and 6 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1 increased <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> to virtually identical supramaximal values at all levels of activation, thus, completely eliminating the activation dependence of <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub>. These results show that <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> is not maximal in control fibers, even at saturating [Ca<sup>2+</sup>], and suggest that activation dependence of <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> is due to the combined activating effects of Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding to TnC and cross-bridge binding to actin.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>cooperativity</kwd><kwd>regulation of contraction</kwd><kwd>skeletal muscle</kwd><kwd>myosin</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>In skeletal muscle, Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding to low affinity sites on troponin C (TnC) initiates a series of molecular events that ultimately allow strong binding of cross-bridges to actin and subsequent force development (for review see <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Gordonetal2000">Gordon et al. 2000</xref>). During relaxation, dissociation of Ca<sup>2+</sup> from TnC initiates inactivation of the thin filament and subsequent detachment of cross-bridges from actin. While Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding to TnC is required for contraction, complete activation of tension and the kinetics of tension development appears to arise from interactive effects of Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding to TnC and cross-bridge binding to actin (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Lehrer1994">Lehrer 1994</xref>&#x0003b; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Gordonetal2000">Gordon et al. 2000</xref>). Previously, <xref ref-type="bib" rid="McKillopandGeeves1993">McKillop and Geeves 1993</xref> proposed a general model for the regulation of muscle contraction in which the thin filament exists in three distinct states&#x0003b; i.e., blocked, closed, and open. In this model, Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding to TnC shifts the thin filament from the blocked state to the closed state, which appears to involve Ca<sup>2+</sup>-dependent movement of tropomyosin (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Haselgrove1973">Haselgrove 1973</xref>&#x0003b; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Huxley1973">Huxley 1973</xref>&#x0003b; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="ParryandSquire1973">Parry and Squire 1973</xref>). In the presence of Ca<sup>2+</sup>, strong binding of cross-bridges to actin shifts the thin filament from the closed state to the open state. Thus, complete activation of the thin filament in terms of numbers of strongly bound cross-bridges requires both Ca<sup>2+</sup> and strong-binding myosin cross-bridges, an idea which has gained considerable experimental support (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Gordonetal2000">Gordon et al. 2000</xref>).</p><p>It is well established that the regulation of Ca<sup>2+</sup>-activated force in striated muscles involves cooperative interactions within the thin filament. This is evident, for example, in the biphasic form of the force-pCa relationship, which is steeper at low levels of Ca<sup>2+</sup> than at high because of greater intermolecular cooperation at forces less than &#x0223c;0.50 P<sub>o</sub> (for review see <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Moss1992">Moss 1992</xref>). Furthermore, most investigators have observed that the steepness of the force-pCa relationship is relatively high in skeletal muscle, i.e., Hill coefficients of 4 and greater (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Moss1992">Moss 1992</xref>). Since skeletal TnC has just two low affinity Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding sites (for review see <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Grabareketal1992">Grabarek et al. 1992</xref>), the large Hill coefficients observed in skinned fibers are generally thought to manifest cooperative processes in the activation of contraction. For example, activation of one region of the thin filament by Ca<sup>2+</sup> or strong-binding cross-bridges appears to increase the likelihood of activation of adjacent regions (for review see <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Lehrer1994">Lehrer 1994</xref>).</p><p>A model of activation proposed by <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Campbell1997">Campbell 1997</xref> predicts that cooperative interactions within the thin filament are a dynamic component of force development in striated muscles. Cross-bridge binding to the thin filament was proposed to cooperatively increase the number of cross-bridges bound to the thin filament and the rate of subsequent cross-bridge binding. In fact, there are several reports that the rate of force redevelopment (<italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub>) in skeletal muscles varies as much as 10-fold when [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] is varied from threshold to maximal values (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="BrennerandEisenberg1986">Brenner and Eisenberg 1986</xref>&#x0003b; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Metzgeretal1989">Metzger et al. 1989</xref>&#x0003b; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="SwartzandMoss1992">Swartz and Moss 1992</xref>&#x0003b; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="PalmerandKentish1998">Palmer and Kentish 1998</xref>). Typically, <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> is thought to be the sum of forward and reverse rate constants describing the transition between non&#x02013;force- and force-generating states, i.e., <italic>f</italic><sub>app</sub> and <italic>g</italic><sub>app</sub>, respectively (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="BrennerandEisenberg1986">Brenner and Eisenberg 1986</xref>). A model in which <italic>f</italic><sub>app</sub> varies with the level of activator Ca<sup>2+</sup> has been proposed to account for the activation dependence of <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Brenner1988">Brenner 1988</xref>), but this and other models (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="LandesbergandSideman1994">Landesberg and Sideman 1994</xref>&#x0003b; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Hancocketal1997">Hancock et al. 1997</xref>&#x0003b; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Regnieretal1998">Regnier et al. 1998</xref>&#x0003b; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="BrennerandChalovich1999">Brenner and Chalovich 1999</xref>) do not account for the effects of strong-binding cross-bridges on <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="SwartzandMoss1992">Swartz and Moss 1992</xref>). According to Campbell's model, the Ca<sup>2+</sup> dependence of <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> is not due to direct effects on either <italic>f</italic><sub>app</sub> or <italic>g</italic><sub>app</sub>, but instead arises because of effects of strongly bound cross-bridges to cooperatively recruit noncycling cross-bridges. At low [Ca<sup>2+</sup>], the number of noncycling cross-bridges is high, so that progressive cooperative recruitment of cross-bridges from this pool would slow the overall rate of force development. The first cross-bridges that bind recruit additional cross-bridges, which then bind and recruit still more cross-bridges, and so forth, until the force becomes steady. At higher levels of Ca<sup>2+</sup>, cooperative slowing of the rate of force redevelopment would be minimized because Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding to TnC would immediately recruit most cross-bridges into the cycling pool, leaving few cross-bridges available for cooperative recruitment. If this model is correct, eliminating the effects of molecular cooperation would be expected to eliminate the activation dependence of <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub>, i.e., <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> should be similar at all levels of activation. Previous studies on skinned fibers used a strong-binding, non&#x02013;force-generating derivative of myosin subfragment-1 (i.e., <italic>N</italic>-ethylmaleimide&#x02013;modified myosin subfragment-1 or NEM-S1) to increase the number of strongly bound cross-bridges and found that NEM-S1 increased <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> at submaximal levels of activation, i.e., at low [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] or low force (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="SwartzandMoss1992">Swartz and Moss 1992</xref>). However, activation dependence of <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> was not completely eliminated by NEM-S1, since <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> at intermediate levels of activation was still less than at low or high levels of activation.</p><p>The present study was done to further investigate the mechanisms underlying the activation dependence of the rate of force development in skinned skeletal muscle fibers, which was done by varying the degree of molecular cooperation during activation. Fibers were treated with NEM-S1 to promote strong binding of endogenous cross-bridges (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="SwartzandMoss1992">Swartz and Moss 1992</xref>), or subjected to partial extraction of TnC to limit the spread of activation along the thin filament (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Brandtetal1984">Brandt et al. 1984</xref>, <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Brandtetal1990">Brandt et al. 1990</xref>&#x0003b; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Mossetal1985">Moss et al. 1985</xref>), or both. Our findings show that it is necessary to apply both NEM-S1 and the partially extracted TnC to completely eliminate the activation dependence of <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Experimental Solutions</title><p>The composition of relaxing solution was as follows (in mM): 100 KCl, 20 imidazole, 4 MgATP, 2 EGTA, and 1 free Mg<sup>2+</sup>, pH 7.0 at 22&#x000b0;C. Activating solution contained (in mM): 79.2 KCl, 20 imidazole, 14.5 creatine phosphate, 7 EGTA, 5.42 MgCl<sub>2</sub>, and 4.68 ATP, with [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>free</sub> ranging from 1 nM (i.e., 9.0 pCa) to 32 &#x003bc;M (i.e., 4.5 pCa), pH 7.0 at 15&#x000b0;C and an ionic strength of 180 mM. A computer program (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Fabiato1988">Fabiato 1988</xref>) was used to calculate the final concentrations of each metal, ligand, and metal&#x02013;ligand complex based on stability constants listed by <xref ref-type="bib" rid="GodtandLindley1982">Godt and Lindley 1982</xref>.</p></sec><sec><title>Skinned Fiber Preparations</title><p>Fast-twitch skeletal muscle fibers were obtained from the psoas muscles of adult New Zealand rabbits. Bundles of &#x0223c;30 fibers were dissected from psoas muscles while in relaxing solution. Each bundle was tied with 4/0 suture to glass capillary tubes, placed in relaxing solution containing 1% Triton X-100 for 4&#x02013;5 h at 4&#x000b0;C, and then stored in relaxing solution containing 50% glycerol at &#x02212;20&#x000b0;C for up to 3 wk. Chemically skinned fibers were ready for experimental use 1&#x02013;2 d after dissection.</p></sec><sec><title>Experimental Apparatus and General Protocols</title><p>Before each experiment, an individual skinned psoas fiber was carefully pulled from one end of a fiber bundle and mounted between a force transducer (model 400A&#x0003b; Aurora Scientific) and a DC torque motor (model 308B&#x0003b; Aurora Scientific) in an experimental apparatus similar to one described previously (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Moss1979">Moss 1979</xref>). A fiber segment 1.0&#x02013;1.5 mm long remained exposed to the solution between the force transducer and the motor. Before mechanical measurements, the experimental apparatus was set on the stage of an inverted microscope (Carl Zeiss, Inc.). The length and force signals of each fiber were digitized at 1 kHz, using a 12-bit A/D converter (model AT-MIO-16F-5&#x0003b; National Instruments Corp.), and displayed and stored on a personal computer using customized software (LabView Full Development System for Windows, version 5.01&#x0003b; National Instruments Corp.). Length changes were driven by computer-generated voltage commands, which were output to the torque motor via a 12-bit D/A converter. All experiments were performed at 15&#x000b0;C and at a sarcomere length of &#x0223c;2.35 &#x003bc;m in relaxing solution. During activation and relaxation, sarcomere length and fiber dimensions were recorded on videotape using a video camera (model WV-BL730&#x0003b; Panasonic) and VHS recorder (model SVO-1420&#x0003b; Sony).</p><p>Mechanical measurements were first performed on all fibers under control conditions (N = 33). Next, fibers were either subjected to (1) partial extraction of TnC (N = 15), (2) treatment with NEM-S1 (N = 18), or (3) both (N = 15)&#x0003b; and mechanical measurements were repeated.</p></sec><sec><title>Experimental Treatments</title><sec><title>Partial Extraction of Troponin C.</title><p>Approximately 50% of endogenous TnC was specifically extracted from thin filaments of psoas fibers using a modification of a method reported previously (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="MetzgerandMoss1991">Metzger and Moss 1991</xref>). After initial measurements of mechanical properties, each psoas fiber was bathed for 1&#x02013;3 min in a TnC extraction solution containing 10 mM imidazole, 5 mM EGTA and 200 &#x003bc;M trifluoperazine dihydrochloride (TFP&#x0003b; Sigma-Aldrich), pH 7.0 at 15&#x000b0;C. The fiber was subsequently washed three to four times in fresh relaxing solution to remove any residual TFP. Sarcomere length during the extraction protocol was &#x0223c;2.35 &#x003bc;m. Maximal Ca<sup>2+</sup>-activated force was significantly reduced after partial extraction of TnC, ranging from 0.15 to 0.65 of the P<sub>o</sub> measured in the preextracted fiber. Measurements of <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> and force were subsequently obtained as functions of pCa in the partially TnC-extracted fibers. Control experiments demonstrated that incubating the partially TnC-extracted fibers for &#x0223c;30 s in relaxing solution containing 0.6 mg skeletal TnC/ml resulted in complete recovery of steady-state force and restored Hill coefficients to control values (data not shown).</p></sec><sec><title>Preparation and Use of NEM-S1.</title><p>Myosin subfragment 1 (S1) was purified from rabbit fast-twitch skeletal muscle and modified with <italic>N</italic>-ethylmaleimide (NEM) as described previously (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="SwartzandMoss1992">Swartz and Moss 1992</xref>). Although NEM-S1 significantly increases myosin ATPase activity in solutions containing myosin, regulated actin, and Ca<sup>2+</sup> (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Williamsetal1984">Williams et al. 1984</xref>&#x0003b; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Greeneetal1987">Greene et al. 1987</xref>), it exhibits no ATPase activity of its own (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Williamsetal1984">Williams et al. 1984</xref>). NEM-S1 forms long lasting complexes with actin in the presence or absence of Ca<sup>2+</sup> and ATP (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="SwartzandMoss1992">Swartz and Moss 1992</xref>). In the present study, the concentration of NEM-S1 was estimated by absorbance at 280 nm (with light-scattering correction performed at 320 nm) using a mass absorptivity of 0.75 and a molecular mass of 118,000 D for S1. A stock solution of NEM-S1 was prepared by overnight dialysis against a solution containing 20 mM imidazole, pH 7.0, and 1 mM DTT. A working solution of NEM-S1 was prepared immediately before use by mixing equal volumes of NEM-S1 stock and a 2&#x000d7; stock of pCa 9.0 solution. NEM-S1 was adjusted to the desired concentration by adding the appropriate amount of 1&#x000d7; pCa 9.0 solution. Before mechanical measurements, each fiber was incubated for 15 min at 15&#x000b0;C in solution of pCa 9.0 containing either 3, 6, or 10 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1. The skinned fiber was subsequently transferred to activating solutions of varying pCa without NEM-S1 to measure the steady-state force and the rate of force redevelopment. After mechanical measurements, the skinned fiber was returned to the pCa 9.0 solution containing NEM-S1.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Specific Experimental Protocols</title><sec><title>Rate of Tension Redevelopment.</title><p>The rate constant of force redevelopment (<italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub>) in skinned psoas fibers was assessed using a modification of an experimental protocol described previously (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="BrennerandEisenberg1986">Brenner and Eisenberg 1986</xref>). Measurement of <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> involves a mechanical slack-restretch maneuver to dissociate bound cross-bridges from actin in a steadily Ca<sup>2+</sup>-activated preparation. Each skinned fiber was transferred from relaxing to activating solutions of varying pCa (i.e., pCa 6.6&#x02013;4.5) and allowed to generate steady-state force. The preparation was rapidly (&#x0003c;2 ms) slackened by 20% of its original length, resulting in an abrupt reduction of force to zero (i.e., &#x0003c;5% of steady isometric force). This was followed by a brief period of unloaded shortening (e.g., 20&#x02013;25 ms) after which the fiber was rapidly (&#x0003c;2 ms) restretched to its initial length. Force redevelopment following the slack-restretch maneuver and force recovery to the original steady-state value reflect the rate of cross-bridge cycling between weakly bound and strongly bound, force-generating states (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="BrennerandEisenberg1986">Brenner and Eisenberg 1986</xref>). A <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub>-pCa relationship was obtained by first maximally activating the skinned fiber in a solution of pCa 4.5, and then in a series of submaximally activating solutions between pCa 6.6 and 5.6. To assess any decline in maximal <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub>, the fiber was activated in a solution of pCa 4.5 at the end of each protocol. The reference value of maximal <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> for each submaximal activation was obtained by interpolation between the initial and final measurements of maximal <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub>. The apparent rate constants of force redevelopment (<italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub>) were estimated by linear transformation of the half-time of force redevelopment, i.e., <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> = 0.693/t<sup>1/2</sup>, as described previously (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Regnieretal1998">Regnier et al. 1998</xref>). Most <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> measurements were done without sarcomere length control, although experiments performed with sarcomere length control yielded quantitatively similar results (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref>). Force redevelopment traces in a representative skinned psoas fiber at maximal and submaximal levels of Ca<sup>2+</sup> activation are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>: the top panel depicts the mechanical release-restretch maneuver imposed to determine the rate of force redevelopment (<italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub>)&#x0003b; and the bottom panel illustrates changes in submaximal force in solutions of pCa 6.1 (trace b) and pCa 6.0 (trace c) under control conditions. The change in force is expressed relative to maximum force (P<sub>o</sub>) generated by the same fiber under control conditions when exposed to solution of pCa 4.5 solution (trace a).</p></sec><sec><title>Force-pCa Relationship.</title><p>During measurements of <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub>, each skinned psoas fiber was exposed to solutions of varying pCa and allowed to develop steady-state force. The difference between steady-state force and the force baseline after the slack step was measured as the total force at that pCa. Active force was obtained by subtracting Ca<sup>2+</sup>-independent force, measured in solution of pCa 9.0, from the total force. Force-pCa relationships were determined by expressing submaximal force (P) at each pCa as a fraction of maximal force (P<sub>o</sub>) determined at pCa 4.5, i.e., P/P<sub>o</sub>. The apparent cooperativity in the activation of force development was inferred from the steepness of the force-pCa relationship at forces &#x0003c;0.50 P<sub>o</sub>, and was quantified using a Hill plot transformation of the force-pCa data (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Strangetal1994">Strang et al. 1994</xref>). We focused on this region of the curve because the force-pCa relationship is biphasic, with most of the cooperative activation evident at forces less than 0.50 P<sub>o</sub> (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Moss1992">Moss 1992</xref>). The force-pCa data were fit using the equation, P/P<sub>o</sub> = [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sup>n</sup>/(<italic>k</italic><sup>n</sup> + [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sup>n</sup>), where n is the Hill coefficient, and <italic>k</italic> is the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] required for half-maximal activation.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Quantification of Partial TnC Extraction by SDS-PAGE</title><p>The extent of TnC extraction was assessed using SDS-PAGE and ultrasensitive silver staining (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="SweitzerandMoss1993">Sweitzer and Moss 1993</xref>). Upon completion of a given experiment, &#x0223c;0.75 mm of fiber segment was placed in a microfuge tube containing SDS sample buffer (10 &#x003bc;l/mm segment length) and stored at &#x02212;80&#x000b0;C until analyzed for TnC content. The proportion of TnC present in the fiber was determined by densitometric analysis of silver-stained gels using a GS-670 imaging densitometer and Molecular Analyst software (BioRad Laboratories). To quantify the amount of TnC extracted, the ratio of TnC/(MLC1 + MLC3) was determined for each fiber (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Moss1992">Moss 1992</xref>). The ratio measured in the extracted fiber segment was divided by the ratio obtained from a segment obtained from the same fiber before extraction to yield an estimate of the TnC content of the partially TnC-extracted segment.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistics</title><p>All data are expressed as mean &#x000b1; SEM. Where appropriate, either a two-tailed <italic>t</italic> test for independent samples or a paired <italic>t</italic> test was used as a post hoc test of significance, with significance set at <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>The Effects of NEM-S1 and Partial Extraction of TnC on Steady-state Mechanical Properties</title><p>Our studies of cooperative mechanisms in skinned skeletal muscle fibers involved two perturbations that previously have been shown to alter cooperation in the activation of contraction. NEM-S1 was used to mimic the effects of strong-binding cross-bridges to further activate Ca<sup>2+</sup>-dependent tension and the rate of tension development (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="SwartzandMoss1992">Swartz and Moss 1992</xref>), and thin filaments were partially TnC-extracted to disrupt near-neighbor cooperativity between adjacent functional groups (one troponin, one tropomyosin, and associated actins) in the thin filament (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Brandtetal1984">Brandt et al. 1984</xref>&#x0003b; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Mossetal1985">Moss et al. 1985</xref>).</p><sec><title>Treatment with NEM-S1.</title><p>NEM-S1 had pronounced effects on maximal Ca<sup>2+</sup>-activated tension (P<sub>o</sub>), Ca<sup>2+</sup>-independent tension, Ca<sup>2+</sup> sensitivity of tension (pCa<sub>50</sub>), and Hill coefficient (n<sub>2</sub>) in single skinned psoas fibers, as reported earlier (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="SwartzandMoss1992">Swartz and Moss 1992</xref>) and summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table </xref>. The application of 3, 6, or 10 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1 increased Ca<sup>2+</sup>-independent tension at pCa 9.0 in a concentration-dependent manner (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). At the two highest concentrations used, the increase in Ca<sup>2+</sup>-independent tension was accompanied by small (at 6 &#x003bc;M) or large (at 10 &#x003bc;M) reductions in maximal Ca<sup>2+</sup>-activated tension, indicating that at these concentrations NEM-S1 competed with endogenous cross-bridges for binding sites on actin. For this reason, 6 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1 was preferentially used in most of the experiments described below. The increases in Ca<sup>2+</sup>-independent tension are most likely due to cooperative activation of the thin filament by NEM-S1, thereby allowing strong binding of endogenous cross-bridges (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="SwartzandMoss1992">Swartz and Moss 1992</xref>).</p><p>NEM-S1 also potentiated submaximal Ca<sup>2+</sup>-activated force in a concentration-dependent manner (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). Mean pCa<sub>50</sub> was significantly increased after treatment with either 6 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1 (&#x00394;pCa<sub>50</sub> = 0.07 &#x000b1; 0.01, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) or 10 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1 (&#x00394;pCa50 = 0.12 &#x000b1; 0.03, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05), so that Ca<sup>2+</sup> sensitivity of force was increased. Such increases are consistent with the idea that, at low levels of Ca<sup>2+</sup>, NEM-S1 promotes the formation of strongly bound, force-generating cross-bridges (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="SwartzandMoss1992">Swartz and Moss 1992</xref>). At higher Ca<sup>2+</sup> concentrations, i.e., pCa &#x0003c; 5.9, NEM-S1 had small or negligible effects on Ca<sup>2+</sup>-activated forces relative to the control. Commensurate with the increase in force at low levels of Ca<sup>2+</sup>, NEM-S1 significantly reduced the slope of the force-pCa relationship for Ca<sup>2+</sup>-activated tensions &#x0003c;0.50 P<sub>o</sub> (n<sub>2</sub>), an effect that increased with increasing concentrations of NEM-S1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref> B and <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table </xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Treatment with NEM-S1 and Partial Extraction of TnC.</title><p>To further examine the mechanisms of cooperative activation of thin filaments, single fibers were first incubated with 200 &#x003bc;M TFP to partially extract TnC and were subsequently treated with NEM-S1. Such an approach allows dissection of the relative roles of cross-bridge binding and near-neighbor interactions in the thin filament in activation of contraction. In these experiments, segments of each fiber were analyzed by SDS-PAGE (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>) before TnC extraction (lane 1), after partial TnC extraction (lane 2), after TnC extraction plus NEM-S1 (lane 3), and after readdition of skeletal TnC to a previously extracted fiber (lane 4). Densitometric scans of the gels indicated that &#x0223c;50% of the endogenous TnC was extracted from psoas fibers under the conditions used. Furthermore, the extraction procedure was specific for TnC since the relative amounts of other myofibrillar proteins (e.g., myosin light chains, TnI, and TnT) were unchanged.</p><p>Partial extraction of TnC had reversible effects on maximal Ca<sup>2+</sup>-activated tension (P<sub>o</sub>), Ca<sup>2+</sup>-independent tension, Ca<sup>2+</sup> sensitivity of tension, and the Hill coefficient (n<sub>2</sub>), which are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table </xref>. As reported previously (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Brandtetal1984">Brandt et al. 1984</xref>, <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Brandtetal1990">Brandt et al. 1990</xref>&#x0003b; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Mossetal1985">Moss et al. 1985</xref>&#x0003b; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="BrandtandSchachat1997">Brandt and Schachat 1997</xref>), partial extraction of TnC resulted in a significant decrease in maximum Ca<sup>2+</sup>-activated tension, presumably because of the inactivation of thin filament functional groups. Subsequent treatment of partially TnC-extracted fibers with NEM-S1 resulted in a further reduction in maximal Ca<sup>2+</sup>-activated tension similar to that observed after NEM-S1 treatment alone. Although resting tension was unaffected by partial TnC extraction alone, TnC extraction elicited significant increases in NEM-S1&#x02013;induced Ca<sup>2+</sup>-independent tension (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). The increase in Ca<sup>2+</sup>-independent tension, as the percent maximum force in untreated fibers, was less than that observed because of NEM-S1 treatment alone, suggesting that TnC extraction reduced the number of NEM-S1 or endogenous cross-bridges bound to actin, perhaps by disrupting near-neighbor interactions between adjacent functional groups. However, when scaled to the maximum force after TnC extraction, the combined effects of TnC extraction and NEM-S1 were greater than with NEM-S1 alone.</p><p>Partial extraction of TnC also affected the Ca<sup>2+</sup> sensitivity of tension and reduced the responsiveness of fibers to NEM-S1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>). Mean pCa<sub>50</sub> in control fibers was 5.97 &#x000b1; 0.01, which decreased to 5.75 &#x000b1; 0.02 after extraction of TnC (&#x00394;pCa<sub>50</sub> = 0.22 &#x000b1; 0.03, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05). Subsequent treatment with 3 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1 did not alter the Ca<sup>2+</sup> sensitivity of force (&#x00394;pCa<sub>50</sub> = 0.01 &#x000b1; 0.01)&#x0003b; however, 6 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1 increased the Ca<sup>2+</sup> sensitivity of force, i.e., pCa<sub>50</sub> increased to 5.89 &#x000b1; 0.02 (&#x00394;pCa<sub>50</sub> = 0.15 &#x000b1; 0.01&#x0003b; <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05), a mean value near that observed in TnC-replete fibers when treated with NEM-S1 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table </xref>). Partial extraction of TnC and successive treatment with increasing concentrations of NEM-S1 resulted in progressive reductions in the steepness of the force-pCa relationship (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table </xref>), suggesting that the effects of these two treatments on cooperativity are additive and most likely involve different molecular mechanisms.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Effects of NEM-S1 and Partial Extraction of TnC on the Rate of Force Redevelopment</title><p>According to <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Campbell1997">Campbell 1997</xref> model of regulation, cooperative interactions within the thin filament, such as cross-bridge&#x02013;induced cross-bridge binding, are thought to speed the rate of force redevelopment (<italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub>), and may provide the basis for the steep activation dependence of <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> in the skeletal muscle fibers observed by <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Brenner1988">Brenner 1988</xref> and others. Previous work in which NEM-S1 was found to accelerate <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> at all submaximal levels of Ca<sup>2+</sup> activation (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="SwartzandMoss1992">Swartz and Moss 1992</xref>) provided strong support for this idea. However, the picture that emerged from that study was incomplete since in the presence of NEM-S1, <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> was maximal at low and high levels of activation but less than maximal at intermediate levels of activation. Therefore, we have done additional experiments in an attempt to determine the basis for activation dependence of <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> in the presence of NEM-S1 (data are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table </xref>). This was done by examining the activation dependence of <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> in the presence of varying amounts of NEM-S1 and also by partial extraction of TnC to perturb cooperative interactions within the thin filament.</p><p>Consistent with earlier results, <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> was found to vary &#x0223c;10-fold as Ca<sup>2+</sup> activation was varied from near threshold to maximal levels. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref> A for a single submaximal pCa (pCa 6.1), the rate of force redevelopment at submaximal concentrations of Ca<sup>2+</sup> was accelerated by NEM-S1, with the degree of acceleration increasing with the concentration of NEM-S1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref> A, traces b&#x02013;d), compared with control (trace a). Under identical experimental conditions, another fiber was subjected to partial TnC extraction and subsequent treatment with 6 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref> B). As summarized previously, <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> under control conditions varied with the level of Ca<sup>2+</sup> activation, increasing when Ca<sup>2+</sup> concentration was increased from pCa 5.9 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref> B, trace b) to pCa 4.5 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref> B, trace a). After partial extraction of TnC, the steady force decreased at each pCa, but the rate of force redevelopment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref> B, trace c) at pCa 5.9 was nearly equivalent to that of the preextracted fiber at the same pCa. Subsequent treatment with 6 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1 significantly increased steady force at pCa 5.9 and markedly accelerated the rate of force redevelopment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref> B, trace d).</p><p>The relationship between <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> and steady-state isometric force (as a measure of the level of activation due to Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding and cooperative mechanisms) was variably affected by interventions to increase numbers of strongly bound cross-bridges (i.e., NEM-S1) and to disrupt near-neighbor cooperativity in the thin filament (partial extraction of TnC). As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref> A, <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> during maximal activation was unaffected by NEM-S1, but <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> values at low levels of activation were increased to levels either identical to (at 3 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1) or greater than (at 6 or 10 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1) the values obtained in maximally activated fibers. At intermediate levels of activation, NEM-S1 increased <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> to greater than the control values, but <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> was still less than maximal. Similar effects of NEM-S1 were observed in fibers that were subjected to sarcomere length control during measurements of <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref>). Progressive increases in the concentration of NEM-S1 further increased the value of <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> at intermediate levels of activation, but even the highest concentration used (10 &#x003bc;M) did not accelerate <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> to maximal values. In the absence of Ca<sup>2+</sup> (pCa 9.0), application of NEM-S1 induced active tension development (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table </xref>)&#x0003b; under these conditions, <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> was supramaximal when compared with the maximal values measured at pCa 4.5 under control conditions.</p><p>Partial extraction of TnC also increased <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> at intermediate levels of activation as compared with the control (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref> B). In fact, the increase in <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> varied with the extent of TnC extraction, i.e., fibers containing smaller amounts of residual TnC exhibited faster rates of force redevelopment during submaximal activation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 10</xref>). Subsequent treatment of partially TnC extracted fibers with 3 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1 resulted in a <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub>&#x02013;relative force relationship similar to that observed with NEM-S1 treatment alone, although <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> at each level of activation was somewhat greater than the value obtained with NEM-S1 alone. However, the combination of partial TnC extraction and 6 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1 increased <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> at each level of activation to values greater than the maximum measured in control fibers and completely eliminated the activation dependence of <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref> B).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>The results of the present study show that strong binding of cross-bridges to actin increases the rate of force development in skeletal muscle and suggest that cooperativity in cross-bridge binding is an important determinant of activation kinetics. NEM-S1 increased the <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> measured during submaximal activations, with greatest effects at low levels of activation where NEM-S1 increased <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> to values greater than the maximum observed in control fibers at saturating [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]. From this result, it is evident that the rate of force development measured in control fibers at pCa 4.5 is not a true maximum. Although NEM-S1 dramatically accelerated <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub>, strong binding of cross-bridges does not entirely account for the activation of cross-bridge kinetics, since NEM-S1 alone was insufficient at intermediate levels of activation to increase <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> to maximal or to completely eliminate the activation dependence of <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub>. Instead, elimination of activation dependence required both NEM-S1 and partial extraction of TnC from the thin filament. Since partial extraction of TnC should disrupt near-neighbor communication between functional groups in the thin filament (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Brandtetal1984">Brandt et al. 1984</xref>, <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Brandtetal1990">Brandt et al. 1990</xref>&#x0003b; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Mossetal1985">Moss et al. 1985</xref>), we conclude that activation dependence of <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> results from effects of strongly bound cross-bridges to cooperatively recruit additional cross-bridges within the same and neighboring regions of the thin filament.</p><sec><title>Models for Activation of Contraction</title><p>Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding to TnC initiates muscle contraction, but complete activation of tension and the kinetics of tension development appears to involve cooperative effects due to cross-bridge binding to actin (for reviews see <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Lehrer1994">Lehrer 1994</xref>&#x0003b; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Gordonetal2000">Gordon et al. 2000</xref>). Biochemical data suggest that activation is a positive cooperative process (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Williamsetal1984">Williams et al. 1984</xref>, <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Williamsetal1988">Williams et al. 1988</xref>), such that activation of a thin filament functional group (estimated to be &#x000b1; 10&#x02013;14 actin monomers&#x0003b; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="GeevesandLehrer1994">Geeves and Lehrer 1994</xref>&#x0003b; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Swartzetal1996">Swartz et al. 1996</xref>) by Ca<sup>2+</sup> and/or strong binding cross-bridges influences the activation of neighboring functional groups (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Lehrer1994">Lehrer 1994</xref>). Cooperation is apparent in contracting muscle in the greater than expected (on the basis of the numbers of Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding sites on TnC) steepness of the tension-pCa relationship, especially at low levels of Ca<sup>2+</sup> (for review see <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Moss1992">Moss 1992</xref>), and previously observed effects of strong-binding cross-bridges to speed the rate of submaximal force development in skinned skeletal muscle fibers (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="SwartzandMoss1992">Swartz and Moss 1992</xref>).</p><p>The rate constant of force redevelopment (<italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub>) in steadily activated skeletal muscle preparations exhibits an &#x0223c;10-fold activation as [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] is increased from threshold to saturating levels, which was originally shown by <xref ref-type="bib" rid="BrennerandEisenberg1986">Brenner and Eisenberg 1986</xref> and, subsequently, has been reported by other groups. Brenner (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Brenner1988">Brenner 1988</xref>&#x0003b; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="BrennerandChalovich1999">Brenner and Chalovich 1999</xref>) has explained the activation dependence of <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> using a model in which Ca<sup>2+</sup> influences the rate constant of cross-bridge attachment to actin, <italic>f<sub>app</sub></italic>, i.e., <italic>f<sub>app</sub></italic> decreases when [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] is lowered, presumably by an allosteric mechanism. Such a model does not straightforwardly account for our observation that strong-binding cross-bridges (NEM-S1) markedly accelerate <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub>, an effect which is greatest at low levels of Ca<sup>2+</sup> activation: but, our results don't exclude the possibility that this type of mechanism modulates kinetics in control fibers. A simple explanation is that increased [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] effectively increases <italic>f<sub>app</sub></italic> as a consequence of the cooperative effects of increased numbers of cross-bridges bound to the thin filament.</p><p>At least two models of activation might be used to explain the activation dependence of <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub>. <xref ref-type="bib" rid="LandesbergandSideman1994">Landesberg and Sideman 1994</xref> developed a model in which the activation dependence of the rate of force development in cardiac muscle was due to a cross-bridge binding&#x02013;dependent increase in Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding affinity of TnC. Alternatively, the steep activation dependence of <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> can be explained by the cooperation-mediated slowing of force development at low levels of activation (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Campbell1997">Campbell 1997</xref>), which is the framework we will use to discuss our results. In Campbell's model, cross-bridges are distributed between cycling and noncycling populations: cycling cross-bridges undergo repeated transitions between non&#x02013;force-bearing and force-bearing states (under the influence of the rate constants <italic>f<sub>app</sub></italic> and <italic>g<sub>app</sub></italic>), whereas noncycling cross-bridges are recruited to the cycling population as a result of Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding to troponin or cooperative effects of strong binding cross-bridges to enhance activation of the thin filament. At lower levels of Ca<sup>2+</sup>, a smaller fraction of cross-bridges is initially recruited into the cycling population as a direct result of Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding to the thin filament, so that most cross-bridges are in the noncycling pool and, thus, are available for cooperative recruitment to the cycling pool. Progressive recruitment of cross-bridges from the noncycling pool would then slow the rate of force development. In contrast, at high levels of Ca<sup>2+</sup>, the rate constant of force development is much greater because most cross-bridges are recruited to the cycling pool when Ca<sup>2+</sup> binds to troponin, which leaves few cross-bridges available in the noncycling pool for subsequent cooperative recruitment. At a saturating [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] of pCa 4.5, the rate constant of force development will thus be equal to <italic>f<sub>app</sub></italic> + <italic>g<sub>app</sub></italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>Activation Dependence of Force and k<sub>tr</sub> Involves Activating Effects of Cross-bridge Binding and Near-neighbor Cooperativity within the Thin Filament</title><p>The results of our study provide support for models of regulation in which cross-bridge interaction kinetics are activated by cross-bridge binding to the thin filament. Experiments here show that force at submaximal [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] is increased due to activating effects of strongly bound cross-bridges, which confirms results from earlier studies from this and other laboratories (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Swartzetal1996">Swartz et al. 1996</xref> and references therein). The Ca<sup>2+</sup> dependence of <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> appears to involve two factors: activating effects due to cross-bridge binding to the thin filament, and near-neighbor interactions between adjacent functional groups, such that activation of a given functional group facilitates cross-bridge binding in neighboring functional groups. Thus, Ca<sup>2+</sup> does not seem to regulate kinetics (e.g., by binding to a regulatory site) but, instead, has indirect effects on kinetics by influencing the number of cross-bridges bound to actin. Our results also show that cooperative effects due to cross-bridge binding to thin filaments are large but insufficient to completely account for activation dependence of <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub>, since it was necessary to add NEM-S1 and disrupt near-neighbor cooperativity in the thin filament to achieve maximal <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> at all levels of activation.</p><sec><title>Effects on Force and k<sub>tr</sub> due to Partial Extraction of Troponin C.</title><p>In this study, partial extraction of TnC was used to disrupt the spread of activation between adjacent functional groups in the thin filament, presumably because of constitutive inactivation of functional groups from which TnC was removed (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Brandtetal1984">Brandt et al. 1984</xref>&#x0003b; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Mossetal1985">Moss et al. 1985</xref>&#x0003b; for review see <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Moss1992">Moss 1992</xref>). Our findings that the maximum force and the steepness of the force-pCa relationship were reduced by TnC extraction (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table </xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>) confirm earlier results (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Brandtetal1984">Brandt et al. 1984</xref>, <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Brandtetal1990">Brandt et al. 1990</xref>&#x0003b; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Mossetal1985">Moss et al. 1985</xref>&#x0003b; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="MetzgerandMoss1991">Metzger and Moss 1991</xref>) and support the idea that near-neighbor interactions between functional groups contribute to force development in skeletal muscle.</p><p>Whereas steady-state Ca<sup>2+</sup>-activated force was reduced after TnC extraction, the rate constant of force redevelopment (<italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub>) increased at each submaximal force, when compared with nonextracted fibers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref> B). Although not anticipated in <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Campbell1997">Campbell 1997</xref> model of activation, this result is consistent with the idea that cooperative interactions between thin filament functional groups contribute to a slowing of force development at low activation. By extracting TnC, these interactions were presumably disrupted and cooperative recruitment of cross-bridges from neighboring functional groups was reduced or eliminated, thereby speeding the rate of force development. By varying the amount of TnC extracted, it should be possible to vary the rate of force development independent of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>], which is what we observed. Fibers containing less TnC and, therefore, having fewer functional groups that could be activated by Ca<sup>2+</sup> exhibited a faster rate of force redevelopment at each submaximal force (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 10</xref>). Although it might be possible to explain these results by an alternate mechanism (e.g., direct effects on <italic>f<sub>app</sub></italic> due to extraction of TnC), a modification of <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Campbell1997">Campbell 1997</xref> model to include near-neighbor interactions that cooperatively recruit cross-bridges to strongly bound states also accounts for our results (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Razumovaetal2000">Razumova et al. 2000</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Effects on Force and k<sub>tr</sub> due to NEM-S1.</title><p>As reported earlier (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="SwartzandMoss1992">Swartz and Moss 1992</xref>), treatment of fibers with NEM-S1 reduced the steepness of the force-pCa relationship (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table </xref>). This decrease in the apparent cooperativity of activation can be explained by near saturation of the myosin cross-bridge binding component of thin filament activation due to binding of NEM-S1. NEM-S1 also induced concentration-dependent increases in the resting (Ca<sup>2+</sup>-independent) tension, submaximal Ca<sup>2+</sup>-activated force, and the Ca<sup>2+</sup> sensitivity of force, i.e., a left shift of the tension-pCa relationship (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table </xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). Together, these results support the idea that binding of NEM-S1 to actin increased the level of thin filament activation and increased the number of endogenous cross-bridges in strongly bound force-generating states.</p><p>At submaximal levels of activation, NEM-S1 increased the rate of force redevelopment at each level of activation, but the increase was much greater at very low than at intermediate levels of activation. As the concentration of NEM-S1 was increased, <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> at low levels of activation was increased to maximal and supramaximal values. One possible way to explain this phenomenon is that at low levels of Ca<sup>2+</sup>, the increased force and maximal values of <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> are manifestations of preferential Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding to functional groups in which NEM-S1 is also bound. The combined activating effects of Ca<sup>2+</sup> and strongly bound cross-bridges within these functional groups would facilitate binding of endogenous cross-bridges and would accelerate the rate of binding. Although this is a plausible mechanism, it does not account for all of our results, since fibers activated with NEM-S1 in the absence of Ca<sup>2+</sup> developed small forces but yielded <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> values that were maximal or supramaximal. This finding indicates that <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> measured in control fibers at pCa 4.5 is not the maximum value for this variable. Furthermore, it is possible to achieve maximal and even higher values of <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> in the absence of Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding to TnC (i.e., at pCa 9.0) simply by increasing the numbers of strong-binding cross-bridges in the form of NEM-S1. We don't know the mechanism of this effect, but it is possible that such high values of <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> are due to a combination of NEM-S1 binding to a few discrete regions of the filament, and isolation of these regions from adjacent, inactive regions by intervening troponin complexes having no Ca<sup>2+</sup> bound. The first condition would arise if the binding of NEM-S1 was not uniform along the thin filament, and would limit the number of endogenous cross-bridges that could bind to the thin filament, and thereby account for the small forces developed in the absence of Ca<sup>2+</sup>. The second condition would reduce or eliminate communication between adjacent functional groups, eliminate near-neighbor cooperative recruitment of cross-bridges from the noncycling pool, and thereby speed <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub>. The fact that NEM-S1 does not further accelerate <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> in maximally Ca<sup>2+</sup>-activated fibers is consistent with both ideas, i.e., if NEM-S1 is nonuniformly distributed along the thin filament, then the maximum value of <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> would be limited by cooperative recruitment of cross-bridges from adjacent functional groups with less or no NEM-S1 bound.</p><p>At intermediate levels of activation (indexed by force or [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]), <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> measured in the presence of NEM-S1 was less than that observed at low and maximal activations, but was much faster than control values measured at similar levels of force or Ca<sup>2+</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref> A). The finding that <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> in the presence of NEM-S1 is not maximal at all levels of activation suggests that the thin filament is not saturated by Ca<sup>2+</sup>, cross-bridge binding, or by both. Again, it seems likely that NEM-S1 binding to the thin filament is not uniform, resulting in some regions with NEM-S1 bound and other regions with less or no NEM-S1. As discussed above, functional groups with NEM-S1 bound should be activated at lower levels of Ca<sup>2+</sup>, because of a greater Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding affinity, and the rate of force development would be maximal because of the combined effects of Ca<sup>2+</sup> and bound cross-bridges. By similar reasoning, those with less or no NEM-S1 would be recruited at higher (intermediate) levels of Ca<sup>2+</sup> and will have fewer bound cross-bridges, i.e., cross-bridge activation of these functional groups is less, and force development is therefore slower. The fact that the records of force redevelopment at intermediate activation are well fit by a single rate constant suggests that the mix of variably activated functional groups confers a single level of activation to the entire thin filament. Thus, the effective size of a functional group appears to increase as [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] is increased to intermediate levels&#x0003b; the central region of the functional group has the greatest amounts of Ca<sup>2+</sup> and NEM-S1 bound. Because of this, the rate of force development at intermediate levels of activation will be slowed because of cooperative recruitment of cross-bridges into the end regions of the functional group or adjacent functional groups. Ultimately, at high [Ca<sup>2+</sup>], fewer inactivated functional groups remain and the impact of cooperative interactions is reduced, but not totally eliminated since, in control fibers, <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> never achieves the maximum possible value. Correspondingly, the time course of force redevelopment becomes progressively faster, and <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> converges to the value obtained during maximal activation.</p><p>The effects of NEM-S1 to accelerate <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> appear to be significantly greater than the effects due to partial extraction of TnC (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref> B). This result suggests that effects on kinetics due to cross-bridge binding within functional groups are greater than effects due to near-neighbor interactions between functional groups. Nevertheless, both mechanisms contribute to activation kinetics, since it was necessary to add NEM-S1 and partially extract TnC to eliminate the activation dependence of <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub>.</p></sec><sec><title>Effects due to Partial Extraction of TnC and Treatment with NEM-S1.</title><p>Partial extraction of TnC or application of NEM-S1 has been shown to independently alter the Ca<sup>2+</sup> activation of force in skeletal muscle, effects that are additive or synergistic. When fibers were treated in either way, the steepness of the force-pCa relationship was reduced (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table </xref>), indicating a decrease in the apparent cooperativity of activation. Importantly, effects on steepness were much greater in fibers subjected to both interventions, i.e., extraction of 50% TnC and application of 6 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1, than with either alone. At present, we do not have a unique explanation for this result, but a simple model is one in which initial cross-bridge binding facilitates additional binding in the same and adjacent functional groups. In such a model, partial extraction of TnC would reduce steepness by disrupting near-neighbor interactions within the thin filament, and NEM-S1 would reduce steepness by cooperatively increasing the number of endogenous cross-bridges that bind within a functional group or in neighboring functional groups at each submaximal pCa.</p><p>The combination of TnC extraction and application of NEM-S1 also had greater effects on the activation dependence of <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> than either treatment alone. In fact, addition of 6 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1 to partially TnC-extracted fibers increased <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> to greater than maximal values at all levels of activation and completely eliminated the activation dependence of <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref> B). These results strongly suggest that the slowing of <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> observed in untreated fibers at low and intermediate levels of activation is due to cooperative binding of cross-bridges within the same and neighboring functional groups, and the acceleration of <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> at high levels of activation reflects a decrease in the importance of such cooperation. This conclusion is consistent with <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Campbell1997">Campbell 1997</xref> model of activation in which slowing of <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> at low levels of activation involves progressive cooperative recruitment of cross-bridges from noncycling to cycling states. However, to account for the effects of TnC extraction to accelerate <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub>, this model must be expanded to include near-neighbor effects, i.e., cross-bridge binding in one functional group seems to cooperatively activate adjacent functional groups and thereby induce further cross-bridge binding (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Razumovaetal2000">Razumova et al. 2000</xref>). In support of this idea, partial extraction of TnC was needed to completely eliminate the activation dependence of <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub>.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Consideration of Possible Artifacts in Experimental Measurements</title><p>Most measurements of <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> in the present study were done without sarcomere length control, which has been shown previously to result in underestimation of the rate constant by as much as 50% because of mechanical effects of end compliance at the points of attachment to the fiber (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Brenner1988">Brenner 1988</xref>). Such slowing, if undetected or variably present, could distort the results and affect our conclusions. Several lines of evidence suggest that this was not the case here. First, the mean maximum <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> obtained in control fibers (&#x0223c;14 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> was &#x0223c;80% of the value [&#x0223c;18 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>] obtained in an earlier study using sarcomere length control&#x0003b; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Metzgeretal1989">Metzger et al. 1989</xref>). The 10-fold variation in <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> is similar to that observed under sarcomere length control. Second, under conditions that eliminated the activation dependence of <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub>, i.e., NEM-S1 plus partial extraction of TnC, <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> was identical at all levels of activation regardless of force (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref> B), again indicating that variations in end compliance with developed force were not the basis for activation dependence of <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub>. Finally, in several fibers in which sarcomere length control was used, the effects of NEM-S1 on the activation dependence of <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> were similar with (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref>) and without (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref> A) sarcomere length control.</p><p>Another possibility is that NEM-S1 actually stiffens the fiber, thereby increasing <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> at each level of activation. We regard this as highly unlikely for a couple of reasons. First, in our previous measurement of <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Metzgeretal1989">Metzger et al. 1989</xref>), sarcomere length clamping at very low levels of activation (P/P<sub>o</sub> = 0.14, pCa 6.2) resulted in <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> values of &#x0223c;1 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. This is much lower than the values of <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> measured in the present study in the presence of NEM-S1 (&#x0223c;16 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) and with both NEM-S1 treatment and partial extraction of TnC (&#x0223c;19 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>). Second, treatment with NEM-S1 alone had no effect on <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> in maximally activated fibers (<italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> = &#x0223c;14 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), but NEM-S1 plus partial extraction of TnC increased <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> to &#x0223c;19 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>.</p></sec><sec><title>Implications of Results for Regulation of Force and the Kinetics of Force Development under Physiological Conditions</title><p>Our results support the idea that Ca<sup>2+</sup> activation of isometric force involves significant contributions due to cooperativity in cross-bridge binding (for most recent review see <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Gordonetal2000">Gordon et al. 2000</xref>), i.e., NEM-S1 increased the Ca<sup>2+</sup> sensitivity of force. The fact that partial extraction of TnC reduced the Ca<sup>2+</sup> sensitivity of force suggests that cooperation in cross-bridge binding occurs both within and between neighboring functional groups.</p><p>Our results also indicate that the Ca<sup>2+</sup> dependence of the kinetics of force development can be completely eliminated by a combination of strong-binding cross-bridges (treatment with NEM-S1) and disruption of near-neighbor cooperativity in the thin filament (partial extraction of TnC). Although it is tempting to conclude from these results that cross-bridge binding is the primary activator of cross-bridge kinetics, our results do not exclude the possibility that other mechanisms are operative under physiological conditions, where the number of strongly bound cross-bridges is certainly less than in our experiments with NEM-S1. In support of the this idea, <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> in control fibers did not increase substantially until Ca<sup>2+</sup>-activated isometric forces were greater than half-maximal (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref> A). Thus, it is possible in our experiments that strong binding cross-bridges in the form of NEM-S1 are such potent activators of the thin filament that other activating processes involving the effects of Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding to potential regulatory sites, such as regulatory light chain (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Diffeeetal1995">Diffee et al. 1995</xref>), are masked. Another possibility is that cross-bridge binding to the thin filament increases Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding affinity of TnC, and the resulting increase in Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding increases <italic>f<sub>app</sub></italic> (for review see <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Gordonetal2000">Gordon et al. 2000</xref>).</p><p>We also observed that the effects on <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> because of NEM-S1 alone were greater than the effects of TnC extraction alone. At first glance, this suggests that cooperativity in the activation of contraction is predominantly due to cross-bridge binding within functional groups, with much lesser contributions due to near-neighbor cooperation between adjacent functional groups. However, it must again be recognized that the addition of NEM-S1 in our experiments substantially increases the number of strong-binding cross-bridges above that normally found in skeletal muscle fibers under physiological conditions. Thus, it is likely that strong-binding cross-bridges are not as dominant in activating contraction in living muscles, and that near-neighbor mechanisms play a proportionately greater role than implied by our present results with NEM-S1. Our finding that partial extraction of TnC was required to completely eliminate the activation dependence of <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> is consistent with this conclusion.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors thank Chad Warren for the preparation of NEM-S1 and Dr. James Graham for SDS-PAGE analysis of the muscle fibers.</p><p>This study was supported by grant HL-54581 from the National Institutes of Health to R.L. Moss.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="BrandtandSchachat1997"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brandt</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schachat</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Troponin C modulates the activation of the thin filaments by rigor cross-bridges</article-title><source>Biophys. J.</source><volume>72</volume><year>1997</year><fpage>2262</fpage><lpage>2267</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9129829</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="Brandtetal1984"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brandt</surname><given-names>P.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Diamond</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schachat</surname><given-names>F.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The thin filament of vertebrate skeletal muscle co-operatively activates as a unit</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol.</source><volume>180</volume><year>1984</year><fpage>379</fpage><lpage>384</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6542594</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="Brandtetal1990"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brandt</surname><given-names>P.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roemer</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schachat</surname><given-names>F.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cooperative activation of skeletal muscle thin filaments by rigor crossbridgesthe effect of troponin C extraction</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol.</source><volume>212</volume><year>1990</year><fpage>473</fpage><lpage>480</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2325129</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="Brenner1988"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of Ca<sup>2+</sup> on cross-bridge turnover kinetics in skinned single rabbit psoas fibersimplications for regulation of muscle contraction</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA.</source><volume>85</volume><year>1988</year><fpage>3265</fpage><lpage>3269</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2966401</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="BrennerandEisenberg1986"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eisenberg</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rate of force generation in musclecorrelation with actomyosin ATPase activity in solution</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA.</source><volume>83</volume><year>1986</year><fpage>3542</fpage><lpage>3546</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2939452</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="BrennerandChalovich1999"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chalovich</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Kinetics of thin filament activation probed by fluorescence of N-((2-(iodoacetoxy)ethyl)-N-methyl)amino-7-nitrobenz-2-oxa-1,3-diazole-labeled troponin I incorporated into skinned fibers of rabbit psoas muscleImplications for regulation of muscle contraction</article-title><source>Biophys. J.</source><volume>77</volume><year>1999</year><fpage>2692</fpage><lpage>2708</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10545369</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="Campbell1997"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rate constant of muscle force redevelopment reflects cooperative activation as well as cross-bridge kinetics</article-title><source>Biophys. J.</source><volume>72</volume><year>1997</year><fpage>254</fpage><lpage>262</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8994610</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CampbellandMoss2000"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>K.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A thixotropic effect in contracting rabbit psoas muscleprior movement reduces the initial tension response to stretch</article-title><source>J. Physiol.</source><volume>525</volume><year>2000</year><fpage>531</fpage><lpage>548</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10835052</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="Diffeeetal1995"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Diffee</surname><given-names>G.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Greaser</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reinach</surname><given-names>F.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of a non-divalent cation binding mutant of myosin regulatory light chain on tension generation in skinned skeletal muscle fibers</article-title><source>Biophys. J.</source><volume>68</volume><year>1995</year><fpage>1443</fpage><lpage>1452</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7787030</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="Fabiato1988"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fabiato</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Computer programs for calculating total from specified free and free from specified total ionic concentrations in aqueous solutions containing multiple metals or ligands</article-title><source>Methods Enzymol.</source><volume>157</volume><year>1988</year><fpage>378</fpage><lpage>417</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3231093</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="GeevesandLehrer1994"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Geeves</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lehrer</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dynamics of the muscle thin filament regulatory switchthe size of the cooperative unit</article-title><source>Biophys. J.</source><volume>67</volume><year>1994</year><fpage>273</fpage><lpage>282</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7918995</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="GodtandLindley1982"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Godt</surname><given-names>R.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindley</surname><given-names>B.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of temperature upon contractile activation and isometric force production in mechanically skinned muscle fibers of the frog</article-title><source>J. Gen. Physiol.</source><volume>80</volume><year>1982</year><fpage>279</fpage><lpage>297</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6981684</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="Gordonetal2000"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Homsher</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Regnier</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of contraction in striated muscle</article-title><source>Physiol. Rev.</source><volume>80</volume><year>2000</year><fpage>853</fpage><lpage>924</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10747208</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="Grabareketal1992"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grabarek</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gergely</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular mechanism of troponin-C function</article-title><source>J. Muscle Res. Cell Motil.</source><volume>13</volume><year>1992</year><fpage>383</fpage><lpage>393</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1401036</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="Greeneetal1987"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greene</surname><given-names>L.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eisenberg</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of actomyosin ATPase activity by troponin-tropomyosineffect of the binding of the myosin subfragment 1 (S-1)-ATP complex</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA.</source><volume>84</volume><year>1987</year><fpage>3102</fpage><lpage>3106</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2953023</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="Hancocketal1997"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hancock</surname><given-names>W.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huntsman</surname><given-names>L.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Models of calcium activation account for differences between skeletal and cardiac force redevelopment kinetics</article-title><source>J. Muscle Res. Cell Motil.</source><volume>18</volume><year>1997</year><fpage>671</fpage><lpage>681</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9429160</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="Haselgrove1973"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haselgrove</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>X-ray evidence for a conformational change in actin-containing filaments of vertebrate striated muscle</article-title><source>Cold Spring Harbor Symp. Quant. Biol.</source><volume>37</volume><year>1973</year><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>234</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="Huxley1973"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huxley</surname><given-names>H.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural changes in actin- and myosin-containing filaments during contraction</article-title><source>Cold Spring Harbor Symp. Quant. Biol.</source><volume>37</volume><year>1973</year><fpage>361</fpage><lpage>376</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="LandesbergandSideman1994"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Landesberg</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sideman</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coupling calcium binding to troponin C and cross-bridge cycling in skinned cardiac cells</article-title><source>Am. J. Physiol.</source><volume>266</volume><year>1994</year><fpage>H1260</fpage><lpage>H1271</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8160831</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="Lehrer1994"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lehrer</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The regulatory switch of the muscle thin filamentCa<sup>2+</sup> or myosin heads</article-title><source>J. Muscle Res. Cell Motil.</source><volume>15</volume><year>1994</year><fpage>232</fpage><lpage>236</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7929789</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="McKillopandGeeves1993"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McKillop</surname><given-names>D.F.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Geeves</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of the interaction between actin and myosin subfragment 1evidence for three states of the thin filament</article-title><source>Biophys. J.</source><volume>65</volume><year>1993</year><fpage>693</fpage><lpage>701</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8218897</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="MetzgerandMoss1991"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Metzger</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Kinetics of a Ca<sup>2+</sup>-sensitive cross-bridge state transition in skeletal muscle fibers</article-title><source>J. Gen. Physiol.</source><volume>98</volume><year>1991</year><fpage>233</fpage><lpage>248</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1940850</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="Metzgeretal1989"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Metzger</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Greaser</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Variations in cross-bridge attachment rate and tension with phosphorylation of myosin in mammalian skinned skeletal muscle fibers</article-title><source>J. Gen. Physiol.</source><volume>93</volume><year>1989</year><fpage>855</fpage><lpage>883</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2661721</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="Moss1979"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sarcomere length-tension relations of frog skinned muscle fibers during calcium activation at short lengths</article-title><source>J. Physiol.</source><volume>292</volume><year>1979</year><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>202</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">314975</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="Moss1992"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ca<sup>2+</sup> regulation of mechanical properties of striated muscle</article-title><source>Circ. Res.</source><volume>70</volume><year>1992</year><fpage>865</fpage><lpage>884</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1348975</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="Mossetal1985"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giulian</surname><given-names>G.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Greaser</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effects of partial extraction of TnC upon the tension-pCa relationship in rabbit-skinned skeletal muscle fibers</article-title><source>J. Gen. Physiol.</source><volume>86</volume><year>1985</year><fpage>585</fpage><lpage>600</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4056736</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="PalmerandKentish1998"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kentish</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Roles of Ca<sup>2+</sup> and crossbridge kinetics in determining the maximum rates of Ca<sup>2+</sup> activation and relaxation in rat and guinea pig skinned trabeculae</article-title><source>Circ. Res.</source><volume>83</volume><year>1998</year><fpage>179</fpage><lpage>186</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9686757</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ParryandSquire1973"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parry</surname><given-names>D.A.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Squire</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural role of tropomyosin in muscle regulationanalysis of the x-ray patterns from relaxed and contracting muscles</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol.</source><volume>75</volume><year>1973</year><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4713300</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="Razumovaetal2000"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Razumova</surname><given-names>M.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bukatina</surname><given-names>A.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>K.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Different myofilament nearest-neighbor interactions have distinctive effects on contractile behavior</article-title><source>Biophys. J.</source><volume>78</volume><year>2000</year><fpage>3120</fpage><lpage>3137</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10827989</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="Regnieretal1998"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Regnier</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martyn</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chase</surname><given-names>P.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Calcium regulation of tension redevelopment kinetics with 2-deoxy-ATP or low [ATP] in skinned rabbit psoas fibers</article-title><source>Biophys. J.</source><volume>74</volume><year>1998</year><fpage>2005</fpage><lpage>2015</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9545059</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="Strangetal1994"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Strang</surname><given-names>K.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sweitzer</surname><given-names>N.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Greaser</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>&#x003b2;-Adrenergic receptor stimulation increases unloaded shortening velocity of skinned single ventricular myocytes from rats</article-title><source>Circ. Res.</source><volume>74</volume><year>1994</year><fpage>542</fpage><lpage>549</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8118962</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="SwartzandMoss1992"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Swartz</surname><given-names>D.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of a strong-binding myosin analogue on calcium-sensitive mechanical properties of skinned skeletal muscle fibers</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><volume>267</volume><year>1992</year><fpage>20497</fpage><lpage>20506</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1400367</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="Swartzetal1996"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Swartz</surname><given-names>D.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Greaser</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Calcium alone does not fully activate the thin filament for S1 binding to rigor myofibrils</article-title><source>Biophys. J.</source><volume>71</volume><year>1996</year><fpage>1891</fpage><lpage>1904</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8889164</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="SweitzerandMoss1993"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sweitzer</surname><given-names>N.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Determinants of loaded shortening velocity in single cardiac myocytes permeabilized with &#x003b1;-hemolysin</article-title><source>Circ. Res.</source><volume>73</volume><year>1993</year><fpage>1150</fpage><lpage>1162</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8222086</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="Williamsetal1984"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Greene</surname><given-names>L.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eisenberg</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of effects of smooth and skeletal muscle tropomyosins on interactions of actin and myosin subfragment 1</article-title><source>Biochemistry.</source><volume>23</volume><year>1984</year><fpage>4150</fpage><lpage>4155</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6487594</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="Williamsetal1988"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Greene</surname><given-names>L.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eisenberg</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cooperative turning on of myosin subfragment 1 adenosine triphosphatase activity by the troponin-tropomyosin-actin complex</article-title><source>Biochemistry.</source><volume>27</volume><year>1988</year><fpage>6987</fpage><lpage>6993</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2973810</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list><fn-group><fn><p><italic>Abbreviations used in this paper:</italic> NEM, <italic>N</italic>-ethylmaleimide&#x0003b; NEM-S1, NEM-modified myosin subfragment-1&#x0003b; TnC, troponin C.</p></fn></fn-group></back><floats-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Steady-state Mechanical Measurements in Skinned Single Psoas Fibers after Partial Tnc Extraction and Treatment with NEM-S1</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr valign="bottom" align="center"><th>Group</th><th>P<sub>o</sub></th><th/><th>P<sub>pCa9.0</sub></th><th>n<sub>2</sub></th><th>n<sub>1</sub></th><th>pCa<sub>50</sub></th><th>&#x00394;pCa<sub>50</sub></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr valign="bottom" align="center"><td/><td>mN/mm<sup>2</sup></td><td/><td>mN/mm<sup>2</sup></td><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left">Control (15)</td><td align="char" char=".">159.7 &#x000b1; 8.0</td><td align="center"/><td align="char" char=".">0.96 &#x000b1; 0.13</td><td align="char" char=".">7.25 &#x000b1; 0.44</td><td align="char" char=".">2.73 &#x000b1; 0.09</td><td align="char" char=".">5.97 &#x000b1; 0.01</td><td align="center"/></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left">(&#x02212;) TnC (15)</td><td align="char" char=".">65.3 &#x000b1; 3.7</td><td align="center"/><td align="char" char=".">0.78 &#x000b1; 0.09</td><td align="char" char=".">4.53 &#x000b1; 0.24</td><td align="char" char=".">2.31 &#x000b1; 0.11</td><td align="char" char=".">5.75 &#x000b1; 0.02</td><td align="char" char=".">0.22 &#x000b1; 0.03</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left">(&#x02212;) TnC/3 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1 (7)</td><td align="char" char=".">54.8 &#x000b1; 4.5</td><td align="center"/><td align="char" char=".">1.24 &#x000b1; 0.20</td><td align="char" char=".">3.21 &#x000b1; 0.16</td><td align="char" char=".">2.33 &#x000b1; 0.12</td><td align="char" char=".">5.76 &#x000b1; 0.02</td><td align="char" char=".">0.01 &#x000b1; 0.01</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left">(&#x02212;) TnC/6 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1 (8)</td><td align="char" char=".">55.6 &#x000b1; 3.5</td><td align="center"/><td align="char" char=".">5.86 &#x000b1; 0.50</td><td align="char" char=".">1.71 &#x000b1; 0.11</td><td align="char" char=".">2.14 &#x000b1; 0.21</td><td align="char" char=".">5.89 &#x000b1; 0.02</td><td align="char" char=".">0.15 &#x000b1; 0.01</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left">Control (18)</td><td align="char" char=".">165.1 &#x000b1; 6.4</td><td align="center"/><td align="char" char=".">0.74 &#x000b1; 0.11</td><td align="char" char=".">7.94 &#x000b1; 0.44</td><td align="char" char=".">2.76 &#x000b1; 0.08</td><td align="char" char=".">6.00 &#x000b1; 0.01</td><td align="center"/></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left">3 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1 (7)</td><td align="char" char=".">164.5 &#x000b1; 10.7</td><td align="center"/><td align="char" char=".">2.42 &#x000b1; 0.32</td><td align="char" char=".">4.63 &#x000b1; 0.22</td><td align="char" char=".">2.50 &#x000b1; 0.09</td><td align="char" char=".">6.04 &#x000b1; 0.02</td><td align="char" char=".">0.03 &#x000b1; 0.01</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left">6 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1 (8)</td><td align="char" char=".">149.2 &#x000b1; 3.9</td><td align="center"/><td align="char" char=".">8.78 &#x000b1; 1.04</td><td align="char" char=".">3.14 &#x000b1; 0.19</td><td align="char" char=".">2.42 &#x000b1; 0.10</td><td align="char" char=".">6.06 &#x000b1; 0.02</td><td align="char" char=".">0.07 &#x000b1; 0.01</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left">10 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1 (3)</td><td align="char" char=".">108.8 &#x000b1; 2.8</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="2" rowspan="1">12.45 &#x000b1; 1.01</td><td align="char" char=".">1.77 &#x000b1; 0.04</td><td align="char" char=".">2.14 &#x000b1; 0.26</td><td align="char" char=".">6.12 &#x000b1; 0.04</td><td align="char" char=".">0.12 &#x000b1; 0.03</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>All values are expressed as means &#x000b1; SEM, with the number of skeletal fibers given in parentheses. (&#x02212;) TnC, partial TnC extraction&#x0003b; P<sub>o</sub>, maximal Ca<sup>2</sup>+-activated tension measured in pCa 4.5&#x0003b; P<sub>pCa9.0</sub>, Ca<sup>2</sup>+-independent resting tension measured in oCa 9.0&#x0003b; n<sub>2</sub>, Hill coefficient for Ca<sup>2</sup>+-activated force &#x0003c;0.50 P<sub>o</sub>&#x0003b; n<sub>1</sub>, Hill coefficient for Ca<sup>2</sup>+-activated force &#x0003e;0.50 P<sub>o</sub>&#x0003b; pCa<sub>50</sub>, pCa required for half-maximal activation.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Summaries of k<sub>tr</sub> and Ca<sup>2</sup>+-activated Force at Maximal and Submaximal Concentrations of Ca<sup>2</sup>+ after Partial Tnc Extraction and Treatment with NEM-S1 in Skinned Psoas Fibers</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr valign="bottom" align="center"><th/><th>Control(15)</th><th>(&#x02212;) TnC (15)</th><th>(&#x02212;) TnC/3 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1 (7)</th><th>(&#x02212;) TnC/6 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1 (8)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left">pCa 4.5</td><td align="center"/><td align="center"/><td align="center"/><td align="center"/></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left"><italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub></td><td align="char" char=".">14.3 &#x000b1; 0.8</td><td align="char" char=".">14.8 &#x000b1; 0.4</td><td align="char" char=".">17.3 &#x000b1; 0.7</td><td align="char" char=".">18.7 &#x000b1; 0.5</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left">pCa 6.0</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="center"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left">P/P<sub>o</sub></td><td align="char" char=".">0.45 &#x000b1; 0.03</td><td align="char" char=".">0.14 &#x000b1; 0.01</td><td align="char" char=".">0.17 &#x000b1; 0.02</td><td align="char" char=".">0.37 &#x000b1; 0.01</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left"><italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub></td><td align="char" char=".">4.2 &#x000b1; 0.2</td><td align="char" char=".">3.2 &#x000b1; 0.2</td><td align="char" char=".">11.0 &#x000b1; 1.4</td><td align="char" char=".">18.9 &#x000b1; 1.0</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left">relative <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub></td><td align="char" char=".">0.30 &#x000b1; 0.02</td><td align="char" char=".">0.22 &#x000b1; 0.02</td><td align="char" char=".">0.63 &#x000b1; 0.06</td><td align="char" char=".">1.02 &#x000b1; 0.02</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left"/><td align="center">Control (18)</td><td align="center">3 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1 (7)</td><td align="center">6 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1 (8)</td><td align="center">10 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1 (3)</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left">pCa 4.5</td><td align="center"/><td align="center"/><td align="center"/><td align="center"/></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left"><italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub></td><td align="char" char=".">13.6 &#x000b1; 0.5</td><td align="char" char=".">13.5 &#x000b1; 0.7</td><td align="char" char=".">13.4 &#x000b1; 0.59</td><td align="char" char=".">13.2 &#x000b1; 0.7</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left">pCa6.1</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="center"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left">P/P<sub>o</sub></td><td align="char" char=".">0.27 &#x000b1; 0.02</td><td align="char" char=".">0.39 &#x000b1; 0.03</td><td align="char" char=".">0.45 &#x000b1; 0.02</td><td align="char" char=".">0.55 &#x000b1; 0.04</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left"><italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub></td><td align="char" char=".">1.9 &#x000b1; 0.1</td><td align="char" char=".">7.2 &#x000b1; 0.4</td><td align="char" char=".">9.5 &#x000b1; 0.6</td><td align="char" char=".">11.8 &#x000b1; 1.2</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left">relative <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub></td><td align="char" char=".">0.14 &#x000b1; 0.01</td><td align="char" char=".">0.56 &#x000b1; 0.05</td><td align="char" char=".">0.70 &#x000b1; 0.06</td><td align="char" char=".">0.88 &#x000b1; 0.01</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>All values are expressed as means &#x000b1; SEM, with the number of skeletal muscle fibers given in parentheses. (&#x02212;) TnC, partial TnC extraction&#x0003b; P/P<sub>o</sub>, relative Ca<sup>2</sup>+-activated force&#x0003b; <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub>, rate of tension redevelopment in seconds<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>&#x0003b; relative <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub>, the relative rate of force redevelopment. Both P/P<sub>o</sub> and relative <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> values obtained in pCa 6.0 and pCa 6.1 were normalized to maximal values in pCa 4.5 under the same conditions (i.e., partial TnC extraction, partial TnC extraction and NEM-S1 treatment, or NEM-S1 treatment).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Summaries of k<sub>tr</sub> in Solution of pCa after Partial TnC Extraction and Treatment with NEM-S1 in Skinned Psoas Fibers</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr valign="bottom" align="center"><th/><th>Control (15)</th><th>(&#x02212;) TnC (15)</th><th>(&#x02212;) TnC/3 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1 (7)</th><th>(&#x02212;) TnC/6 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1 (8)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left">pCa 4.5</td><td align="center"/><td align="center"/><td align="center"/><td align="center"/></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left"><italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub></td><td align="char" char=".">14.3 &#x000b1; 0.8</td><td align="char" char=".">14.8 &#x000b1; 0.4</td><td align="char" char=".">17.3 &#x000b1; 0.7</td><td align="char" char=".">18.7 &#x000b1; 0.5</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left">pCa 9.0</td><td align="center"/><td align="center"/><td align="center"/><td align="center"/></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left"><italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub></td><td align="center"/><td align="center"/><td align="center"/><td align="char" char=".">19.0 &#x000b1; 0.5</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left">relative <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub></td><td align="center"/><td align="center"/><td align="center"/><td align="char" char=".">1.02 &#x000b1; 0.04</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left"/><td align="center">Control (18)</td><td align="center">3 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1 (7)</td><td align="center">6 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1 (8)</td><td align="center">10 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1 (3)</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left">pCa 4.5</td><td align="center"/><td align="center"/><td align="center"/><td align="center"/></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left"><italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub></td><td align="char" char=".">13.6 &#x000b1; 0.5</td><td align="char" char=".">13.5 &#x000b1; 0.7</td><td align="char" char=".">13.4 &#x000b1; 0.59</td><td align="char" char=".">13.2 &#x000b1; 0.7</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left">pCa 9.0</td><td align="center"/><td align="char" char=".">18.4 &#x000b1; 1.0</td><td align="char" char=".">19.4 &#x000b1; 1.0</td><td align="char" char=".">18.2 &#x000b1; 0.8</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left"><italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub></td><td align="center"/><td align="char" char=".">1.34 &#x000b1; 0.12</td><td align="char" char=".">1.37 &#x000b1; 0.13</td><td align="char" char=".">1.39 &#x000b1; 0.04</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>All values are expressed as means &#x000b1; SEM, with the number of skeletal muscle fibers given in parentheses. (&#x02212;) TnC, partial TnC extraction&#x0003b; P/P<sub>o</sub>, relative Ca<sup>2</sup>+-activated force&#x0003b; <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub>, rate of tension redevelopment in seconds<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>&#x0003b; relative <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub>, the relative rate of force redevelopment. Relative <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> values obtained in pCa 9.0 were normalized to maximal values in pCa 4.5 under the same conditions (i.e., partial TnC extraction, partial TnC extraction and NEM-S1 treatment, or NEM-S1 treatment).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Double Exponential Phases of Force Redevelopment in Skinned Single Psoas Fibers after Partial TnC Extraction and Treatment with NEM-S1</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr valign="bottom" align="center"><th>Group</th><th>P/P<sub>o</sub></th><th>a</th><th><italic>k</italic><sub>1</sub></th><th>b</th><th><italic>k</italic><sub>2</sub></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left">Control (15)</td><td align="char" char=".">0.23 &#x000b1; 0.02</td><td align="char" char=".">0.48 &#x000b1; 0.08</td><td align="char" char=".">4.8 &#x000b1; 0.8</td><td align="char" char=".">0.56 &#x000b1; 0.06</td><td align="char" char=".">2.0 &#x000b1; 0.1</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left"/><td align="char" char=".">0.54 &#x000b1; 0.01</td><td align="char" char=".">0.63 &#x000b1; 0.08</td><td align="char" char=".">7.0 &#x000b1; 0.6</td><td align="char" char=".">0.46 &#x000b1; 0.07</td><td align="char" char=".">3.6 &#x000b1; 0.3</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left"/><td align="char" char=".">1.0</td><td align="char" char=".">0.74 &#x000b1; 0.01</td><td align="char" char=".">20.4 &#x000b1; 1.3</td><td align="char" char=".">0.25 &#x000b1; 0.01</td><td align="char" char=".">3.9 &#x000b1; 0.2</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left">(&#x02212;) TnC (15)</td><td align="char" char=".">0.22 &#x000b1; 0.02</td><td align="char" char=".">0.27 &#x000b1; 0.05</td><td align="char" char=".">10.9 &#x000b1; 1.0</td><td align="char" char=".">0.65 &#x000b1; 0.05</td><td align="char" char=".">2.8 &#x000b1; 0.2</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left"/><td align="char" char=".">0.54 &#x000b1; 0.01</td><td align="char" char=".">0.38 &#x000b1; 0.04</td><td align="char" char=".">17.3 &#x000b1; 1.7</td><td align="char" char=".">0.58 &#x000b1; 0.04</td><td align="char" char=".">4.3 &#x000b1; 0.3</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left"/><td align="char" char=".">1.0</td><td align="char" char=".">0.51 &#x000b1; 0.02</td><td align="char" char=".">28.8 &#x000b1; 1.7</td><td align="char" char=".">0.47 &#x000b1; 0.02</td><td align="char" char=".">6.1 &#x000b1; 0.3</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left">(&#x02212;) TnC/3 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1 (7)</td><td align="char" char=".">0.20 &#x000b1; 0.01</td><td align="char" char=".">0.45 &#x000b1; 0.02</td><td align="char" char=".">33.1 &#x000b1; 4.0</td><td align="char" char=".">0.44 &#x000b1; 0.03</td><td align="char" char=".">4.5 &#x000b1; 0.5</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left"/><td align="char" char=".">0.52 &#x000b1; 0.02</td><td align="char" char=".">0.39 &#x000b1; 0.03</td><td align="char" char=".">39.9 &#x000b1; 6.0</td><td align="char" char=".">0.57 &#x000b1; 0.03</td><td align="char" char=".">6.4 &#x000b1; 0.5</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left"/><td align="char" char=".">1.0</td><td align="char" char=".">0.46 &#x000b1; 0.03</td><td align="char" char=".">32.1 &#x000b1; 2.6</td><td align="char" char=".">0.52 &#x000b1; 0.02</td><td align="char" char=".">7.2 &#x000b1; 0.5</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left">(&#x02212;) TnC/6 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1 (8)</td><td align="char" char=".">0.21 &#x000b1; 0.01</td><td align="char" char=".">0.64 &#x000b1; 0.02</td><td align="char" char=".">37.0 &#x000b1; 4.1</td><td align="char" char=".">0.30 &#x000b1; 0.02</td><td align="char" char=".">4.6 &#x000b1; 0.5</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left"/><td align="char" char=".">0.51 &#x000b1; 0.01</td><td align="char" char=".">0.61 &#x000b1; 0.02</td><td align="char" char=".">35.1 &#x000b1; 3.1</td><td align="char" char=".">0.36 &#x000b1; 0.02</td><td align="char" char=".">5.0 &#x000b1; 0.5</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left"/><td align="char" char=".">1.0</td><td align="char" char=".">0.63 &#x000b1; 0.01</td><td align="char" char=".">32.3 &#x000b1; 1.3</td><td align="char" char=".">0.36 &#x000b1; 0.01</td><td align="char" char=".">5.8 &#x000b1; 0.4</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left">Control (18)</td><td align="char" char=".">0.25 &#x000b1; 0.02</td><td align="char" char=".">0.52 &#x000b1; 0.09</td><td align="char" char=".">2.2 &#x000b1; 0.1</td><td align="char" char=".">0.46 &#x000b1; 0.08</td><td align="char" char=".">1.9 &#x000b1; 0.1</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left"/><td align="char" char=".">0.58 &#x000b1; 0.02</td><td align="char" char=".">0.47 &#x000b1; 0.10</td><td align="char" char=".">8.3 &#x000b1; 0.8</td><td align="char" char=".">0.67 &#x000b1; 0.08</td><td align="char" char=".">4.3 &#x000b1; 0.3</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left"/><td align="char" char=".">1.0</td><td align="char" char=".">0.73 &#x000b1; 0.01</td><td align="char" char=".">19.3 &#x000b1; 1.0</td><td align="char" char=".">0.26 &#x000b1; 0.01</td><td align="char" char=".">3.9 &#x000b1; 0.2</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left">3 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1 (7)</td><td align="char" char=".">0.26 &#x000b1; 0.02</td><td align="char" char=".">0.35 &#x000b1; 0.02</td><td align="char" char=".">28.7 &#x000b1; 3.5</td><td align="char" char=".">0.62 &#x000b1; 0.04</td><td align="char" char=".">4.3 &#x000b1; 0.4</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left"/><td align="char" char=".">0.52 &#x000b1; 0.03</td><td align="char" char=".">0.26 &#x000b1; 0.03</td><td align="char" char=".">27.9 &#x000b1; 3.3</td><td align="char" char=".">0.73 &#x000b1; 0.03</td><td align="char" char=".">5.3 &#x000b1; 0.4</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left"/><td align="char" char=".">1.0</td><td align="char" char=".">0.72 &#x000b1; 0.01</td><td align="char" char=".">18.7 &#x000b1; 1.0</td><td align="char" char=".">0.28 &#x000b1; 0.01</td><td align="char" char=".">3.6 &#x000b1; 0.2</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left">6 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1 (8)</td><td align="char" char=".">0.27 &#x000b1; 0.01</td><td align="char" char=".">0.64 &#x000b1; 0.03</td><td align="char" char=".">25.5 &#x000b1; 2.5</td><td align="char" char=".">0.34 &#x000b1; 0.03</td><td align="char" char=".">4.4 &#x000b1; 0.5</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left"/><td align="char" char=".">0.47 &#x000b1; 0.02</td><td align="char" char=".">0.48 &#x000b1; 0.04</td><td align="char" char=".">27.1 &#x000b1; 3.0</td><td align="char" char=".">0.50 &#x000b1; 0.03</td><td align="char" char=".">5.2 &#x000b1; 0.8</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left"/><td align="char" char=".">1.0</td><td align="char" char=".">0.74 &#x000b1; 0.01</td><td align="char" char=".">21.0 &#x000b1; 0.01</td><td align="char" char=".">0.26 &#x000b1; 0.01</td><td align="char" char=".">3.9 &#x000b1; 0.3</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left">10 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1 (3)</td><td align="char" char=".">0.20 &#x000b1; 0.02</td><td align="char" char=".">0.71 &#x000b1; 0.01</td><td align="char" char=".">22.0 &#x000b1; 0.8</td><td align="char" char=".">0.27 &#x000b1; 0.01</td><td align="char" char=".">3.2 &#x000b1; 0.2</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left"/><td align="char" char=".">0.52 &#x000b1; 0.01</td><td align="char" char=".">0.59 &#x000b1; 0.01</td><td align="char" char=".">21.8 &#x000b1; 2.2</td><td align="char" char=".">0.40 &#x000b1; 0.01</td><td align="char" char=".">3.9 &#x000b1; 0.4</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left"/><td align="char" char=".">1.0</td><td align="char" char=".">0.74 &#x000b1; 0.01</td><td align="char" char=".">18.7 &#x000b1; 1.2</td><td align="char" char=".">0.25 &#x000b1; 0.01</td><td align="char" char=".">3.3 &#x000b1; 0.1</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>All values are expressed as means &#x000b1; SEM, with the number of skeletal muscle fibers given in parentheses. Force redevelopment traces were fit with a double exponential equation, y = a&#x000b7;exp(&#x02212;<italic>k</italic><sub>1</sub> &#x000b7; x) + b&#x000b7;exp(&#x02212;<italic>k</italic><sub>2</sub>&#x000b7; x), where a is the amplitude of the first exponential phase that rises with a rate constant of <italic>k</italic><sub>1</sub> and b is the amplitude of the second exponential phase that rises with a rate constant of <italic>k</italic><sub>2</sub>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Force redevelopment traces in a skinned psoas fiber at maximal and submaximal levels of Ca<sup>2+</sup> activation. (Top) Depicts the mechanical release-restretch maneuver imposed on a skinned psoas fiber to determine the rate constant of force redevelopment (<italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub>). The length change was sufficient to slacken the fiber, so that shortening velocity was maximal. (Bottom) Changes in submaximal force in solutions of pCa 6.1 (trace b) and pCa 6.0 (trace c) in a skinned psoas fiber under control conditions. The change in force is expressed relative to the maximum force (P<sub>o</sub>) generated by the same fiber under control conditions when exposed to a solution of pCa 4.5 (trace a). The solid lines are exponential fits to the data: single exponentials were adequate for fits at low and intermediate [Ca<sup>2+</sup>], whereas two exponentials were required for fits at maximal [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]. These fits are for illustrative purposes only, as <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> was calculated in each case from the half-time of tension rise, as described in <sc>materials and methods</sc>. <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">Table </xref> summarizes the double exponential fits at low, intermediate, and high levels of activation.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JGP8209.f1"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Effect of partial TnC extraction and NEM-S1 treatment on resting tension. Values are mean &#x000b1; SEM, with numbers of fibers per treatment listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table </xref>. (&#x02212;) TnC indicates partial TnC extraction. (Asterisk) Statistical difference experimental groups versus appropriate control groups, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JGP8209.f2"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Effect of NEM-S1 on the force-pCa relationships in skinned psoas fibers. Values are means &#x000b1; SEM. Fiber characteristics are listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table </xref>. (A) Force-pCa relationships were determined in control fibers and in the same fibers after exposure to NEM-S1. Smooth lines were generated by fitting the mean data with the Hill equation: P/P<sub>o</sub> = [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sup>n</sup>/(<italic>k</italic><sup>n</sup> + [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sup>n</sup>), where n is the Hill coefficient, and <italic>k</italic> is the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] required for half-maximal activation (i.e., pCa<sub>50</sub>). pCa<sub>50</sub> values from skinned fibers in the absence and presence of NEM-S1 were as follows: control (&#x02022;), 6.00 &#x000b1; 0.01&#x0003b; 3 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1 (&#x025a1;), 6.04 &#x000b1; 0.02&#x0003b; 6 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1 (&#x025be;), 6.06 &#x000b1; 0.02&#x0003b; and 10 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1 (&#x025b5;), 6.12 &#x000b1; 0.04. (B) Hill plot transformations of the tension-pCa data were generated using the following equation: log[P<sub>rel</sub>/(1 &#x02212; P<sub>rel</sub>)] = n(log[Ca<sup>2+</sup>] + <italic>k</italic>), where P<sub>rel</sub> is force as a fraction of P<sub>o</sub>, n is the Hill coefficient, and <italic>k</italic> is the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] required for half-maximal activation (i.e., pCa<sub>50</sub>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JGP8209.f3"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Troponin C content of single psoas fibers after partial extraction of TnC. 12% SDS-PAGE of single-skinned psoas fibers before TnC extraction (lane 1), after partial TnC extraction (lanes 2 and 3), and after readdition of skeletal TnC to a TnC-extracted fiber (lane 4). To quantify the amount of TnC extracted, the ratio [TnC/(LC<sub>1</sub> + LC<sub>2</sub>)] was determined for control, extracted, and reconstituted fiber segments by measuring the areas under the densitometric peaks corresponding to these proteins. The ratios from extracted and reconstituted fiber segments were divided by the ratio from a control segment of the same fiber to determine TnC content. Approximately 50% of endogenous TnC was extracted (lane 2 and 3) from these fibers, whereas readdition of skeletal TnC was stoichiometric (lane 4). Comparisons of the [MLC<sub>2</sub>/(MLC<sub>1</sub> + MLC<sub>3</sub>)] ratios revealed no alterations in MLC<sub>2</sub> content after partial TnC extraction.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JGP8209.f4"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Effects of partial TnC extraction and NEM-S1 on force-pCa relationships in skinned psoas fibers. Values are means &#x000b1; SEM. Force-pCa relationships were determined in control fibers and then in the same fibers after treatment with NEM-S1. Smooth lines were generated by fitting the mean data with the Hill equation: P/P<sub>o</sub> = [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sup>n</sup>/(<italic>k</italic><sup>n</sup> + [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sup>n</sup>), where n is the Hill coefficient, and <italic>k</italic> is the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] required for half-maximal activation (i.e., pCa<sub>50</sub>). pCa<sub>50</sub> values from skinned fibers under control conditions, after partial TnC extraction ((&#x02212;) TnC) and after partial TnC and NEM-S1 treatment were as follows: control (&#x02022;), 5.97 &#x000b1; 0.01&#x0003b; (&#x02212;) TnC (&#x025a1;), 5.75 &#x000b1; 0.02&#x0003b; (&#x02212;) TnC/3 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1 (&#x025bf;), 5.76 &#x000b1; 0.02&#x0003b; and (&#x02212;) TnC / 6 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1 (&#x025b4;), 5.89 &#x000b1; 0.02. Fiber characteristics are listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table </xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JGP8209.f5"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Effects of reduced cooperativity of activation on the rate of force redevelopment. Differences in the rate constant of force redevelopment (<italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub>) were expressed relative to respective peak forces. (A) The rates of force redevelopment at pCa 6.1 in skinned psoas fibers in the absence (trace a, P/P<sub>o</sub> = 0.20, <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> = 2.2 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) and presence of 3 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1, (trace b, P/P<sub>o</sub> = 0.41, <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> = 7.1 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), 6 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1 (trace c, P/P<sub>o</sub> = 0.47, <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> = 12.6 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), or 10 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1 (trace d, P/P<sub>o</sub> = 0.53, <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> = 14.1 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>). Maximal <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> was 15.1 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> for the fiber in traces a and c, 15.8 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> for the fiber in trace b, and 15.4 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> for the fiber in trace d. (B) The rates of force redevelopment in skinned psoas fibers incubated in solutions of pCa 4.5 (trace a, P/P<sub>o</sub> = 1.0, <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> = 11.4 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) and pCa 5.9 under control conditions (trace b, P/P<sub>o</sub> = 0.64, <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> = 5.9 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), after partial TnC extraction (trace c, P/P<sub>o</sub> = 0.32, <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> = 5.1 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), and after the combined treatment of partial TnC extraction and 6 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1 (trace d, P/P<sub>o</sub> = 0.48, <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> = 18.7 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>). The relative force values obtained at pCa 5.9 were normalized to 1.0 to allow comparisons between the various experimental conditions, i.e., control, TnC-extracted or TnC-extracted/NEM-S1.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JGP8209.f6"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F7"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Alteration in the activation dependence of the rate of force redevelopment after partial extraction of TnC and treatment with NEM-S1. Force redevelopment following the release-restretch mechanical maneuver was recorded as a function of relative steady-state isometric force (P/P<sub>o</sub>) developed before the maneuver. All values are means &#x000b1; SEM. (A) NEM-S1&#x02013;induced effects on the force dependence of <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> in the absence (&#x02022;) and presence of 3 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1 (&#x025a1;), 6 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1 (&#x025be;), and 10 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1 (&#x025b5;). (B) Force dependence of <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> in fibers under control conditions (&#x02022;), after partial TnC extraction (&#x025a1;), partial TnC extraction, and after treatment with 3 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1 (&#x025bf;), and partial TnC extraction and treatment with 6 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1 (&#x025b4;).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JGP8209.f7"/></fig><fig id="F8"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Effects of NEM-S1 on the rate of force redevelopment measured under sarcomere length control. (A) Force redevelopment records from a single psoas fiber during maximal (pCa 4.5) and submaximal (pCa 6.1) levels of Ca<sup>2+</sup> activation and under either sarcomere length or fiber length control. Sarcomere length control was done as described previously by <xref ref-type="bib" rid="CampbellandMoss2000">Campbell and Moss 2000</xref>. (B) Plot showing the activation dependence of <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> measured in an untreated control fiber without (&#x025cb;) and with (&#x02022;) sarcomere length control. (C) Plot showing the activation dependence of <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> measured in a fiber after treatment with 3 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1, both without (&#x025cb;) and with (&#x02022;) sarcomere length control.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JGP8209.f8a"/><graphic xlink:href="JGP8209.f8b"/><graphic xlink:href="JGP8209.f8c"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F9"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p>Force redevelopment time course at pCa 9.0 in NEM-S1&#x02013;treated fiber. Ca<sup>2+</sup>-independent force and force redevelopment in a representative skinned psoas fiber in skinned single fibers in the absence (trace a) and presence of 10 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1 (trace b). Force at pCa 4.5 (P<sub>o</sub>) in the absence of NEM-S1 was 139 mN/mm<sup>2</sup>&#x0003b; <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> under the same conditions was 12.8 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. Ca<sup>2+</sup>-independent force in the absence of NEM-S1 was 0.8% P<sub>o</sub>&#x0003b; Ca<sup>2+</sup>-independent force in the presence of NEM-S1 was 8.5% P<sub>o</sub>&#x0003b; <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> in the presence of NEM-S1 was 19.3 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JGP8209.f9"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F10"><label>Figure 10</label><caption><p>Effects of variable extraction of TnC on the activation dependence of <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub>. The relationship between <italic>k</italic><sub>tr</sub> and the relative force is presented for two distinct fibers, 2801B (open symbols) and 2901B (closed symbols), under control conditions (&#x025cb;, &#x02022;) after partial TnC extraction (&#x025a1;, &#x025aa;), and after partial TnC extraction and treatment with 6 &#x003bc;M NEM-S1 (&#x025b5;, &#x025b4;). Varying the extent of TnC extraction (by reducing the incubation time in extracting solution) reduced the maximal force to 0.15 P<sub>o</sub> in fiber 2801B and to 0.65 P<sub>o</sub> in fiber 2901B.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JGP8209.f10"/></fig></floats-wrap></article>


