<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">mBio</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">MBio</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">mbio</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">mbio</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">mBio</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>mBio</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2150-7511</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Society of Microbiology</publisher-name><publisher-loc>1752 N St., N.W., Washington, DC</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26060277</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4462621</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">mBio00775-15</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mBio.00775-15</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Genome-Wide Identification of <italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> Fitness Genes during Lung Infection</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head"><italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> Fitness in Lung Infection</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="short-authors">Bachman et al.</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-2507-6987</contrib-id><name><surname>Bachman</surname><given-names>Michael A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>a</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Breen</surname><given-names>Paul</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>a</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Deornellas</surname><given-names>Valerie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>b</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mu</surname><given-names>Qiao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>a</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Lili</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>c</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Weisheng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>d</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cavalcoli</surname><given-names>James D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>e</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mobley</surname><given-names>Harry L. T.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>b</sup></xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label><sup>a</sup></label><addr-line>Department of Pathology, School of Medicine, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, Michigan, USA</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff2"><label><sup>b</sup></label><addr-line>Department of Microbiology and Immunology, School of Medicine, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, Michigan, USA</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff3"><label><sup>c</sup></label><addr-line>Department of Biostatistics, School of Public Heath, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, Michigan, USA</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff4"><label><sup>d</sup></label><addr-line>BRCF Bioinformatics Core, School of Medicine, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, Michigan, USA</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff5"><label><sup>e</sup></label><addr-line>Department of Computational Medicine and Bioinformatics, School of Medicine, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, Michigan, USA</addr-line></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Gilmore</surname><given-names>Michael S.</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><aff>Harvard Medical School</aff></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Address correspondence to Michael A. Bachman, <email>mikebach@umich.edu</email>.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>9</day><month>6</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><season>May-Jun</season><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>3</issue><elocation-id>e00775-15</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>8</day><month>5</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>5</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2015 Bachman et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Bachman et al.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported license</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="mbo003152358001.pdf"/><abstract><title>ABSTRACT</title><p><italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> is an urgent public health threat because of resistance to carbapenems, antibiotics of last resort against Gram-negative bacterial infections. Despite the fact that <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> is a leading cause of pneumonia in hospitalized patients, the bacterial factors required to cause disease are poorly understood. Insertion site sequencing combines transposon mutagenesis with high-throughput sequencing to simultaneously screen thousands of insertion mutants for fitness defects during infection. Using the recently sequenced <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> strain KPPR1 in a well-established mouse model of pneumonia, insertion site sequencing was performed on a pool of &#x0003e;25,000 transposon mutants. The relative fitness requirement of each gene was ranked based on the ratio of lung to inoculum read counts and concordance between insertions in the same gene. This analysis revealed over 300 mutants with at least a 2-fold fitness defect and 69 with defects ranging from 10- to &#x0003e;2,000-fold. Construction of 6 isogenic mutants for use in competitive infections with the wild type confirmed their requirement for lung fitness. Critical fitness genes included those for the synthesis of branched-chain and aromatic amino acids that are essential in mice and humans, the transcriptional elongation factor RfaH, and the copper efflux pump CopA<italic>.</italic> The majority of fitness genes were conserved among reference strains representative of diverse pathotypes. These results indicate that regulation of outer membrane components and synthesis of amino acids that are essential to its host are critical for <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> fitness in the lung.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="executive-summary"><title>IMPORTANCE</title><p><italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> is a bacterium that commonly causes pneumonia in patients after they are admitted to the hospital. <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> is becoming resistant to all available antibiotics, and when these infections spread to the bloodstream, over half of patients die. Since currently available antibiotics are failing, we must discover new ways to treat these infections. In this study, we asked what genes the bacterium needs to cause an infection, since the proteins encoded by these genes could be targets for new antibiotics. We identified over 300 genes that <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> requires to grow in a mouse model of pneumonia. Many of the genes that we identified are found in <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> isolates from throughout the world, including antibiotic-resistant forms. If new antibiotics could be made against the proteins that these genes encode, they may be broadly effective against <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae.</italic></p></abstract><counts><count count-type="supplementary-material" count="8"/><fig-count count="8"/><table-count count="1"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="39"/><page-count count="9"/><word-count count="8337"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>May/June 2015</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="h0.0"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p><italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> is a pathogenic Gram-negative bacterium that is a member of the <italic>Enterobacteriaceae</italic> family. While the bacterium is normally found in the flora of human skin, mouth, and intestinal tract, it is also well characterized as an opportunistic pathogen (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> infections are associated with hospitalized patients with a weakened immune system. The bacterium causes a wide range of human diseases that include urinary tract infections, pyogenic liver abscess (PLA), and pneumonia (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). Due to the alarming increase in carbapenem-resistant <italic>Enterobacteriaceae</italic> (CRE), of which <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> comprises the majority of infections, the Centers for Disease Control (CDC) have designated these bacteria as an urgent threat to public health (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>).</p><p>Because of the decreasing efficacy of antibiotics against <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic>, new treatment modalities must be developed, and a promising approach is through identifying bacterial factors required to cause disease. The few virulence factors identified to date include capsule and lipopolysaccharide (LPS), which vary by structure and serotype, and adhesins and siderophores, which vary in frequency among clinical isolates (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">&#x02013;</xref><xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). To develop novel therapies that will be broadly effective against <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic>, conserved targets must be identified.</p><p>Barriers to identifying new <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> virulence factors include limitations with genetic sequencing techniques and the difficulties in manipulating the <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> chromosome. In recent years, newer approaches such as transposon insertion site sequencing (InSeq) have allowed for greatly enhanced genetic screening. This method uses high-throughput sequencing to determine the frequency and chromosomal location of thousands of transposon mutations from a large pool of mutants in a single experiment (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>).</p><p>InSeq requires a fully sequenced genome and confirmation of mutant phenotypes by either simultaneously constructing an indexed transposon mutant library or constructing mutants in selected genes that elicit fitness defects. Because of advances in genetic sequencing, a number of high-quality reference sequences of <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> are now available (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">&#x02013;</xref><xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). However, many of the standard methods for gene replacement in <italic>Escherichia&#x000a0;coli</italic>, such as suicide vector conjugation and linear DNA homologous recombination, are less efficient in <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> or are complicated by intrinsic and acquired antibiotic resistance (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). The Lambda Red recombinase system, which is incredibly efficient in <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>), could greatly increase the efficiency of gene recombination in <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). These advances now provide the ability to rigorously screen the genome for novel genes that contribute to virulence or <italic>in vivo</italic> fitness. Using this new sequencing approach and the Lambda Red recombinase system, we have identified numerous novel <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> fitness genes required to infect the lung in a mouse model of pneumonia.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="h1"><title>RESULTS</title><sec id="s1.1"><title>Transposon library construction, inoculation, and validation.</title><p><italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> KPPR1 causes acute pneumonia complicated by bacteremia in a well-established murine model (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). To facilitate InSeq analysis, the KPPR1 genome was sequenced to generate a single, gapless contig and the genes contained in it were annotated (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). The genome contains 5,191 predicted genes, including 25 rRNA, 85 tRNA, and 5,081 protein-coding sequences. To identify fitness factors required during lung infection, a library of ~25,000 transposon mutants was constructed to provide 99% genome coverage. Colony PCR and Southern blotting of representative transconjugants indicated that the library contained single, random transposon insertions at varied locations in the chromosome without integration of the vector (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="figS1">Fig.&#x000a0;S1</xref> in the supplemental material). This library was inoculated into mice using an aspiration model of pneumonia at a dose of 1.4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup>&#x000a0;CFU (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). After 24&#x000a0;h, the mean bacterial density increased to 5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup>&#x000a0;CFU in the lung (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig.&#x000a0;1A</xref>). To quantify and map each transposon onto the chromosome, genomic DNA was extracted from the inoculum and lung homogenates, and transposon junction fragments were generated. These fragments were sequenced using an Illumina HiSeq2500 instrument, mapped to the chromosome, and enumerated based on read count (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). Each sample had at least 68 million reads corresponding to 25,346 unique transposon insertions within genes (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="tabS1">Table&#x000a0;S1</xref>), meeting the coverage goal as stated above. Of 5,191 predicted genes, 4,312 had at least one insertion detected, whereas 879 genes did not. Because the transconjugants were required to grow to a colony for inclusion in the library, genes without insertions may be essential. However, a larger mutagenesis library would be required to estimate more precisely the number of essential genes (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>).</p><fig id="fig1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIG&#x000a0;1&#x000a0;</label><caption><p>InSeq analysis indicates that fitness genes are important during pneumonia based on differential transposon read counts between the inoculum and mouse lung. Mice (<italic>n</italic> = 5) inoculated with 1.4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup>&#x000a0;CFU of a pool of ~25,000 transposon mutants for 24&#x000a0;h were sacrificed and cultured on LB agar for CFU (A) or for DNA extraction, Illumina sequencing of transposon junctions, and read alignment with the KPPR1 genome to map and count transposon insertions. The locations and frequencies of transposon insertions in <italic>ilvD</italic> (B) and <italic>VK055_468</italic> (C) are shown.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="mbo0031523580001"/></fig></sec><sec id="s1.2"><title>InSeq analysis identifies hundreds of potential <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> lung fitness factors.</title><p>To identify <italic>in vivo</italic> fitness genes, the numbers of transposon insertion reads within each gene were compared between the lung and inoculum pools. Of genes with insertions, 3,880 had at least one shared transposon between the inoculum and lung samples (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="dataS1">Data Set&#x000a0;S1</xref> in the supplemental material) and were used for subsequent analysis. Since input and output data are &#x0201c;paired&#x0201d; in nature for each insertion, a <italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;value was calculated for each insertion using an exact Poisson test and then combined into a single <italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;value for each gene using Fisher&#x02019;s method. This method is similar to an approach called CEDER, which uses information from each exon of a eukaryotic gene to determine if there is consistent differential expression in RNA transcriptome sequencing (RNA-Seq) data for a given gene (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). Therefore, we call this <italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;value a CEDER <italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;value. Genes were sorted based on their fitness factor (total insertion counts in the inoculum/total insertion counts in the lung) and their CEDER <italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;value (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="dataS3">Data Set&#x000a0;S3</xref>). Inspection of transposon numbers and counts in individual genes suggested that the CEDER <italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;value could be used as a selection criterion for true-positive results of identification of fitness genes by InSeq. For example, <italic>ilvD</italic>, required for branched-chain amino acid (BCAA) synthesis, had a <italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;value of 0 based on 18 insertions in the input and 13 in the lung with 11 shared insertions having an average fitness factor of 192 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig.&#x000a0;1B</xref>). In contrast, <italic>VK055_468</italic>, a putative transcriptional regulatory gene, had a CEDER <italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;value of 2e&#x02212;14 based on a 186-fold fitness factor but only one insertion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig.&#x000a0;1C</xref>).</p><p>To confirm fitness defects and test the predictive power of CEDER, seven potential fitness genes identified by InSeq analysis were selected for experimental validation by coinfection. Six genes (<italic>rfaH</italic>, <italic>ilvC</italic>, <italic>ilvD</italic>, <italic>copA</italic>, <italic>aroE</italic>, and <italic>VK055_4417</italic>) with a CEDER <italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;value of 0 and a fitness factor of &#x0003e;10 were tested compared to <italic>VK055_468</italic> (<italic>P</italic> = 2e&#x02212;14; fitness factor of 168). These genes were mutated using Lambda Red recombinase to replace the entire coding sequence with a kanamycin resistance gene (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). Mice were then infected as described in Materials and Methods, but with a 1:1 ratio of the wild type (WT) and each mutant. Based on the bacterial density of each strain after 24&#x000a0;h, the competitive index was calculated. All six mutants with a CEDER <italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;value of 0 had a fitness defect in the lung compared to the wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>), ranging from 1.4-fold (<italic>VK055_4417</italic>) to 11,694-fold (<italic>rfaH</italic>). In contrast, <italic>VK055_468</italic> did not have a fitness defect compared to the wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>). Therefore, genes with a CEDER <italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;value of &#x0003e;0 were not characterized further. In total, 1272 genes had a <italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;value of 0 (top 25 shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tab1">Table&#x000a0;1</xref>), including 69 genes with a fitness factor of &#x0003e;10 and 333 genes with a fitness factor of &#x0003e;2. There were also 452 genes with a fitness factor of &#x0003c;0.5 and 97 genes with a fitness factor of &#x0003c;0.1, suggesting that insertion mutants increase lung fitness. Since the goal of the study was to identify mutants with decreased lung fitness, mutants overrepresented in the lung were not pursued further.</p><fig id="fig2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIG&#x000a0;2&#x000a0;</label><caption><p>Competitive infection against the wild-type strain confirms the fitness defect of mutants selected by InSeq. Insertion-deletion mutants of six genes selected and one gene not selected by CEDER analysis (<italic>VK055_468</italic>) of InSeq fitness were constructed using Lambda Red recombinase and used to coinfect mouse lungs with the wild type (WT), or WT carrying pACYC184 where noted, at a 1:1 ratio in a total inoculum of 1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup>&#x000a0;CFU. Mean competitive index (log<sub>10</sub>) for each mutant compared to the wild type at 24&#x000a0;h is shown. *, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05; **, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01; ***, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001, by one-sample <italic>t</italic>&#x000a0;test on log<sub>10</sub>-transformed data (&#x02265;4 mice per group); ###, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001 by two-sample <italic>t</italic>&#x000a0;test.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="mbo0031523580002"/></fig><table-wrap id="tab1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>TABLE&#x000a0;1&#x000a0;</label><caption><p>Top 25 <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> KPPR1 lung fitness genes<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="ngtab1.1"><sup>a</sup></xref></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Locus ID (<italic>VK055</italic>_<italic>x</italic>)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Product</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ratio (input/lung)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>5014</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Capsule assembly Wzi family protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2820.95</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>3141</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>rfaH</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Transcriptional activator</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2696.77</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>5096</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2486.08</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>3202</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>ilvC</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Ketol-acid reductoisomerase</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2248.61</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>3832</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>argR</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arginine repressor</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1140.74</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>5025</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Undecaprenyl-phosphate glucose phosphotransferase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">840.55</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>5012</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>galF</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regulatory protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">704.99</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>3206</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ilvE</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Branched-chain amino acid aminotransferase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">581.10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>3515</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rhodanese-like domain protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">508.09</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>4417</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>MarR family protein</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>442.14</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>4811</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>purF</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amidophosphoribosyltransferase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">378.16</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>4619</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>purL</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phosphoribosylformylglycinamidine synthase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">312.03</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>1194</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>trpD</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anthranilate synthase component II</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">301.31</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>4135</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>serA</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><sc>d</sc>-3-Phosphoglycerate dehydrogenase; provisional</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">248.61</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>2495</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>leuC</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3-Isopropylmalate isomerase subunit, dehydratase component</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">246.77</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>3142</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>tatC</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Twin arginine-targeting protein translocase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">219.96</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>3205</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>ilvD</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Dihydroxy acid dehydratase</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>203.61</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>5023</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">172.11</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>4883</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>rcsB</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transcriptional regulator</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">126.39</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>2215</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>phoR</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phosphate regulon sensor kinase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">110.92</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>4579</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>pheA</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bifunctional chorismate mutase/prephenate dehydratase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.55</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>3368</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2-Oxo-3-deoxygalactonate 6-phosphate aldolase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>2084</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>copA</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Copper-translocating P-type ATPase</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>69.70</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>3086</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>purH</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phosphoribosylaminoimidazole carboxamide formyltransferase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.84</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>3791</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>aroE</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Dehydroshikimate reductase</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>61.93</bold></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="ngtab1.1"><label><sup>a</sup></label><p>Experimentally validated genes are shown in boldface.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s1.3"><title><italic>rfaH</italic> is required for serum resistance.</title><p>RfaH is an antiterminator that specifically promotes the transcription of long virulence operons, including capsule and lipopolysaccharide (LPS) synthesis genes, in <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> and <italic>Salmonella enterica</italic> serotype Typhimurium (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">&#x02013;</xref><xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). In KPPR1, an <italic>rfaH</italic> mutant is severely attenuated in the lung (&#x0003e;10,000-fold compared to wild type), and the fitness of the mutant is significantly restored by complementation with the <italic>rfaH</italic> gene ligated into pACYC184 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>). This mutant forms a small colony compared to the wild type, suggesting a defect in capsule biosynthesis. Indeed, India ink staining of bacteria delineated copious capsule in KPPR1 but no visible capsule in the <italic>rfaH</italic> mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig.&#x000a0;3A and B</xref>). To assess mucoviscosity, a phenotype associated with hypervirulent capsular serotypes in <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> clinical isolates, low-speed centrifugation was performed and the optical density of the supernatant was measured (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). Whereas the wild-type suspension remained turbid, the <italic>rfaH</italic> mutant pelleted readily, and complementation restored mucoviscosity significantly (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig.&#x000a0;3D</xref>). Both capsule and O antigen of LPS can contribute to resistance to complement-mediated killing (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>), which has been correlated with the ability to cause patient infections (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). Incubation of the <italic>rfaH</italic> mutant in serum demonstrated a &#x0003e;1,000-fold loss in viability, greater than that for the susceptible control strain KP297, whereas there was no loss of viability in the wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig.&#x000a0;4</xref>). Complementation restored serum resistance. In RPMI medium with 10% heat-inactivated serum, complement is disabled and <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> grows robustly but requires the siderophore enterobactin or its glycosylated derivative salmochelin to acquire iron; yersiniabactin does not support growth under this condition (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). Whereas the wild type replicates robustly, the <italic>rfaH</italic> mutant had a moderate growth defect comparable to the loss of salmochelin expression (<italic>iroA ybtS</italic> mutant) but not as severe as the siderophore null <italic>entB ybtS</italic> mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig.&#x000a0;5</xref>). In contrast, the <italic>rfaH</italic> mutant grew well in RPMI medium without added serum (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="figS2">Fig.&#x000a0;S2A</xref> in the supplemental material). Together, these data indicate that <italic>rfaH</italic> is required for wild-type capsule production, to resist complement-mediated serum killing, and for maximal growth in iron-limited serum.</p><fig id="fig3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIG&#x000a0;3&#x000a0;</label><caption><p>The <italic>rfaH</italic> mutant is deficient in extracellular capsule. (A to C) India ink staining of <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> KPPR1 (WT) (A) and isogenic <italic>rfaH</italic> (B) and <italic>aroE</italic> (C) mutants after overnight culture in LB broth is shown by phase-contrast microscopy, in which the presence of capsule is indicated by an area of negative staining around the bacteria. Magnification, &#x000d7;1,000. (D) Mucoviscosity, as measured by optical density (OD<sub>600</sub>) after centrifugation for 5&#x000a0;min at 1,000 &#x000d7; <italic>g</italic> with a starting turbidity of 1.0, is shown as the mean and standard deviation from 6 biological replicates. *, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.0001 by ANOVA with Fisher&#x02019;s LSD test compared to the wild type; #, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.0001 compared to both WT carrying pACYC and the <italic>rfaH</italic> mutant carrying pRfaH.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="mbo0031523580003"/></fig><fig id="fig4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIG&#x000a0;4&#x000a0;</label><caption><p>The <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> rfaH and <italic>aroE</italic> mutants are susceptible to serum killing. Viability of <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> KPPR1 (WT) and isogenic mutants, without (A) or containing pACYC184 with or without <italic>rfaH</italic> (B), after a 3-h incubation in human serum is shown as mean log<sub>10</sub> CFU/ml &#x000b1; standard deviation from at least two replicates per group. *, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.0001 by ANOVA with Fisher&#x02019;s LSD test compared to the wild type.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="mbo0031523580004"/></fig><fig id="fig5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIG&#x000a0;5&#x000a0;</label><caption><p>The <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic>
<italic>rfaH</italic> mutant has a mild growth defect in heat-inactivated serum. <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> KPPR1 (WT) and isogenic mutant growth (log<sub>10</sub> CFU/ml) after overnight incubation of a 1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>3</sup>-CFU/ml inoculum in RPMI medium supplemented with 10% heat-inactivated serum is shown as the mean &#x000b1; standard deviation from 4 independent experiments. *, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05; **, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01; ****, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.0001, by ANOVA with Fisher&#x02019;s LSD test.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="mbo0031523580005"/></fig></sec><sec id="s1.4"><title><italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> requires branched-chain amino acid synthesis for full virulence.</title><p>The <italic>ilv</italic> locus encodes enzymes for synthesis of the branched-chain amino acids isoleucine and valine and the precursors for leucine (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). <italic>ilvC</italic> and <italic>ilvD</italic> mutants had 100- and 66-fold defects in competition with the wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>), respectively, indicating that branched-chain amino acid synthesis is required for fitness in the lung. To confirm that the <italic>ilvC</italic> and <italic>ilvD</italic> mutants are auxotrophs for branched-chain amino acids, their growth in minimal medium was compared to that of the wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig.&#x000a0;6</xref>). Neither mutant grew significantly, but growth of both was restored by supplementation of the medium with the branched-chain amino acids isoleucine and valine at 10&#x000a0;mM concentrations. These data indicate that synthesis of branched-chain amino acids is required for lung fitness.</p><fig id="fig6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIG&#x000a0;6&#x000a0;</label><caption><p><italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> ilvC and <italic>ilvD</italic> mutants are unable to replicate in minimal medium without branched-chain amino acids. Optical density (OD<sub>600</sub>) of <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> KPPR1 (WT) and <italic>ilvC</italic> and <italic>ilvD</italic> mutants in M9 minimal medium with or without 10&#x000a0;mM isoleucine (I) and valine (V) is shown as the mean from triplicate samples representative of 3 independent experiments.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="mbo0031523580006"/></fig></sec><sec id="s1.5"><title><italic>aroE</italic> is required for serum resistance.</title><p>Disruption of the <italic>aroE</italic> gene, which encodes shikimate dehydrogenase required for aromatic amino acid synthesis, causes a 13-fold decrease in fitness in competitive infection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>). Unlike for <italic>ilvC</italic> and <italic>ilvD</italic> mutants, the <italic>aroE</italic> mutant is not defective for growth in minimal medium (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="figS2">Fig.&#x000a0;S2B</xref> in the supplemental material), perhaps due to compensation by the <italic>ydiB</italic>-encoded quinate/shikimate dehydrogenase (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). However, the <italic>aroE</italic> mutant does have a moderate defect in serum survival (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig.&#x000a0;4</xref>) and a defect in mucoviscosity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig.&#x000a0;3D</xref>), despite production of capsule as measured by India ink (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig.&#x000a0;3C</xref>). These data indicate that <italic>aroE</italic> is dispensable for bacterial growth <italic>in vitro</italic> but is required to evade complement-mediated serum killing.</p></sec><sec id="s1.6"><title><italic>copA</italic> is required to prevent copper toxicity.</title><p>Mutation of the <italic>copA</italic> gene, encoding a P-type ATPase copper efflux pump (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>), causes a 37-fold fitness defect in competitive infection with the wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>). To determine whether deletion of <italic>copA</italic> increases susceptibility to copper toxicity, as seen in <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic>, the wild type and <italic>copA</italic> mutant were incubated in M9 minimal medium with increasing amounts of copper (5 to 25&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M). We found that CFU are significantly lower in <italic>copA</italic> mutants on average (<italic>P</italic> = 0.02) and the rate of decreasing CFU with increasing Cu concentration is significantly higher in a <italic>copA</italic> mutant (<italic>P</italic> = 0.0003) than in the wild type (WT) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig.&#x000a0;7A</xref>). Complementation with a plasmid-expressed copy of <italic>copA</italic> restored copper resistance to the mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig.&#x000a0;7B</xref>). In <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic>, copper toxicity occurs through inactivation of dehydratases such as IlvD in the branched-chain synthesis pathway (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). The <italic>ilvD</italic> mutant was more resistant to copper than the <italic>copA</italic> mutant, suggesting additional cellular targets of copper toxicity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig.&#x000a0;7C</xref>). However, the addition of branched-chain amino acids significantly protected the <italic>copA</italic> mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig.&#x000a0;7C</xref>). These data indicate that copper resistance and branched-chain amino acid metabolism pathways may overlap in their contribution to <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> lung fitness<italic>.</italic></p><fig id="fig7" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIG&#x000a0;7&#x000a0;</label><caption><p>The <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic>
<italic>copA</italic> mutant has increased sensitivity to copper. (A) Viability of a 1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>8</sup>-CFU inoculum of <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> WT and <italic>copA</italic> mutant after an 18-h incubation in M9 broth with concentrations of cupric sulfate indicated is shown as mean &#x000b1; standard deviation of results from at least 3 independent experiments. Based on a linear regression model (modeling log-transformed CFU as a function of the Cu concentration, group [WT or <italic>copA</italic>], and interaction between concentration and group), the <italic>copA</italic> mutant has a significantly faster-decreasing rate over concentrations than the wild type (#). (B) Viability of <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> harboring pACYC184 (pACYC) or pACYC184 with <italic>copA</italic> (pCopA) after incubation in 25&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M CuSO<sub>4</sub> is shown as the mean &#x000b1; standard deviation from three independent experiments. #, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.0001 compared to both strains by ANOVA with Fisher&#x02019;s LSD test; ns, not significant. (C) Viability of <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> mutants as indicated in 25&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M CuSO<sub>4</sub> with or without 10&#x000a0;mM isoleucine and valine is shown as the mean &#x000b1; standard deviation from at least three independent experiments. ****, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.0001 by ANOVA with Fisher&#x02019;s LSD.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="mbo0031523580007"/></fig></sec><sec id="s1.7"><title>InSeq identifies conserved genes as critical fitness factors for <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> lung infection.</title><p>To define broad pathways that may contribute to <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> fitness in the lung, gene enrichment analysis was performed. The KEGG classification of the 333 genes in which mutants were &#x0003e;2-fold underrepresented in the lung was determined, and the representation of each class was compared to the total gene set in the KPPR1 genome as annotated based on KEGG assignment. The pathways for 2-oxocarboxylic acid metabolism; valine, leucine, and isoleucine biosynthesis; and biosynthesis of amino acids were significantly overrepresented among genes identified as fitness factors by InSeq (corrected <italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;values of &#x0003c;0.01), indicating the critical importance of branched-chain amino acid synthesis during lung infection.</p><p>The products of conserved fitness genes could serve as targets for novel therapeutics against <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic>. To identify conserved genes in other clinically significant isolates, the KPPR1 genome was compared to the following reference sequences: MGH78578, an isolate from a patient with pneumonia; NTUH-K2044, an isolate that caused a PLA; NJST258_1, a carbapenem-resistant (KPC) ST258 isolate; and Kp342, a plant endophyte. All combinations of shared, full-length chromosomal genes were analyzed, and overlapping gene sets were tabulated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig.&#x000a0;8A</xref>; see also <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="dataS3">Data Set&#x000a0;S3</xref> in the supplemental material). KPPR1 shares a conserved set of 3,865 genes (quadrant X; 76% of predicted protein-encoding genes) with all strains; 121 genes with human isolates MGH78578, NTUH-K2044, and NJST258_1 but not the plant endophyte Kp342 (quadrant XIV); and 20, 89, 40, and 27 genes exclusively with MGH78578 (quadrant II), NTUH-K2044 (quadrant XV), NJST258_1 (quadrant IV), and Kp342 (quadrant VIII), respectively. To assess the conservation of the top fitness genes identified by InSeq analysis, the 69 genes with a fitness factor of &#x0003e;10 were mapped to the regions of overlap between KPPR1 and 4 reference genomes. In fact, 60 of 68 mapped genes were conserved between all <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> isolates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig.&#x000a0;8B</xref>), and all 6 fitness genes verified by targeted mutation are conserved. These data indicate that InSeq analysis detects lung fitness genes conserved in reference strains causing nosocomial pneumonia, pyogenic liver abscess, and carbapenem-resistant infections.</p><fig id="fig8" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIG&#x000a0;8&#x000a0;</label><caption><p><italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> conserved genes are fitness factors during pneumonia. (A) The number of genes shared between KPPR1 (orange), pneumonia isolate MGH78578 (green), pyogenic liver abscess isolate NTUH-K2044 (pink), carbapenem-resistant isolate NJST258_1 (blue), and plant endophyte Kp342 (yellow) is shown with the number of genes in each quadrant (labeled by Roman numerals) indicated as calculated by CloVR comparative software. (B) Based on InSeq analysis, 60 of 69 genes with a fitness factor of &#x0003e;10 were conserved in all five isolates (green), 2 were present in human isolates but not Kp342 (yellow), and 2 were shared with hypervirulent NTUH-K2044 (red).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="mbo0031523580008"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="h2"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>By performing InSeq analysis of <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> KPPR1, leveraging high-quality genome sequence and a well-established animal model, this study identified over 300 fitness genes important in lung infection. Detection of known virulence genes such as the <italic>wzi</italic> capsule gene validated this approach. Adaptation of CEDER analysis for ranking of fitness genes, based on the concordance of read count ratios from multiple transposon insertions within genes, provided a reliable list of fitness genes that were experimentally validated. These validation experiments demonstrated that aromatic and branched-chain amino acid synthesis pathways, copper efflux, and global virulence gene regulators such as RfaH are critical for <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> to cause pneumonia. The identification of genes such as <italic>rfaH</italic>, with a profound contribution to lung fitness, indicates the benefit of applying InSeq even when prior forward genetic screens have been performed (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Enrichment analysis further substantiated amino acid synthesis as central to lung fitness, and comparative genomics indicated that many critical fitness genes are highly conserved in <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic>. The large set of fitness genes in KPPR1 newly identified by InSeq should accelerate progress in defining the virulence strategies of <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae.</italic></p><p>Enrichment analysis and experimental validation of InSeq-selected genes indicate that <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> must synthesize amino acids that the host cannot. Since essential amino acids are acquired through diet, it does not necessarily follow that these amino acids would be limiting in the lung. However, based on measurements in human subjects, the concentrations of these amino acids are significantly lower in pulmonary epithelial lining fluid than in plasma (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). InSeq identified mutants with decreased fitness in pathways that synthesize the host&#x02019;s essential amino acids histidine (<italic>hisG</italic>); isoleucine, valine, and leucine (<italic>ilvABCDEN</italic> and <italic>leuABC</italic>); methionine/cysteine (<italic>metACBFL</italic>); phenylalanine and tryptophan (<italic>aroE</italic>, <italic>pheA</italic>, and <italic>trpD</italic>); and threonine (<italic>thrBC</italic>) (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="dataS2">Data Set&#x000a0;S2</xref> in the supplemental material) (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). This indicates that synthesis of amino acids that are essential to its host is also critical for <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> to infect the lung.</p><p>Branched-chain amino acid metabolism may be critical for <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> lung fitness for two reasons: nutrient limitation and copper toxicity. In contrast to reduced branched-chain amino acid levels, copper is increased in human lungs compared to serum (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). Our data show that <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> must synthesize branched-chain amino acids in the lung, but in <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic>, this pathway is blocked by copper through its inhibition of dehydratases such as IlvD (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). In <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic>, the <italic>copA</italic> mutant is exquisitely sensitive to copper but is protected by exogenous isoleucine and valine (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig.&#x000a0;7C</xref>), consistent with this mechanism of copper toxicity. Sulfonylurea herbicides that inhibit acetohydroxy acid synthase in the branched-chain amino acid synthesis pathway can protect mice from <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> and <italic>Burkholderia pseudomallei</italic> pneumonia, but <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> is predicted to contain a resistant isozyme (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). The nine <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> synthesis genes identified by InSeq (<italic>ilvABCDEN</italic> and <italic>leuABC</italic>) could provide novel targets to block branched-chain amino acid (BCAA) synthesis.</p><p>In contrast to <italic>ilv</italic> mutants, the <italic>aroE</italic> mutant is not auxotrophic in minimal medium but has reduced fitness in the lung. In <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic>, the YdiB quinate/shikimate dehydrogenase can perform the same function as AroE, albeit with lower efficiency (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). The fact that the <italic>aroE</italic> mutant is susceptible to serum killing suggests a specific defect that affects complement resistance. <italic>Salmonella enterica</italic> aro mutants are also attenuated <italic>in vivo</italic> and are susceptible to serum killing in addition to their auxotrophy (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). The mechanism for the increased serum sensitivity of the <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> aroE mutant is unclear.</p><p>In addition to synthesizing building blocks for replication despite nutrient limitations, <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> must also evade host defenses to cause disease. Polysaccharide capsule is a critical virulence factor of <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> that evades complement-mediated killing and opsonophagocytosis. Detection of the capsular assembly gene <italic>wzi</italic> as the most significant fitness gene by InSeq analysis reinforces the critical role of capsule. Phenotypic assays indicate that <italic>rfaH</italic> is important in capsular synthesis and is required for survival <italic>in vivo</italic> and in serum. <italic>S</italic>.&#x000a0;Typhimurium and uropathogenic <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic>
<italic>rfaH</italic> mutants are also severely attenuated in animal models, corresponding to defects in <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> capsular synthesis and LPS synthesis in both (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). RfaH appears to be a critical virulence factor that is conserved among <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> strains and with other pathogenic <italic>Enterobacteriaceae.</italic></p><p>Treatment of <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> infections has become increasingly challenging due to carbapenem and extended-spectrum &#x003b2;-lactamase resistance (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Therefore, novel therapeutic approaches are needed to fight these common and life-threatening nosocomial infections. Targets for antimicrobials should be conserved within a species or a group of closely related species at a minimum, have a low potential for toxicity or disruption of human metabolism, and ideally not have a preexisting resistance mechanism. This study identifies 60 genes that are conserved among diverse representatives of <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> and have a 10- to 10,000-fold defect when disrupted, and many are in prokaryote-specific functions such as synthesis of amino acids that humans do not make or transcription of polycistronic RNAs (<italic>rfaH</italic>). Through careful study of their function during infection, some of these gene products could be pursued as targets for novel antimicrobials.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="h3"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec id="s3.1"><title>Bacterial strains and media.</title><p><italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> KPPR1 (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>) and isogenic mutants were cultured in Luria-Bertani (LB) broth at 37&#x000b0;C with shaking or 30&#x000b0;C on agar (Becton, Dickinson and Company, Sparks, MD) supplemented with kanamycin (25&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/ml), spectinomycin (50&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/ml), chloramphenicol (20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/ml), and rifampin (30&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/ml) as indicated.</p></sec><sec id="s3.2"><title>Murine pneumonia model.</title><p>Six- to 8-week-old C57BL/6 mice (Jackson Laboratory, Bar Harbor, ME) were anesthetized with isoflurane and inoculated retropharyngeally with 1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup>&#x000a0;CFU of pooled <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> transposon mutants. LB broth-grown cultures were centrifuged, resuspended, and diluted in phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) to a concentration of 2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>7</sup>&#x000a0;CFU, and 50&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l of the suspension was administered. After 24&#x000a0;h, mice were euthanized by CO<sub>2</sub> asphyxiation. To determine bacterial density, lungs and spleens were removed, homogenized in 1&#x000a0;ml PBS, and cultured on LB agar with appropriate antibiotics. To determine competitive indices, mice (at least 4 per group) were infected as described above with 50&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l of a 1:1 mixture of wild-type and mutant <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> strains in a total inoculum of 1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup>&#x000a0;CFU. After 24&#x000a0;h, mice were euthanized, lungs were homogenized in 1&#x000a0;ml PBS, wild-type CFU were measured by culture on LB plates supplemented with rifampin, and mutant CFU were measured on LB plates with rifampin and kanamycin. The competitive index was calculated as (mutant lung CFU/wild-type lung CFU)/(mutant inoculum CFU/wild-type inoculum CFU).</p></sec><sec id="s3.3"><title>Transposon library construction and sequencing.</title><p>The transposon library was constructed by conjugation of the pSAM_Cam plasmid, a modified version of pSAM_Ec (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>) containing the chloramphenicol acetyltransferase gene from pKD3 (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>), into KPPR1 (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="textS1">Text&#x000a0;S1</xref>&#x000a0;in the supplemental material for detailed methods). Insertion sequencing (InSeq; Sequence Read Archive ID <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sra/?term=SRP051394">SRP051394</ext-link>) was performed as previously described (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s3.4"><title>Construction and complementation of mutants.</title><p>Lambda Red mutagenesis was performed as previously described (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). To make electrocompetent cells, <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> containing the pKD46 plasmid (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>), modified to encode spectinomycin resistance (a gift from Chris Alteri), was cultured overnight in LB broth containing spectinomycin at 30&#x000b0;C with shaking. The following day, cultures were diluted 1:100 in LB broth with spectinomycin and 50&#x000a0;mM <sc>l</sc>-arabinose and cultured at 30&#x000b0;C until reaching a reading of optical density at 600 nm (OD<sub>600</sub>) of 0.5 to 0.6 (approximately 4&#x000a0;h). Cultures were placed on ice for at least 30&#x000a0;min and centrifuged in sterile cold bottles at 8,000 &#x000d7;&#x000a0;<italic>g</italic> for 15&#x000a0;min at 4&#x000b0;C. The supernatant was decanted, and bacteria were serially washed and centrifuged in ice-cold sterile volumes of 50&#x000a0;ml 1&#x000a0;mM HEPES at pH&#x000a0;7.4 (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA), 50&#x000a0;ml distilled water (dH<sub>2</sub>O), and 20&#x000a0;ml 10% glycerol. Pellets were resuspended in ice-cold sterile 10% glycerol at a final density of 2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>10</sup> to 3 &#x000d7; 10<sup>10</sup>&#x000a0;CFU/ml and stored at &#x02212;80&#x000b0;C in 50-&#x000b5;l aliquots.</p><p>To generate null mutants, <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> BW25141 containing the pKD4 plasmid was cultured overnight in LB broth containing 50&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/ml kanamycin (MP Biomedicals, Santa Ana, CA) at 30&#x000b0;C. The pKD4 plasmid was isolated using a Spin Miniprep kit (Qiagen, Valencia, CA). Oligonucleotide primers were then designed with 60-bp homology flanking the region targeted for deletion added to 5&#x02032; ends of P1 and P2 sites of the pKD4 kanamycin resistance cassette (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="tabS2">Table&#x000a0;S2</xref>&#x000a0;in the supplemental material). The targeting fragment was generated by PCR consisting of 95&#x000b0;C for 5&#x000a0;min; 30 cycles of 95&#x000b0;C for 1&#x000a0;min, 58&#x000b0;C for 1&#x000a0;min, and 72&#x000b0;C for 1&#x000a0;min; and 72&#x000b0;C for 5&#x000a0;min. PCR products were pooled and purified using a Qiagen PCR purification kit. PCR products were digested overnight at 37&#x000b0;C with DpnI, and 10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l was added to the electrocompetent pKD46 cells, gently mixed, and incubated on ice for 10&#x000a0;min. The mixture was electroporated using a 0.1-cm-gap cuvette (Fisher Scientific; catalog no. FB101) at 1.8&#x000a0;kV, 400 &#x003a9;, 25&#x000a0;&#x000b5;F, with a Bio-Rad Micropulser (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA), and cells were recovered with SOC medium and incubated overnight at 30&#x000b0;C with shaking in sterile culture tubes. Next, cells were spun down, resuspended in LB broth, plated onto LB broth plates containing kanamycin, and incubated at 37&#x000b0;C overnight. Transformants were restreaked on LB agar and confirmed by colony PCR using flanking primers (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="tabS2">Table&#x000a0;S2</xref>).</p><p>To complement the <italic>rfaH</italic> and <italic>copA</italic> mutants, PCR products containing the open reading frame and upstream sequence (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="tabS2">Table&#x000a0;S2</xref>&#x000a0;in the supplemental material) were inserted into pCR 2.1 by TOPO TA cloning (Life Technologies, Carlsbad, CA) and transferred to pACYC184 by ligation after digestion with Xbal and HindIII. The resulting complementation plasmid or pACYC184 alone was introduced into WT or mutant <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> by electroporation.</p></sec><sec id="s3.5"><title>Serum growth assay.</title><p>RPMI medium (Invitrogen, Grand Island, NY), supplemented with 10% (vol/vol) heat-inactivated pooled human serum, was inoculated with 1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>3</sup>&#x000a0;CFU/ml of an overnight culture of <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> and incubated overnight in a final volume of 100&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l in 96-well plates at 37&#x000b0;C with 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. To determine bacterial density, samples were serially diluted and plated on LB agar (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA) with appropriate antibiotics.</p></sec><sec id="s3.6"><title>Growth curves.</title><p><italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> strains were cultured overnight in LB broth. On the following day, cultures were incubated in LB or M9 (Invitrogen) medium with or without isoleucine and valine supplementation (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO) at a starting density of 2.6 &#x000d7; 10<sup>7</sup>&#x000a0;CFU/ml and cultured for 8&#x000a0;h at 37&#x000b0;C. Absorbance readings at 600&#x000a0;nm were taken every 15&#x000a0;min using an Eon microplate spectrophotometer with Gen5 software (BioTek, Winooski, VT).</p></sec><sec id="s3.7"><title>Capsule staining.</title><p><italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> strains were cultured overnight in LB broth. On the following day, 10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l of culture was added to slides and allowed to air dry. The dried bacteria were then heat fixed to the slide (3&#x000a0;min at 56&#x000b0;C); 10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l of India ink (Becton, Dickinson and Company, Sparks, MD) diluted 1:3 in PBS was added and wet mounted with a coverslip. Superfrost slides (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA) were viewed and imaged using an Axioplan2 phase-contrast microscope (Zeiss, Irvine, CA) with a SPOT diagnostic camera and software (SPOT Imagine Solutions, Sterling Heights, MI).</p></sec><sec id="s3.8"><title>Mucoviscosity assay.</title><p>Overnight cultures were pelleted by centrifugation at 9,400 &#x000d7; <italic>g</italic> and resuspended in PBS to an OD<sub>600</sub> of ~1. The suspensions were centrifuged for 5&#x000a0;min at 1,000 &#x000d7; <italic>g</italic>, and the OD<sub>600</sub> of the supernatants was measured. Final readings were normalized to the OD<sub>600</sub> of the wild type before centrifugation.</p></sec><sec id="s3.9"><title>Serum killing assay.</title><p><italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> strains were cultured overnight in LB broth. On the second day, cultures were diluted to 2.5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup>&#x000a0;CFU/ml in non-heat-inactivated human serum and incubated for 3&#x000a0;h at 37&#x000b0;C. Aliquots at <italic>t</italic> = 0 and <italic>t</italic> = 3&#x000a0;h were plated for CFU on LB agar with appropriate antibiotics.</p></sec><sec id="s3.10"><title>Copper sensitivity assay.</title><p>Sensitivity to copper was measured by washing 3&#x000a0;ml of stationary-phase cultures twice with PBS and then centrifuging them at 10,000 &#x000d7; <italic>g</italic> and resuspending them in M9 minimal medium. Next, 2-ml reaction mixtures were prepared with defined concentrations of copper sulfate (98% pure; Sigma, St. Louis, MO) in M9 medium with bacterial cultures normalized to an OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.2. Reaction mixtures were incubated for 18&#x000a0;h at 37&#x000b0;C in six-well plates. Following incubation, CFU were enumerated by quantitative culture.</p></sec><sec id="s3.11"><title>Genome comparison and gene enrichment analysis.</title><p>To identify genes shared between KPPR1 (GenBank identifier [ID] <ext-link ext-link-type="NCBI:nucleotide" xlink:href="CP009208">CP009208</ext-link>) and reference <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> isolates MGH78578 (GenBank ID <ext-link ext-link-type="NCBI:nucleotide" xlink:href="CP000647">CP000647</ext-link>), NTUH-K2044 (GenBank ID <ext-link ext-link-type="NCBI:nucleotide" xlink:href="AP006725">AP006725</ext-link>), NJST258_1 (GenBank ID <ext-link ext-link-type="NCBI:nucleotide" xlink:href="CP006923.1">CP006923.1</ext-link>), and Kp342 (GenBank ID <ext-link ext-link-type="NCBI:nucleotide" xlink:href="CP000964">CP000964</ext-link>), reference genomes were compared by CloVR comparative software (on the DIAG computing platform), generating clusters of genes shared between genomes. The number of genes shared between each genome was tabulated, and a Venn diagram was generated with free R (v.3.1.1) software and the Venn diagram package. To identify biological pathways associated with lung fitness, enrichment analysis was performed using KOBAS 2.0 (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s3.12"><title>Statistical analysis.</title><p>To quantify the significance of each gene as a potential fitness factor, we first tested the difference in counts between inoculum and lung at each transposon insertion using an exact Poisson test and then combined the insertion-level <italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;values into a <italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;value for each gene using Fisher&#x02019;s method (using R 3.1.1 software) in a modification of CEDER analysis (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). A small <italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;value indicates an important fitness factor. To test whether the <italic>copA</italic> mutant is more sensitive to copper than the wild type, a linear regression model was used (the relation between log-transformed CFU and Cu concentration is approximately linear). Statistical analysis of CFU data was performed on log-transformed data by a one-sample <italic>t</italic>&#x000a0;test for competitive index and a two-sample <italic>t</italic>&#x000a0;test or analysis of variance (ANOVA) with Fisher&#x02019;s least significant difference (LSD) test as indicated using Prism 6 (GraphPad Software, La Jolla, CA).</p></sec><sec id="s3.13"><title>Ethics statement.</title><p>This study was performed in strict accordance with the recommendations in the <italic>Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals</italic> (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>). The University of Michigan Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee (IACUC) approved this research (PRO00005795).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sm1"><title>SUPPLEMENTAL MATERIAL</title><supplementary-material id="textS1"><label>Text&#x000a0;S1&#x000a0;</label><caption><p>Supplemental methods. Download </p></caption><media xlink:href="mbo003152358s1.pdf"><caption><p>Text&#x000a0;S1, PDF file, 0.1 MB</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="dataS1"><label>Data Set&#x000a0;S1</label><caption><p>Transposon insertion sites and counts. Download </p></caption><media xlink:href="mbo003152358sd1.xlsx"><caption><p>Data Set&#x000a0;S1, XLSX file, 2.2 MB</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="dataS2"><label>Data Set&#x000a0;S2</label><caption><p>Fitness ratio and CEDER analysis of <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> KPPR1 genes. Download </p></caption><media xlink:href="mbo003152358sd2.xls"><caption><p>Data Set&#x000a0;S2, XLS file, 0.8 MB</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="dataS3"><label>Data Set&#x000a0;S3</label><caption><p>Gene intersection lists. Download </p></caption><media xlink:href="mbo003152358sd3.xlsx"><caption><p>Data Set&#x000a0;S3, XLSX file, 0.8 MB</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="figS1"><label>Figure&#x000a0;S1&#x000a0;</label><caption><p>pSAM_Cam is suicidal in <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic>, and transposon insertion is random. (a) Relevant features of pSAM_Cam. (b) To verify that pSAM_Cam was suicidal in <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic>, colony PCR was performed using primers that anneal within the plasmid backbone (top) and primers that anneal within the Kan cassette (bottom). The presence of pSAM_Cam generates a 999-bp PCR product from the plasmid backbone and a 1,338-bp product from the Kan cassette. The presence of the transposon-containing Kan cassette inserted into <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> generates a 1,338-bp product. (c) To assess the randomness of the transposon mutant library, genomic DNA from Rif<sup>r</sup> Kan<sup>r</sup> colonies was harvested, digested with EcoRI, and subjected to Southern blotting. The variation in sizes of fragments containing the Kan cassette indicates that the transposon is inserted in a different region of the chromosome for each of the mutants tested. Download </p></caption><media xlink:href="mbo003152358sf1.tif"><caption><p>Figure&#x000a0;S1, TIF file, 0.2 MB</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="figS2"><label>Figure&#x000a0;S2&#x000a0;</label><caption><p>The <italic>aroE</italic> and <italic>rfaH</italic> mutants do not have growth defects in M9 or RPMI medium. (A) CFU per milliliter after inoculation with 1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>3</sup>&#x000a0;CFU and overnight incubation in RPMI medium is shown as mean &#x000b1; standard deviation from two independent experiments. (B) Optical density of <italic>K.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> KP4 and isogenic mutants during incubation in M9 minimal medium at 37&#x000b0;C is shown as mean &#x000b1; standard deviation from triplicate cultures and is representative of three independent experiments. Download </p></caption><media xlink:href="mbo003152358sf2.tif"><caption><p>Figure&#x000a0;S2, TIF file, 0.1 MB</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="tabS1"><label>Table&#x000a0;S1&#x000a0;</label><caption><p>Read counts from InSeq analysis.</p></caption><media xlink:href="mbo003152358st1.pdf"><caption><p>Table&#x000a0;S1, PDF file, 0.02 MB</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="tabS2"><label>Table&#x000a0;S2&#x000a0;</label><caption><p>Primers used in this study.</p></caption><media xlink:href="mbo003152358st2.pdf"><caption><p>Table&#x000a0;S2, PDF file, 0.1 MB</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Citation</bold> Bachman MA, Breen P, Deornellas V, Mu Q, Zhao L, Wu W, Cavalcoli JD, Mobley HLT. 2015. Genome-wide identification of <italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> fitness genes during lung infection. mBio 6(3):e00775-15. doi:10.1128/mBio.00775-15.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title><p>This research was supported in part by the University of Michigan Medical School Host Microbiome Initiative. Research using CloVR was conducted on the National Science Foundation funded MRI-R2 project #DBI-0959894.</p><p>We thank Victoria Holden for assistance with bacterial plating, Sargurunathan Subashchandrabose for scientific discussions about the project, the University of Michigan DNA Sequencing Core for consultation and Illumina HiSeq sequencing, and the Center for Live Cell Imaging for microscope training and access.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Podschun</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ullmann</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1998</year>
<article-title><italic>Klebsiella</italic> spp. as nosocomial pathogens: epidemiology, taxonomy, typing methods, and pathogenicity factors</article-title>. <source>Clin Microbiol Rev</source>
<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>589</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>603</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9767057</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maroncle</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Balestrino</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rich</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Forestier</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Identification of <italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> genes involved in intestinal colonization and adhesion using signature-tagged mutagenesis</article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source>
<volume>70</volume>:<fpage>4729</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4734</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.70.8.4729-4734.2002</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12117993</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>CZ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Serum-induced iron-acquisition systems and TonB contribute to virulence in <italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> causing primary pyogenic liver abscess</article-title>. <source>J Infect Dis</source>
<volume>197</volume>:<fpage>1717</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1727</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/588383</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18433330</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</collab></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<source>Antibiotic resistance threats in the United States</source>. <publisher-name>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Atlanta, GA</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bachman</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oyler</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Burns</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Caza</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>L&#x000e9;pine</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dozois</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weiser</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title><italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> yersiniabactin promotes respiratory tract infection through evasion of lipocalin 2</article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source>
<volume>79</volume>:<fpage>3309</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3316</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.05114-11</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21576334</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lawlor</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rick</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Identification of <italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> virulence determinants using an intranasal infection model</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>58</volume>:<fpage>1054</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1073</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2005.04918.x</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16262790</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Struve</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Forestier</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krogfelt</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Application of a novel multi-screening signature-tagged mutagenesis assay for identification of <italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> genes essential in colonization and infection</article-title>. <source>Microbiology</source>
<volume>149</volume>:<fpage>167</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>176</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/mic.0.25833-0</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12576590</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Langridge</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Phan</surname><given-names>M-D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Perkins</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Parts</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haase</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Charles</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maskell</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dougan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wain</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Parkhill</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Simultaneous assay of every <italic>Salmonella</italic> typhi gene using one million transposon mutants</article-title>. <source>Genome Res</source>
<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>2308</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2316</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.097097.109</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19826075</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McNulty</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leip</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mitra</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lozupone</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Identifying genetic determinants needed to establish a human gut symbiont in its habitat</article-title>. <source>Cell Host Microbe</source>
<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>279</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>289</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chom.2009.08.003</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19748469</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Broberg</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cavalcoli</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bachman</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Complete genome sequence of <italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> strain ATCC 43816 KPPR1, a rifampin-resistant mutant commonly used in animal, genetic, and molecular biology studies</article-title>. <source>Genome Announc</source>
<volume>2</volume>(<issue-id>5</issue-id>):<fpage>e00924-14</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/genomeA.00924-14</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25291761</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsao</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fung</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shu</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shiau</surname><given-names>YR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lauderdale</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kirby</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Genome sequencing and comparative analysis of <italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> NTUH-K2044, a strain causing liver abscess and meningitis</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>191</volume>:<fpage>4492</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4501</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.00315-09</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19447910</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>DeLeo</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Porcella</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martens</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chavda</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mathema</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Olsen</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bonomo</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Musser</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kreiswirth</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Molecular dissection of the evolution of carbapenem-resistant multilocus sequence type 258 <italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic></article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>111</volume>:<fpage>4988</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4993</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1321364111</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24639510</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fouts</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tyler</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deboy</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Daugherty</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Badger</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Durkin</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huot</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shrivastava</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kothari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dodson</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mohamoud</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khouri</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roesch</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krogfelt</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Struve</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Triplett</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meth&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Complete genome sequence of the N2-fixing broad host range endophyte <italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> 342 and virulence predictions verified in mice</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source>
<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>e1000141</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1000141</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18654632</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Red recombinase assisted gene replacement in <italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic></article-title>. <source>J Ind Microbiol Biotechnol</source>
<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>1219</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1226</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10295-012-1117-x</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22430500</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Datsenko</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wanner</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>One-step inactivation of chromosomal genes in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> K-12 using PCR products</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>97</volume>:<fpage>6640</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6645</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.120163297</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10829079</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>T-W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>H-Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Palsson</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Charusanti</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Capsule deletion via a &#x003bb;-red knockout system perturbs biofilm formation and fimbriae expression in <italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> MGH 78578</article-title>. <source>BMC Res Notes</source>
<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>13</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1756-0500-7-13</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24398052</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carbon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1976</year>
<article-title>A colony bank containing synthetic Col El hybrid plasmids representative of the entire <italic>E. coli</italic> genome</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>91</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>99</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0092-8674(76)90055-6</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">788919</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Identifying microbial fitness determinants by insertion sequencing using genome-wide transposon mutant libraries</article-title>. <source>Nat Protoc</source>
<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>1969</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1980</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2011.417</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22094732</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>CEDER: accurate detection of differentially expressed genes by combining significance of exons using RNA-Seq</article-title>. <source>IEEE/ACM Trans Comput Biol Bioinform</source>
<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>1281</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1292</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/TCBB.2012.83</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22641709</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nagy</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Danino</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dobrindt</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pallen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chaudhuri</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Em&#x000f6;dy</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hinton</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hacker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Down-regulation of key virulence factors makes the <italic>Salmonella enterica</italic> serovar Typhimurium <italic>rfaH</italic> mutant a promising live-attenuated vaccine candidate</article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source>
<volume>74</volume>:<fpage>5914</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5925</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.00619-06</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16988271</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>RfaH promotes the ability of the avian pathogenic <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> O2 strain E058 to cause avian colibacillosis</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>195</volume>:<fpage>2474</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2480</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.02074-12</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23504015</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Burmann</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Knauer</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sevostyanova</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schweimer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mooney</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Landick</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Artsimovitch</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>R&#x000f6;sch</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>An &#x003b1; helix to &#x003b2; barrel domain switch transforms the transcription factor RfaH into a translation factor</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>150</volume>:<fpage>291</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>303</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2012.05.042</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22817892</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>T-L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>F-L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>A-S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>H-P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>T-L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>M-D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>S-H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J-T</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Amino acid substitutions of MagA in <italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> affect the biosynthesis of the capsular polysaccharide</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>e46783</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0046783</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23118860</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>C-T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chuang</surname><given-names>YP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shun</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>A novel virulence gene in <italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> strains causing primary liver abscess and septic metastatic complications</article-title>. <source>J Exp Med</source>
<volume>199</volume>:<fpage>697</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>705</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.20030857</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14993253</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Merino</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Camprub&#x000ed;</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Albert&#x000ed;</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bened&#x000ed;</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tom&#x000e1;s</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1992</year>
<article-title>Mechanisms of <italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> resistance to complement-mediated killing</article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source>
<volume>60</volume>:<fpage>2529</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2535</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1587619</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bachman</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weiser</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Mucosal lipocalin 2 has pro-inflammatory and iron-sequestering effects in response to bacterial enterobactin</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog</source>
<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>e1000622</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000622</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19834550</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Subashchandrabose</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>LeVeque</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kirkwood</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kiupel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mulks</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Branched-chain amino acids are required for the survival and virulence of <italic>Actinobacillus pleuropneumoniae</italic> in swine</article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source>
<volume>77</volume>:<fpage>4925</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4933</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.00671-09</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19703979</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Michel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roszak</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sauv&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maclean</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matte</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Coggins</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cygler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lapthorn</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Structures of shikimate dehydrogenase AroE and its paralog YdiB. A common structural framework for different activities</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>278</volume>:<fpage>19463</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>19472</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M300794200</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12637497</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rensing</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mitra</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rosen</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>CopA: an <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> Cu(I)-translocating P-type ATPase</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>97</volume>:<fpage>652</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>656</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.97.2.652</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10639134</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Macomber</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Imlay</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>The iron-sulfur clusters of dehydratases are primary intracellular targets of copper toxicity</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>106</volume>:<fpage>8344</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8349</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0812808106</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19416816</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hofford</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Milakofsky</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fish</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pollice</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1997</year>
<article-title>Levels of amino acids and related compounds in bronchoalveolar lavage fluids of asthmatic patients</article-title>. <source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source>
<volume>155</volume>:<fpage>432</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>435</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/ajrccm.155.2.9032174</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9032174</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>John</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1976</year>
<article-title>Amino acid requirements of the growing mouse</article-title>. <source>J Nutr</source>
<volume>106</volume>:<fpage>1361</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1367</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">956917</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shafeeq</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yesilkaya</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kloosterman</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Narayanan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wandel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Andrew</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuipers</surname><given-names>OP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morrissey</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>The <italic>cop</italic> operon is required for copper homeostasis and contributes to virulence in <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic></article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>81</volume>:<fpage>1255</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1270</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2011.07758.x</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21736642</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kreisberg</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ong</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krishna</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Joseph</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ong</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ooi</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Siew</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Biot</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cuccui</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wren</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sivalingam</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Growth inhibition of pathogenic bacteria by sulfonylurea herbicides</article-title>. <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source>
<volume>57</volume>:<fpage>1513</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1517</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.02327-12</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23263008</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sebkova</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Karasova</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Crhanova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Budinska</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rychlik</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Aro mutations in <italic>Salmonella enterica</italic> cause defects in cell wall and outer membrane integrity</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>190</volume>:<fpage>3155</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3160</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.00053-08</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18310348</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nagy</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dobrindt</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hacker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Em&#x000f6;dy</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Loss of regulatory protein RfaH attenuates virulence of uropathogenic <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source>
<volume>70</volume>:<fpage>4406</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4413</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.70.8.4406-4413.2002</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12117951</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiles</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Norton</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dalley</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mulvey</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Combining quantitative genetic footprinting and trait enrichment analysis to identify fitness determinants of a bacterial pathogen</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source>
<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e1003716</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1003716</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23990803</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>KOBAS 2.0: a web server for annotation and identification of enriched pathways and diseases</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>W316</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>W322</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkr483</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21715386</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>National Research Council</collab></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<source>Guide for the care and use of laboratory animals</source>, <edition>8th ed.</edition>
<publisher-name>National Academies Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>