<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22110729</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3216988</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-11-15023</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0027699</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Anatomy and Physiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Physiological Processes</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Molecular Cell Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cellular Structures</subject><subj-group><subject>Cytoskeleton</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Nucleic Acids</subject><subj-group><subject>RNA</subject><subj-group><subject>RNA transport</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Cellular Stress Responses</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Anatomy and Physiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Physiological Processes</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Drugs and Devices</subject><subj-group><subject>Drug Research and Development</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Oncology</subject><subj-group><subject>Basic Cancer Research</subject><subject>Cancer Treatment</subject><subject>Oncology Agents</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Darinaparsin Is a Multivalent Chemotherapeutic Which Induces Incomplete Stress Response with Disruption of Microtubules and Shh Signaling</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">A Multivalent Chemotherapeutic</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>Twila A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kolobova</surname><given-names>Elena</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Jiang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Roland</surname><given-names>Joseph T.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>Chin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Goldenring</surname><given-names>James R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>&#x0002a;</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Department of Cell and Developmental Biology, Vanderbilt University Medical Center, Nashville, Tennessee, United States of America</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Epithelial Biology Center, Vanderbilt University Medical Center, Nashville, Tennessee, United States of America</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Department of Surgery, Vanderbilt University Medical Center, Nashville, Tennessee, United States of America</addr-line></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Srivastava</surname><given-names>Rakesh K.</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">The University of Kansas Medical Center, United States of America</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">&#x0002a; E-mail: <email>jim.goldenring@vanderbilt.edu</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: TAM EK JL JTR CC JRG. Performed the experiments: TAM EK JL JTR JRG. Analyzed the data: TAM EK JL JTR CC JRG. Wrote the paper: TAM EK JL CC JRG.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>11</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>11</issue><elocation-id>e27699</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>2</day><month>8</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>10</month><year>2011</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Mason et al. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year></permissions><abstract><p>Chemotherapeutics and other pharmaceuticals are common sources of cellular stress. Darinaparsin (ZIO-101) is a novel organic arsenical under evaluation as a cancer chemotherapeutic, but the drug's precise mechanism of action is unclear. Stress granule formation is an important cellular stress response, but the mechanisms of formation, maintenance, and dispersal of RNA-containing granules are not fully understood. During stress, small, diffuse granules initially form throughout the cytoplasm. These granules then coalesce near the nucleus into larger granules that disperse once the cellular stress is removed. Complete stress granule formation is dependent upon microtubules. Human cervical cancer (HeLa) cells, pre-treated with nocodazole for microtubule depolymerization, formed only small, diffuse stress granules upon sodium arsenite treatment. Darinaparsin, as a single agent, also induced the formation of small, diffuse stress granules, an effect similar to that of the combination of nocodazole with sodium arsenite. Darinaparsin inhibited the polymerization of microtubules both <italic>in vivo</italic> and <italic>in vitro</italic>. Interestingly, upon removal of darinaparsin, the small, diffuse stress granules completed formation with coalescence in the perinuclear region prior to disassembly. These results indicate that RNA stress granules must complete formation prior to disassembly, and completion of stress granule formation is dependent upon microtubules. Finally, treatment of cells with darinaparsin led to a reduction in Sonic hedgehog (Shh) stimulated activation of Gli1 and a loss of primary cilia. Therefore, darinaparsin represents a unique multivalent chemotherapeutic acting on stress induction, microtubule polymerization, and Shh signaling.</p></abstract><counts><page-count count="9"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>All cells experience various stressors during their physiological processes. Stress is a ubiquitous problem and can trigger a range of responses within cells. Common stressors include heat shock, oxidative conditions, viral infection, hypoxia, mitochondrial stress, DNA-damaging agents, and ultraviolet irradiation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Kolobova1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Kedersha1">[2]</xref>. Chemotherapeutic drugs and other pharmaceuticals are other common sources of cellular stress.</p><p>Arsenicals are one category of chemotherapeutics undergoing continual investigation. Organic and inorganic arsenicals have been used in the treatment of disease for thousands of years <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Verstovsek1">[3]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Tsimberidou1">[4]</xref>. However, arsenicals are typically very potent and their toxicity typically limits their use <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Tsimberidou1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Camps1">[5]</xref>. Currently, arsenic trioxide (ATO, As<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>), an inorganic arsenical, is used for treatment in cases of recurrent acute promyelocytic leukemia <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Mann1">[6]</xref>. This drug is limited by its toxicity on the liver and cardiovascular system. Because of these toxicity issues, the development of less toxic arsenicals has become an area of great interest.</p><p>Darinaparsin (ZIO-101, S-dimethylarsino-glutathione) is an organic arsenical that is currently in Phase II clinical trials as a chemotherapeutic agent <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Camps1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Wu1">[7]</xref>. While darinaparsin shows clinical promise, the drug's mechanism of action continues to be investigated. A series of in vitro and in vivo studies, coupled with observed differences in toxicity and potency, suggest darinaparsin employs a mechanism of action that is different from that of ATO. Darinaparsin appears more potent than ATO as some ATO-resistant cells are sensitive to the drug. Moreover, other cell types have shown an increased sensitivity to darinaparsin compared to ATO. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Camps1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Mann1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Diaz1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Matulis1">[9]</xref>. Importantly darinaparsin does not demonstrate the same level or type of toxicity as ATO with no apparent toxicity to the liver or cardiovascular system.</p><p>Previous studies have shown that both ATO and darinaparsin cause apoptosis and cell cycle arrest at G<sub>2</sub>/M in tumor cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Tsimberidou1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Mann1">[6]</xref>. This effect is thought to occur in part through the disruption of mitochondrial functions, which leads to increased production of reactive oxygen species (ROS) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-QuintsCardama1">[10]</xref>. An increase in ROS, if great enough, can trigger a cellular stress response. Recent preclinical studies of darinaparsin have shown anti-angiogenic activity in vitro and in vivo through controlling several signal transduction pathways <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Mann1">[6]</xref> and that darinaparsin is more potent than ATO under hypoxic conditions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Tian1">[11]</xref>.</p><p>One critical mechanism in the cellular stress response is the formation of RNA stress granules. Stress granules function to sequester mRNAs and proteins during cellular stress. Importantly, stress granules are not stable structures, but are dynamic with a constant flux of proteins and mRNAs. Stress granules are generally composed of a variety of preinitiation- and translation-related factors, proteins linked to mRNA metabolism, mRNAs, and RNA-binding proteins, as well as signaling proteins with no known link to mRNA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Kedersha1">[2]</xref>. Typically, proteins and mRNAs necessary for cell survival during stress, such as heat shock proteins, are not sequestered in stress granules. The mRNAs are sequestered in stress granules until the cell is no longer stressed or undergoes apoptosis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Thomas1">[12]</xref>. Once stress is no longer present, stress granules disperse, and the sequestered mRNAs can be translated. Other RNA granules also exist in cells without stress, such as processing bodies (P-bodies) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Kolobova1">[1]</xref>. The different RNA granules do contain unique components, with stress granules containing components specialized for adaptation to dynamic stressors. Though stress granule formation appears to be a ubiquitous cellular response, the mechanisms regulating formation, maintenance, and dispersal remain largely obscure.</p><p>In this study, we examined both the mechanism of action for darinaparsin and the dynamics of stress granules formation, maintenance, and dispersal. We propose that darinaparsin is a potent chemotherapeutic because it initiates a stress response, while also stalling the completion of the stress response by simultaneously depolymerizing microtubules. The depolymerization of microtubules causes the stress granules to form incompletely, preventing the coalescence of stress granule components. When darinaparsin is withdrawn, stress granules progress to final coalescence as microtubules repolymerize and disperse only after complete granule formation. In addition, likely due to microtubule depolymerization, darinaparsin causes a loss of primary cilia and a reduction in Shh signaling. These findings support the concept that darinaparsin is a multivalent chemotherapeutic affecting several critical processes in neoplastic cells.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Darinaparsin and sodium arsenite induce stress granule formation</title><p>Since darinaparsin is an organic arsenical, we first sought to evaluate whether darinaparsin could elicit RNA stress granules. To determine the effect of darinaparsin on cells, we treated cells with darinaparsin and compared its effects to those of sodium arsenite. Treatment of HeLa cells with 0.05 mM darinaparsin for 30 minutes induced stress granule formation, detected with antibodies against G3BP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0027699-g001">Figure 1</xref>). A titration of darinaparsin for short incubations showed stress granule formation was induced in a majority of cells at 0.03 mM. Sodium arsenite treatment at 0.5 mM induced stress granule formation, as previously reported <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Kolobova1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Kedersha1">[2]</xref>. Nevertheless, the stress granules induced by darinaparsin appeared smaller and were significantly greater in number when compared to sodium arsenite-induced stress granules, and the granules were more dispersed throughout the cytoplasm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0027699-g001">Figure 1E</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0027699-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0027699.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Darinaparsin and sodium arsenite induce RNA stress granules.</title><p>HeLa cells were treated with 0.5 mM Sodium arsenite or 0.05 mM darinaparsin for 45 minutes at 37&#x000b0;C. Cells were fixed with supplemented 4&#x00025; PFA. All cells are stained for DNA with Dapi (blue) and <bold>A.</bold> G3BP (green) and GW-182 (red), <bold>B.</bold> AKAP350 (green) and G3BP (red), <bold>C.</bold> Caprin-1 (green) and G3BP (red), <bold>D.</bold> CCAR1 (green) and G3BP (red). <bold>E.</bold> The number of granules in sodium arsenite- and darinaparsin-treated cells was quantified using ImageJ software. Results are mean &#x0002b;/&#x02212; standard error. &#x0002a;p&#x0003c;0.0001 (Scale bars: 20 &#x000b5;M).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0027699.g001"/></fig><p>As noted above, stress granule formation is a dynamic process. Upon initial stress granule induction, many small granules form throughout the cytoplasm. As stress continues, the smaller granules coalesce near the nucleus to form large, complete stress granules <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Kolobova1">[1]</xref>. The large, complete stress granules generally have similar compositions, but the smaller granules can vary in composition <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Kolobova1">[1]</xref>. Because stress granules can vary in composition, we evaluated the stress granules induced by darinaparsin in HeLa cells compared with stress granules induced by sodium arsenite, and cells that received no treatment served as a control (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0027699-g001">Figure 1</xref>). We first studied the association of markers of Processing bodies (P bodies) with induced stress granules. P-bodies serve as RNA degradation centers and are present in the absence or presence of cellular stress <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Kedersha1">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Anderson1">[13]</xref>. Stress granules and P-bodies are separate entities, but they do communicate with one another and are dynamically linked <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Kedersha2">[14]</xref>. To ensure the granules induced by darinaparsin were not P-bodies, we compared staining of a P-body marker, GW182, and a stress granule marker, G3BP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0027699-g001">Figure 1A</xref>). In untreated cells, GW182-stained P-bodies were small and distributed throughout the cytoplasm, while G3BP was diffuse throughout the cytosol. Sodium arsenite treatment induced large G3BP-staining stress granules that clustered in the perinuclear region. Only a few of the larger stress granules showed dual immunostaining with both G3BP and GW182. Similarly, there was little overlap between the smaller darinaparsin-induced granules and GW182-labelled P-bodies.</p><p>We next examined the presence of proteins previously found in stress granules in the granules induced by darinaparsin. AKAP350A, a large scaffolding protein, localizes to stress granules and is important for their complete formation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Kolobova1">[1]</xref>. Knockdown of AKAP350A with siRNA results in smaller stress granules upon treatment with sodium arsenite. AKAP350A colocalized with G3BP in stress granules induced by sodium arsenite (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0027699-g001">Figure 1B</xref>). After darinaparsin treatment, some granules contained both AKAP350A and G3BP, while others contained only one of the components. Granules containing only one component were typically smaller and in the periphery of the cytoplasm. AKAP350A interacts with RNA-binding proteins Caprin-1 and CCAR1, both of which are also present in stress granules <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Kolobova1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Solomon1">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Rishi1">[16]</xref>. Caprin-1 colocalized with G3BP in stress granules induced by both sodium arsenite and darinaparsin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0027699-g001">Figure 1C</xref>). CCAR1 and G3BP colocalized in stress granules induced by sodium arsenite (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0027699-g001">Figure 1D</xref>). However, as with AKAP350A, in darinaparsin-treated cells some stress granules contain both CCAR1 and G3BP, but many smaller granules stained for only one of the components.</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Darinaparsin inhibits microtubule polymerization</title><p>In previous studies, we have shown that microtubules are necessary for complete stress granule formation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Kolobova1">[1]</xref>. Pre-treatment of cells with nocodazole, which inhibits microtubule polymerization, prior to treatment with sodium arsenite, leads to the formation of stress granules which are smaller and greater in number. The smaller granules suggest incomplete stress granule formation. The similarity between darinaparsin-induced and nocodazole/sodium arsenite-induced stress granules led us to hypothesize that darinaparsin induces incomplete stress granule formation due to microtubule depolymerization. Immunofluorescence in HeLa cells demonstrated that treatment with darinaparsin did induce microtubule depolymerization along with inducing stress granule formation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0027699-g002">Figure 2A</xref>). In cells treated with darinaparsin, microtubules were almost completely depolymerized, showing mainly cytosolic alpha-tubulin staining. In contrast, sodium arsenite treatment had no demonstrable effect on microtubules.</p><fig id="pone-0027699-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0027699.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Darinaparsin inhibits microtubule polymerization.</title><p><bold>A.</bold> HeLa cells were treated with 0.5 mM Sodium arsenite or 0.05 mM darinaparsin, or 33 nM Nocodazole/0.5 mM Sodium arsenite. Cells are stained for DNA (Dapi, blue), a-tubulin (red), and Caprin-1 (green; stress granule marker). GTP-initiation microtubule polymerization in the presence of darinaparsin (<bold>B</bold>) and sodium arsenite (<bold>C</bold>) was measured <italic>in vitro</italic>. (Scale bars: 20 &#x000b5;M).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0027699.g002"/></fig><p>To verify the effects of darinaparsin on microtubules, we assessed <italic>in vitro</italic> microtubule polymerization (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0027699-g002">Figure 2B</xref>). Darinaparsin inhibited GTP-stimulated microtubule polymerization in a concentration-dependent manner. Darinaparsin also inhibited polymerization of microtubules stimulated by taxol, a microtubule stabilizer, at similar concentrations (data not shown). These results suggest that darinaparsin sequesters free tubulin monomers, similar to the action of nocodazole <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Xu1">[17]</xref>. In contrast, sodium arsenite had only minimal effect on microtubule polymerization at concentrations up to 1 mM. Importantly, darinaparsin had no ability <italic>in vitro</italic> to depolymerize already polymerized microtubules (data not shown).</p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Stress granules must complete formation before dispersal</title><p>We have previously shown that stress granules initially form as small granules in the cytosol, that then coalesce into the final, complete stress granules in the perinuclear region <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Kolobova1">[1]</xref>. We now sought to evaluate stress granule dynamics further by investigating their dispersal once stress is relieved. Because darinaparsin, sodium arsenite, and nocodazole/sodium arsenite have differing effects, we monitored the dynamics of stress granule formation and dispersal during each treatment.</p><p>We assessed the course of recovery of HeLa cells after treatment with 0.05 mM darinaparsin, 0.5 mM sodium arsenite, or a combination of 33 nM nocodazole and 0.5 mM sodium arsenite. Cells were fixed at the end of treatment for 45 minutes and after periods of recovery without treatment for up to three hours in complete media (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0027699-g003">Figure 3</xref>). At the end of treatment, sodium arsenite-treated cells had large, complete stress granules and intact microtubules, as expected (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0027699-g003">Figure 3</xref>). After recovering without drug for one hour, the sodium arsenite-treated cells showed fewer stress granules, and by two hours of recovery, the stress granules had completely dispersed into the cytoplasm. The microtubules remained unaffected by the sodium arsenite treatment for the duration of the experiment.</p><fig id="pone-0027699-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0027699.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Stress granules must complete formation before dispersal.</title><p>HeLa cells were treated with 0.5 mM Sodium arsenite or 0.05 mM darinaparsin. The 0 hour timepoint was taken at the end of treatment. For recovery, cells were incubated in complete RPMI media. Cells were fixed at timepoints with supplemented 4&#x00025; PFA and stained for Caprin-1 and &#x003b1;-tubulin (<bold>A</bold>). <bold>B.</bold> Granule size was quantified for each hour of recovery using ImageJ software. There were no granules at 2 hours of recovery from sodium arsenite. Results are mean &#x0002b;/&#x02212; standard error. &#x0002b;p&#x0003c;0.0001 vs. sodium arsenite-treated. &#x0002a;p&#x0003c;0.0001 vs. darinaparsin 0 hours of recovery. &#x0002a;&#x0002a;p&#x0003c;0.0001 vs. darinaparsin 1 hour of recovery. (Scale bars: 20 &#x000b5;M).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0027699.g003"/></fig><p>In cells treated with darinaparsin, the microtubules were depolymerized and stress granules were significantly smaller than sodium arsenite-induced stress granules at the end of treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0027699-g003">Figure 3</xref>). After one hour of recovery in the absence of drug, the microtubules in cells treated with darinaparsin were repolymerized, and larger stress granules were now observed, especially in the perinuclear region. After three hours of recovery, darinaparsin treated cells fully recovered with dispersal of stress granules. Similar results were obtained in recovery from the combination of treatment with both nocodazole and sodium arsenite, but recovery occurred more slowly (data not shown). The dynamics of stress granule formation are more clearly seen in continuous live cell imaging. <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0027699.s001">Movie S1</xref> demonstrates that, following removal of darinaparsin, small G3BP-labeled stress granules first coalesced in the perinuclear region and then dispersed. These results suggest that stress granules must complete formation by coalescence along microtubule-dependent tracks before they can disperse into the cytoplasm.</p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>Darinaparsin affects Sonic Hedgehog signaling</title><p>Recent investigations have reported that ATO inhibits hedgehog signaling <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Beauchamp1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Kim1">[19]</xref>. We sought to investigate whether darinaparsin also affects hedgehog signaling. Previous studies have shown that ATO does not affect primary cilium formation in mouse embryonic fibroblasts (MEFs) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Beauchamp1">[18]</xref>. To test the effects of darinaparsin on primary cilia, NIH 3T3 cells were grown and induced to form primary cilia. The cells were treated with 100 nM Smoothened Agonist (SAG) with or without 600 nM or 1 &#x000b5;M darinaparsin for 24 hours <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Ehtesham1">[20]</xref>. The concentration of darinaparsin needed for long incubations was titrated, and 600 nM was the optimal concentration to have an effect while not causing cell death. Fixed cells were stained for Arl13b to mark primary cilia. Unlike cells treated with ATO, cells treated with 600 nM darinaparsin had a significant decrease in the number of primary cilia. There was further loss of primary cilia at 1 &#x000b5;M darinaparsin, suggesting a concentration-dependent decrease in primary cilia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0027699-g004">Figure 4</xref>). In darinaparsin-treated cells that did form primary cilia, the primary cilia were shorter in length. Similar to ATO <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Beauchamp1">[18]</xref>, darinaparsin treatment did not alter the intracellular localization of Gli1 (data not shown). Given the loss of primary cilia observed with darinaparsin treatment, we also evaluated the drug's effect on Shh signaling through an assay of Gli1 activation. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0027699-g004">Figure 4</xref> demonstrates that darinaparsin elicited a concentration-dependent inhibition of Shh signaling, as seen with ATO <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Kim1">[19]</xref>. These results indicate that darinaparsin has broad effects on stress granule formation, microtubule dynamics and Shh signaling.</p><fig id="pone-0027699-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0027699.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Darinaparsin inhibits Sonic Hedgehog signaling and primary cilia formation.</title><p>NIH 3T3 fibroblasts were treated with 1001 nM SAG (Shh agonist) with or without 0.6 &#x000b5;M or 1 &#x000b5;M darinaparsin (ZIO-101). <bold>A.</bold> Cells were fixed with 4&#x00025; PFA and stained for DNA (Dapi; blue), primary cilia (Arl13b; green), and &#x003b1;-tubulin (red). <bold>B.</bold> The number of primary cilia was determined from 6 samples per genotype (15&#x02013;30 cells per sample). <bold>C.</bold> The length of primary cilia was determined using Image J software. P values were calculated using unpaired t-test with n&#x02013;1 degree of freedom (GraphPad). &#x0002a;&#x0002a;p&#x0003c;0.005, &#x0002a;&#x0002a;&#x0002a;p&#x0003c;0.0001. <bold>D.</bold> Luciferase assays were performed in the absence or presence of darinaparsin. (Scale bars: 20 &#x000b5;M).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0027699.g004"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2e"><title>Darinaparsin effects are independent of Mdr1 expression</title><p>Darinaparsin is a multivalent drug that appears to be more potent than similar drugs, such as ATO. Therefore, we tested its efficacy in cells with multiple drug resistance. Multiple drug resistance transporters are often a limiting factor on the practical efficacy of chemotherapeutic agents, especially in recurrent cancers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Chan1">[21]</xref>. While ATO is used to treat hematological malignancies, its use is limited in cancers expressing the multiple drug resistance protein, MRP-1 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Diaz1">[8]</xref>. MRP1-expressing cells are resistant to ATO treatment, but are sensitive to treatment with darinaparsin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Diaz1">[8]</xref>. This prompted us to examine another major drug resistance protein, Mdr1, which can rapidly pump drugs out of resistant cancer cells. Previous investigations have shown that ATO is not a substrate for Mdr1, and thus is effective in Mdr1-expressing cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Chan1">[21]</xref>. We evaluated the effects of darinaparsin on stress granule formation in uterine sarcoma cells lines with or without expression of Mdr1. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0027699-g005">Figure 5</xref> demonstrates that darinaparsin and sodium arsenite induced stress granules in both ME-SA cells, which do not express Mdr1, and ME-SA/Dx5 cells, which strongly over-express Mdr1. Indeed, the Mdr1-over-expressing cells appeared to be more susceptible to darinaparsin treatment as shown by the rapid rounding up of these cells after treatment. Along with previous studies, these results demonstrate that darinaparsin effects are not altered by expression of multiple-drug resistance transporters.</p><fig id="pone-0027699-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0027699.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Darinaparsin is effective in Mdr-1-expressing cells.</title><p>ME-SA and ME-SA/Dx5 cells were untreated or treated with 0.5 mM Sodium arsenite or 0.05 mM darinaparsin for 30 minutes at 37&#x000b0;C. Cells were fixed with supplemented 4&#x00025; PFA and stained for G3BP.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0027699.g005"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Discussion</title><p>Arsenic salts are one of the oldest pharmaceutical classes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Verstovsek1">[3]</xref>. Treatment with arsenicals has been utilized for both infectious diseases and cancer. While ATO is approved for treatment of refractory leukemias, its toxicity limits its use <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Mann1">[6]</xref>. In contrast, darinaparsin, an organic arsenical, shows a wide range of potency against many cancer cells and has low toxicity when administered in humans <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Mann1">[6]</xref>. While darinaparsin induces apoptosis and G<sub>2</sub>/M arrest in a number of cell lines, the exact mechanism responsible for the anti-neoplastic effects of the compound seem to vary according to cell types <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Mann1">[6]</xref>. The present investigation indicates that darinaparsin acts as a multivalent pharmaceutical that induces a stress response, but does not permit its completion due to its influence as a microtubule polymerization inhibitor. Microtubule depolymerization by darinaparsin also causes loss of primary cilia and Shh signaling, likely due to a loss of Smoothened presentation. Inhibition of microtubule polymerization by darinaparsin likely accounts for the arrest of cells in G<sub>2</sub>/M noted in previous studies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Mann1">[6]</xref>. The G<sub>2</sub>/M arrest is characteristic of microtubule depolymerization inhibitors such as nocodazole <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Jordan1">[22]</xref>. Together these effects make this organic arsenical drug a potent chemotherapeutic with multiple mechanisms that target key regulators of neoplasia.</p><p>Formation of RNA stress granules following various cellular stressors is considered a critical adaptive mechanism in cell survival. Stress granules accumulate translational intermediates including critical mRNAs that are important for reestablishment of cell function after the release of stress <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Kedersha1">[2]</xref>. Darinaparsin induces stress granule formation and simultaneously inhibits microtubule polymerization. This scenario leads to incomplete formation of stress granules. The inability to form stress granules or incomplete stress granule formation likely leads to apoptosis in affected cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Thomas1">[12]</xref>. Importantly, the unique property of darinaparsin to stimulate incomplete stress granule formation has allowed us to investigate the process of stress granule processing after removal of the blockade. Removal of darinaparsin led to completion of stress granule formation, with coalescence of smaller granules into larger perinuclear granules, coincident with the repolymerization of microtubules. These results are consistent with our previous results that stress granules form initially in the cell periphery and then coalesce after centripetal transport along microtubule tracks <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Kolobova1">[1]</xref>. Following withdrawal of darinaparsin, stress granules only dissipated after completion of granule formation. These findings indicate that stress granules must complete their full program of formation and coalescence prior to subsequent disassembly.</p><p>Recent investigations have noted that arsenic trioxide can inhibit Shh signaling <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Beauchamp1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Kim1">[19]</xref>. Similarly, we have observed that darinaparsin also strongly inhibits Shh-induced Gli1 expression. Nevertheless, in contrast with arsenic trioxide, darinaparsin also causes the loss of microtubules and the primary cilium, the site of Smoothened presentation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Beauchamp1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Kim1">[19]</xref>. Since Shh is considered a major driver in multiple cancers, it appears that darinaparsin has the ability to dismantle key aspects of Shh signaling machinery necessary for the proliferative drive in neoplastic cells.</p><p>Darinaparsin appears to be more potent but less toxic than ATO. Previous studies have noted that darinaparsin and ATO both induce an increase in ROS, but darinaparsin produces a greater increase <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Tsimberidou1">[4]</xref>. Darinaparsin is a potent inhibitor of microtubule polymerization while the effects of ATO on microtubules can vary. Some studies have reported that ATO is a strong microtubule polymerizing agent that synergizes with taxol, while others have shown ATO inhibition of the effects of taxol <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Carr1">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Duan1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Ling1">[25]</xref>. Also, darinaparsin is effective in cells with ATO-resistance <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Diaz1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Matulis1">[9]</xref>. Part of this latter difference may be due to the ability of some multiple drug resistance transporters, such as MRP1, to transport ATO out of cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Matulis1">[9]</xref>. In contrast, the expression of MRP1 does not alter the effects or potency of darinaparsin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Diaz1">[8]</xref>. As noted previously for ATO <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Chan1">[21]</xref>, effectiveness of darinaparsin is not altered in Mdr1-expressing cells. In clinical trials, darinaparsin appears less toxic than ATO <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Mann1">[6]</xref>. In general, organic arsenicals, such as darinaparsin, are typically less toxic than inorganic arsenicals, such as ATO <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Matulis1">[9]</xref>. The lower toxicity of darinaparsin may seem a bit counterintuitive given its broad range of activities, including strong action against microtubule polymerization. Indeed, the differences in practical therapeutic effects of darinaparsin may accrue from a relative therapeutic index of multiple specific target activities impacting neoplastic cells versus non-specific generalized effects of arsenicals affecting mitochondrial functions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Mann1">[6]</xref>. In any case, the range of actions of darinaparsin against multiple drivers of neoplastic cells may make this organic arsenical an effective therapy for multiple resistant solid and hematological malignancies.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s4"><title>Methods</title><sec id="s4a"><title>Cell Culture</title><p>HeLa cells (American Type Culture Collection, ATCC) were maintained at 37&#x000b0;C in 5&#x00025; CO<sub>2</sub> using complete RPMI media supplemented with 10&#x00025; fetal bovine serum (FBS). Polyjet was used for transfections according to the manufacturer's protocol (SignaGen). NIH 3T3 fibroblasts were maintained in high-glucose Dulbecco's modified Eagle's (DMEM) medium supplemented with 10&#x00025; FBS. To induce cilia formation, 3T3 cells were grown on poly-<italic>L</italic>-lysine coated coverslips and maintained in DMEM medium supplemented with 0.5&#x00025; calf serum. ME-SA and ME-SA/Dx5 cells (American Type Culture Collection, ATCC) were maintained at 37&#x000b0;C in 5&#x00025; CO<sub>2</sub> using complete McCoy's media supplemented with 10&#x00025; FBS.</p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title>Cell stress and recovery</title><p>For stress induction, HeLa cells were incubated at 37&#x000b0;C for 45 minutes (fixed cells) or 30 minutes (live cells) with a final concentration of either 0.5 mM sodium arsenite (Riedel de Haen) or 0.05 mM darinaparsin (Ziopharm). For microtubule depolymerization, cells were first incubated on ice for 30 minutes. Then, cells were treated with 33 nM nocodazole (Calbiochem) for 90 minutes at 37&#x000b0;C. In recovery experiments, cells were washed twice with serum-free media after treatment, and incubated in complete RPMI media at 37&#x000b0;C for duration of recovery. For primary cilia staining, 3T3 cells were treated with100 nM Smoothened Agonist (SAG) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0027699-Ehtesham1">[20]</xref>, and with or without darinaparsin 18 hours before staining.</p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title>Fluorescence microscopy and analysis</title><p>For stress and recovery studies, HeLa cells grown on coverslips were fixed at room temperature for 15 minutes using 4&#x00025; paraformaldehyde (PFA) supplemented with 0.1&#x00025; Triton X-100, 80 mM K-PIPES pH 7.2, 1 mM EGTA, 1 mM MgSO<sub>4</sub>, and 30&#x00025; glycerol. Cells were permeabilized with 0.25&#x00025; Triton X-100 and blocked with 5&#x00025; normal serum for one hour at room temperature. The cells were incubated with primary antibodies for one hour at room temperature: rabbit anti-AKAP350A (1&#x02236;200), rabbit anti-Caprin-1 (1&#x02236;1000), mouse anti-&#x003b1;-tubulin (1&#x02236;5000, Sigma), rabbit anti-CCAR1 (1&#x02236;1000), goat anti-GW182 (1&#x02236;100, Santa Cruz), and mouse anti-G3BP (1&#x02236;800, BD Transduction). This was followed by incubation at room temperature for one hour with species-specific fluorescent secondary antibodies (1&#x02236;500; Invitrogen or Jackson Immunoresearch). Coverslips were mounted using Prolong Gold with DAPI (Invitrogen). Cells were imaged using a 60&#x000d7; oil immersion lens on Olympus FV-1000 confocal fluorescence microscope (Vanderbilt Cell Imaging Shared Resource). The number and average size of granules in sodium arsenite- and darinaparsin-treated cells were determined using ImageJ software (NIH). At least ten cells were used per calculation. Changes in granule number and size were analyzed using a Student's t-test. Changes in granule size over time in darinaparsin-treated cells were analyzed using a one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) with post hoc examination of significant means using Tukey's test. Live-cell imaging was performed using a 60&#x000d7; oil immersion lens on the DeltaVision Deconvolution microscope (Vanderbilt Epithelial Biology Center Imaging Resource).</p><p>For primary cilia staining, 3T3 cells grown on coverslips were fixed for 20 minutes in 4&#x00025; paraformaldehyde and permeabilized for 15 minutes in PBS with 0.3&#x00025; Triton-X 100. The cells were incubated in primary antibodies overnight at 4&#x000b0;C: rabbit-anti-Arl13b (1&#x02236;2000; gift from Tamara Caspary, Emery University) and mouse-anti-&#x003b1;-tubulin (1&#x02236;5000; Calbiochem). This was followed by incubation at room temperature for one hour with species-specific fluorescent secondary antibodies (1&#x02236;1000; Invitrogen). DAPI was included in the final washes before the samples were mounted in Fluor Saver (Calbiochem) for microscopy. Images were taken with Opti-Grid Confocal microscope. Cilia frequencies were determined from Arl13b/DAPI- stained cells from 6 samples per treatment (15&#x02013;30 cells per sample). Ciliary length was measured using NIH ImageJ software. Bases and ends of immunolabeled individual cilia were marked in the confocal z-stack images and outlined, and the calculated length was recorded. P values were calculated using unpaired t-test (GraphPad).</p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title>Microtubule polymerization</title><p>The effects of darinaparsin on microtubule polymerization were assayed using a fluorescence-based polymerization assay (Cytoskeleton, Inc). Microtubule polymerization was initiated by GTP or GTP/Taxol (1 &#x000b5;M) in the presence of increasing concentrations of either darinaparsin (0.3 &#x000b5;M to 300 &#x000b5;M) or arsenite (1 &#x000b5;M to 1 mM). Polymerization was monitored each minute by fluorescence measurement for a total of one hour in a Biotek Fluorescence plate reader.</p></sec><sec id="s4e"><title>Luciferase reporter assay</title><p>NIH3T3 cells were plated at 1.0&#x000d7;10<sup>5</sup> cells/ml (24-well plate) 16 hours before transfection. Cells were co-transfected with 0.3 &#x000b5;g 8XGli1-luciferase reporter construct and 0.03 &#x000b5;g Renilla-luciferase control construct in each well. At 8 hours after transfection, cells were fed low serum medium (0.5&#x00025; calf serum &#x0002b; DMEM), and then treated with Shh agonist (10 nM SAG) with or without darinaparsin for an additional 20 hours. Luciferase assays were performed with the Dual-Glo Luciferase System (Promega) according to the manufacturer's instructions. Each assay was performed in triplicate and the results are presented as the relative fold-increase (normalized to Renilla-luciferase activity) over non-SAG-treated cells.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0027699.s001"><label>Movie S1</label><caption><p>Stress granules must complete formation before dispersal. HeLa cells were transfected with pcherry-G3BP using Effectene. Cells were treated with 0.05 mM darinaparsin for 30 minutes, washed with serum-free media twice, then incubated in complete media for recovery.</p><p>(MOV)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0027699.s001.mov" mimetype="video" mime-subtype="quicktime"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>Confocal images were generated using the Vanderbilt University Medical Center Cell Imaging Shared Resource. Ziopharm provided darinaparsin. John Schrader provided the Caprin-1 antibody, and Tamara Caspary provided the Arl13b antibody.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="conflict"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>This work was supported in part by funding from Ziopharm, who is the maker of Darinaparsin. The funding was an unrestricted research grant to Dr. Kolobova. No other financial interactions are involved. This funding from Ziopharm does not alter the authors' adherence to all the PLoS ONE policies on sharing data and materials.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding: </bold>This work was supported by National Institutes of Health grants RO1DK43405 (to J.R.G.) and NS042205 (to C.C.). Funding was also provided by the Childhood Brain Tumor Foundation (to C.C.). Confocal images were generated using the Vanderbilt University Medical Center Cell Imaging Shared Resource (supported by National Institutes of Health grants CA68485, DK20593, DK58404, HD15052, DK59637, and EY08126). Ziopharm provided funding for E.K. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0027699-Kolobova1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kolobova</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Efimov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaverina</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Rishi</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Schrader</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Microtubule-dependent association of AKAP350A and CCAR1 with RNA stress granules.</article-title>             <source>Exp Cell Res</source>             <volume>15</volume>             <fpage>542</fpage>             <lpage>555</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19073175</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027699-Kedersha1"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kedersha</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Mammalian stress granules and processing bodies.</article-title>             <source>Methods Enzymol</source>             <volume>431</volume>             <fpage>61</fpage>             <lpage>81</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17923231</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027699-Verstovsek1"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Verstovsek</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Giles</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Quint&#x000e1;s-Cardama</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Perez</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ravandi-Kashani</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Arsenic derivatives in hematologic malignancies: a role beyond acute promyelocytic leukemia?</article-title>             <source>Hematol Oncol</source>             <volume>24</volume>             <fpage>181</fpage>             <lpage>188</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16783836</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027699-Tsimberidou1"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsimberidou</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Camacho</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Verstovsek</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>A phase I clinical trial of darinaparsin in patients with refractory solid tumors.</article-title>             <source>Clin Cancer Res</source>             <volume>15</volume>             <fpage>4769</fpage>             <lpage>4776</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19584162</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027699-Camps1"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Camp&#x000e0;s</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Casta&#x000f1;er</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Darinaparsin.</article-title>             <source>Drugs Future</source>             <volume>34</volume>             <fpage>97</fpage>             <lpage>100</lpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027699-Mann1"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallner</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lossos</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>WH</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Darinaparsin: a novel organic arsenical with promising anticancer activity.</article-title>             <source>Drug Evaluation</source>             <volume>18</volume>             <fpage>1727</fpage>             <lpage>1734</lpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027699-Wu1"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Feun</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Veldhuizen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gold</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Phase II study of darinaparsin in patients with advanced hepatocellular carcinoma.</article-title>             <source>Invest New Drugs</source>             <volume>28</volume>             <fpage>670</fpage>             <lpage>676</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19565187</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027699-Diaz1"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Diaz</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Marcoux</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kourelis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Colombo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>A novel arsenical has antitumor activity toward As2O3-resistant and MRP1/ABCC1-overexpressing cell lines.</article-title>             <source>Leukemia</source>             <volume>22</volume>             <fpage>1853</fpage>             <lpage>1863</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18633430</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027699-Matulis1"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matulis</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Morales</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Yehiayan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Croutch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gutman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Darinaparsin induces a unique cellular response and is active in an arsenic-trioxide resistant myeloma cell line.</article-title>             <source>Mol Cancer Ther</source>             <volume>8</volume>             <fpage>1197</fpage>             <lpage>1206</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19417148</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027699-QuintsCardama1"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quint&#x000e1;s-Cardama</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Verstovsek</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Freireich</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kantarjian</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Chemical and clinical development of darinaparsin, a novel organic arsenic derivative.</article-title>             <source>Anticancer Agents Med Chem</source>             <volume>8</volume>             <fpage>904</fpage>             <lpage>909</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19075572</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027699-Tian1"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Peehl</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Knox</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Darinaparsin (ZIO-101) is a novel cytotoxic and radiosensitizing agent for prostate cancer.</article-title>             <source>Eur J Cancer Supplements</source>             <volume>8</volume>             <fpage>161</fpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027699-Thomas1"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Loschi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Desbats</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Boccaccio</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>RNA granules: the good, the bad and the ugly.</article-title>             <source>Cell Signal</source>             <volume>23</volume>             <fpage>324</fpage>             <lpage>334</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20813183</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027699-Anderson1"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kedersha</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>RNA granules.</article-title>             <source>Cell Biol</source>             <volume>172</volume>             <fpage>803</fpage>             <lpage>808</lpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027699-Kedersha2"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kedersha</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Stoecklin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayodele</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yacono</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lykke-Andersen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Stress granules and processing bodies are dynamically linked sites of mRNP remodeling.</article-title>             <source>J Cell Biol</source>             <volume>169</volume>             <fpage>871</fpage>             <lpage>884</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15967811</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027699-Solomon1"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Solomon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>David</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Schubert</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Distinct structural features of caprin-1 mediate its interaction with G3BP-1 and its induction of phosphorylation of eukaryotic translation initiation factor 2alpha, entry to cytoplasmic stress granules, and selective interaction with a subset of mRNAs.</article-title>             <source>Mol Cell Biol</source>             <volume>27</volume>             <fpage>2324</fpage>             <lpage>2342</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17210633</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027699-Rishi1"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rishi</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyanapalli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wali</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohammad</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Identification and characterization of a cell cycle and apoptosis regulatory protein-1 as a novel mediator of apoptosis signaling by retinoid CD437.</article-title>             <source>J Biol Chem</source>             <volume>278</volume>             <fpage>33422</fpage>             <lpage>33435</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12816952</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027699-Xu1"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ludue&#x000f1;a</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Interaction of nocodazole with tubulin isotypes.</article-title>             <source>Drug Dev Res</source>             <volume>55</volume>             <fpage>91</fpage>             <lpage>96</lpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027699-Beauchamp1"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beauchamp</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ringer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bulut</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Sajwan</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Arsenic trioxide inhibits human cancer cell growth and tumor development in mice by blocking Hedgehog/GLI pathway.</article-title>             <source>J Clin Inves</source>             <volume>121</volume>             <fpage>148</fpage>             <lpage>160</lpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027699-Kim1"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Beachy</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Arsenic antagonizes the Hedgehog pathway by preventing ciliary accumulation and reducing stability of the Gli2 transcriptional effector.</article-title>             <source>PNAS</source>             <volume>107</volume>             <fpage>13432</fpage>             <lpage>13437</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20624968</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027699-Ehtesham1"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ehtesham</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarangi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Valadez</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Chanthaphaychith</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Becher</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Ligand-dependent activation of the hedgehog pathway in glioma progenitor cells.</article-title>             <source>Oncogene</source>             <volume>26</volume>             <fpage>5752</fpage>             <lpage>5761</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17353902</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027699-Chan1"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>JY-W</given-names></name><name><surname>Siu</surname><given-names>KP-Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Fung</surname><given-names>K-P</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Effect of arsenic trioxide on multidrug resistant hepatocellular carcinoma cells.</article-title>             <source>Cancer Lett</source>             <volume>236</volume>             <fpage>250</fpage>             <lpage>258</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15982806</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027699-Jordan1"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Thrower</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1992</year>             <article-title>Effects of vinblastin, podophyllotoxin, and nocodazole on mitotic spindles. Implications for the role of microtubule dynamics in mitosis.</article-title>             <source>J Cell Sci</source>             <volume>102</volume>             <fpage>401</fpage>             <lpage>416</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1506423</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027699-Carr1"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carr&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Carles</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Andr&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Douillard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ciccolini</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Involvement of microtubules and mitochondria in the antagonism of arsenic trioxide on paclitaxel-induced apoptosis.</article-title>             <source>Biochem Pharmacol</source>             <volume>63</volume>             <fpage>1831</fpage>             <lpage>1842</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12034367</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027699-Duan1"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>X-F</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y-L</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>H-Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>H-Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Synergistic mitosis-arresting effects of arsenic trioxide and paclitaxel on human malignant lymphocytes.</article-title>             <source>Chem Biol Interact</source>             <volume>183</volume>             <fpage>220</fpage>             <lpage>230</lpage>          </element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0027699-Ling1"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>Y-H</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>J-D</given-names></name><name><surname>Holland</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Perez-Soler</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Arsenic trioxide produces polymerization of microtubules and mitotic arrest before apoptosis in human tumor cell lines.</article-title>             <source>Mol Pharmacol</source>             <volume>62</volume>             <fpage>529</fpage>             <lpage>538</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12181429</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>