<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25153181</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4143374</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-12153</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0105788</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Engineering and Technology</subject><subj-group><subject>Nanotechnology</subject><subj-group><subject>Nanomaterials</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Physical Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Chemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Physical Chemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Chemical Equilibrium</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Chemical Properties</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Materials Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Materials by Attribute</subject><subject>Materials by Structure</subject><subject>Materials Characterization</subject><subject>Materials Chemistry</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Physics</subject><subj-group><subject>Thermodynamics</subject><subj-group><subject>Free Energy</subject><subj-group><subject>Gibbs Free Energy</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Enthalpy</subject><subject>Entropy</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>High Temperature Stability of Onion-Like Carbon vs Highly Oriented Pyrolytic Graphite</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Onion-Like Carbon Stability</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Latini</surname><given-names>Alessandro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tomellini</surname><given-names>Massimo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lazzarini</surname><given-names>Laura</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bertoni</surname><given-names>Giovanni</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gazzoli</surname><given-names>Delia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bossa</surname><given-names>Luigi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gozzi</surname><given-names>Daniele</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Dipartimento di Chimica, Universit&#x000e0; di Roma La Sapienza, Roma, Italy</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Dipartimento di Scienze e Tecnologie Chimiche, Universit&#x000e0; di Roma Tor Vergata, Roma, Italy</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>IMEM &#x02013; CNR, Parma, Italy</addr-line></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Roccatano</surname><given-names>Danilo</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Jacobs University Bremen, Germany</addr-line></aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>daniele.gozzi@uniroma1.it</email></corresp><fn fn-type="conflict"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: AL D. Gozzi. Performed the experiments: AL D. Gozzi LL GB D. Gazzoli LB. Analyzed the data: D. Gozzi MT. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: AL. Contributed to the writing of the manuscript: D. Gozzi MT. Galvanic cell and experiment preparation, emf measurements, data elaboration: AL LB D. Gozzi. Evaluation of surface contribution and discussion of results: MT. HRTEM and EELS measurements: LL GB. microRaman measurements: D. Gazzoli.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>25</day><month>8</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue>8</issue><elocation-id>e105788</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>19</day><month>3</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>7</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Latini et al</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>The thermodynamic stability of onion-like carbon (OLC) nanostructures with respect to highly oriented pyrolytic graphite (HOPG) was determined in the interval 765&#x02013;1030 K by the electromotive force (<italic>emf</italic>) measurements of solid electrolyte galvanic cell: (Low) Pt|Cr<sub>3</sub>C<sub>2</sub>,CrF<sub>2</sub>,OLC|CaF<sub>2</sub>s.c.|Cr<sub>3</sub>C<sub>2</sub>,CrF<sub>2</sub>,HOPG|Pt (High). The free energy change of transformation HOPG&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;OLC was found positive below 920.6 K crossing the zero value at this temperature. Its trend with temperature was well described by a 3<sup>rd</sup> degree polynomial. The unexpected too high values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e001.jpg"/></inline-formula> jointly to the HR-TEM, STEM and EELS evidences that showed OLC completely embedded in rigid cages made of a Cr<sub>3</sub>C<sub>2</sub>/CrF<sub>2</sub> matrix, suggested that carbon in the electrodes experienced different internal pressures. This was confirmed by the evaluation under constant volume of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e002.jpg"/></inline-formula> by the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e003.jpg"/></inline-formula> ratio for OLC (0.5 MPa K<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) and HOPG (8 Pa K<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e004.jpg"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e005.jpg"/></inline-formula> are the isobaric thermal expansion and isothermal compressibility coefficients, respectively. The temperature dependency of the pressure was derived and utilized to calculate the enthalpy and entropy changes as function of temperature and pressure. The highest value of the internal pressure experienced by OLC was calculated to be about 7 GPa at the highest temperature. At 920.6 K, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e006.jpg"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e007.jpg"/></inline-formula> values are 95.8 kJ mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and 104.1 JK<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, respectively. The surface contributions to the energetic of the system were evaluated and they were found negligible compared with the bulk terms. As a consequence of the high internal pressure, the values of the enthalpy and entropy changes were mainly attributed to the formation of carbon defects in OLC considered as multishell fullerenes. The change of the carbon defect fraction is reported as a function of temperature.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was partially financed through the PRIN 2009 Project no. 2009N4BJ4J and "Acquisizione di medie e grandi attrezzature scientifiche 2010" Universit&#x000e0; di Roma La Sapienza, no. C26G10KKK5. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="16"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>The authors confirm that all data underlying the findings are fully available without restriction. All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><title>Data Availability</title><p>The authors confirm that all data underlying the findings are fully available without restriction. All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</p></notes></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>The modifications of the internal arrangements and related energies of single wall carbon nanotubes (SWCNTs) in bundles were studied <xref rid="pone.0105788-Gozzi1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref> by our group in the particular situation where their dilatation due to the high temperatures was hindered being the bundles embedded in a matrix much less dilatable. This generates high internal pressures, which are a direct consequence of the increase of the internal energy of the system producing changes in the SWCNT configuration inside the bundle and deformation of SWCNTs too.</p><p>The knowledge of the thermodynamic stability of nanostructures is a fundamental aspect to design new nanostructured materials as well as to forecast their behaviour. Most of the information on this subject comes from computational studies <xref rid="pone.0105788-Tomanek1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref><xref rid="pone.0105788-Bernholc1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref><xref rid="pone.0105788-Girifalco1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref><xref rid="pone.0105788-Jiang1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref><xref rid="pone.0105788-Barnard1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref> and to a lesser extent by experimental works <xref rid="pone.0105788-Banhart1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref><xref rid="pone.0105788-Banhart2" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref><xref rid="pone.0105788-Sun1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>. To the best of author knowledge and with the exception of reference <xref rid="pone.0105788-Latini1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref><xref rid="pone.0105788-Latini2" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref><xref rid="pone.0105788-Gozzi2" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref> there are no articles dealing with thermodynamic measurements at high temperature on carbon nanostructures.</p><p>On the other hand, the 3D carbon phase diagram, where the third axis is the particle size, is still under consideration. The contribution of the surface energy to the bulk Gibbs free energy per atom of a cluster of <italic>n</italic> atoms in a given phase is strongly affected by the number of atoms itself. In general, a review of the literature regarding the structure of carbon nanoparticles <xref rid="pone.0105788-Shenderova1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref> highlights that at sizes below 1.8 nm, other carbon forms are abundant, such as fullerenes and onion-like carbon (OLC). Therefore, Kuznetsov et al. <xref rid="pone.0105788-Kuznetsov1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref> suggested to assign a corresponding region of the phase diagram to closed-shell <italic>sp</italic><sup>2</sup>-bonded nanocarbons. In their phase diagram the regions of stability are specifically indicated for fullerenes and OLC for <italic>n</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;10 to 10<sup>2</sup> atoms. The complete and thorough vision of the phase diagrams of these nanostructures in comparison with the phase diagram of the corresponding bulk materials has not been realized yet. There is still a great deal of work to be done in the construction of a complete <italic>P&#x02013;T&#x02013;n</italic> phase diagram of carbon. It is likely however that knowledge gained from theoretical and computational studies <xref rid="pone.0105788-Lee1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref> of nanocarbon stability plays an important role in the conception of such a diagram, with thermodynamic treatments of phase equilibrium showing the right way for pursuing the final goal.</p><p>Onion-like carbon are another class of carbon nanostructures, which are not exhaustively investigated yet though some published results envisage interesting applications such as an easy route to produce diamond nanoparticles <xref rid="pone.0105788-Banhart1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref><xref rid="pone.0105788-Banhart2" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref><xref rid="pone.0105788-Zaiser1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref> as well as to use them as reaction cells on the nanoscale <xref rid="pone.0105788-Sun1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>.</p><p>The scope of this work is to study, in conditions of reversibility, the thermodynamics of the high temperature transformation under volume constraint from highly oriented pyrolytic graphite (HOPG) to OLC.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Experimental</title><p>Since the experimental set-up was published elsewhere <xref rid="pone.0105788-Latini1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref><xref rid="pone.0105788-Latini2" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref><xref rid="pone.0105788-Gozzi2" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref> and there is the will of the authors to give in this paper more room to the chemical thermodynamics of our experiment and discussion of the results, we decided to describe more in details the wide experimental part in the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0105788.s001">Supporting Information S1</xref>. A list of all the aspects that took part to the whole experimentation of this work, which are reported in the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0105788.s001">Supporting Information S1</xref>, follows:</p><sec id="s2a"><title>1. Starting materials for the electrode preparation</title><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p>1.1. <underline>HOPG, OLC, Cr<sub>3</sub>C<sub>2</sub>, CrF<sub>2</sub></underline></p></list-item><list-item><p>1.2. <underline>Characterization</underline></p><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p>1.2.1. Thermogravimetry (TG) and Differential Thermal Analysis (DTA)</p></list-item><list-item><p>1.2.2. x-ray diffraction (XRD)</p></list-item><list-item><p>1.2.3. microRaman (mR)</p></list-item><list-item><p>1.2.4. High Resolution Transmission Electron Spectroscopy (HR-TEM)</p></list-item><list-item><p>1.2.5. Electron Energy Loss Spectroscopy (EELS)</p></list-item><list-item><p>1.2.6. X-ray Photoelectron Spectroscopy (XPS)</p></list-item></list></list-item><list-item><p>1.3. <underline>Preparation of electrodes and cell assembly</underline></p><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p>1.3.1. Electrodes</p></list-item><list-item><p>1.3.2. Cell assembly</p></list-item></list></list-item><list-item><p>1.4. <underline>Experimental apparatus for the <italic>emf</italic> measurements</underline></p></list-item><list-item><p>1.5. <underline>Procedure adopted for the <italic>emf</italic> measurements and their data acquisition</underline></p></list-item><list-item><p>1.6. <underline>Analysis of electrodes before and after experiment</underline></p><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p>1.6.1. X-ray diffraction (XRD)</p></list-item><list-item><p>1.6.2. microRaman spectroscopy (mR)</p></list-item><list-item><p>1.6.3. EELS</p></list-item></list></list-item></list></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Results and Discussion</title><p>In order to satisfy the requirement of reversibility, the experimental technique utilized is the electromotive force (<italic>emf</italic>) measurement as function of temperature of galvanic cells, with CaF<sub>2</sub> single crystal as solid electrolyte. Since long time this technique was utilized in our laboratory and it is well known that the method is one of the best way to achieve reliable thermodynamic data.</p><p>The galvanic cell:</p><p>(Low) Pt|Cr<sub>3</sub>C<sub>2</sub>,CrF<sub>2</sub>,OLC|CaF<sub>2</sub>s.c.|Cr<sub>3</sub>C<sub>2</sub>,CrF<sub>2</sub>,HOPG|Pt (High) (A)</p><p>was assembled to perform the <italic>emf</italic> vs <italic>T</italic> measurement. Cell A is a fluorine concentration cell being the solid electrolyte an ionic conductor by F<sup>-</sup> Frenkel type defects. The positive electrode is the electrode where the chemical potential of F<sub>2</sub>(g) is higher and the chemical potential of carbon is lower. This implies that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e008.jpg"/></inline-formula>. The cell reaction can be written as:<disp-formula id="pone.0105788.e009"><graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e009.jpg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/><label>(B)</label></disp-formula>The main advantage of this kind of cells is that no supplementary thermodynamic data are necessary to derive the thermodynamics of the cell reaction. Only the <italic>emf vs T</italic> experimental data are necessary to obtain the reaction Gibbs free energy change, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e010.jpg"/></inline-formula>. The reaction changes of enthalpy, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e011.jpg"/></inline-formula>, and entropy, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e012.jpg"/></inline-formula>, can be also obtained as shown in the followings.</p><p>The adopted experimental procedure requires accumulating many isothermal and stationary values of <italic>emf</italic> through several stair shaped thermal cycles each one composed of tens of isotherms. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0105788-g001">Figure 1</xref> shows the typical behaviour, almost equal for each one, of five tested cells. The first thermal cycles are characterized by hysteresis that tends to disappear. The presence of a vanishing hysteresis in the <italic>emf</italic> trend demonstrates that the whole system of the carbon shells in the OLC and OLC themselves change to reach new stable configurations that convert reciprocally and reversibly as function of temperature. These findings are qualitatively and quantitatively similar to the behaviour we found in the bundles of SWCNTs <xref rid="pone.0105788-Gozzi1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>. The main difference with the present experiment is the final shape of the <italic>emf</italic> vs <italic>T</italic> curve that is characterized here by an exponential growth-like behaviour.</p><fig id="pone-0105788-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0105788.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>The electromotive force (<italic>emf</italic>) vs temperature of galvanic cell A.</title><p>The progressive disappearing hysteresis is shown from 1<sup>st</sup> to 3<sup>rd</sup> thermal cycle (see &#x000a7;1.4 of the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0105788.s001">Supporting Information S1</xref>). The bottom plot combines the 3<sup>rd</sup> and 4<sup>th</sup> cycles where the red curve is the best fitting curve given by a 3<sup>rd</sup> degree polynomial (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0105788-t001">Table 1</xref>). The residuals of fit are also reported. Most of the error bars are within the size of the experimental points.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.g001"/></fig><p>The trend of the Gibbs free energy change is given by:<disp-formula id="pone.0105788.e013"><graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e013.jpg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/><label>(1)</label></disp-formula>being 3 the number of moles of electrons exchanged in reaction B and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e014.jpg"/></inline-formula> the Faraday constant. The curve <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e015.jpg"/></inline-formula> is well fit by the 3<sup>rd</sup> degree polynomial:</p><p><disp-formula id="pone.0105788.e016"><graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e016.jpg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/><label>(2)</label></disp-formula>.The coefficients and related errors of fit of <italic>emf</italic> vs <italic>T</italic> are given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0105788-t001">Table 1</xref>. The representation of eq 1 is given in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0105788-g002">Fig. 2</xref> where at 920.6 K the equality of the chemical potential of carbon <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e017.jpg"/></inline-formula>is satisfied.</p><fig id="pone-0105788-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0105788.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Gibbs free energy change for C<sub>HOPG</sub>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;C<sub>OLC</sub> transformation calculated according to eq 1.</title><p>At 920.6 K, the curve crosses zero.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.g002"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone-0105788-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0105788.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Coefficients and related errors of <italic>emf</italic> vs <italic>T</italic> polynomial fit: <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e018.jpg"/></inline-formula>.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0105788-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0105788.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>a</italic>/V</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>b</italic>/VK<sup>&#x02212;1</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>c</italic>/VK<sup>&#x02212;2</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>d</italic>/VK<sup>&#x02212;3</sup></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>coefficient</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.207</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0045698</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;5.7832&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;6</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.437&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;9</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>error</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12433</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0004144</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.5905&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;7</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.691&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;10</sup></td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p>R&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.99836; &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;1.5935&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>If each point of the curve of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0105788-g002">Fig. 2</xref> were a point taken at constant temperature and pressure, the enthalpy change of the transformation, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e019.jpg"/></inline-formula>, would be given by:<disp-formula id="pone.0105788.e020"><graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e020.jpg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/><label>(3)</label></disp-formula>The temperature dependency of eq 3 should be written as given in any chemical thermodynamics textbook by equation:<disp-formula id="pone.0105788.e021"><graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e021.jpg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/><label>(4)</label></disp-formula>being <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e022.jpg"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e023.jpg"/></inline-formula> the molar heat capacity at constant pressure. In the case of reaction B and at the experimental temperatures, it is expected that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e024.jpg"/></inline-formula> should be quite low. <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0105788.e021">Equation 4</xref> implies the same value of pressure at each temperature for both the electrodes, i.e., <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e025.jpg"/></inline-formula>. The 1<sup>st</sup> partial derivative against <italic>T</italic> of eq 3, i.e. eq 4, shows too high <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e026.jpg"/></inline-formula> values which are unexpected for the process under study. For this reason, the assumption of constant pressure is not more valid. Therefore, the total derivative of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e027.jpg"/></inline-formula>, i.e.,<disp-formula id="pone.0105788.e028"><graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e028.jpg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/><label>(5)</label></disp-formula>should be considered where,<disp-formula id="pone.0105788.e029"><graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e029.jpg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/><label>(6)</label></disp-formula>being <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e030.jpg"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e031.jpg"/></inline-formula> is the molar volume. By substituting eq 6 in eq 5 and combining with eq 3, the <italic>P</italic>, <italic>T</italic> dependency of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e032.jpg"/></inline-formula> is found:</p><p><disp-formula id="pone.0105788.e033"><graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e033.jpg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/><label>(7)</label></disp-formula>Accordingly, eq 7 differs from eq 3 for the extra term <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e034.jpg"/></inline-formula>, which entails <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e035.jpg"/></inline-formula>.</p><p>The 1<sup>st</sup> derivative of eq 7 with respect to <italic>T</italic> is:<disp-formula id="pone.0105788.e036"><graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e036.jpg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/><label>(8)</label></disp-formula>From the total differential of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e037.jpg"/></inline-formula>, the relationship below follows:<disp-formula id="pone.0105788.e038"><graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e038.jpg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/><label>(9)</label></disp-formula>where &#x003b1; and &#x003ba; are, respectively, the isobaric volume expansion coefficient and isothermal compressibility. By making use of eq 9, eq 8 can be conveniently modified in the form:<disp-formula id="pone.0105788.e039"><graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e039.jpg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/><label>(10)</label></disp-formula><xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0105788.e039">Equation 10</xref> should be compared with well-known equation <xref rid="pone.0105788-Klotz1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>:<disp-formula id="pone.0105788.e040"><graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e040.jpg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/><label>(11)</label></disp-formula>which states that if some phase transition occurs, the equilibrium pressure does not remain constant as the temperature is varied. Since we can write that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e041.jpg"/></inline-formula>, by equating eq 10 and eq 11, the following 2<sup>nd</sup> order differential equation for <italic>P</italic> is found:</p><p><disp-formula id="pone.0105788.e042"><graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e042.jpg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/><label>(12)</label></disp-formula></p><p>To simplify eq 12, we can reasonably neglect <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e043.jpg"/></inline-formula> and assume <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e044.jpg"/></inline-formula> being both OLC and HOPG graphitic materials at the same quite high temperature where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e045.jpg"/></inline-formula> is for both ones close to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e046.jpg"/></inline-formula>. Therefore, eq 12 becomes a quadratic equation in the 1<sup>st</sup> derivative with respect to <italic>T</italic> of the pressure:</p><p><disp-formula id="pone.0105788.e047"><graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e047.jpg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/><label>(13)</label></disp-formula>The solution of eq 13 has been obtained by using the experimental data, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e048.jpg"/></inline-formula>, and the knowledge of the <italic>T</italic> and <italic>P</italic> functions of the physical data of HOPG and OLC. The <italic>T</italic> functions are reported in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0105788-t002">Table 2</xref> and their related coefficients given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0105788-t003">Table 3</xref>. Unfortunately, &#x003b1; and &#x003ba; data of OLC are unavailable and we utilized, as first approximation, the data of fullerene C<sub>60</sub>
<xref rid="pone.0105788-Girifalco2" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>. Due to lack of data on the temperature dependency of the OLC molar volume, an estimation can be done starting from the definition of the isobaric expansion coefficient <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e049.jpg"/></inline-formula> and its <italic>T</italic> dependency reported in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0105788-t002">Table 2</xref> together the coefficients for C<sub>60</sub> given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0105788-t003">Table 3</xref>. Therefore, equation below has been considered:<disp-formula id="pone.0105788.e050"><graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e050.jpg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/><label>(14)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e051.jpg"/></inline-formula> holds. The final approximated value is justified by the amount in braces, which is <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e052.jpg"/></inline-formula> being <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e053.jpg"/></inline-formula>. The values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e054.jpg"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e055.jpg"/></inline-formula> are reported in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0105788-t003">Table 3</xref>. The <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e056.jpg"/></inline-formula> value was taken equal to 7.31&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;6</sup> m<sup>3</sup> mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> at <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e057.jpg"/></inline-formula>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;298 K which is the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e058.jpg"/></inline-formula> value of OLC <xref rid="pone.0105788-Sano1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>) (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0105788-t003">Table 3</xref>). Due to the lack of data on the pressure dependence of <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>, <italic>&#x003ba;</italic> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e059.jpg"/></inline-formula> for OLC, all these parameters were considered constant with pressure for the carbon species present in both electrodes. This choice was mandatory to ensure a balanced behaviour to both OLC and HOPG. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0105788-g003">Figure 3</xref> shows the trend of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e060.jpg"/></inline-formula> vs <italic>T</italic> in the left axis calculated according to eq 11 after solving eq 13 to find <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e061.jpg"/></inline-formula>, being the latter quantity plotted on the right axis. It should be noticed that the shape of the curve <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e062.jpg"/></inline-formula> might be affected by the approximation <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e063.jpg"/></inline-formula> introduced in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0105788.e042">equation 12</xref>.</p><fig id="pone-0105788-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0105788.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Representation of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e064.jpg"/></inline-formula> vs <italic>T</italic> obtained by solving eq 13 (right axis) and trend of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e065.jpg"/></inline-formula> calculated by eq 11 (left axis).</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.g003"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone-0105788-t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0105788.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Temperature functions of the molar volume, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e066.jpg"/></inline-formula>, isobaric volume expansion coefficient, <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>, and isothermal compressibility, <italic>&#x003ba;</italic>, used for computing eq 13.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0105788-t002-2" xlink:href="pone.0105788.t002"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>V</italic><sup>0</sup>(<italic>T</italic>)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">[a]</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x003b1;</italic>(<italic>T</italic>)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">[b]</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x003ba;</italic>(<italic>T</italic>)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">[b]</xref></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>HOPG<sup>25</sup></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e067.jpg"/></inline-formula></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e068.jpg"/></inline-formula></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e069.jpg"/></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>OLC</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>V</italic><sup>0</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e070.jpg"/></inline-formula></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e071.jpg"/></inline-formula></td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt102"><label>[a]</label><p>Fullerene C<sub>60</sub> data were assumed for OLC from reference <xref rid="pone.0105788-Girifalco2" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref> (see also text) with the exception of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e072.jpg"/></inline-formula>, which is known <xref rid="pone.0105788-Sano1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>.</p></fn><fn id="nt103"><label>[b]</label><p>Linear equations for OLC (C<sub>60</sub>) were taken up from the plots in reference <xref rid="pone.0105788-Girifalco2" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone-0105788-t003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0105788.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Values of the coefficients of <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0105788-t002">Table 2</xref>.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0105788-t003-3" xlink:href="pone.0105788.t003"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coefficient <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">[a]</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Value</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>a</italic></bold><bold><sub>1</sub>/m<sup>3</sup>mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.30&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;6</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="pone.0105788-Colonna1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>a</italic></bold><bold><sub>2</sub>/m<sup>3</sup> mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>K<sup>&#x02212;1</sup></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.14&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;10</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="pone.0105788-Colonna1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>a</italic></bold><bold><sub>3</sub>/m<sup>3</sup> mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>K<sup>&#x02212;2</sup></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.95&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;14</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="pone.0105788-Colonna1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>b</italic></bold><bold><sub>1</sub>/Pa</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.63&#x000d7;10<sup>10</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="pone.0105788-Colonna1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>b</italic></bold><bold><sub>2</sub>/Pa</bold>
<bold>K<sup>&#x02212;1</sup></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.32&#x000d7;10<sup>7</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="pone.0105788-Colonna1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>b</italic></bold><bold><sub>3</sub>/Pa K<sup>&#x02212;2</sup></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.45&#x000d7;10<sup>3</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="pone.0105788-Colonna1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>c</italic></bold><bold><sub>0</sub>/Pa<sup>&#x02212;1</sup></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.37&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;11</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="pone.0105788-Girifalco2" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>c</italic></bold><bold><sub>1</sub>/Pa<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>K<sup>&#x02212;1</sup></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.66&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;15</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="pone.0105788-Girifalco2" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>d</italic></bold><bold><sub>0</sub>/K<sup>&#x02212;1</sup></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.30&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="pone.0105788-Girifalco2" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>d</italic></bold><bold><sub>1</sub>/K<sup>&#x02212;2</sup></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.27&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;9</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="pone.0105788-Girifalco2" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>V</italic></bold><bold><sup>0</sup>/m<sup>3</sup>mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.31&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;6</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="pone.0105788-Sano1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref></td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt104"><label>[a]</label><p>The original values of coefficients <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e073.jpg"/></inline-formula> are given in nm<sup>3</sup>. They were multiplied by 10<sup>&#x02212;27</sup>
<italic>N</italic><sub>A</sub> being <italic>N</italic><sub>A</sub> the Avogadro number.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>From the total differential of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e074.jpg"/></inline-formula> the quantity <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e075.jpg"/></inline-formula> can be obtained and plotted against <italic>T</italic> in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0105788-g004">Fig. 4</xref> (right axis) together <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e076.jpg"/></inline-formula> (left axis). <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0105788.e021">Equation 4</xref> was used for this calculation.</p><fig id="pone-0105788-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0105788.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Partial derivatives of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e077.jpg"/></inline-formula>.</title><p>The quantity in the left axis was calculated according to eq 4. The quantity in the right axis was calculated by the total differential of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e078.jpg"/></inline-formula> through <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e079.jpg"/></inline-formula> vs <italic>T</italic> function, obtained by solving eq 13.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.g004"/></fig><p>The entropy change of transformation B as function of temperature and pressure, was calculated as:</p><p><disp-formula id="pone.0105788.e080"><graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e080.jpg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/><label>(15)</label></disp-formula>.This equation can be calculated through eq 7, after solving the quadratic eq 13, by using the experimental data of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e081.jpg"/></inline-formula> reported on <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0105788-g002">Fig. 2</xref>. These thermodynamic functions are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0105788-g005">Fig. 5</xref>. At 920.6 K, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e082.jpg"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e083.jpg"/></inline-formula> values are 95.8 kJ mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and 104.1 JK<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, respectively.</p><fig id="pone-0105788-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0105788.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Representation on left axis of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e084.jpg"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e085.jpg"/></inline-formula> vs <italic>T</italic> obtained respectively by eq 7, after solving quadratic <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0105788.e047">equation 13</xref>, and eq 1.</title><p>On the right axis, the trend of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e086.jpg"/></inline-formula> calculated by eq 15 is also displayed.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.g005"/></fig><p>Why does the pressure change with temperature in our experiment? The experiment is carried out under high vacuum and the static pressure on the cell is maintained constant at about 0.1 bar as described in the experimental section (see &#x000a7; 1.3 of the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0105788.s001">Supporting Information S1</xref>). Thus, the present experimental conditions cannot justify the presence of the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e087.jpg"/></inline-formula> quantity. The explanation for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e088.jpg"/></inline-formula> should be searched in the growth of the pressure inside the cell, which is caused by a process occurring under volume constraint. The positive sign of <italic>emf</italic> indicates that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e089.jpg"/></inline-formula> where <italic>&#x000b5;</italic> is the chemical potential of carbon. By itself this does not justify the increase of <italic>P</italic> with <italic>T</italic> but the trend of <italic>emf</italic> with <italic>T</italic> suggests it. Furthermore, there are experimental evidences indicating that the electrode containing OLC is the site where the volume constraint is particularly high. They arise from the comparative analysis of both electrode powder mixtures, before and after the experiments, by making use of x-ray diffraction (XRD), micro Raman spectroscopy (mR) and high-resolution transmission electron microscopy (HR-TEM):</p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>The XRD patterns spectra demonstrate that no chemical change occurred (see &#x000a7;1.5.1 of the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0105788.s001">Supporting Information S1</xref>). The large increase of crystallinity of CrF<sub>2</sub> was the unique difference found in XRD. Due to their almost amorphous state, OLC give low intensity XRD features differently from HOPG, which is very well revealed. In the present case, the situation is complicated by the presence of features of other species in the electrode that superimpose and/or they are very close to the OLC features (see &#x000a7;1.1.2.2 of the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0105788.s001">Supporting Information S1</xref>). It is reported <xref rid="pone.0105788-Dubitsky1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref> in high temperature &#x02013; high pressure experiments on OLC, that their most intense feature (<italic>d</italic><sub>200</sub>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.354 nm, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e090.jpg"/></inline-formula>; see &#x000a7;1.1.2.2 of the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0105788.s001">Supporting Information S1</xref>) is negligibly shifted as function of pressure at constant <italic>T</italic>. For instance, at 500 &#x000b0;C the lattice parameter changes with pressure as &#x02212;9.6&#x000d7;10<sup>-13</sup> nmPa<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. At our calculated pressures, which are in the order of tens of MPa (see below), a shift of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e091.jpg"/></inline-formula> is expected, which is clearly undetectable. The mR spectroscopy does not reveal differences (see &#x000a7;1.5.2 of the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0105788.s001">Supporting Information S1</xref>) with exception of some changes in the relative intensities, which are meaningless. There is superimposition of the OLC and HOPG features with the features of the mixture Cr<sub>3</sub>C<sub>2</sub> - CrF<sub>2</sub> (see &#x000a7;1.1.2.3 of the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0105788.s001">Supporting Information S1</xref>). Therefore, though this inconvenient, the absence of any new feature is a proof that both carbon species remain unchanged;</p></list-item><list-item><p>HR-TEM and STEM analyses show a very different scenario of the electrode powder with OLC before and after the experiments. Before, OLC are easy identifiable in the mixture as reported in the STEM image of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0105788-g006">Fig. 6A</xref>. Free OLC nanostructures (red arrows) are quite abundant, where they can be seen either as spots with very light contrast on the holey carbon grid or mixed with the Cr<sub>3</sub>C<sub>2</sub>-CrF<sub>2</sub> powder. The HAADF-STEM mode is also known as Z contrast mode because the intensity in each point of the image is proportional to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e092.jpg"/></inline-formula> with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e093.jpg"/></inline-formula> and <italic>Z</italic> the atomic number. Carbon appears dark, as it is much lighter than the other compounds present in these samples. The OLC morphology at the nanoscale is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0105788-g006">Fig. 6B</xref> and is found in agreement with previous experimental results <xref rid="pone.0105788-Banhart1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref><xref rid="pone.0105788-Welz1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. The inset in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0105788-g006">Fig. 6B</xref> shows the Fast Fourier Transform (FFT) of OLC where the reflections of graphitic planes appear quite diffuse.</p></list-item></list><fig id="pone-0105788-g006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0105788.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Before the experiment.</title><p>Panel A: STEM image of the powder of the electrode containing OLC. The OLC nanostructures appear on the holey carbon grid as spot with very light contrast. Some of them are indicated with red arrows. Panel B: HR-TEM of OLC. The FFT image in the inset shows poor crystallinity of OLC.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.g006"/></fig><p>The powder mixture of the same electrode after the experiment appears completely different: OLC are practically disappeared while large grains with round shaped contours were found as shown in the STEM image in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0105788-g007">Fig. 7A</xref>. Free OLC are hardly observable: just small pieces on the agglomerates, while the holey carbon grid is practically clean. The analysis on the very few OLC found in the sample reveals some significant differences with respect to the OLC before the experiment: the graphitic planes form now better ordered quasi-spherical structures (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0105788-g007">Fig.7B</xref>). The electron energy loss spectroscopy measurements (see &#x000a7; 1.5.3. of the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0105788.s001">Supporting Information S1</xref>) agree with this result: the sp<sup>2</sup> carbon coordination values were found 82&#x000b1;3% and 86&#x000b1;3% for OLC before and after, respectively and the result seems to point to a further graphitization of OLC towards multishell ordered structures in the process (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s3">discussion</xref> below). The sintered agglomerates usually are so thick to result non-transparent to electrons and to prevent the analysis of their internal structure. When small particles are found, the EELS revealed typical features of variable size inside the particle. Their contrast is typical of cavities, but it was not possible to assess whether they are empty or possibly filled with OLC. This is the most reasonable hypothesis, being OLC otherwise missing.</p><fig id="pone-0105788-g007" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0105788.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>After the experiment.</title><p>Panel A: STEM image of the powder of the electrode containing OLC. The OLC nanostructures are practically disappeared. The holey carbon grid is clean and only large grains with rounded shape stay on the grid. A few visible OLC are indicated with red arrow. Panel B: HR-TEM of OLC. The FFT image in the inset shows that the crystallinity of OLC is higher with respect to the FFT image in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0105788-g006">Figure 6B</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.g007"/></fig><p>The zero loss TEM image of a typical small sintered particle containing several cavities is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0105788-g008">Fig. 8a</xref>. The fact that these cavities are empty or filled with material lighter than the surrounding sample is proven by the comparison between the HRTEM and STEM images in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0105788-g008">Fig. 8b</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0105788-g008">Fig. 8c</xref> of the same cavity, that is whiter in b and darker in c.</p><fig id="pone-0105788-g008" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0105788.g008</object-id><label>Figure 8</label><caption><title>Zero loss TEM image (Panel a) of a typical small sintered particle (as the particles in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0105788-g007">Figure 7A</xref>) of the electrode with OLC after the experiment.</title><p>The particle contains several cavities, that can be empty, or at least full of material much lighter than the surrounding sample, as it is proven by the comparison between the HRTEM (panel <bold>b</bold>) and STEM (panel <bold>c</bold>) images of the same cavity, that is whiter in <bold>b</bold> and darker in <bold>c</bold>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.g008"/></fig><p>The electrode containing HOPG and the same Cr<sub>3</sub>C<sub>2</sub> - CrF<sub>2</sub> mixture does not show any modification after the experiment, as it can be seen by comparing the STEM images in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0105788-g009">Fig.9</xref> A and B.</p><fig id="pone-0105788-g009" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0105788.g009</object-id><label>Figure 9</label><caption><title>STEM images of the electrode containing HOPG.</title><p>Panel A, <bold>before the experiment</bold>. Panel B, <bold>after the experiment</bold>. No differences were found and no sintering was observed.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.g009"/></fig><p>The following considerations arise from the above evidences:</p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>The temperature range explored in the experiments does not allow suspecting any vaporization of carbon from OLC. The C-nanostructures are still in the electrode;</p></list-item><list-item><p>High temperatures and experiments lasting hundreds of hours create the ideal conditions to favour the sintering of the whole mixture where OLC remain embedded in the very hard and refractory structure of Cr<sub>3</sub>C<sub>2</sub>. The melting points of Cr<sub>3</sub>C<sub>2</sub> and CrF<sub>2</sub> are respectively 2168 and 1167 K. The highest temperature reached in the experiments was 1030 K, which is close to the melting point of CrF<sub>2.</sub> Thus, it is expected that its softening acts as a sintering medium of the whole mixture. The high specific surface area of OLC (&#x0003e;100 m<sup>2</sup>g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, see &#x000a7; 1.1.1 of the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0105788.s001">Supporting Information S1</xref>) contributes to this process and facilitates the embedding of the nanostructure. Therefore, the role of OLC nanoparticles seems to be crucial and it explains the absence of any modification of the electrode containing HOPG (and the same Cr<sub>3</sub>C<sub>2</sub>-CrF<sub>2</sub> mixture) which worked in the same experimental conditions;</p></list-item><list-item><p>Consider as rough approximation the electrodes as cylinders free of expanding with temperature filled with rigid particles (sintered Cr<sub>3</sub>C<sub>2</sub>-CrF<sub>2</sub> mixture) embedding nanoparticles (OLC) the dilatation of which is hindered. By imposing no volume change for both OLC and HOPG, the respective <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e094.jpg"/></inline-formula> values can be evaluated and compared as follows:</p></list-item></list><p><disp-formula id="pone.0105788.e095"><graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e095.jpg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/><label>(16)</label></disp-formula>The subscripts O and H stand for OLC and HOPG. The temperature dependence of the quantities entering eq 16 has been neglected in the computation and the coefficients <italic>a</italic><sub>2</sub>, <italic>b</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic>c</italic><sub>0</sub> and <italic>d</italic><sub>0</sub> were only retained in the expression reported in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0105788-t003">Table 3</xref>. The values found in eq 16 demonstrate clearly the great difference in the internal pressures to which both carbon forms are subjected in the respective electrodes. For the sake of comparison, the quantity <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e096.jpg"/></inline-formula> for Cr<sub>3</sub>C<sub>2</sub> is: <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e097.jpg"/></inline-formula> where <italic>&#x003ba;</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0105788-Chao1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref> and <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0105788-Scabarozi1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref> are available in literature. Due to the negligible changes with temperature of the internal pressure (see eq 16), the chemical potential of carbon in HOPG, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e098.jpg"/></inline-formula>, is only a function of <italic>T</italic> differently to the chemical potential of carbon in OLC, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e099.jpg"/></inline-formula>, that is a function of <italic>T</italic> and <italic>P</italic>(<italic>T</italic>). Therefore, we can write that:<disp-formula id="pone.0105788.e100"><graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e100.jpg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/><label>(17)</label></disp-formula></p><sec id="s3a"><title>Evaluation of the surface contribution</title><p>Owing to the nanometric size of the carbon particles, the surface contribution to the energetics of the process cannot be neglected, in principle. In the following of this section the shape of the nanoparticle is assumed to be spherical. Let us estimate the chemical potential difference using the thermodynamic approach, based on the Gibbs model for interface <xref rid="pone.0105788-Shuttleworth1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>, in terms of bulk chemical potential, surface free energy and surface tension.</p><p>The difference between surface energy and surface tension plays a fundamental role when dealing with interphases in the solid state. In this respect, we briefly recall the definition of these quantities, which are needed for the discussion that follows. The surface energy excess, &#x003c3;, is the reversible work required to create a unit surface at constant volume, temperature, pressure and composition <xref rid="pone.0105788-Shuttleworth1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>. In such a process the surface is not stretched during its formation. On the other hand, the surface tension, &#x003b3;, is defined as the reversible work (per unit area) required to change the area of the surface through a stretching process. It is worth noticing that in this definition the infinitesimal deformation of the surface involves an &#x0201c;initial&#x0201d; configuration of the system where the solid is not stressed. By including bulk and surface contributions, the general expression of the chemical potential difference reads (see &#x000a7;2 of the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0105788.s001">Supporting Information S1</xref>)<disp-formula id="pone.0105788.e101"><graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e101.jpg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/><label>(18)</label></disp-formula>where <italic>r</italic> is the radius of the nanoparticle and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e102.jpg"/></inline-formula> denotes the "bulk" contribution, that is <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e103.jpg"/></inline-formula>. In the following we focus our attention on the impact of the surface term (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e104.jpg"/></inline-formula>) on <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e105.jpg"/></inline-formula> and on its temperature dependence.</p><p>The contribution of the surface tension containing term to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e106.jpg"/></inline-formula> is usually smaller than that due to the surface excess free energy, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e107.jpg"/></inline-formula>. Consequently, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e108.jpg"/></inline-formula> is expected to be higher than zero. Typical values of the quantities entering eq 18 are <xref rid="pone.0105788-Colonna1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>
<italic>V</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;5.36&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;6</sup> m<sup>3</sup> mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, &#x003ba;&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;3.24&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;10</sup> Pa<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and <italic>r</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;10 nm. As far as the <italic>&#x003c3;</italic> value is concerned, for nanocarbon structures, such as fullerene, single and multi walled nanotubes, it is found <xref rid="pone.0105788-Jiang1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref> to range between 0 and 0.045 Jm<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>. On this basis, the upper bound of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e109.jpg"/></inline-formula> is estimated to be about 50 Jmol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> for <italic>r</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;10 nm.</p><p>As far as the temperature dependence of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e110.jpg"/></inline-formula> is concerned, it is ascribed to the temperature dependence of the physical quantities entering in eq 18. In particular, the temperature dependence of <italic>&#x003c3;</italic> is given by the Gibbs adsorption equation that, for one component system, implies <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e111.jpg"/></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e112.jpg"/></inline-formula> is the excess surface entropy. From this equation, neglecting as a first approximation the temperature dependence of the excess entropy in the temperature range here considered, we get <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e113.jpg"/></inline-formula> where <italic>T</italic>* is the temperature at which <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e114.jpg"/></inline-formula>. Concerning the temperature dependence of the surface tension, given by eq 1 in the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0105788.s001">Supporting Information S1</xref> (&#x000a7; 2), it is obtained<disp-formula id="pone.0105788.e115"><graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e115.jpg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/><label>(19)</label></disp-formula>where we exploit the fact that the surface energy is a function of the independent variables temperature and &#x0201c;stretched area&#x0201d; <italic>A</italic> (the subscript <italic>s</italic> stands just to remind us that the variation is performed by stretching). According to the discussion that follows this derivative can be estimated using the Born-Stern method <xref rid="pone.0105788-Mutaftschiev1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>. In this approach, the entropy excess per unitary area of a solid-vacuum interface is equal to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e116.jpg"/></inline-formula> where <italic>S</italic> is the entropy of the actual solid, <italic>S'</italic> the entropy of the model system (without interface), <italic>&#x003c1;<sub>a</sub></italic> the surface density and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e117.jpg"/></inline-formula> the entropy, per atom, of surface (bulk) species. By assuming, as usual, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e118.jpg"/></inline-formula>independent of temperature and deformation of the surface <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e119.jpg"/></inline-formula>, for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e120.jpg"/></inline-formula> one obtains <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e121.jpg"/></inline-formula>. For instance, by considering the excess entropy equal to the change in the vibrational entropy of the atom the expression <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e122.jpg"/></inline-formula> holds where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e123.jpg"/></inline-formula> is the vibrational frequency of the surface (fully coordinated) atom along the &#x0201c;broken bond&#x0201d; direction. Since for the number of mole of atoms in the particle, <italic>N</italic>, is constant we set <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e124.jpg"/></inline-formula> in eq 18 to obtain <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e125.jpg"/></inline-formula>. Moreover, <disp-formula id="pone.0105788.e126"><graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e126.jpg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/><label>(20)</label></disp-formula>where &#x003b1; is of the order of 10<sup>&#x02212;6</sup> K<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. A crude estimate of the vibrational contribution of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e127.jpg"/></inline-formula>, on the basis of the Kossell model <xref rid="pone.0105788-Mutaftschiev1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref> shows that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e128.jpg"/></inline-formula> that implies, using <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e129.jpg"/></inline-formula> with <italic>&#x003c1;<sub>g</sub></italic> the graphite density, a value of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e130.jpg"/></inline-formula> J m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> K<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. This figure is about two orders of magnitude larger than &#x003b1;. Moreover, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e131.jpg"/></inline-formula> J mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> K<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. From eq 15, the value of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e132.jpg"/></inline-formula>, in the middle of temperature range, is equal to 96.75 Jmol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>K<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, which is not consistent with the value <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e133.jpg"/></inline-formula>.</p><p>The present analysis indicates that the bulk term is the dominant contribution both to the chemical potential change of transformation B and its derivative on <italic>T</italic>. At this point, a comment is in order on the use of the Gibbs model for dealing with OLC systems. In fact, in this approach &#x0201c;bulk&#x0201d; and surface terms sum up as two independent contributions where the &#x0201c;size effect&#x0201d; is usually contained in the surface term only, i.e., <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e134.jpg"/></inline-formula> is independent of <italic>r</italic>. On the other hand - still remaining in the framework of the Gibbs model - owing to the variable curvature of the sheets, which made up the nanoparticles, in the OLC the &#x0201c;bulk&#x0201d; term has to be considered a function of the particle radius. For this reason in the following we refer to &#x0201c;atomistic&#x0201d; approaches for determining the energetics of the OLC particles. In fact, in these methods a suitable interaction potential functions for the C atoms is used and this makes it possible to estimate <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e135.jpg"/></inline-formula> as a function of <italic>r</italic>.</p><p>Now we focus our attention on the internal energy of the particle due to the isothermal transformation from a relaxed state at internal energy <italic>U</italic><sub>0</sub> and volume <italic>V</italic><sub>0</sub> to a stressed state at <italic>U</italic> and <italic>V</italic>. To do this the <italic>energy equation</italic>, namely <disp-formula id="pone.0105788.e136"><graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e136.jpg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/><label>(21)</label></disp-formula>was utilized. The integration of eq 21 gives the change of internal energy as (see &#x000a7;3 of the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0105788.s001">Supporting Information S1</xref>):</p><p><disp-formula id="pone.0105788.e137"><graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e137.jpg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/><label>(22)</label></disp-formula>The value of <italic>V</italic><sup>0</sup>, <italic>&#x003b1;</italic> and <italic>&#x003ba;</italic>&#x003ba; are given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0105788-t002">Tables 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0105788-t003">3</xref>. The pressure as function of <italic>T</italic> was obtained by numerical integration of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e138.jpg"/></inline-formula> assuming <italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0 at <italic>T</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;776.6 K, which was the lowest experimental temperature. The resulting function satisfies the relationship <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e139.jpg"/></inline-formula>where <italic>m</italic><sub>0</sub>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;1.2947&#x000d7;10<sup>6</sup> bar; <italic>m</italic><sub>1</sub>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;&#x02212;4187.2 bar K<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>; <italic>m</italic><sub>2</sub>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;4.2571 bar K<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>; <italic>m</italic><sub>3</sub>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;&#x02212;1.3067&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;3</sup> bar K<sup>&#x02212;3</sup> with correlation coefficient 0.9999. At the highest temperature, the maximum pressure value is about 70 kbar. The trend of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e140.jpg"/></inline-formula> with temperature, which is almost perfectly quadratic, is plotted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0105788-g010">Fig. 10</xref>.</p><fig id="pone-0105788-g010" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0105788.g010</object-id><label>Figure 10</label><caption><title>The change of internal energy <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e141.jpg"/></inline-formula> of OLC is reported against temperature according to eq 22.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.g010"/></fig><p>It is worth noticing that the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e142.jpg"/></inline-formula> values and its trend with temperature are not comparable with values and trend of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e143.jpg"/></inline-formula> reported in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0105788-g005">Fig. 5</xref>. For example, at 903 K, which is the temperature in the middle of the explored temperature interval, the ratio <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e144.jpg"/></inline-formula>.</p><p>Due to such a high ratio jointly to the very small surface contribution, we assume that as a consequence of the high internal pressure another process connected to B should be considered. We are likely dealing with a reversible process that requires the formation of C defects in OLC, probably already defective. Thus, the whole process determining the <italic>emf</italic> of the cell could be written as:<disp-formula id="pone.0105788.e145"><graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e145.jpg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/><label>(B1)</label></disp-formula>instead of process B.</p><p>Obviously, this implies that the previously considered relation <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e146.jpg"/></inline-formula> should be written as <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e147.jpg"/></inline-formula> where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e148.jpg"/></inline-formula> is the mean chemical potential of carbon atoms in the electrode containing the OLC nanostructures. In this quantity, the C atoms formed should be considered adsorbed atoms, C<italic><sub>ad</sub></italic> the formation of which causes dangling bonds. A rough evaluation of the defect fraction in equilibrium B1 can be evaluated through equation:<disp-formula id="pone.0105788.e149"><graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e149.jpg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/><label>(23)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e150.jpg"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e151.jpg"/></inline-formula> are the enthalpy of formation per carbon atom of defective OLC and free carbon atom (7.43 eV at 298 K) <xref rid="pone.0105788-IVTANTHERMO1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>, respectively. The quantity <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e152.jpg"/></inline-formula> depends on the number of shells as described for multishell fullerene (MSF) made of concentric circumspheres of polyhedra <italic>C<sub>n</sub></italic> (<italic>I<sub>h</sub></italic>, <italic>n</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;60<italic>k</italic><sup>2</sup>) and <italic>C<sub>n</sub></italic> (<italic>I<sub>h</sub></italic>, <italic>n</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;180<italic>k</italic><sup>2</sup>) where <italic>k</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;1,2 up to <italic>L</italic> is any positive integer representing the number of shells. <italic>I<sub>h</sub></italic> and <italic>n</italic> are respectively the symmetry group and number of C atoms. According to the literature <xref rid="pone.0105788-Tang1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>, the quantity <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e153.jpg"/></inline-formula> is of the order of magnitude of meV and therefore it is negligible when compared to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e154.jpg"/></inline-formula> which is about 1 eV. Even the formation energy of a single carbon shell starting from graphene implies negligible energy values ranging from 331 to 34 meV at<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> for C<sub>60</sub> and C<sub>960</sub>, respectively (see J. Bernholc et al. <xref rid="pone.0105788-Bernholc1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>). As stated in the above reference, the authors showed that the larger the size of the shell, the lower the energy of formation. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0105788-g011">Figure 11</xref> shows how <italic>y</italic> changes with <italic>T</italic>.</p><fig id="pone-0105788-g011" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0105788.g011</object-id><label>Figure 11</label><caption><title>Trend of the change of the fraction of C defects in OLC against <italic>T</italic>.</title><p>One assumes that the real transformation involves equilibrium <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e155.jpg"/></inline-formula> and <italic>y</italic> is calculated by eq 23.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.g011"/></fig><p>Due to the assumption for obtaining eq 23, the trend of <italic>y</italic> is the same as <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e156.jpg"/></inline-formula> shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0105788-g005">Fig. 5</xref>. Anyway, the value of <italic>y</italic> is likely consistent with a change corresponding to one or more OLC shells. The experimental evidence through the <italic>emf</italic> vs <italic>T</italic> data shows that this process occurs reversibly. In addition, defects imply the formation of dangling bonds, which also contribute to the increase of the entropy change.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Conclusions</title><p>In the present experimental work, we obtained high temperature data of the stability of onion-like carbon with respect to highly oriented pyrolytic graphite. Since this was performed in reversible way, through the <italic>emf</italic> measurement of a galvanic cell, the quantities related to the transformation investigated have to be considered reliable thermodynamic data.</p><p>The evidence that in the operating conditions the <italic>emf</italic> data cannot be only function of temperature allowed measuring the changes of the chemical potential of carbon in OLC under volume constraint. The volume constraint is reasonably proven by the HR-TEM images where the rigid cages made of sintered CrF<sub>2</sub>&#x02013;Cr<sub>3</sub>C<sub>2</sub> mixture likely embed OLC.</p><p>The positive value of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0105788.e157.jpg"/></inline-formula> and its increase with temperature indicate that the OLC is a nanostructured system with a large number of defects. The change of their fraction with <italic>T</italic> was evaluated. The present analysis indicates that the bulk term is the dominant contribution to both chemical potential and entropy change of the transformation.</p><p>The absence of any chemical change in the electrodes after hundreds hours of work at high temperature guarantees the whole reliability of the experiments.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0105788.s001"><label>Supporting Information S1</label><caption><p>(DOC)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0105788.s001.doc"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>This work was partially financed through the PRIN 2009 Project no. 2009N4BJ4J and &#x0201c;Acquisizione di medie e grandi attrezzature scientifiche 2010&#x0201d; Universit&#x000e0; di Roma <italic>La Sapienza</italic>, no. C26G10KKK5.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0105788-Gozzi1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gozzi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Latini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lazzarini</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>High-temperature determination of surface free energy of copper nanoparticles</article-title>. <source>J Am Chem Soc</source>
<volume>131</volume>: <fpage>12474</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12482</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19655757</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0105788-Tomanek1"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tomanek</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Krastev</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Stability of multishell fullerenes <italic>Phys Rev B</italic></article-title>. <volume>48</volume>: <fpage>15461</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>15464</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0105788-Bernholc1"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bernholc</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brabec</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Maiti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>J-Y</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Structural transformations, reactions, and electronic properties of fullerenes, onions, and buckytubes</article-title>. <source>Comp Mat Science</source>
<volume>2</volume>: <fpage>547</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>556</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0105788-Girifalco1"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Girifalco</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hodak</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Carbon nanotubes, buckyballs, ropes, and a universal graphitic potential</article-title>. <source>Phys Rev B</source>
<volume>62</volume>: <fpage>13104</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>13110</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0105788-Jiang1"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>ZP</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Thermodynamic phase stabilities of nanocarbon</article-title>. <source>Carbon</source>
<volume>44</volume>: <fpage>79</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>83</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0105788-Barnard1"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Barnard</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Theory and modeling of nanocarbon phase stability</article-title>. <source>Diamond &#x00026; Related Mat</source>
<volume>15</volume>: <fpage>285</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>291</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0105788-Banhart1"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Banhart</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ajayan</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Carbon onions as nanoscopic pressure cells for diamond formation</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>382</volume>: <fpage>433</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>435</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0105788-Banhart2"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Banhart</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>F&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Redlich</surname><given-names>Ph</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ajayan</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>The formation, annealing and self-compression of carbon onions under electron irradiation</article-title>. <source>Chem Phys Lett</source>
<volume>269</volume>: <fpage>349</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>355</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0105788-Sun1"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Banhart</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Graphitic onions as reaction cells on the nanoscale</article-title>. <source>Appl Phys Lett</source>
<volume>88</volume>: <fpage>193121</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>193123</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0105788-Latini1"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Latini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gozzi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ferraris</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lazzarini</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>High-temperature resistivity of dense mats of single-walled carbon nanotube bundles</article-title>. <source>J Phys Chem C</source>
<volume>115</volume>: <fpage>11023</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11029</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0105788-Latini2"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Latini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tomellini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Thermodynamics of CVD synthesis of multiwalled carbon nanotubes: a case study</article-title>. <source>J Phys Chem C</source>
<volume>113</volume>: <fpage>45</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>53</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0105788-Gozzi2"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gozzi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Iervolino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Latini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The thermodynamics of the transformation of graphite to multiwalled carbon nanotubes</article-title>. <source>J Am Chem Soc</source>
<volume>129</volume>: <fpage>10269</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10275</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17665913</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0105788-Shenderova1"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Shenderova OA, Zhirnov VV, Brenner DW (2002) Carbon nanostructures. Crit Rev Solid State Mater Sci <volume>27</volume>: ; 227&#x02013;356.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0105788-Kuznetsov1"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kuznetsov</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chuvilin</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Butenko</surname><given-names>YV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mal'kov</surname><given-names>IY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gutakovskii</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Study of onion-like carbon OLC formation from ultra disperse diamond (UDD)</article-title>. <source>Mater Res Soc Symp Proc</source>
<volume>359</volume>: <fpage>105</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>110</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0105788-Lee1"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>RKF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>General formulae for interacting spherical nanoparticles and fullerenes</article-title>. <source>J Math Chem</source>
<volume>50</volume>: <fpage>1289</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1303</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0105788-Zaiser1"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zaiser</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Banhart</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Radiation-induced transformation of graphite to diamond</article-title>. <source>Phys Rev Lett</source>
<volume>79</volume>: <fpage>3680</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3683</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0105788-Klotz1"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Klotz IM, Rosemberg RM (2008) Chemical Thermodynamics. 7th Edition, John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Inc., Publishing, p. 200.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0105788-Girifalco2"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Girifalco</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Extended Mie-Gr&#x000fc;neisen theory applied to C60 in the disordered fcc phase</article-title>. <source>Phys Rev B</source>
<volume>52</volume>: <fpage>9910</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9916</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0105788-Sano1"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sano</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alexandrou</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chhowalla</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Teo</surname><given-names>KBK</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Properties of carbon onions produced by an arc discharge in water</article-title>. <source>J Appl Phys</source>
<volume>92</volume>: <fpage>2783</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2788</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0105788-Dubitsky1"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dubitsky</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Serebryanaya</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Blank</surname><given-names>VD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Skryleva</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kulnitsky</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Effect of high pressures and temperatures on carbon nanoonion structures: comparison with C60</article-title>. <source>Russ Chem Bull Int Ed</source>
<volume>60</volume>: <fpage>413</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>418</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0105788-Welz1"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Welz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McNallan</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gogotsi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Carbon structures in silicon carbide derived carbon</article-title>. <source>J Mat Proc Tech</source>
<volume>179</volume>: <fpage>11</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>22</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0105788-Chao1"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>First-principles study of structural, elastic, and electronic properties of chromium carbides</article-title>. <source>Appl Phys Lett</source>
<volume>92</volume>: <fpage>041909</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>041911</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0105788-Scabarozi1"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Scabarozi</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Amini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Leaffer</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ganguly</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Thermal expansion of select <italic>Mn</italic>+1<italic>AXn M</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;early transition metal, <italic>A</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;A group element, <italic>X</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;C or N) phases measured by high temperature x-ray diffraction and dilatometry</article-title>. <source>J Appl Phys</source>
<volume>105</volume>: <fpage>013543</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>0135410</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0105788-Shuttleworth1"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shuttleworth</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>1950</year>) <article-title>The Surface Tension of Solids</article-title>. <source>Proc Phys Soc (London) A</source>
<volume>63</volume>: <fpage>444</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>457</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0105788-Colonna1"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Colonna</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fasolino</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Meijer</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>High-pressure high-temperature equation of state of graphite from Monte Carlo simulations</article-title>. <source>Carbon</source>
<volume>49</volume>: <fpage>364</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>368</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0105788-Mutaftschiev1"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mutaftschiev B (2001) The atomistic Nature of Crystal Growth. Springer-Verlag.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0105788-IVTANTHERMO1"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">IVTANTHERMO for Windows, v.3.0; database of thermodynamic properties of individual substances and thermodynamic modeling software; Glushko Thermocenter of RAS: 2005</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0105788-Tang1"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>FQ</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Theoretical studies of multishell fullerenes</article-title>. <source>Phys Rev B</source>
<volume>52</volume>: <fpage>17435</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>17438</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>