<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24416389</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3885696</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-24067</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0085318</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Computational Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Molecular Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Gene Expression</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Model Organisms</subject><subj-group><subject>Animal Models</subject><subj-group><subject>Zebrafish</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Molecular Cell Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Signal Transduction</subject><subj-group><subject>Signaling Cascades</subject><subj-group><subject>Akt Signaling Cascade</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Gene Expression</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Oncology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cancer Risk Factors</subject><subj-group><subject>Genetic Causes of Cancer</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Cancers and Neoplasms</subject><subj-group><subject>Gastrointestinal Tumors</subject><subj-group><subject>Hepatocellular Carcinoma</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Overexpression of Endothelin 1 Triggers Hepatocarcinogenesis in Zebrafish and Promotes Cell Proliferation and Migration through the AKT Pathway</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">EDN1 Induces HCC by Activating PI3K/AKT Pathway</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Jeng-Wei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>Chung-Yi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Wan-Yu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Yueh-Min</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Shiow-Lian Catherine</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Horng-Dar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yuh</surname><given-names>Chiou-Hwa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6"><sup>6</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7"><sup>7</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Institute of Molecular and Genomic Medicine, National Health Research Institutes, Zhunan, Miaoli, Taiwan</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Department of Life Sciences, National Central University, Jhongli City, Taoyuan, Taiwan</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Department of Pathology, Changhua Christian Hospital, Changhua City, Changhua County, Taiwan</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><addr-line>Department of Medical Technology, Jen-Teh Junior College of Medicine, Nursing and Management, Miaoli, Taiwan</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff5"><label>5</label><addr-line>Institute of Biotechnology, National Tsing Hua University, Hsinchu, Taiwan</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff6"><label>6</label><addr-line>Institute of Bioinformatics and Structural Biology, National Tsing Hua University, Hsinchu, Taiwan</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff7"><label>7</label><addr-line>Department of Biological Science and Technology, National Chiao Tung University, Hsinchu, Taiwan</addr-line></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>Zhiyuan</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1"><addr-line>National University of Singapore, Singapore</addr-line></aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>chyuh@nhri.org.tw</email></corresp><fn fn-type="conflict"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: LWL CYL WYY CHY. Performed the experiments: LWL CYL WYY. Analyzed the data: JWL CYL CHY. Wrote the paper: CHY. Performed the pathological analysis of the specimens: YML. Critically revised the manuscript for important intellectual content: SLJ HDW.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>8</day><month>1</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>e85318</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>6</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>4</day><month>12</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Lu et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Hepatocarcinogenesis commonly involves the gradual progression from hepatitis to fibrosis and cirrhosis, and ultimately to hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC). Endothelin 1 (<italic>Edn1</italic>) has been identified as a gene that is significantly up-regulated in HBx-induced HCC in mice. In this study, we further investigated the role of <italic>edn1</italic> in hepatocarcinogenesis using a transgenic zebrafish model and a cell culture system. Liver-specific <italic>edn1</italic> expression caused steatosis, fibrosis, glycogen accumulation, bile duct dilation, hyperplasia, and HCC in zebrafish. Overexpression of <italic>EDN1</italic> in 293T cells enhanced cell proliferation and cell migration in <italic>in vitro</italic> and xenotransplantation assays and was accompanied with up-regulation of several cell cycle/proliferation- and migration-specific genes. Furthermore, expression of the unfolded protein response (UPR) pathway-related mediators, such as spliced XBP1, ATF6, IRE1, and PERK, was also up-regulated at both the RNA and protein levels. In the presence of an EDN1 inhibitor or an AKT inhibitor, these increases were diminished and the EDN1-induced migration ability also was disappeared, suggesting that the EDN1 effects act through activation of the AKT pathway to enhance the UPR and subsequently activate the expression of downstream genes. Additionally, p-AKT is enhanced in the <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish compared to the GFP-mCherry control. The micro RNA miR-1 was found to inhibit the expression of EDN1. We also observed an inverse correlation between EDN1 and miR-1 expression in HCC patients. In conclusion, our data suggest that EDN1 plays an important role in HCC progression by activating the PI3K/AKT pathway and is regulated by miR-1.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This research was supported by grants from the National Research Program for Genomic Medicine (NRPGM) (99-3112-B-400-010) and the National Science Council (NSC) (101-2321-B-400-017) to CHY. Additional funding from the National Health Research Institute provided to CHY is gratefully acknowledged. The fellowship and funding to Jeng-Wei Lu and Dr. Chiou-Hwa Yuh, respectively, from the Liver Disease Prevention &#x00026; Treatment Research Foundation (Taiwan) is also highly acknowledged. The authors would like to thank the Taiwan Zebrafish Core Facility at NTHU-NHRI for providing the fish lines and resources; TZeTH is supported by a grant from the NSC (101-2321-B-400-014). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="17"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Hepatocarcinogenesis involves the gradual progression from hepatitis to fibrosis and cirrhosis, and ultimately to hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC). HCC is the most common type of liver cancer and has a poor prognosis, especially in Asia and Africa <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-ElSerag1">[1]</xref>. Factors associated with an increased risk of HCC include viral infection by hepatitis B virus (HBV) or hepatitis C virus HCV (HCV), chronic alcohol consumption, tobacco smoking, cirrhosis, and aflatoxin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-ElSerag2">[2]</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Seeff1">[6]</xref>. The multistep process of HCC is initiated by hyperplasia, which is followed by dysplasia, early HCC, and finally, full-blown HCC <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Jain1">[7]</xref>. The therapeutic options for advanced or metastatic HCC are very limited <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Lin1">[8]</xref>, partially because the molecular mechanisms underlying hepatocarcinogenesis remain unclear <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Bosch1">[9]</xref>. Suitable animal models and efficient cell culture systems have provided a major breakthrough for understanding these mechanisms <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Kim1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-vanMalenstein1">[11]</xref>.</p><p>Endothelin 1 (EDN1) is a 21-amino acid peptide that exerts a wide range of biological activities. It is recognized as a vasoconstrictor peptide and has been implicated in the growth regulation of several tumors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Pfab1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Yanagisawa1">[13]</xref>. EDN1 has been found to enhance tumor growth by promoting angiogenesis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Komuro1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Pedram1">[15]</xref>. Vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) has been shown to enhance the expression and secretion of EDN1 in endothelial cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Matsuura1">[16]</xref>. Previous studies have revealed that EDN1 may also affect tumor invasion and metastasis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Rosano1">[17]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Zhao1">[18]</xref>. The increased expression of EDN1 has been observed in many malignant tumors, including breast, colorectal, prostate, pancreatic, and hepatocellular carcinomas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Ali1">[19]</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Grant1">[25]</xref>.</p><p>EDN1 secretion in hepatoma cells has been described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Kar1">[26]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Ishibashi1">[27]</xref>. Hepatoma cell growth increases upon the exogenous addition of EDN1 in a dose-dependent manner <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Pfab1">[12]</xref>. The tissue concentrations of EDN1, big ET-1, and the ETA receptor were significantly increased in hepatoma tissue compared to normal liver tissue <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Pfab1">[12]</xref>. Previously, in a hepatitis B virus X antigen-induced HCC mouse model, we identified genes that were significantly up-regulated at the pre-cancer and cancer stages, including Edn1, Src, Bmp4, and Bmp7 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Lu1">[28]</xref>. Transient transfection of the <italic>EDN1</italic> gene into Hep3B cells increases cell viability, promotes cell migration and invasiveness, and enhances colony formation of these cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Lu1">[28]</xref>. In addition, it has been reported that methylation-mediated silencing of the miR-1 gene induces hepatoma cell proliferation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Datta1">[29]</xref>. miR-1 inhibits <italic>EDN1</italic> expression and leads to attenuation of hepatoma cell proliferation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Lu1">[28]</xref>. These results suggest that a decrease of miR-1-mediated repression of <italic>EDN1</italic> may contribute to the development of HCC.</p><p>The zebrafish is an excellent animal model for studying liver disease and HCC. Many zebrafish disease models are similar to human disease states with respect to morphology and the expression profiles of dysregulated genes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Lam1">[30]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Lieschke1">[31]</xref>. Previously, we found that HBx and aflatoxin B1 act synergistically to cause hepatitis, steatosis, and liver hyperplasia <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Lu2">[32]</xref>, and overexpression of HBx together with p53 mutation caused HCC <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Lu2">[32]</xref>. Co-expression of HBx and the HCV core protein in liver tissues induces intrahepatic cholangiocarcinoma in zebrafish <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Liu1">[33]</xref>. Additionally, the liver-specific expression of Kras (V16) reportedly induces HCC in zebrafish <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Nguyen1">[34]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Nguyen2">[35]</xref>. Furthermore, the inducible overexpression of xmrk and Myc also causes HCC; however, the HCC regresses rapidly upon withdrawal of the inducer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Liu1">[33]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Li1">[36]</xref>. The aim of the present study was to identify the role of <italic>edn1</italic> in promoting liver disease and tumorigenesis and to understand the underlying mechanism using a zebrafish model and an <italic>in vitro</italic> cell culture system.</p><p>In this report, we demonstrate that the liver-specific overexpression of <italic>edn1</italic> results in HCC. Additionally, we show that a cell line stably overexpressing <italic>EDN1</italic> exhibits enhanced migration, proliferation, and invasion, and these effects can be reversed by the presence of EDN1 inhibitor or AKT inhibitor.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Zebrafish husbandry</title><p>The zebrafish embryos, larvae, and adult fish were maintained in the Zebrafish Core Facility at NTHU-NHRI (ZeTH) according to established protocols and methods <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Tseng1">[37]</xref>. The animal protocols for zebrafish experiments were approved by the Institutional Animal Care Use Committee (IACUC) of the National Health Research Institutes. The animal protocol numbers are NHRI-IACUC-100062-A and NHRI-IACUC-101005-A.</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Generation and maintenance of transgenic zebrafish</title><p>The transgenic founders were created using the Tol2 transposon system as described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Kwan1">[38]</xref>. The construction of the Tol2 construct, which contains <italic>edn1</italic> under the control of <italic>fabp10a</italic>, was described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Lu2">[32]</xref>. The zebrafish <italic>edn1</italic> gene was amplified using the attB1-<italic>edn1</italic>-F and attB2-<italic>edn1</italic>-R primers and the 24-hr zebrafish embryo cDNA as a template. The primer sequences are listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0085318-t001">Table 1</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0085318-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0085318.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Oligonucleotides primers used in this study.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0085318-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0085318.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene Name</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primer name</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Start end</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence (5&#x02032; to 3&#x02032;)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Accession number</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Size (bp)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>edn1</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">attB1-F-<italic>edn1</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline><named-content content-type="gene">GGGGACAAGTTTGTACAAAAAAGCAGGCT</named-content></underline><named-content content-type="gene">ATGCATTTGAGGATTATTTTCCCAGTTCTGACC</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_131519.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">567</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">attB2-R-<italic>edn1</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">567</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline><named-content content-type="gene">GGGGACCACTTTGTACAAGAAAGCTGGGT</named-content></underline><named-content content-type="gene">CTATGAGTTTTCAGAAATCCACGCTTGGC</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>srebf1</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>srebf1</italic>-F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2163</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">CATCCACATGGCTCTGAGTG</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_001105129.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">250</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>srebf1</italic>-R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2412</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">CTCATCCACAAAGAAGCGGT</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>cebpa</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q- <italic>cebpa</italic>-F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1080</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">AACGGAGCGAGCTTGACTT</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_131885</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">250</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q- <italic>cebpa</italic>-R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1329</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">AAATCATGCCCATTAGCTGC</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>fasn</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>fasn</italic>-F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7183</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">ATCTGTTCCTGTTCGATGGC</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XM_682295</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">250</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>fasn</italic>-R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7432</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">AGCATATCTCGGCTGACGTT</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>agapt</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q<italic>-agapt</italic>-F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">517</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">TTGGCGAAAAAGGAACTGTC</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_212992</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">250</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>agapt</italic>-R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">820</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">GGTGGTACTTGAGTTTGGGG</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>caveolin</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>caveolin</italic> -F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1832</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">AGCAGGTCGTGAAGATTGAA</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BC115201.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">250</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>caveolin</italic> -R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2081</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">CCACTTTAGCAGCAGCCTCT</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ccna1</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>ccna1</italic>-F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">151</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">TTGTGCTTGGTGTTTTGACC</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_212818.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">197</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>ccna1</italic>-R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">347</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">TAGCAGTTCTGAAGGCAGCA</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ccnb1</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>ccnb1</italic>-F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">603</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">GCGTGCCATTCTTATCGACT</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_131513.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">199</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>ccnb1</italic>-R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">801</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">TGCAATCTCTGGTGGGTACA</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ccne1</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>ccne1</italic>-F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">371</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">TCCCGACACAGGTTACACAA</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_130995.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>ccne1</italic>-R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">571</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">TTGTCTTTTCCGAGCAGGTT</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ccng1</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>ccng1</italic>-F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">603</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">GCTCAACTGGAAGGTCAAGG</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_199481.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">199</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>ccng1</italic>-R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">801</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">CAGGGCCAGAAGAGACAAAG</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>cdk1</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>cdk1</italic>-F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">779</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">CTCTGGGGACCCCTAACAAT</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_212564.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">200</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>cdk1</italic>-R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">978</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">CGGATGTGTCATTGCTTGTC</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>cdk2</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>cdk2</italic>-F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">794</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">CAGCTCTTCCGGATATTTCG</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_213406.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">199</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>cdk2</italic>-R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">992</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">CCGAGATCCTCTTGTTTGGA</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>pcna</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>pcna</italic>-F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">571</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">GGCAACATCAAGCTCTCACA</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_131404.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">195</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>pcna</italic>-R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">765</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">TGCAATTTTGTCCTCAACCA</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>col1a1a</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>col1a1a</italic>-F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2811</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">TATTGGTGGTCAGCGTGGTA</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_199214.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">199</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>col1a1a</italic>-R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3009</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">TCCTGGAGTACCCTCACGAC</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ctgfa</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>ctgfa</italic>-F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">481</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">TGTGTGTTTGGTGGAATGGT</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_001015041.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">198</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>ctgfa</italic>-R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">678</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">GGAGTCACACACCCACTCCT</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>hpse</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>hpse</italic>-F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">713</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">GCTCTGGTTTGGAGCTCATC</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_001045005.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">203</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>hpse</italic>-R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">915</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">GAAATCCCGACCAAGTTGAA</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>lepr</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>lepr</italic>-F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1471</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">AAACGCCCCTCTTTACCTGT</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_001113376.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">204</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>lepr</italic>-R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1674</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">GCTCCAGTCGCTCCAGTATC</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>mmp2</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>mmp2</italic>-F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">191</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">TCTTGCTTCCCTGCAAACTT</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_198067.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">209</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>mmp2</italic>-R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">399</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">GGTCAATCTCCCCTGTCTCA</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>tgfb1a</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>tgfb1a</italic>-F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1027</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">TTTCGGAAAGATCTGGGTTG</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_182873.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">199</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>tgfb1a</italic>-R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1225</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">AAAGAATTGGCAGAGGGTCA</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>timp2a</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>timp2a</italic>-F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">327</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">CGTTCTGCAATGCTGATGTT</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_182874.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">202</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>timp2a</italic>-R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">528</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">TCCAAATTGGTCACTCCACA</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>tp53</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>p53</italic>-F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">597</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">TTGTCCCATATGAAGCACCA</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_131327.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">200</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>p53</italic>-R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">796</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">TTTCCTGTCTCTGCCTGGAC</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>mycb</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q<italic>-mycb-F</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">688</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">GGTGTTTCCCTTTCCACTGA</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_200172.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">197</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q<italic>-mycb-R</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">884</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">TTCTCTTTTCCACCGTGACC</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ccnd1</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>ccnd1</italic>-F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">769</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">TTCCTTGCCAAACTGCCTAT</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_131025.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>ccnd1</italic>-R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">969</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">GGTGAGGTTCTGGGATGAGA</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>edn1</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>edn1</italic>-F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">220</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">GGAAACGCTCCACGTAAGAA</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_131519.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">208</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>edn1</italic>-R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">427</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">TTTCTGCCAGCTTGTGTTTG</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>18s</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>18s</italic>-F2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">551</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">GAGAAACGGCTACCACATCC</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XM_001922869.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">169</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>18s</italic>-R2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">719</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">ACCAGACTTGCCCTCCAA</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>actin</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>actin</italic> -F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">893</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">CTCCATCATGAAGTGCGACGT</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_131031.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">180</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>actin</italic> -R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1072</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">CAGACGGAGTATTTGCGCTCA</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>EDN1</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>EDN1</italic>-F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">367</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">TGCCAAGCAGGAAAAGAACT</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_001955.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">195</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>EDN1-</italic>R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">561</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">TTTGACGCTGTTTCTCATGG</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>18S</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>18S</italic>-F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1332</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">ATGGCCGTTCTTAGTTGGTG</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M10098.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">217</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>18S</italic>-R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1548</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">CGCTGAGCCAGTCAGTGTAG</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>AKT3</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>AKT3</italic>-F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">954</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">AGAAGATAATGACTATGGCCG</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_005465.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>AKT3</italic>R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1052</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">ATGGTCCTGGTTGTAGAAAG</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>OS9</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>OS9</italic>-F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">900</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">CCCGACCAAGGATGACA</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_006812.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">140</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>OS9-</italic>R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1039</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">GAGCACCAGAAGCTGAAT</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>CCNA2</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>CCNA2</italic>-F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1061</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">TTATTGCTGGAGCTGCCTTT</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_001237.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">224</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>CCNA2-</italic>R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1284</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">CTCTGGTGGGTTGAGGAGAG</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>CCNE2</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>CCNE2</italic>-F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1086</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">CTATTTGGCTATGCTGGAGG</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_057749.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">101</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>CCNE2-</italic>R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1186</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">TCTTCGGTGGTGTCATAATG</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>CDKN2B</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>CDKN2B</italic>-F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">TAGTGGAGAAGGTGCGACAG</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_004936.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">166</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>CDKN2B-</italic>R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">242</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">GTGAGAGTGGCAGGGTCTG</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>PCNA</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>PCNA</italic>-F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">161</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">CTGAGGGCTTCGACACCTAC</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_004530.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">170</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>PCNA-</italic>R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">330</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">TTTCTCCTGGTTTGGTGCTT</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>MMP2</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>MMP2</italic>-F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">417</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">AGTGGATGATGCCTTTGCTC</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_004530.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">154</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>MMP2-</italic>R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">570</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">GAGTCCGTCCTTACCGTCAA</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>MMP9</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>MMP9-</italic>F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1144</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">GACAAGAAGTGGGGCTTCTG</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_004994.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">171</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>MMP9-</italic>R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1314</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">GCCATTCACGTCGTCCTTAT</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ATF6</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>ATF6-</italic>F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">546</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">GCCTTTATTGCTTCCAGCAG</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_007348.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">165</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>ATF6-</italic>R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">710</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">TGAGACAGCAAAACCGTCTG</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>BIP</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>BIP-</italic>F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1541</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">AAGACAAGGGTACAGGGA</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_005347.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">106</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>BIP-</italic>R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1646</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">GCAAACTTCTCAGCATCATTAAC</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>IRE1</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>IRE1-</italic>F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1868</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">CGAACGTGATCCGCTAC</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AF059198.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">101</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>IRE1-</italic>R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1968</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">CTTCTGCTCCACATACTCTTG</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>PERK</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>PERK-</italic>F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1643</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">CTCACAGGCAAAGGAAGGAG</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_004836.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">179</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>PERK-</italic>R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1821</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">AACAACTCCAAAGCCACCAC</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>XBP1(total)</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>XBP1(t)-</italic>F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">393</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">GGAGTTAAGACAGCGCTTGG</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_005080.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">248</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>XBP1-</italic>R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">640</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">ACTGGGTCCAAGTTGTCCAG</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>XBP1(unspliced)</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>XBP1(un)-</italic>F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">499</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">CTCAGACTACGTGCACCTCT GCAGCA</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_005080.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">142</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-<italic>XBP1-</italic>R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">640</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene">ACTGGGTCCAAGTTGTCCAG</named-content></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Collection of liver tissue and histochemical analysis</title><p>A total of 37 samples were collected from the <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish at five different ages (3, 5, 7, 9, and 11 months) as described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Lu2">[32]</xref>. The histochemistry and immunohistochemistry analyses were conducted as described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Lu2">[32]</xref>. The multiple cancer tissue array (catalog #: MC801) and multiple normal tissue array (catalog #: BN1002a) were purchased from US Biomax, Inc. (Rockville, MD, USA) for the endothelin 1 immunohistochemistry analysis. The Liver cancer survey tissue array (catalog#: LV809) were purchased from US Biomax (Rockville, MD, USA) for miR-1 <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization and EDN1 immunohistochemistry analysis. The staining intensity of EDN1 was scored as 0 (&#x0003c;5%), 1 (5&#x02013;25%), 2 (25%&#x02013;50%), or 3 (50%&#x02013;100%) based on the percentage of positively stained cells as described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Lu1">[28]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Lu2">[32]</xref>. Diagnoses of the Edn1 transgenic fish liver tissue were determined by a single-blind evaluation of all samples by a trained pathologist (Dr. Yueh-Min Lin, Changhua Christian Hospital, Changhua, Taiwan).</p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>Immunohistochemistry analyses</title><p>For immunohistochemistry, the sections were incubated at 4&#x000b0;C overnight with 1&#x02236;100 dilutions of primary antibodies, including rabbit anti-active caspase 3 (BD Biosciences, San Jose, CA, USA), mouse anti-PCNA (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc., Santa Cruz, CA, USA), rabbit anti-endothelin 1 (GeneTex Inc., Hsinchu, Taiwan), rabbit anti-phospho-AKT (Ser473) (Cell Signaling Technology, Danvers, MA, USA), and anti-AKT (Cell Signaling Technology, Danvers, MA, USA). After washing with PBS, the sections were incubated with a 1&#x02236;100 dilution of the secondary antibody, either goat anti-rabbit IgG (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc., Santa Cruz, CA, USA) or goat anti-mouse IgG (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc. Santa Cruz, CA, USA), at room temperature. The protocol of immunohistochemistry was described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Lu2">[32]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title><italic>In situ</italic> hybridization of miR-1</title><p><italic>In situ</italic> hybridization of miR-1 was performed using the miRCURY LNA microRNA ISH Optimization Kit (Exiqon, Vedbaek, Denmark). Locked nucleic acid (LNA)-modified DNA oligonucleotide probe (hsa-miR-1, <named-content content-type="gene">ACATACTTCTTTACATTCCA</named-content>; Exiqon, Vedbaek, Denmark) were used to detect the <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization signals of miR-1 in liver tissue sections. The tissue sections were then dehydrated, cleared, mounted, and examined by light or fluorescence microscopy.</p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title>Sirius Red, Periodic Acid-Schiff, TUNEL, and oil red O staining</title><p>All of the staining procedures were performed as described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Lu2">[32]</xref>. The scoring method was also described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Lu2">[32]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s2g"><title>RNA isolation and quantitative RT-PCR</title><p>Liver tissues were frozen in liquid nitrogen immediately after dissection and stored at -70&#x000b0;C till RNA extraction. RNA isolation and qPCR were performed as described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Lu2">[32]</xref>. The qPCR primer sequences are listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0085318-t001">Table 1</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s2h"><title>Cell lines</title><p>The 293T cell line was obtained from the Bioresource Collection and Research Center (Taiwan). The 293T cells were cultured at 37&#x000b0;C with 5% CO<sub>2</sub> in Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium (DMEM) (Gibco, Grand Island, NY, USA) supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum (Gibco) and 1% penicillin-streptomycin (Gibco).</p></sec><sec id="s2i"><title>Expression constructs and transfection</title><p>To generate 293T cells with stable EDN1 expression, two expression constructs, pDsRed-Monomer-Hyg-N1:<italic>EDN1</italic> and pDsRed-Monomer-Hyg-N1, were generated and used to transfect 293T cells. <italic>EDN1</italic> was amplified using a human cDNA derived from the Hep3B hepatoma cell line as a template and the following primers: SalI-F-h<italic>EDN1</italic>, 5&#x02032; <named-content content-type="gene">GATC<underline>GTCGAC</underline><bold>ATG</bold>GATTATTTGCTCATGATTTTCTC</named-content> 3&#x02032; (the <italic>Sal</italic>I site is underlined, and the ATG translation initiation site of EDN1 is bolded) and <italic>BamH</italic>I-R-h<italic>EDN1</italic>, <sup>5&#x02032;</sup>GATC<underline>GGATCC</underline><bold>CA</bold>CCAATGTGCTCGGTTGTG<sup>3&#x02032;</sup> (the <italic>BamH</italic>I site is underlined. CA is the reverse complement of TG, which is the first two nucleotides of the TGA stop codon and is bolded). The amplified product was cloned into the <italic>Sal</italic>I and <italic>BamH</italic>I sites of the pDsRed-Monomer-Hyg-N1 vector. The cells were transfected with this expression construct using the Mirus TransIT&#x000ae;-LT1 Transfection Reagent (Mirus Bio LLC, Madison, WI, USA) according to the manufacturer's instructions. Briefly, 293T cells were seeded at 3&#x000d7;10<sup>6</sup> cells in 100-mm dish and grown for 18 to 24 hours until they achieved 50%&#x0223c;70% confluence. Serum-free DMEM medium was pre-mixed with 15 &#x000b5;g of plasmid and 45 &#x000b5;l of TransIT-LT1 reagent (1.5 ml final volume), incubated at room temperature for 25 minutes, and then added to cells with 15.5 ml complete medium. The stable clones were selected in the presence of 300 &#x000b5;g/ml hygromycin for 2 weeks.</p></sec><sec id="s2j"><title>Cell proliferation assay</title><p>Cell proliferation was analyzed by the WST-1 assay. Cells (6&#x000d7;10<sup>3</sup>) were seeded in 96-well plates and each well contained 100 &#x000b5;l of complete DMEM medium. After 18 hours of incubation, the media was removed and 100 &#x000b5;l of fresh complete DMDM medium containing premixed WST-1 cell proliferation reagent (Clontech, Mountain View, CA, USA) (1&#x02236;10 dilution in complete DMEM medium) was added to each well. The plates were incubated at 37&#x000b0;C with 5% CO<sub>2</sub> for 3 hours, followed by shaking thoroughly for 1 minute on a shaker. The absorbance at 440 nm was measured using a microplate reader. This assay was performed each day during the 5-day experiment to calculate the growth curve.</p></sec><sec id="s2k"><title><italic>In vitro</italic> cell migration assay</title><p>Migration assays were performed in Transwell plates (BD, Franklin Lakes, NJ, USA). Initially, 1&#x000d7;10<sup>5</sup> cells (diluted in 500 &#x000b5;l serum-free DMEM medium) were seeded in the upper chamber, and 1ml of complete DMEM medium was added to the lower chamber. After 18 or 48 hours, the non-migrating cells in the upper chamber were removed with a cotton swab, and the cells that had migrated through the 8-&#x000b5;m membrane were stained with 1X DAPI and counted. The average number of cells was calculated from ten randomly captured images (200X), and this value corresponds to the cell migration of each sample. The images were captured with a Leica DMIRB inverted fluorescence microscope coupled to a CoolSNAPTM Cooled CCD camera (Roper Scientific-Princeton Instruments, Trenton, NJ, USA).</p></sec><sec id="s2l"><title>Xenotransplantation assay</title><p>The <italic>fli1:EGFP</italic> transgenic <italic>()</italic> zebrafish were purchased from ZIRC (Oregon, USA). At two days post-fertilization (dpf), the zebrafish embryos were dechorionated and subsequently anesthetized with tricaine (0.04 mg/ml, Sigma, St. Louis, MO, USA). 293T cells stably overexpressing EDN1 or DsRed control were harvested, diluted to a concentration of 9&#x000d7;10<sup>7</sup> cells/ml in serum-free culture medium, and labeled with CM-Dil (red fluorescence) (Vybrant; Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA). Approximately 400 cells (4.6 nl) were implanted into the yolk of each 2-dpf embryo using a Nanoject II Auto-Nanoliter Injector (Drummond Scientific, Broomall, PA, USA). After injection, the zebrafish embryos were washed once with fish water and incubated for 1 hour at 28&#x000b0;C. The embryos were checked for fluorescent cells at 2 hours post-transplantation and were examined for metastasis every other day by fluorescence microscopy.</p></sec><sec id="s2m"><title>Inhibition assay</title><p>293T cells (2&#x000d7;10<sup>6</sup> per 10 cm<sup>2</sup> dish) stably overexpressing EDN1 (passage 15) or DsRed control cells (passage 17) were seeded in dishes supplemented with DMEM medium. Dishes were cultured overnight at 37&#x000b0;C with 5% CO<sub>2</sub> prior to the addition of the EDN1 inhibitor Ambrisentan (10 &#x000b5;M), the AKT inhibitor MK-2206 (0.5 &#x000b5;M), or the PI3K inhibitor LY294002 (25 &#x000b5;M)Following 48 hour treatment, cells were analyzed for RNA and protein expression levels.</p></sec><sec id="s2n"><title>Western blot analysis</title><p>Cells were harvested and cell lysate were prepared by incubating the cells in RIPA (radio-immunoprecipitation assay) buffer containing protease inhibitor cocktail (10 &#x000b5;l/ml) (Roche Molecular Biochemicals, Mannheim, Germany) for 30 minutes on ice. Total protein concentrations were determined using the Bradford protein assay (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA, USA). Cell lysate (20 &#x000b5;g total protein per sample) were subjected to SDS-PAGE followed by transferring to PVDF membrane. The membrane was incubated for 1 hour in blocking buffer, probed with the primary antibody for 1 hour at room temperature, and then washed twice with blocking buffer without milk. The membrane was then incubated with the appropriate secondary antibody for 1 hour at room temperature. After washing with blocking buffer, the protein bands were visualized using the Western Lightning Plus-ECL Reagent (Perkin Elmer, Waltham, MA, USA). Images of the blots were captured using the BioSpectrumAC Imaging System (UVP, Upland, CA, USA). The band intensity was quantified using UVP Visionworks LS software.</p><p>The anti-Endothelin 1 antibody was purchased from Abcam (Cambridge, MA, USA) and the anti-&#x003b2; actin antibody from Sigma-Aldrich (St. Louis, MO, USA). The mouse HRP-conjugated secondary antibody was purchased from Santa Cruz Biotechnology (Santa Cruz, CA, USA).</p></sec><sec id="s2o"><title>Statistical analyses</title><p>Statistical analyses of the human tissue microarray, <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization, and qPCR data were performed using the unpaired Student's <italic>t</italic>-test. The cumulative frequency of the pathological changes in the transgenic zebrafish was calculated using Kaplan-Meier analysis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Zhu1">[39]</xref>. The association of EDN1 and miR-1 expression in patients with HCC was determined using the Wilcoxon signed-rank test <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Lu3">[40]</xref>. For all of the statistical analyses, a p-value of less than 0.05 was considered to be statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec id="s3a"><title>Generation of Tg(<italic>fabp10a</italic>:<italic>edn1)</italic> transgenic zebrafish</title><p>We previously reported an up-regulation of <italic>Edn1</italic> in the HBx-induced HCC transgenic mouse model using a systems biology approach <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Lu1">[28]</xref>. To further investigate the role of <italic>edn1</italic> in hepatocarcinogenesis, we generated the pTol2-<italic>fabp10a</italic>:<italic>edn1</italic>-pA/CG2 construct to express <italic>edn1</italic> and <italic>GFP</italic> in zebrafish under the control of the <italic>fabp10a</italic> and <italic>cmlc2</italic> promoter respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g001">Fig. 1A</xref>). The construct was flanked with the Tol2 transposon element <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Kwan1">[38]</xref> and co-injected with Tol2 transposase mRNA into one-cell embryos to generate <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic zebrafish founder. One transgenic line was generated using a wild-type background zebrafish microinjected with the expression construct, and transgene expression was demonstrated in F1 and F2 fish by visualizing GFP in the heart of 11-month-old fish (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g001">Fig. 1B</xref>). The expression of <italic>edn1</italic> RNA in three independent Edn1 transgenic fish was assessed by qPCR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g001">Fig. 1C</xref>). The absolute amounts of <italic>edn1</italic> RNA by qPCR analysis were previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Tseng1">[37]</xref>. More than 1&#x000d7;10<sup>6</sup>
<italic>edn1</italic> RNA molecules from three independent <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish were expressed at different stages, but only a few thousand molecules of <italic>edn1</italic> RNA were expressed in the control GFP-mCherry transgenic fish.</p><fig id="pone-0085318-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0085318.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Generation and characterization of <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish.</title><p>(A) Diagram of the <italic>fabp10a</italic>:<italic>edn1</italic>-pA/<italic>CG2</italic> construct that contains Tol2 sequences and the <italic>cmlc2:GFP</italic> expression cassette. (B) The Edn1 protein was expressed in the liver of the wild-type fish carrying the <italic>fabp10a</italic>:<italic>edn1</italic>-pA/<italic>CG2</italic> transgene, as indicated by the expression of <italic>cmlc2</italic>:<italic>GFP</italic> in the heart (green fluorescence, 200X). Scale bars: 2 mm. (C) Quantitative RT-PCR analysis of <italic>edn1</italic> mRNA expression in hepatocytes from 3-, 5-, 7-, 9- and 11-month-old <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish (n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;3) and control <italic>fabp10a:GFP-mCherry</italic> transgenic fish. For qPCR analysis, a series of known PCR fragment (GFP) of known concentrations were used as the standard. The <italic>edn1</italic> RNA concentration was calculated base on the standard curve. The differences between the <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish and control fish were assessed using a two-tailed Student's <italic>t</italic>-test. Asterisks <sub>***</sub> represent the P value is less than 0.001.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0085318.g001"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3b"><title>Histopathological examination of the <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic zebrafish</title><p>Liver tissues of the <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish derived from the <italic>fabp10a</italic>:<italic>edn1</italic>-pA/CG2 construct and the control transgenic fish from the <italic>fabp10a</italic>:<italic>GFP-mCherry</italic> construct were analyzed at five different ages (3, 5, 7, 9, and 11 months). All of the data presented in this work refer to the fish of the F1 generation. Thirty-seven <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish were used for H&#x00026;E and other staining, and twenty-seven GFP-mCherry transgenic fish were included as control. Detailed results are shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0085318.s003">Table S1</xref>. Liver lesions in the zebrafish were examined by an experienced pathologist and were identified based on the criteria developed by the National Toxicology Program and in the literature <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Boorman1">[41]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Hobbie1">[42]</xref>. Steatosis is characterized by clear intracytoplasmic vacuoles that are positive to the Oil red O staining. Hyperplasia is featured by the accelerated proliferation of atypical hepatocytes with enlarged and mildly irregular nuclei. HCC is identified as an increased nuclear pleomorphism, prominent nucleoli, and an increased number of mitotic figures. The H&#x00026;E staining revealed that overexpression of <italic>edn1</italic> caused an increase in cytoplasmic vacuoles although the vacuoles were rarely stained red (lipid droplets) by the Oil red O staining (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g002">Fig. 2B1&#x02013;2B4</xref>). Additionally, the PAS score showed high levels of glycogen accumulation in the liver with <italic>edn1</italic> overexpression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g003">Fig. 3C</xref>). Thus, the cytoplasmic vacuoles may represent both lipid and glycogen accumulation. Overexpression of <italic>edn1</italic> also induced bile duct dilation, hyperplasia, and HCC from five and eleven months of age (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g002">Fig. 2A</xref>1&#x02013;2A6). The accumulative frequency of liver pathology was analyzed using the Kaplan-Meier method (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g002">Fig. 2C</xref>). Compared to the control zebrafish, which showed normal pathology at all stages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g003">Fig. 3A</xref>), liver-specific <italic>edn1</italic> expression significantly induced steatosis, bile duct dilation, and HCC (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05).</p><fig id="pone-0085318-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0085318.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Histopathology of <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic hepatocytes.</title><p>(A1&#x02013;A6) H&#x00026;E staining of the liver sections from the <italic>GFP-mCherry</italic> control fish at 11 months (A1), and from the <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish at 3, 5, 7, 9 months (A2&#x02013;A6). The images were captured at 200X magnification. The A1&#x02032;&#x02013;A6&#x02032; images resemble the A1&#x02013;A6 images, though they were captured at 400X magnification. H&#x00026;E staining of liver sections from <italic>GFP-mCherry</italic> control fish showed normal histology, while <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish showed normal, steatosis, bile duct dilation, hyperplasia, and HCC at 3, 5, 7, and 9 months. Scale bars: 50 &#x000b5;m. (B). The Tg(<italic>fabp10a:GFP-mCherry</italic>) and Tg(<italic>fabp10a</italic>:<italic>edn1</italic>-pA/CG2) liver sections were stained by H&#x00026;E (B1 and B2). The same sections were also stained with oil red O (B3 and B4). Tissues from the Tg(<italic>fabp10a</italic>:<italic>edn1</italic>-pA/CG2) fish showed positive staining with oil red O in the hepatocytes (400X). Scale bars: 50 &#x000b5;m. (C) The cumulative frequency of steatosis, bile duct dilation, hyperplasia, and HCC in the <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish was determined by Kaplan-Meier analysis. The different colors denote different liver diseases: steatosis (green), bile duct dilation (blue), hyperplasia (brown), and HCC (red). The differences between the <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish and control fish were assessed using a two-tailed Student's <italic>t</italic>-test. The <italic>P</italic> value is less than 0.05.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0085318.g002"/></fig><fig id="pone-0085318-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0085318.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Comparison of hepatocyte histology from <italic>GFP-mCherry</italic> and <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish from 3 to 11 months of age.</title><p>Twenty-seven <italic>GFP-mCherry</italic> transgenic fish (as control) and thirty-seven <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish were compared. H&#x00026;E and additional staining methods were conducted on all the fish samples. (A) Statistical analysis of H&#x00026;E staining. Different colors denote different pathological features: normal (gray), steatosis (green), bile duct dilation (yellow), hyperplasia (orange), and HCC (red). (B) Liver fibrosis was determined by Sirius Red staining. (C) Glycogen accumulation was identified by Periodic Acid-Schiff (PAS) staining. (D) Apoptosis was examined using the TUNEL assay. (E) Active caspase 3a and (F) Nuclear PCNA expression were assessed by IHC. Different colors represent different pathological scores. There are four possible scores for B and D: 0 (gray), 1 (yellow), 2 (orange), and 3 (red), and five possible scores: 0 (gray), 1 (green), 2 (yellow), 3 (orange), and 4 (red) for C, E and F. The y-axes correspond to &#x0201c;percentage of embryos&#x0201d;.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0085318.g003"/></fig><p>In the control GFP-mCherry fish, all of the liver sections examined were normal based on the H&#x00026;E staining (from 3 to 11 months of age). However, 83% of the <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish showed steatosis by 5 months, and approximately 30% of the fish still exhibited steatosis from 7 to 11 months. Bile duct dilation was observed in 33%&#x02013;45% of the <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish by 7 to 11 months of age. Furthermore, approximately 17&#x02013;18% of the <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish developed hyperplasia by 7 to 9 months. The incidence of HCC formation at 7, 9, and 11 months was 17&#x02013;20% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g003">Fig. 3A</xref>). These results provide the first <italic>in vivo</italic> evidence that <italic>edn1</italic> overexpression in zebrafish facilitates HCC formation.</p><p>The penetrance of HCC formation in this study in <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish is less than 25%, which is similar to our previous findings that 17% fish showed src-induced HCC <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Lu2">[32]</xref>. Similarly, overexpression of HBx in p53 mutant fish caused 44% of fish developing HCC at 11 months of age <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Lu2">[32]</xref>. In a transgenic zebrafish cancer model, overexpression of MYCN resulted in the development of neuroblastoma with a penetrance of less than 20% <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Zhu1">[39]</xref>. Another study demonstrated that overexpression of KrasV12 induced liver tumors with a penetrance of 28% in p53<sup>+/+</sup> fish, and this rate of tumorigenesis increased to 32% in p53<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> fish <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Nguyen1">[34]</xref>. Thus, it is ordinary to observe a low penetrance of tumor formation with overexpression of a single oncogene in the zebrafish animal model, and the synergistic effects between multiple oncogenes can enhance the penetrance of tumor formation.</p></sec><sec id="s3c"><title>Pathological alterations in the livers of <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic zebrafish</title><p>We previously demonstrated that liver-specific overexpression of HBx affects collagen expression, glycogen accumulation, apoptosis, and cell proliferation in zebrafish <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Lu2">[32]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Lu4">[43]</xref>. Thus, in this study we examined these pathological parameters for the <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g003">Fig. 3</xref>). Thirty-seven <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish and 27 GFP-mCherry control fish were analyzed using different staining methods as described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Lu2">[32]</xref>. Representative pictures used for pathological scoring are shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0085318.s001">Fig. S1</xref>. In a semi-quantitative analysis using Sirius Red staining, we found that overexpression of <italic>edn1</italic> increased in collagen expression beginning at 3 months and continuing to 11 months while there was no sign of collagen expression in the control fish (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g003">Fig. 3B</xref>). This result was consistent with a previous study showing that HBx expression in wild-type zebrafish causes fibrosis from 3 to 11 months.</p><p>Glycogen accumulation was assessed by Periodic Acid-Schiff (PAS) staining. The results showed that the <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish accumulated higher levels of glycogen in the liver compared to the GFP-mCherry control fish (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g003">Fig. 3C</xref>). Glycogen began to accumulate in the hepatocytes as early as 3 months of age but was decreased with the progression of hepatocarcinogenesis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g003">Fig. 3C</xref>). These changes were similar to those observed in the HBx transgenic fish.</p><p>Apoptosis was analyzed using the TUNEL assay and immunohistochemical staining for active caspase3. No apoptosis was detected in the control fish, whereas an increased apoptosis was detected in the <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish (3 to 11 months of age) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g003">Fig. 3D and 3E</xref>). In addition, nuclear PCNA accumulation was observed in the hepatocytes of the <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish, and the highest PCNA expression levels was observed at 9 and 11 months. However, only low PCNA expression was observed in the control fish of the same age (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g003">Fig. 3F</xref>). These pathological alterations reflect the gradual progression of HCC in the <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic zebrafish, from steatosis to fibrosis, hyperplasia, and to HCC within 6 months (between 5 and 11 months of age).</p></sec><sec id="s3d"><title>Up-regulation of genes related to lipid metabolism, cell cycle, and metastasis and increased in fibrosis and tumor markers in <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic zebrafish</title><p>Using quantitative RT-PCR analysis (qPCR), we previously showed that HBx overexpression in wild-type zebrafish enhances expression of several genes related to the observed pathological changes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Lu2">[32]</xref>. To assess whether <italic>edn1</italic> overexpression also causes similar effects, we analyzed the expression of lipogenic factors, lipogenic enzymes, the PPAR-&#x003b3; targeting gene <italic>caveolin</italic>, cell cycle/division related genes, fibrosis and metastasis related genes, and tumor makers. For the qPCR analysis, three biological replicates and multiple technical replicates were performed for each gene at the various stages of the <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish and GFP-mCherry control fish. Among these genes, the sterol regulatory binding protein-1 (<italic>srebp1</italic>) gene encodes a transcription factor that binds to the sterol regulatory element-1 (SRE1) site of genes involved in sterol biosynthesis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g004">Fig. 4A</xref>). The CCAAT enhancer binding protein-alpha (<italic>cebpa</italic>) gene encodes a bZIP transcription factor that can bind as a homodimer to certain promoters and enhancers and is transcriptionally activated during adipocyte differentiation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g004">Fig. 4A</xref>). Fatty acid synthase (FASN) is a multi-enzyme that plays a key role in fatty acid synthesis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g004">Fig. 4B</xref>), and acyl-CoA: 1-acylglycerol-sn-3-phosphate acyl-transferase (AGAPT) is an enzyme critical in triglyceride biosynthesis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g004">Fig. 4B</xref>). Caveolin belongs to a family of integral membrane proteins that are the principal components of caveolae membranes and are involved in receptor-independent endocytosis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g004">Fig. 4C</xref>). All these genes were analyzed in the 5-month-old <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish to verify the presence of steatosis at the molecular level.</p><fig id="pone-0085318-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0085318.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Quantitative RT-PCR analysis of selected marker genes in <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish.</title><p>Genes encoding (A) lipogenic factors, (B) lipogenic enzymes, and (C) PPAR-gamma were up-regulated in 5-month-old <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish. (D) Cell cycle/division-related genes were analyzed in fish aged 7 to 11 months and were found to be up-regulated most significantly at 11 months. (E) Cell cycle/division-related genes from three independent <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish at 11 month of age were compared. (F) Fibrosis- and metastasis-related genes and (G) tumor markers were up-regulated at 11 months. The mRNA levels of these genes in the liver samples of three independent <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish and the age matched <italic>GFP-mCherry</italic> control fish were analyzed by qPCR at 5 different ages (3, 5, 7, 9, and 11 months). Each Ct value was normalized using &#x003b2;-actin as control, and was then compared with the Ct value determined for the <italic>GFP-mCherry</italic> control fish, and then were converted into fold differences. The formula for the relative quantification is: &#x00394;&#x00394;Ct &#x0200a;=&#x0200a; (C<sub>t,target</sub> &#x02212;C<sub>t,&#x003b2;-actin</sub>)<sub>edn1 fish</sub>&#x02212;(C<sub>t,target</sub> &#x02212;C<sub>t, &#x003b2;-actin</sub>)<sub>GFP-mC fish</sub>, and fold change &#x0200a;=&#x0200a;1.94<sup>&#x02212;&#x00394;&#x00394;Ct</sup>. Multiple replicates were performed, and the means are presented with their standard deviations. The differences among the variables were assessed using a two-tailed Student's <italic>t</italic>-test. Significant differences between the control and <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish are indicated (<sub>*</sub>, <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05; <sub>**</sub>, <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.01; and <sub>***</sub>, <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0085318.g004"/></fig><p>We also determined the expression levels of cell cycle and cell division related genes, including <italic>ccna1</italic>, <italic>ccnb1</italic>, <italic>ccne1</italic>, <italic>ccng1</italic>, <italic>cdk1</italic>, <italic>cdk2,</italic> and <italic>pcna</italic> in a 7-month-old and a 9-month-old <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g004">Fig. 4D</xref>) as well as in three independent 11-month-old <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g004">Fig. 4E</xref>). Moreover, the fibrosis and metastasis related genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g004">Fig. 4F</xref>) and tumor markers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g004">Fig. 4G</xref>) were also analyzed in three independent 11 month-old <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish to confirm the presence of hyperplasia and HCC (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g004">Fig. 4G</xref>). The fibrosis markers examined included 1) collagen of type I alpha 1(<italic>col1a1</italic>); 2) connective tissue growth factor (<italic>ctgfa</italic>), a factor that mirrors some of the effects of TGF beta on skin fibroblasts including the stimulation of extracellular matrix production, chemotaxis, proliferation, and integrin expression; 3) heparanase (<italic>hpse</italic>), an enzyme that acts both at the cell surface and in the extracellular matrix to degrade polymeric heparan sulfate molecules into shorter chain length oligosaccharides; 4) leptin receptor (<italic>lepr</italic>), a single transmembrane domain receptor of the cytokine receptor family that functions as a receptor for the fat cell-specific hormone leptin; 5) matrix metalloproteinase-2 (<italic>mmp2</italic>); 6) TGF-&#x003b2;-1Transforming growth factor beta 1 (<italic>tgfb1a</italic>), a growth factor that acts synergistically with TGFA to induce transformation; and 7) tissue inhibitor of metalloproteinase 2&#x003b1; (<italic>timp2a</italic>), an enzyme that maintains connective tissue integrity by modulating MMP activity. The tumor makers analyzed included 1) protein 53 or tumor protein 53 (<italic>tp53</italic>), a gene that is important in multicellular organisms because of its functions as a tumor suppressor and cell cycle regulator; 2) c-myb proto-oncogene (<italic>cmyb</italic>), a gene important in the control of proliferation and differentiation of hematopoietic progenitor cells; and 3) cyclin D1 (<italic>ccnd1</italic>), a regulatory subunit for CDK4 or CDK6 and an essential factor for the cell cycle G1/S transition. The primer sequences used in qPCR analysis for these genes were listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0085318-t001">Table 1</xref> and also described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Lu2">[32]</xref>.</p><p>The qPCR results indicated that the analyzed genes representing lipogenic factors and enzymes and the PPAR-&#x003b3; targeting caveolin were all up-regulated at 5 months of age in the three independent <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish, with the exception that one fish (fish #3) showed a decrease in <italic>cebpa</italic> and <italic>fasn</italic> expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g004">Fig. 4A, B and C</xref>). Many other genes in these categories were examined, and some of them (<italic>pparg</italic>, <italic>chrebp</italic>, <italic>pap</italic>, <italic>dgat2</italic>, <italic>ucp2</italic>, and <italic>cfdl</italic>) showed no significant changes (data not shown). Cell cycle/division-related genes were not up-regulated at 5 months, but showed increases at 7 and 9 months and were markedly increased at 11 months for one of the three <italic>edn1</italic> fish (fish #1) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g004">Fig. 4D</xref>). The other two <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish also show a similar increasing trend at 11 months, except for the expression of <italic>ccng</italic> and <italic>cdk1</italic> which was not up-regulated in <italic>edn1</italic> fish #2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g004">Fig. 4E</xref>). Moreover, the fibrosis- and metastasis-related genes were also significantly up-regulated in the three <italic>edn1</italic> fish at 11 months with the exception of the TGFb/a expression in <italic>edn1</italic> fish #3 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g004">Fig. 4F</xref>). Additionally, the tumor markers &#x02013; <italic>tp53</italic>, <italic>cmycb,</italic> and <italic>ccnd1</italic> were significantly up-regulated in all three <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish compared to the control fish at 11 months (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g004">Fig. 4G</xref>). Cumulatively, these results demonstrated that the liver-specific expression of <italic>edn1</italic> causes up-regulation of several genes associated with lipid metabolism at 5 months of age, and these changes are consistent with the development of steatosis observed in the pathological analysis. The up-regulation of cell cycle/proliferation-related genes, tumor markers, and metastasis markers detected at 11 months of age in the <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish was also in accord with the observation that at this age <italic>edn1</italic> overexpression caused hyperplasia and HCC in zebrafish.</p></sec><sec id="s3e"><title>Screening for <italic>EDN1</italic> expression in multiple normal and cancerous tissue samples</title><p>We previously have shown that <italic>EDN1</italic> expression at the RNA and protein levels was increased in hepatocellular carcinoma samples when compared to normal tissues <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Lu1">[28]</xref>. To further examine whether the up-regulation of <italic>EDN1</italic> is a common feature in various human cancers, we carried out an immunohistochemical analysis on a cancer tissue array. Additionally, we examined the data set by using the Gene Expression Omnibus website to determine the <italic>EDN1</italic> mRNA levels in tumors and non-tumor samples. <italic>EDN1</italic> overexpression was observed in 80 malignant tumors, which represented 10 tumor types, including breast, cerebrum, colon, liver, lung, prostate, and uterus tumors. EDN1 protein overexpression was less significant in esophagus, kidney and stomach tumors (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g005">Fig. 5A</xref>). Moreover, comparing with the normal control samples, <italic>EDN1</italic> mRNA expression was increased in inflammatory breast cancer, nasopharyngeal carcinoma, metastatic prostate cancer, gastric cancer, papillary thyroid cancer, and ovarian cancer epithelial cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g005">Fig. 5B</xref>). These results indicated that <italic>EDN1</italic> overexpression is a common phenomenon in the development of various human cancers.</p><fig id="pone-0085318-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0085318.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>EDN1 protein and mRNA expression in various human tumor and normal tissue samples.</title><p>(A) To assess EDN1 protein expression in human normal and tumor tissues, the IHC staining of the indicated tissues was performed and the staining intensity was evaluated. A score from 0 to 4 was allocated to each sample and the scores from the same tumor types were averaged. The numbers of samples for each tumor/normal type are indicated. EDN1 expression was enhanced in all tumor types examined. The differences among the variables were assessed using a two-tailed Student's <italic>t</italic>-test. Significant differences between the normal and tumor tissues are indicated (<sub>*</sub>, <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05; <sub>**</sub>, <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.01; and <sub>***</sub>, <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001). (B) <italic>EDN1</italic> mRNA expression from the GSE data set. The data of inflammatory breast cancer, nasopharyngeal carcinoma, metastatic prostate tumor, gastric cancer, papillary thyroid cancer, and ovarian cancer were obtained from the GDS3097, GDS3610, GDS2865, GDS1210, GDS1732, and GDS3592 data set, respectively. The numbers of samples for each tumor/normal type are indicated. Over-expression of <italic>EDN1</italic> transcripts was observed in all tumor types examined. The differences among the variables were assessed using a two-tailed Student's <italic>t</italic>-test. Significant differences between the normal and tumor tissues are indicated (<sub>*</sub>, <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05; <sub>**</sub>, <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.01; and <sub>***</sub>, <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0085318.g005"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3f"><title>Stable overexpression of <italic>EDN1</italic> in 293T cells promotes cell proliferation and migration</title><p>To further elucidate the molecular mechanism by which <italic>edn1</italic> overexpression induces hepatocarcinogenesis, we used a HEK-293T cell line to overexpress <italic>EDN1</italic>. HEK-293T cells were used because of the ease of culturing and their high transfection efficiency. These cells were derived from human embryonic kidney cells and are widely used in laboratory research. HEK-293 cell lines with high passages (&#x0003e;65 passages) are 100% tumorigenic, whereas low passage cells (&#x0003c;52 passages) exhibit no tumorgenecity under the same culturing conditions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Shen1">[44]</xref>. For the purpose of this study, low passage HEK-293T cells (passage 15) were used to generate the <italic>EDN1</italic> stably expressed cell lines. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g006">Fig. 6</xref>, the stable line obtained significantly enhanced the <italic>EDN1</italic> RNA and protein levels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g006">Fig. 6A</xref>) as well as the cell viability at low densities as analyzed by the WST-1 assay (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g006">Fig. 6B</xref>). <italic>EDN1</italic> overexpression also enhanced <italic>in-vitro</italic> migration by more than five folds compared to the control cells at both 18 hours and 48 hours after seeding (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g006">Fig. 6C</xref>), in which 18-h incubation exhibited a stronger effect than the 48-h incubation. Although <italic>EDN1</italic> overexpression could increase cell proliferation, the &#x0201c;migrated cells&#x0201d; observed in the 18-h incubation are not a result of increased proliferation because this incubation time is less than the time required for cell doubling.</p><fig id="pone-0085318-g006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0085318.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Stable <italic>EDN1</italic> overexpression in 293T cells increases cell viability and migration.</title><p>(A) <italic>EDN1</italic> RNA and protein expression in cells stably overexpressing <italic>EDN1</italic>. Total RNA was isolated from the 293T/EDN1 and DsRed/293T control cells, and the mRNA expression level was determined by qPCR. Data are expressed as mean &#x000b1; SD showing the ratio of the <italic>EDN1</italic> expression in the overexpressed cells versus the control cells. The protein expression was analyzed by Western blotting using an EDN1 antibody. The EDN1 protein was expressed exclusively in the stable 293T/EDN1 cells. (B) A WST-1 assay to measure the viability of 293T/EDN1 cells (blue) and 293T/DsRed cells (red); 250 cells/well were seeded in 6-well plates, and the cell viability was measured at 1, 2, 3, 4 and 5 days after seeding. (C) A Transwell assay to assess the migration ability of 293T/EDN1 cells. The method is detailed in the Materials and Methods. The number of migrating 293T/DsRed control cells and 293T/EDN1 cells at 18 and 48 h are expressed as means &#x000b1; SD of three independent experiment. (D) 293T/DsRed or 293T/EDN1 cells labeled with CM-Dil (red) were ectopically injected into the yolk sac of 2-dpf Tg(<italic>fli1:EGFP</italic>) zebrafish embryos. The <italic>fli1:EGFP</italic> embryos injected with 293T/DsRed control cells (D1&#x02013;D4) and 293T/EDN1 cells (D5&#x02013;D8) at 0, 1, 2, and 3 days post-injection (dpi) are shown at a low magnification. The <italic>fli1:EGFP</italic> embryos injected with 293T/DsRed cells (D9&#x02013;D11) and 293T/EDN1 cells (D12&#x02013;D14) at 1, 2, or 3 dpi are shown at a high magnification. Arrows indicate the primary injection site. Scale bar: 50 &#x000b5;m. (E) Quantification of the <italic>in-vivo</italic> cell migration. The percentage of the 3 dpi embryos showing migration behavior after xenotransplantation of 293T/DsRed cells (as a control) and 293T/EDN1 cells are shown. Forty-five and thirty-two two-day-old <italic>fli1:EGFP</italic> embryos were injected with DsRed/293T cells and 293T/EDN1 cells, respectively. These cells were examined at 3 dpi for migration behavior with a microscope. The data are presented as the means &#x000b1; SD. <sub>**</sub>, <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0085318.g006"/></fig><p>To evaluate <italic>in-vivo</italic> migration, we employed a xenotransplantation assay, in which 293T/DsRed cells as control and 293T/EDN1 cells were labeled with DiI and injected into 2 day-old <italic>fli1:EGFP</italic> zebrafish embryos. At three days post-injection (dpi) these embryos were assayed for migration under a fluorescence microscope (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g006">Fig. 6D</xref>). Embryos that lacked fluorescence after injection or contained migrated cells 2 hours post-injection (indicating cell leakage) were eliminated from the analysis. These results showed that the embryos injected with the control 293T/DsRed cells remained the fluorescence in the yolk up to 3 dpi (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g006">Fig. 6D</xref>1&#x02013;D4 and D9&#x02013;D11), while the embryos injected with 293T/EDN1 cells showed the cells migrated into the entire trunk and tail (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g006">Fig. 6D</xref>5&#x02013;D8 and D12&#x02013;D14). In few embryos, we observed the distant migration and extravasation of these cells further within the trunk. The embryos showing migration behavior after injection of 293T/EDN1 cells and 293T/DsRed cells accounted for 26.9% and 6.8% of the fish respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g006">Fig. 6E</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s3g"><title><italic>EDN1</italic> overexpression results in an up-regulation of genes related to the cell cycle, migration, and the UPR pathway, and EDN1 inhibitor and AKT inhibitor can reverse these changes</title><p>To understand the molecular mechanism underlying the <italic>EDN1</italic>-induced proliferation and migration, we measured the expression levels of the genes related to cell cycle, proliferation, and migration by qPCR. The 293T cells overexpressing the DsRed vector were used as a control. An up-regulation of the <italic>CCNE2</italic>, <italic>CDK2b</italic>, <italic>MMP2</italic>, <italic>MMP9</italic>, <italic>PCNA,</italic> and <italic>AKT3</italic> genes was observed in the 293T cells overexpressing <italic>EDN1</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g007">Fig. 7A</xref>). We also determined the expression levels of the mediators of the UPR pathway as this pathway is associated with the risk of steatosis, glycogen accumulation, and tumor formation, all these conditions being observed in the <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish. By qPCR analysis, we found that spliced <italic>XBP1, ATF6</italic>, <italic>BIP</italic>, <italic>IRE1,</italic> and <italic>PERK</italic> were up-regulated in the 293T/EDN1 cells compared to the control cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g007">Fig. 7B</xref>). It has been shown that EDN1 mediates the activation of the PI3K/AKT pathway in lung fibrogenesis and in human chondrosarcoma cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Kulasekaran1">[45]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Wu1">[46]</xref>. Thus, to assess whether the up-regulation of these genes also is mediated by AKT activation, we used the EDN1 and AKT inhibitors Ambrisentan and MK-2206, respectively, to treat the 293T stable cells. The control 293T/DsRed cells incubated with Ambrisentan and/or MK-2206 had no significant changes in the RNA levels of the genes tested (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0085318.s002">Fig. S2</xref>). However, the presence of Ambrisentan or MK-2206, the increase in the RNA expression of these genes in the 293T/EDN1 cells was reversed to the levels not different from the 293T/DsRed control cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g007">Figs. 7A&#x02013;B</xref>). These results confirmed the hypothesis that by binding to its receptor, EDN1 activates the PI3K/AKT signal pathway and then induces the expression of the downstream target genes, including those related to cell cycle, migration, and the UPR pathway. Because the UPR pathway-related genes are also targets of the EDN1/PI3K/AKT pathway, this might partially explain the conditions of steatosis, glycogen accumulation, fibrosis, and HCC observed in the HBx and <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish.</p><fig id="pone-0085318-g007" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0085318.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>Quantitative RT-PCR analysis of selected marker genes in cells stably overexpressing <italic>EDN1</italic>.</title><p>293T/EDN1 and 293T/DsRed stable cells at passage 15 and 18, respectively were used. Data are the means &#x000b1; SD of three to seven independent experiments. Statistical significance was determined using Student's t-test. (A&#x02013;B) RNA expression levels of the cell cycle-, proliferation-, and migration-related genes (A) and the mediators of the UPR pathway (B) in the EDN1 stable cells cultured in the absent (blue) or presence of the EDN1 inhibitor Ambrisentan (red); the AKT inhibitor MK-2206 (green), or the combination of the two inhibitors (purple). (C) Western blots and the quantification of the signal intensities. The expression of the UPR mediators (p-AKT, p-IRE1, proteolytic ATF6, and BIP) was detected in the stable EDN1 cells incubated in the absence (blue) or presence of the EDN1 inhibitor Ambrisentan (red); the AKT inhibitor MK-2206 (green), or combination of the two inhibitors (purple). (D) <italic>in vitro</italic> migration assay of the DsRed control cells (darkest blue) and the stable EDN1 cells incubated in the absence (dark blue) or presence of the AKT inhibitor MK-2206 (light blue) or the PI3K inhibitor LY294002 (lightest blue). Significant differences among the groups are indicated (<sub>*</sub>, <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05; <sub>**</sub>, <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.01; <sub>***</sub>, <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0085318.g007"/></fig><p>We also performed western blot analysis to determine the protein levels of phospho-AKT, phospho-IRE1, proteolytic ATF6, and BIP, all being the effectors of the UPR pathway. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g007">Fig. 7C</xref>, AKT phosphorylation was increased in 293T/EDN1 cells compared to the 293T/DsRed control cells, and it was blocked in the presence of Ambrisentan or MK-2206. The EDN1-induced IRE1 phosphorylation also was reduced by Ambrisentan. The up-regulation of the proteolytic ATF6 and BIP expression following EDN1 overexpression was diminished in the presence of MK-2206. These results confirmed that the UPR mediators were increased by EDN1 at the protein level and that these changes can be reversed by AKT and EDN1 inhibitors. Using the same inhibitors, we further demonstrated that inhibition of AKT or PI3K also blocked the EDN1-induced cell migration (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g007">Fig. 7D</xref>). This finding provides additional evidence for a link between EDN1, PI3/AKT, and cell migration ability.</p><p>The involvement of EDN1 in the AKT pathway was also explored using the <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish. By immunostaining with antibodies specific to phospho-AKT (p-AKT) and AKT, we found that the p-AKT staining is enhanced in the <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish compared to the GFP-mCherry control fish (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g008">Fig. 8B vs. 8E</xref>), while the AKT level was not significantly different between the two transgenic fish (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g008">Fig. 8C vs. 8F</xref>). We observed hyperplasia and HCC in <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish, which mimics hepatocyte proliferation in humans. These data may support the hypothesis that EDN1 promotes liver cell proliferation through the AKT pathway.</p><fig id="pone-0085318-g008" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0085318.g008</object-id><label>Figure 8</label><caption><title>Expression of p-AKT and AKT in the <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish.</title><p>(A) and (D) depict H&#x00026;E staining of the liver sections of the GFP-mCherry control and <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish. (B-C) and (E-F) shows the IHC staining using an anti-phospho-AKT antibody (B and E) or an anti-AKT antibody (C and F).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0085318.g008"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3h"><title>Association of EDN1 and miR-1 expression in patients with HCC</title><p>Several <italic>in vitro</italic> studies have indicated that the 3&#x02032; untranslated region (3&#x02032;UTR) of <italic>EDN1</italic> is a direct target of miR-1, and hence miR-1 inhibit the <italic>EDN1</italic> expression and lead to attenuation of cell proliferation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Lu1">[28]</xref>. To assess the relation of miR-1 to <italic>EDN1</italic>, we initially measured the expression level of miR-1 in the <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g009">Fig. 9A</xref>, miR-1 was expressed at high levels in the 3-month-old <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g009">Fig. 9A1</xref>), but the expression was reduced in the 9-month-old <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish with HCC (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g009">Fig. 9A2</xref>). Thus, the miR-1 level is inversely related to the development of HCC. Because the <italic>edn1</italic> gene in the <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish does not include the 3&#x02032; UTR, the <italic>edn1</italic> expression in the fish should not be targeted by miR-1. Moreover, the <italic>edn1</italic> mRNA levels were at high levels at all ages of the transgenic fish. Interestingly, the miR-1 levels were decreased in the HCC samples of the 9 month-old fish compared to those in the normal tissue samples of the 3 month-old <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish, suggesting that miR-1 may be negatively regulated by <italic>edn1</italic>.</p><fig id="pone-0085318-g009" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0085318.g009</object-id><label>Figure 9</label><caption><title>MiR-1 regulates EDN1 expression in HCC.</title><p>(A) The RNA expression of miR-1 in the <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish and human specimens was determined by <italic>in-situ</italic> hybridization, and EDN1 protein expression in human specimen by IHC. The expression of miR-1 was at the high level in 3-month-old <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish which is normal in pathological analysis (A1) and was decreased in the 9-month-old <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish with HCC (A2). The liver tissue of the GFP-mCherry control zebrafish was stained with (A3) or without (A4) the U6 probe as the positive or negative control, respectively. The miR-1 signal was very intense in the normal human liver tissues (A5), but was weakened in the tissue of HCC at stage I to III tissues. (A6&#x02013;8). The EDN1 signal was very weak in the normal liver tissue (A9), but became intense in the tissue of HCC at stage I to III (A10&#x02013;12). The positive signal is shown in purple for miR-1 <italic>in-situ</italic> and brown for EDN1 IHC (200X). Scale bars: 50 &#x000b5;m. (B) Comparison of the expression of EDN1 and miR-1 in normal and HCC tissues. The staining intensity was scored from 0 to 4. <sub>** or ##</sub>, <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001; <sub>*** or ###</sub>, <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.0001. (C) Correlation between EDN1 and miR-1 expression in the hepatic tissue of HCC patients.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0085318.g009"/></fig><p>Using the immunohistochemistry and in-situ hybridization approaches, we further evaluated the relationship between the EDN1 protein and miR-1 RNA levels in human HCC tissues. The results showed that the expression of miR-1 was significantly higher in normal liver tissue (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g009">Fig. 9A5</xref>) than in the HCC specimens at stages I to III (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g009">Figs. 9A6&#x02013;A8</xref>). Conversely, the EDN1 protein expression was significantly lower in the normal tissue (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g009">Fig. 9A9</xref>) than in the HCC tissues (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g009">Figs. 9A10&#x02013;A12</xref>). Statistical analysis demonstrated that there was an inverse correlation between the EDN1 and miR-1 levels in the HCC tissues (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085318-g009">Figs. 9B&#x02013;C</xref>). These results suggested that up-regulation of EDN1 in HCC may be caused by a down-regulation of miR-1 in these patients.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>The development of liver cancer is a multistep process that includes inflammation, fibrosis, cirrhosis, and finally, HCC. In Asia, more than 80% of HCC cases are due to infection with HBV or HCV. In this study, a zebrafish model was used to study the molecular mechanism of hepatocarcinogenesis, and can also serve as a high-throughput drug-screening platform. Many oncogenes, such as gankyrin, HBx, YY1, KrasV12, Xmrk, and Myc, have been shown to induce steatosis or HCC in zebrafish, and the tumors induced share many similar characteristics with human tumors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Lu2">[32]</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Li1">[36]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Her1">[47]</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Shieh1">[49]</xref>. Herein, we report that the liver-specific expression of <italic>edn1</italic> causes steatosis, fibrosis, hyperplasia, and HCC in the <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic zebrafish. In addition, glycogen accumulation also was increased in these fish. The HCC formation was analyzed by histological, immunochemical and molecular biology methods, and the immunochemical data indicated an increase in proliferating cell nuclear antigen (PCNA) and active caspase 3 expression in the <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic fish at 7 to 11 months of age, which correlates with the age of hyperplasia and HCC formation.</p><p>EDN1 is a growth-promoting peptide that stimulates the proliferation of many malignant cells, such as melanoma, hepatoma, prostate, colorectal, and ovarian cancer cells. We previously have demonstrated that <italic>Edn1</italic> is significantly up-regulated in the HBx-induced HCC model in mice <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Lu1">[28]</xref>. In this study, we also detected the increase in EDN1 protein expression in breast, cerebrum, liver, and prostate tumors. Those findings indicate a role of EDN1 in the cancer development. Using HEK-293T cells, we observed that overexpression of EDN1 enhanced cell proliferation <italic>in vitro</italic> and cell migration both <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic>, and these functional changes might be triggered by the EDN1-induced expression of cell cycle-, proliferation- and migration-related genes. Moreover, the up-regulation of these target genes may be mediated by activation of the AKT signal pathway, as inferred by the reversal effects of EDN1 and AKT inhibitors. Several genes related to the UPR pathway also appeared to be the downstream targets of the EDN1/PI3K/AKT pathway. It has been reported that ER stress negatively regulates the expression of the miR-199a/214 cluster in HCC and is required for tumor survival and progression <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Duan1">[50]</xref>. Additionally, the UPR mediator ATF6-alpha was found to be involved in hepatocarcinogenesis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Arai1">[51]</xref>. Our data indicated that, EDN1 and the UPR can be linked through the AKT pathway, which is known to be involved in cell proliferation and migration, and this EDN1/AKT/UPR link might be the mechanism underlying the development of hepatocarcinogenesis in the <italic>edn1</italic> transgenic zebrafish.</p><p>miRNAs regulate gene expression by inhibiting translation or by degrading target mRNA and are involved in liver cancer progression. microRNA-1 (miR-1) inhibits cell proliferation in HCC by targeting EDN1 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Lu1">[28]</xref>. miR-1 is abnormally down-regulated in several types of cancers, including lung, colorectal, prostate, and thyroid cancers and rhabdomyosarcoma. It acts as a tumor suppressor and enables to inhibit cell proliferation and promote cell differentiation and apoptosis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085318-Lu1">[28]</xref>. In this study, we found that miR-1 was significantly down-regulated and EDN1 was up-regulated in HCC tissues. These findings indicated a potential role of miR-1 in EDN1 regulation HCC.</p><p>In conclusion, we report that the liver-specific expression of <italic>edn1</italic> induced hepatocarcinogenesis in zebrafish. The overexpression of EDN1 in HEK-293T cells enhanced cell proliferation and migration. Many genes involved in cell-cycle, migration, and the UPR pathway were up-regulated in the cells stably overexpressing EDN1. The up-regulation of these genes was reversed by EDN1 and AKT inhibitors. Finally, we are the first to report that the up-regulation of EDN1 in HCC is correlated with a down-regulation of miR-1. Notably, the correlation between EDN1 and miR-1 was observed in the tissues of HCC patients, highlighting the clinical significance of our observations. Thus, our findings provide a novel mechanism for the regulation of EDN1 in HCC, which advances our understanding on both the pleiotropic nature of the EDN1 protein and its role in HCC formation. Moreover, gene therapy using miRNA mimics may be useful for the treatment of HCC. Our zebrafish model also provides new possibilities for screening potential therapeutics to prevent the development and progression of HCC.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0085318.s001"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p><bold>Representative images from different staining methods and their scoring standards.</bold> (A) Sirius Red staining (200X), (B) TUNEL assay (200X), (C) PAS staining (200X), (D) caspase 3 staining (400X), and (E) nuclear PCNA staining (400X). Scale bar: 50 &#x000b5;m.</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0085318.s001.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0085318.s002"><label>Figure S2</label><caption><p><bold>Effects of EDN1 and AKT inhibitors on gene expression in DsRed/293T cell.</bold> RNA was isolated from the DsRed/293T cells cultured in the absence or presence of the EDN1 inhibitor Ambrisentan, the AKT inhibitor MK-2206, or with the combination of the two inhibitors. Expression of the cell cycle- and proliferation-related genes and UPR mediators were analyzed by qPCR.</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0085318.s002.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0085318.s003"><label>Table S1</label><caption><p><bold>Summary of the H&#x00026;E staining results showing the pathological changes of liver tumor progression in </bold><bold><italic>GFP-mCherry</italic></bold><bold> and </bold><bold><italic>edn1</italic></bold><bold> transgenic fish.</bold></p><p>(DOC)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0085318.s003.doc"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0085318-ElSerag1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>El-Serag</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Hepatocellular carcinoma: an epidemiologic view</article-title>. <source>J Clin Gastroenterol</source><volume>35</volume>: <fpage>S72</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>78</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12394209</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085318-ElSerag2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>El-Serag</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rudolph</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Hepatocellular carcinoma: epidemiology and molecular carcinogenesis</article-title>. <source>Gastroenterology</source><volume>132</volume>: <fpage>2557</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2576</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17570226</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085318-Marrero1"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Marrero</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Marrero</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Viral hepatitis and hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Arch Med Res</source><volume>38</volume>: <fpage>612</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>620</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17613352</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085318-McGlynn1"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>McGlynn</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>London</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Epidemiology and natural history of hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Best Pract Res Clin Gastroenterol</source><volume>19</volume>: <fpage>3</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15757802</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085318-Morgan1"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mandayam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jamal</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Alcohol and hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Gastroenterology</source><volume>127</volume>: <fpage>S87</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15508108</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085318-Seeff1"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Seeff</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hoofnagle</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Epidemiology of hepatocellular carcinoma in areas of low hepatitis B and hepatitis C endemicity</article-title>. <source>Oncogene</source><volume>25</volume>: <fpage>3771</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3777</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16799618</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085318-Jain1"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Singhal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Molecular genetics of hepatocellular neoplasia</article-title>. <source>Am J Transl Res</source><volume>2</volume>: <fpage>105</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>118</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20182587</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085318-Lin1"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>Role of surgery in the treatment of primary carcinoma of the liver: a 31-year experience</article-title>. <source>Br J Surg</source><volume>74</volume>: <fpage>839</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>842</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2822201</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085318-Bosch1"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bosch</surname><given-names>FX</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ribes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Borras</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Epidemiology of primary liver cancer</article-title>. <source>Semin Liver Dis</source><volume>19</volume>: <fpage>271</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>285</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10518307</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085318-Kim1"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Koike</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Miyamura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jay</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>HBx gene of hepatitis B virus induces liver cancer in transgenic mice</article-title>. <source>Nature</source><volume>351</volume>: <fpage>317</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>320</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2034275</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085318-vanMalenstein1"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>van Malenstein</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Verslype</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Windmolders</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>van Eijsden</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nevens</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Characterization of a cell culture model for clinically aggressive hepatocellular carcinoma induced by chronic hypoxia</article-title>. <source>Cancer Lett</source><volume>315</volume>: <fpage>178</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>188</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22088439</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085318-Pfab1"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pfab</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stoltenburg-Didinger</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Trautner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Godes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The endothelin system in Morris hepatoma-7777: an endothelin receptor antagonist inhibits growth in vitro and in vivo</article-title>. <source>Br J Pharmacol</source><volume>141</volume>: <fpage>215</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>222</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14662722</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085318-Yanagisawa1"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yanagisawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kurihara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tomobe</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>A novel potent vasoconstrictor peptide produced by vascular endothelial cells</article-title>. <source>Nature</source><volume>332</volume>: <fpage>411</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>415</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2451132</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085318-Komuro1"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Komuro</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kurihara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sugiyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yoshizumi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Takaku</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>Endothelin stimulates c-fos and c-myc expression and proliferation of vascular smooth muscle cells</article-title>. <source>FEBS Lett</source><volume>238</volume>: <fpage>249</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>252</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3139457</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085318-Pedram1"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pedram</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Razandi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Vasoactive peptides modulate vascular endothelial cell growth factor production and endothelial cell proliferation and invasion</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>272</volume>: <fpage>17097</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>17103</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9202027</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085318-Matsuura1"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Matsuura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yamochi</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hirata</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kawashima</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yokoyama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Stimulatory interaction between vascular endothelial growth factor and endothelin-1 on each gene expression</article-title>. <source>Hypertension</source><volume>32</volume>: <fpage>89</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>95</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9674643</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085318-Rosano1"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rosano</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Varmi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Salani</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Di Castro</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Spinella</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Endothelin-1 induces tumor proteinase activation and invasiveness of ovarian carcinoma cells</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source><volume>61</volume>: <fpage>8340</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8346</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11719468</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085318-Zhao1"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Endothelin-1 promotes osteosarcoma cell invasion and survival against cisplatin-induced apoptosis</article-title>. <source>Clin Orthop Relat Res</source><volume>469</volume>: <fpage>3190</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3199</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21656314</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085318-Ali1"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Loizidou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dashwood</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Savage</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sheard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Stimulation of colorectal cancer cell line growth by ET-1 and its inhibition by ET(A) antagonists</article-title>. <source>Gut</source><volume>47</volume>: <fpage>685</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>688</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11034585</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085318-Kojima1"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kojima</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nihei</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Expression of endothelin-1 immunoreactivity in breast cancer</article-title>. <source>Surg Oncol</source><volume>4</volume>: <fpage>309</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>315</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8809953</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085318-Nelson1"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hedican</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>George</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reddi</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Piantadosi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Identification of endothelin-1 in the pathophysiology of metastatic adenocarcinoma of the prostate</article-title>. <source>Nat Med</source><volume>1</volume>: <fpage>944</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>949</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7585222</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085318-Nakamuta1"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nakamuta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ohashi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tabata</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tanabe</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>High plasma concentrations of endothelin-like immunoreactivities in patients with hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Am J Gastroenterol</source><volume>88</volume>: <fpage>248</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>252</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8380950</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085318-Oikawa1"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Oikawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kushuhara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ishikawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hitomi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kono</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Production of endothelin-1 and thrombomodulin by human pancreatic cancer cells</article-title>. <source>Br J Cancer</source><volume>69</volume>: <fpage>1059</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1064</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8198971</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085318-Asham1"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Asham</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shankar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Loizidou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fredericks</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Increased endothelin-1 in colorectal cancer and reduction of tumour growth by ET(A) receptor antagonism</article-title>. <source>Br J Cancer</source><volume>85</volume>: <fpage>1759</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1763</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11742499</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085318-Grant1"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Knowles</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dawas</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Burnstock</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Mechanisms of endothelin 1-stimulated proliferation in colorectal cancer cell lines</article-title>. <source>Br J Surg</source><volume>94</volume>: <fpage>106</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>112</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17078114</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085318-Kar1"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yousem</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carr</surname><given-names>BI</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Endothelin-1 expression by human hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><volume>216</volume>: <fpage>514</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>519</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7488141</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085318-Ishibashi1"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ishibashi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nagai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kako</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Furue</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Production and secretion of endothelin by hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title>. <source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source><volume>76</volume>: <fpage>378</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>383</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7679399</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085318-Lu1"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hsia</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>YI</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Identification of the common regulators for hepatocellular carcinoma induced by hepatitis B virus X antigen in a mouse model</article-title>. <source>Carcinogenesis</source><volume>33</volume>: <fpage>209</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>219</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22021908</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085318-Datta1"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Datta</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kutay</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nasser</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nuovo</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Methylation mediated silencing of MicroRNA-1 gene and its role in hepatocellular carcinogenesis</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source><volume>68</volume>: <fpage>5049</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5058</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18593903</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085318-Lam1"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vega</surname><given-names>VB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Spitsbergen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Conservation of gene expression signatures between zebrafish and human liver tumors and tumor progression</article-title>. <source>Nat Biotechnol</source><volume>24</volume>: <fpage>73</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>75</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16327811</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085318-Lieschke1"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lieschke</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Currie</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Animal models of human disease: zebrafish swim into view</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Genet</source><volume>8</volume>: <fpage>353</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>367</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17440532</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085318-Lu2"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Liver-Specific Expressions of HBx and src in the p53 Mutant Trigger Hepatocarcinogenesis in Zebrafish</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source><volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e76951</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24130815</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085318-Liu1"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>A zebrafish model of intrahepatic cholangiocarcinoma by dual expression of hepatitis B virus X and hepatitis C virus core protein in liver</article-title>. <source>Hepatology</source><volume>56</volume>: <fpage>2268</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2276</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22729936</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085318-Nguyen1"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Emelyanov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Koh</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Spitsbergen</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>A high level of liver-specific expression of oncogenic Kras(V12) drives robust liver tumorigenesis in transgenic zebrafish</article-title>. <source>Dis Model Mech</source><volume>4</volume>: <fpage>801</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>813</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21729876</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085318-Nguyen2"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Emelyanov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Koh</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Spitsbergen</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Parinov</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>An inducible kras(V12) transgenic zebrafish model for liver tumorigenesis and chemical drug screening</article-title>. <source>Dis Model Mech</source><volume>5</volume>: <fpage>63</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21903676</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085318-Li1"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>A transgenic zebrafish liver tumor model with inducible Myc expression reveals conserved Myc signatures with mammalian liver tumors</article-title>. <source>Dis Model Mech</source><volume>6</volume>: <fpage>414</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>423</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23038063</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085318-Tseng1"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tseng</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yuh</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>An evolutionarily conserved kernel of gata5, gata6, otx2 and prdm1a operates in the formation of endoderm in zebrafish</article-title>. <source>Dev Biol</source><volume>357</volume>: <fpage>541</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>557</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21756893</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085318-Kwan1"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kwan</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fujimoto</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Grabher</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mangum</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hardy</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The Tol2kit: a multisite gateway-based construction kit for Tol2 transposon transgenesis constructs</article-title>. <source>Dev Dyn</source><volume>236</volume>: <fpage>3088</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3099</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17937395</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085318-Zhu1"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Perez-Atayde</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Activated ALK collaborates with MYCN in neuroblastoma pathogenesis</article-title>. <source>Cancer Cell</source><volume>21</volume>: <fpage>362</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>373</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22439933</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085318-Lu3"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yeh</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Clinical implications of deregulated CDK4 and Cyclin D1 expression in patients with human hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Med Oncol</source><volume>30</volume>: <fpage>379</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23292829</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085318-Boorman1"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Boorman</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Botts</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bunton</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fournie</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Harshbarger</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Diagnostic criteria for degenerative, inflammatory, proliferative nonneoplastic and neoplastic liver lesions in medaka (Oryzias latipes): consensus of a National Toxicology Program Pathology Working Group</article-title>. <source>Toxicol Pathol</source><volume>25</volume>: <fpage>202</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>210</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9125779</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085318-Hobbie1"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hobbie</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>DeAngelo</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>George</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Law</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Neoplastic and nonneoplastic liver lesions induced by dimethylnitrosamine in Japanese medaka fish</article-title>. <source>Vet Pathol</source><volume>49</volume>: <fpage>372</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>385</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21724976</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085318-Lu4"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yuh</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Hepatitis B virus X antigen and aflatoxin B1 synergistically cause hepatitis, steatosis and liver hyperplasia in transgenic zebrafish</article-title>. <source>Acta Histochem</source><volume>115</volume>: <fpage>728</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>739</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23499292</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085318-Shen1"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Miao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The tumorigenicity diversification in human embryonic kidney 293 cell line cultured in vitro</article-title>. <source>Biologicals</source><volume>36</volume>: <fpage>263</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>268</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18378163</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085318-Kulasekaran1"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kulasekaran</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Scavone</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Arenberg</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thannickal</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Endothelin-1 and transforming growth factor-beta1 independently induce fibroblast resistance to apoptosis via AKT activation</article-title>. <source>Am J Respir Cell Mol Biol</source><volume>41</volume>: <fpage>484</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>493</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19188658</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085318-Wu1"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kuo</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Endothelin-1 promotes MMP-13 production and migration in human chondrosarcoma cells through FAK/PI3K/Akt/mTOR pathways</article-title>. <source>J Cell Physiol</source><volume>227</volume>: <fpage>3016</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3026</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21959927</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085318-Her1"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Her</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pai</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>YW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pang</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Ubiquitous transcription factor YY1 promotes zebrafish liver steatosis and lipotoxicity by inhibiting CHOP-10 expression</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><volume>1831</volume>: <fpage>1037</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1051</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23416188</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085318-Her2"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Her</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Overexpression of gankyrin induces liver steatosis in zebrafish (Danio rerio)</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><volume>1811</volume>: <fpage>536</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>548</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21722753</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085318-Shieh1"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shieh</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jou</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Increase of hepatic fat accumulation by liver specific expression of Hepatitis B virus X protein in zebrafish</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><volume>1801</volume>: <fpage>721</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>730</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20416398</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085318-Duan1"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>ER stress negatively modulates the expression of the miR-199a/214 cluster to regulates tumor survival and progression in human hepatocellular cancer</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source><volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e31518</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22359598</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085318-Arai1"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Arai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kondoh</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Imazeki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hada</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hatsuse</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Transformation-associated gene regulation by ATF6alpha during hepatocarcinogenesis</article-title>. <source>FEBS Lett</source><volume>580</volume>: <fpage>184</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>190</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16364319</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>