<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26372549</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4570783</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0137427</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-15-16484</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Effect of Carotene and Lycopene on the Risk of Prostate Cancer: A Systematic Review and Dose-Response Meta-Analysis of Observational Studies</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">&#x003b1;-Carotene and Lycopene Intake Can Reduce Prostate Cancer Risk</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Yulan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>Ran</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>Yuanyuan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>Juemin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Qing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff001"><label>1</label><addr-line>Department of Clinical Laboratory, Shanghai Tenth People's Hospital, Tongji University, School of Medicine, No.301 Middle Yanchang Road, Zhabei District, Shanghai 200072, China</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff002"><label>2</label><addr-line>Department of Oncology, Shanghai Tenth People's Hospital, Tongji University, School of Medicine, No.301 Middle Yanchang Road, Zhabei District, Shanghai 200072, China</addr-line></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>Bart O.</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Van Andel Institute, UNITED STATES</addr-line></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: YLW RC YYX JMF QX. Performed the experiments: YLW RC. Analyzed the data: YLW RC YYX JMF QX. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: YLW RC YYX JMF. Wrote the paper: YLW RC.</p></fn><corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>18221078212@163.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>9</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue>9</issue><elocation-id>e0137427</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>4</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>17</day><month>8</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Wang et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="pone.0137427.pdf"/><abstract><sec id="sec001"><title>Background</title><p>Many epidemiologic studies have investigated the association between carotenoids intake and risk of Prostate cancer (PCa). However, results have been inconclusive.</p></sec><sec id="sec002"><title>Methods</title><p>We conducted a systematic review and dose-response meta-analysis of dietary intake or blood concentrations of carotenoids in relation to PCa risk. We summarized the data from 34 eligible studies (10 cohort, 11 nested case-control and 13 case-control studies) and estimated summary Risk Ratios (RRs) and 95% confidence intervals (CIs) using random-effects models.</p></sec><sec id="sec003"><title>Results</title><p>Neither dietary &#x003b2;-carotene intake nor its blood levels was associated with reduced PCa risk. Dietary &#x003b1;-carotene intake and lycopene consumption (both dietary intake and its blood levels) were all associated with reduced risk of PCa (RR for dietary &#x003b1;-carotene intake: 0.87, 95%CI: 0.76&#x02013;0.99; RR for dietary lycopene intake: 0.86, 95%CI: 0.75&#x02013;0.98; RR for blood lycopene levels: 0.81, 95%CI: 0.69&#x02013;0.96). However, neither blood &#x003b1;-carotene levels nor blood lycopene levels could reduce the risk of advanced PCa. Dose-response analysis indicated that risk of PCa was reduced by 2% per 0.2mg/day (95%CI: 0.96&#x02013;0.99) increment of dietary &#x003b1;-carotene intake or 3% per 1mg/day (95%CI: 0.94&#x02013;0.99) increment of dietary lycopene intake.</p></sec><sec id="sec004"><title>Conclusions</title><p>&#x003b1;-carotene and lycopene, but not &#x003b2;-carotene, were inversely associated with the risk of PCa. However, both &#x003b1;-carotene and lycopene could not lower the risk of advanced PCa.</p></sec></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (No.: 81372749).</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="4"/><table-count count="2"/><page-count count="20"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><title>Data Availability</title><p>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</p></notes></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec005"><title>Introduction</title><p>PCa is the second most abundant male cancer [<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Owing to the improved screening and early detection procedures, rising incidence rates of PCa have been observed over the last few decades [<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. However, the success in treating advanced PCa remains poor, drawing attention to dietary factors that may influence risk of this malignancy, particularly carotenoids [<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Lots of epidemiological factors, including age, gender, ethnicity, genetic factors, family history, lifestyle, region and diet, have been considered to be associated with the development of PCa [<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. For example, Asian populations are generally at lower PCa risk compared with the Western populations [<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Moreover, the average annual incidence rate of PCa between 1988 and 1992 among Chinese men in the United States was 15 times higher than that of their counterparts living in Shanghai and Tianjin [<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], specially, the change of diet and lifestyle inevitably resulted in the increased prevalence of obesity in East Asia [<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], which might be responsible for increasing trend of PCa in East Asia&#x02014;all of which suggest that variations in lifestyle and diet may play a crucial role in PCa. Among a large number of components of foods, carotenoids, especially its main active ingredients&#x02014;carotene and lycopene, have received special attention due to its promising antioxidative properties [<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].</p><p>Carotenoids, which include &#x003b1;-carotene, &#x003b2;-carotene, lycopene, &#x003b2;-cryptoxanthin, lutein, and zeaxanthin that represent the major carotenoids in the human diet [<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], provide the yellow, orange and red pigments in fruits and vegetables [<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Carotenoids have distinct antioxidative properties, including protecting DNA and other important biomolecules from free radicals [<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. In 1981, Peto et al. hypothesized that dietary &#x003b2;-carotene from fruit and vegetables may reduce human cancer incidence rates [<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], since then a flurry of epidemiologic studies had addressed this topic [<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Carotenes(including &#x003b1;-carotene and &#x003b2;-carotene) have been investigated for many years now, but whether carotenes are related to the PCa are still mostly inconsistent. Lycopene is one of the most effective oxygen radical quenching agents among the carotenoids [<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], which is found in relatively high concentrations in the prostate gland [<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. The results of epidemiological studies have generally supported a protective effect on cancer of carotenoid-rich foods. According to the latest Continuous Update Project(CUP) report summarized by the World Cancer Research Fund(WCRF) in November 2014, there is limited evidence for the effect of lycopene on PCa risk [<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. In contrast, substantial intake of &#x003b2;-carotene is unlikely to have any effect on the PCa risk. These inconsistencies could be mainly due to confounding by nutritional as well as non-nutritional factors and lack of validity of carotenoids estimates due to inaccurate dietary or blood concentration assessment.</p><p>Based on these inconsistencies, we conducted this meta-analysis on all published epidemiologic studies to date to reevaluate and quantify the relation between dietary intake or blood concentrations of &#x003b1;-carotene, &#x003b2;-carotene, lycopene and risk of PCa.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec006"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="sec007"><title>Literature search</title><p>This meta-analysis was conducted in accordance with PRISMA guidelines(<xref rid="pone.0137427.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 PRISMA Checklist</xref>). We conducted a comprehensive literature search of PubMed (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed</ext-link>) and Embase (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.elsevier.com/online-tools/embase">http://www.elsevier.com/online-tools/embase</ext-link>) (up to January 2015) using the key words: carotenoids, carotene, lycopene, prostate cancer, case-control study, cohort study and text terms: micronutrients. Bibliographies from retrieved articles were also scoured to find further eligible studies.</p></sec><sec id="sec008"><title>Study selection</title><p>Our objective was to thoroughly evaluate the relation between dietary intake or blood concentrations of &#x003b1;-carotene, &#x003b2;-carotene, lycopene and risk of PCa. Studies that met the following criteria were included in the meta-analysis: <italic>1</italic>) used epidemiologic investigation design: case-control study, nested case-control study, cohort study, etc; <italic>2</italic>) evaluated the association between carotene(&#x003b1;- and/or &#x003b2;-), lycopene and PCa risk; and <italic>3</italic>) provided RRs with 95% CIs for &#x02265;3 exposure categories. Furthermore, studies that additionally provided the doses of carotenoids, the number of cases, and the number of controls(or person-years) in each of exposure categories were included in the dose-response meta-analysis.</p></sec><sec id="sec009"><title>Data extraction and statistical analysis</title><p>The following information was extracted from each study: name of the first author, year of publication, location of study, study period, study type, age of the study population at baseline, number of cases/controls/total participants, year of follow-up, range of exposure(dietary intake or blood levels) and adjustment for covariates. Independent data extraction was performed by two authors(YL W and RC). Any discrepancies were resolved through discussing with the third reviewer(QX).</p><p>Given the fact that the quality of the included studies evaluating these relations, especially in terms of statistical power and the rigor with which the dietary data were collected, varied considerably, we conducted a quality assessment on preliminarily included studies, by using the 9-star Newcastle-Ottawa Scale (NOS) [<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], which is a validated scale for non-randomized studies in a meta-analysis. This scale includes three aspects of evaluation: the selection of the cohorts, comparability of cohorts, and ascertainment of the exposure and outcome of interest. We regarded scores of 1&#x02013;3, 4&#x02013;6, and 7&#x02013;9 as low, moderate, and high quality, respectively.</p><p>A random-effect model was utilized to consider both within-study and between-study variations in RR estimates [<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. As different studies might report different exposure categories, such as dichotomous, thirds, quarters, or fifths, we used the study specific RR for the highest versus lowest category of dietary carotenoids intake(mg/day) or carotenoids concentration(ug/dl) exposure for the meta-analysis. Cochran Q test and I<sup>2</sup> statistic were used to assess the heterogeneity [<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. We also performed sensitivity analyses to evaluate whether the pooled results could have been markedly affected by sequentially exclude a single study at a time. Subgroup analyses were performed for study type, regions, covariate adjustment.</p><p>For the meta-analysis of the dose-response relationship between carotenoids and PCa risk, the method of generalized least squares for trend estimation proposed by Greenland and Longnecker and Orsini et al [<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0137427.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], was performed using restricted cubic splines with 3 knots at percentiles 33%, 66%, and 99% of the distribution. A <italic>P</italic> value for curvelinearity or nonlinearity was calculated by testing the null hypothesis that the coefficient of the second spline was equal to zero. We used the Stata 12(Stata Corp., College Station, Texas) to perform all statistical tests. <italic>p</italic>&#x0003c;0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec010"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec011"><title>Literature search</title><p>The initial screening yielded 206 publications. After selection, a total of 34 studies (1 article [<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] reported results from two subcohorts) from 33 publications [<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0137427.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>] were included in the meta-analysis. Among these studies, twelve, nineteen and thirteen studies reported the effects of dietary intake of &#x003b1;-carotene, &#x003b2;-carotene, lycopene on PCa risk, respectively. Eleven, thirteen and fifteen studies reported the effects of blood levels of &#x003b1;-carotene, &#x003b2;-carotene, lycopene on PCa risk, respectively(<xref rid="pone.0137427.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>).</p><fig id="pone.0137427.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0137427.g001</object-id><label>Fig 1</label><caption><title>The literature search process.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0137427.g001"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec012"><title>Study characteristics</title><p>Among these 34 studies, 10 studies were cohort studies (two studies were case-cohort studies), 11 studies were nested case-control studies, and 13 studies were case-control studies(<xref rid="pone.0137427.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="pone.0137427.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0137427.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Characteristics of included studies.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0137427.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0137427.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Source, y</th><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Location</th><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study Period</th><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study Type</th><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, y(SD)</th><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No.of Cases</th><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No.of Matched Controls</th><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No.of Participants</th><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Follow-up,y</th><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Range of Exposure:blood(ug/dl);intake(mg/day)</th><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adjustment for Covariates</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Karppi,2009</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Finland</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1993&#x02013;2006</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.2</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">997</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.6</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Serum lycopene:4.68(T1),11.11(T3)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, examination year, alcohol intake, FHPC, physical activity, waist-to-hip ratio, education, smoking, and serum folate.</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shibata,1992</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1981&#x02013;1989</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65&#x02013;85</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,335</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,580</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;8</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intake &#x003b1;-carotene:1.8(T1),8.6(T3)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age and smoking.</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Giovannucci,1995</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1986&#x02013;1992</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40&#x02013;75</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">812</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47,894</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intake &#x003b1;-carotene:0.243(Q1),0.221(Q4);&#x003b2;-carotene:2.1(Q1),10.8(Q4);lycopene:1.5(Q1),10.1(Q4)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age and energy.</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ambrosini,2008</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Australia</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1990&#x02013;2004</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cases:59.2&#x02013;66.2<xref rid="t001fn003" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref> Controls:47.5&#x02013;62.5<xref rid="t001fn003" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,183</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intake &#x003b2;-carotene:1.8(T1),4.6(Q4)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, fruit and vegetable intake, retinol/&#x003b2;-carotene supplement and crocidolite exposure.</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kirsh,2006</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1993&#x02013;2001</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55&#x02013;74</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,338</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29,361</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intake &#x003b1;-carotene:0.47(Q1),2.32(Q5);lycopene:5.05(Q1),15.6(Q5)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, energy, race, study center, FHPC,BMI, smoking, physical activity, fat/red meat intake,history of diabetes, and aspirin use.</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Umesawa,2013</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Japan</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1988&#x02013;1990</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40&#x02013;79</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">143</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15,471</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intake &#x003b1;-carotene:0.11(Q1),0.50(Q5);&#x003b2;-carotene:0.1(Q1),3.72(Q5)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Saturated fat/isoflavone/&#x003b1;-tocopherol intake.</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Daviglus,1996</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1959&#x02013;1989</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40&#x02013;55</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">132</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,899</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intake &#x003b2;-carotene:2.3(Q1),4.0(Q4)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, smoking, cholesteroal/saturated fat/ethanol intake, energy, and occupation.</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Roswall,2013</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Denmark</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1993&#x02013;1997</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50&#x02013;64</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,571</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26,856</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intake &#x003b2;-carotene:1.6(Q1),4.71(Q4)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Height, weight, education, red meat/alcohol/selenium intake.</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Schuurman,2002</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Netherlands</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1986&#x02013;1992</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case-Cohort</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55&#x02013;70</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">642</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,525</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58,279</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR(intake)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, FHPC, socioeconomic status, and alcohol intake.</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Agalliu,2001</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2003&#x02013;2010</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case-Cohort</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cases:66.2(8.4) Subcohort:69.3(10.5)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">661</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,864</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34,291</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intake &#x003b2;-carotene:2.26(Q1),10.77(Q5);lycopene:2.45(Q1),15.87(Q5)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, race, BMI, physical activity, and education.</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Key,2007</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European Countries</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1992&#x02013;2000</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NCCS</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cases:60.4(5.8) Controls:60.1(5.8)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">966</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,064</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">137,001</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plasma &#x003b1;-carotene:2.59(Q1),10.51(Q5);&#x003b2;-carotene:8.21(Q1),27.28(Q5);lycopene:15.04(Q1),49.37(Q5)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, fasting hours prior to blood draw, BMI,FHPC, and education.</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Huang,2002</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CLUE<xref rid="t001fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref> I:1974&#x02013;1996;CLUE II:1989&#x02013;1996</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NCCS</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CLUE I:Cases:54 (9) Controls:54 (9) CLUE II: Cases:66 (8) Controls:66 (9)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CLUE I:182;CLUE II:142</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CLUE I 364 CLUE II 284</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CLUE I:9,804 CLUE II:10,456</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CLUE I:17 CLUE II:3.5</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CLUE I:Serum &#x003b1;-carotene:1.4(Q1),3.9(Q5);&#x003b2;-carotene:4.4(Q1),15.6(Q5);lycopene:21.7(Q1),54.9(Q5) CLUE II:Serum &#x003b1;-carotene:1.2(Q1),5.5(Q5);&#x003b2;-carotene:4.2(Q1),15.8(Q5);lycopene:24.3(Q1),62.8(Q5)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, number of years since blood was drawn, disease stage at diagnosis, smoking, and BMI.</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Goodman,2003</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1983&#x02013;1997</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NCCS</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45&#x02013;75</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">205</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">205</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18,314</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;10</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Serum &#x003b1;-carotene:1.8(Q1),4.3(Q4);&#x003b2;-carotene:9.4(Q1),21.9(Q4);lycopene:22.9(Q1),41.7(Q4)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, study center at randomization, sex, smoking, and year of randomization.</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gann,1999</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1982&#x02013;1995</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NCCS</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40&#x02013;85</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">578</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,294</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22,071</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plasma &#x003b1;-carotene:3.46(Q1),10.33(Q4);lycopene:26.17(Q1),58.01(Q4)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Physical activity, BMI, plasma total cholesterol, alcohol intake, and multivitamin supplement use.</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nomura,1997</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1971&#x02013;1975</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NCCS</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52&#x02013;75</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">142</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">142</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,860</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;20</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR(intake)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beilby,2010</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Australia</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Since 1990</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NCCS</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cases:69.8(7.2) Controls:69.3(6.7)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">226</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,890</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;10</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Serum &#x003b2;-carotene:0.11(T1),1.16(T3);lycopene:0.05(T1),0.43(T3)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, and vitamin A supplement.</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peters,2007</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1993&#x02013;2001</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NCCS</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55&#x02013;75</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">692</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">844</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28,243</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Serum &#x003b1;-carotene:2.6(Q1),16.6(Q5);&#x003b2;-carotene:6.1(Q1),38.7(Q5);lycopene:30.5(Q1),108.4(Q5)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, time since initial screening, year of blood draw, and study center.</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wu,2004</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1993&#x02013;1998</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NCCS</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40&#x02013;75</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">450</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">450</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18,259</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;5</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR(blood)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cholesterol levels, selenium/Vitamin E supplementation, FHPC, BMI, height, physical activity, history of vasectomy and current smoking.</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gill,2009</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1993&#x02013;1996</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NCCS</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45&#x02013;75</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">467</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">936</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96,382</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;3</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Serum &#x003b2;-carotene:9.8(Q1),59.7(Q4);lycopene:22.0(Q1),65.6(Q4)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, fasting hours prior to blood draw, BMI, FHPC, and education.</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hsing,1990</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1974&#x02013;1986</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NCCS</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47&#x02013;91</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">103</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">103</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR(blood)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, race, smoking, education, time of last meal.</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Andersson,1996</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sweden</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1989&#x02013;1994</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;81</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">526</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">536</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,062</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR(intake)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age and energy.</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Norrish,1998</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">New Zealand</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1996&#x02013;1997</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40&#x02013;81</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">317</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">480</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">797</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intake &#x003b2;-carotene:2.5(Q1),6.1(Q4);lycopene:0.7(Q1),2.0(Q4)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, height, NSAIDs, and socioeconomlc status.</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bosetti,2004</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Italy</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1991&#x02013;2002</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46&#x02013;75</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,294</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,451</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,745</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR(intake)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, study center, education, physical activity, BMI,FHPC and energy.</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mettlin,1989</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Since 1987</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55&#x02013;86</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">371</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">371</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">742</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR(intake)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zhang,2007</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1998&#x02013;2003</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cases:64.4(9.0) Controls:59.4(10.5)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">193</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">197</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">390</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plasma &#x003b1;-carotene:0.71(Q1),6.08(Q4);&#x003b2;-carotene:3.47(Q1),28.35(Q4);lycopene:14.05(Q1),51.37(Q4)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, race, BMI, education, and smoking.</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jian,2005</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2001&#x02013;2002</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cases:72.7(7.1) Controls:71.4(7.2)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">130</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">274</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">404</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intake &#x003b1;-carotene:0.24(Q1),1.79(Q4);&#x003b2;-carotene:1.96(Q1),7.49(Q4);lycopene:1.61(Q1),4.92(Q4)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, locality, education, family income, marital status, number of children, FHPC, BMI, tea drinking, energy, fat intake.</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chang,2005</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1996&#x02013;1998</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cases:63.9(7.0) Controls:62.8(6.6)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">118</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">170</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR(blood)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, smoking, and height.</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">McCann,2009</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1986&#x02013;1991</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">433</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">538</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">971</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intake &#x003b1;-carotene:0.63(Q1),1.5(Q4);&#x003b2;-carotene:3.8(Q1),8.04(Q4);lycopene:3.9(Q1),8.86(Q4)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, education, BMI, smoking, and energy.</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Meyer,1997</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1990&#x02013;1993</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;45</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">215</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">593</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">808</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR(intake)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, education, FHPC, energy.</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jain, 1999</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1989&#x02013;1993</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cases:69.8 Controls:69.9</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">617</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">636</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,253</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intake &#x003b1;-carotene:0.84(Q1),2.16(Q4);&#x003b2;-carotene:3.0(Q1),7.83(Q4);lycopene:2.1(Q1),12.67(Q4)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, energy, vasectomy, smoking, marital status, study area, BMI, vitamin use, diet.</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Deneo-Pelligrini,1999</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uruguay</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1994&#x02013;1997</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40&#x02013;89</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">175</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">240</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">415</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intake &#x003b1;-carotene:0.11(Q1),0.60(Q4);&#x003b2;-carotene:2.71(Q1),7.49(Q4);lycopene:1.3(Q1),3.3(Q4)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, residence, education, FHPC, BMI, energy.</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohen,2000</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1993&#x02013;1996</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40&#x02013;64</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">628</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">602</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,230</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intake &#x003b1;-carotene:0.33(Q1),0.81(Q4);&#x003b2;-carotene:2.2(Q1),4.4(Q4);lycopene:4.9(Q1),9.9(Q4)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, race, fat intake, energy, FHPC, BMI, antigen tests, education.</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lu,2001</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1993&#x02013;1997</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cases:59.98(6.19) Controls:41.9(13.64)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">130</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">195</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intake &#x003b1;-carotene:0.39(Q1),1.14(Q4);&#x003b2;-carotene:2.38(Q1),5.85(Q4);lycopene:1.46(Q1),3.45(Q4) Plasma &#x003b1;-carotene:2.02(Q1),5.85(Q4);&#x003b2;-carotene:7.25(Q1),19.9(Q4);lycopene:10.45(Q1),23.39(Q4)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, race, smoking, education, FHPC, alcohol intake, energy.</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t001fn001"><p>Abbreviations: NCCS, nested case-control study; CCS, case-control study; SD, standard deviation; T, tertile; Q, quartile/quintile; BMI, body mass index; NSAIDs, non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs; FHPC, family history of prostate cancer; NR, not reported; NA, not accessible.</p></fn><fn id="t001fn002"><p><sup>a</sup>Derived from the slogan of a campaign, &#x0201c;Give us a CLUE to cancer.&#x0201d;</p></fn><fn id="t001fn003"><p><sup>b</sup>Indicated interquartile range(IQR).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>They involved a total of 15,891 cases and 592,479 participants. Twenty two studies were from the North America, 7 studies were from the Europe, 2 studies were from Australia, 2 study were from the Asian countries, and 1 study was from Uruguay. With respect to the dietary intake of carotenoids, 12 studies studied on &#x003b1;-carotene, 19 studies studied on &#x003b2;-carotene, and 13 studies studied on lycopene. With respect to the blood levels of carotenoids, 11 studies studied on &#x003b1;-carotene, 13 studies studied on &#x003b2;-carotene, 15 studies studied on lycopene. All these included observational studies utilized structured food frequency questionnaire to collect participants&#x02019; information on usual food consumption.</p><p>Most studies provided risk estimates that were adjusted for age (29 studies); few adjusted for smoking(14 studies), body mass index(BMI)(15 studies), family history of PCa(FHPC)(12 studies), energy intake(12 studies), alcohol intake(3 studies), physical activity (6 studies) and education(14 studies). All studies but nine studies [<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0137427.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0137427.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0137427.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0137427.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0137427.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0137427.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0137427.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0137427.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>] provided ranges of exposure in each of exposure categories. The mean NOS score was 7.6 stars (range, 4&#x02013;9 stars; <xref rid="pone.0137427.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Table</xref>), suggesting that the study quality was fair.</p></sec><sec id="sec013"><title>Dietary intake of &#x003b1;-carotene, &#x003b2;-carotene, lycopene and PCa risk</title><p>A significant inverse association was observed between dietary &#x003b1;-carotene intake and PCa(RR:0.81; 95% CI:0.76&#x02013;0.99)(<xref rid="pone.0137427.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>, left). No significant statistical difference was observed between dietary &#x003b2;-carotene and PCa risk(RR:0.90; 95% CI:0.81&#x02013;1.01). Exclusion of any individual study regarding the dietary intake of &#x003b2;-carotene did not change the pooled results substantially. No significant statistical difference was observed in dietary lycopene intake, with a RR of 0.88(95% CI: 0.76&#x02013;1.02; I<sup>2</sup> = 23.61%). However, sensitivity analysis further showed that when omitting the study conducted by Jian et al., which has a wide variation in confidence intervals and deviatesfrom the pooled trend, the results did change appreciably(RR:0.91; 95% CI:0.83&#x02013;1.00) and the heterogeneity among the remaining studies decreased to 0%. Therefore, dietary lycopene intake was inversely associated with the risk of PCa.</p><fig id="pone.0137427.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0137427.g002</object-id><label>Fig 2</label><caption><title>Pooled risks according to dietary carotenoids intake and its blood levels.</title><p>Dietary intake of &#x003b1;-carotene, &#x003b2;-carotene, lycopene and PCa risk(left), blood levels of &#x003b1;-carotene, &#x003b2;-carotene, lycopene and PCa risk(right).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0137427.g002"/></fig><p>We next explored the risk analyses stratified according to the study type, region and covariate adjustments to examine sources of study heterogeneity and the influence of potential residual confounding factors, such as age, BMI, FHPC, education, smoking, etc(<xref rid="pone.0137427.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="pone.0137427.t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0137427.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Subgroup analysis regarding the association between carotenoids consumption and PCa risk.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0137427.t002g" xlink:href="pone.0137427.t002"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subgroup<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></th><th colspan="9" align="center" rowspan="1">Dietary intake(mg/day)</th><th colspan="9" align="center" rowspan="1">Blood levels(ug/dl)</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">&#x003b1;-carotene</th><th colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">&#x003b2;-carotene</th><th colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">lycopene</th><th colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">&#x003b1;-carotene</th><th colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">&#x003b2;-carotene</th><th colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">lycopene</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of studies</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Risk ratio(95%CI)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of studies</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Risk ratio(95%CI)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of Studies</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Risk ratio(95%CI)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of studies</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Risk ratio(95%CI)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of studies</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Risk ratio(95%CI)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of Studies</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Risk ratio(95%CI)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87(0.76&#x02013;0.99)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90(0.81&#x02013;1.01)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88(0.76&#x02013;1.02)<xref rid="t002fn003" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>#</sup></xref></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.083<xref rid="t002fn003" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>#</sup></xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91(0.72&#x02013;1.15)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96(0.81&#x02013;1.14)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81(0.69&#x02013;0.96)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.015</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study type</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort(Case-cohort)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86(0.66&#x02013;1.11)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02(0.92&#x02013;1.14)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87(0.77&#x02013;0.99)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.029</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78(0.37&#x02013;1.65)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52</td></tr><tr><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NCCS</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01(0.86&#x02013;1.19)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02(0.87&#x02013;1.19)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82(0.70&#x02013;0.97)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td></tr><tr><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86(0.74&#x02013;1.01)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80(0.68&#x02013;0.95)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87(0.67&#x02013;1.13)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51(0.18&#x02013;1.43)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62(0.40&#x02013;0.93)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69(0.29&#x02013;1.64)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regions</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asian countries</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44(0.27&#x02013;0.74)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40(0.23&#x02013;0.69)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18(0.08&#x02013;0.41)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.01</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">North America</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96(0.86&#x02013;1.08)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94(0.83&#x02013;1.08)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91(0.81&#x02013;1.01)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88(0.67&#x02013;1.12)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99(0.80&#x02013;1.24)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82(0.68&#x02013;1.00)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European countries</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80(0.64&#x02013;1.01)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93(0.80&#x02013;1.08)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89(0.73&#x02013;1.09)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2(0.87&#x02013;1.66)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87(0.66&#x02013;1.15)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75(0.49&#x02013;1.17)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td></tr><tr><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Australia</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96(0.58&#x02013;1.60)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90(0.50&#x02013;1.61)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00(0.58&#x02013;1.73)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20(0.68&#x02013;2.13)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Covariate adjustments</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adjustment for age</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90(0.80&#x02013;1.01)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90(0.80&#x02013;1.01)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88(0.76&#x02013;1.02)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95(0.71&#x02013;1.29)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92 (0.78&#x02013;1.09)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84(0.70&#x02013;1.01)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td></tr><tr><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No adjustment for age</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46(0.22&#x02013;0.97)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82(0.44&#x02013;1.54)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78(0.59&#x02013;1.02)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.54(0.90&#x02013;2.65)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73(0.50&#x02013;1.06)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td></tr><tr><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adjustment for BMI</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88(0.78&#x02013;1.00)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81(0.65&#x02013;1.01)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87(0.72&#x02013;1.05)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94(0.76&#x02013;1.17)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92(0.76&#x02013;1.11)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77(0.66&#x02013;0.91)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No adjustment for BMI</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78(0.54&#x02013;1.13)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.19</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98(0.89&#x02013;1.09)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88(0.69&#x02013;1.12)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79(0.46&#x02013;1.35)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95(0.64&#x02013;1.39)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90(0.64&#x02013;1.29)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57</td></tr><tr><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adjustment for energy</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98(0.82&#x02013;1.03)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85(0.72&#x02013;0.996)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89(0.74&#x02013;1.08)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26(0.07&#x02013;1.01)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43(0.13&#x02013;1.46)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17 (0.04&#x02013;0.75)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td></tr><tr><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No adjustment for energy</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58(0.38&#x02013;0.87)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99(0.88&#x02013;1.11)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82(0.66&#x02013;1.02)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95(0.76&#x02013;1.18)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98(0.83&#x02013;1.16)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84(0.73&#x02013;0.97)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td></tr><tr><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adjustment for education</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81(0.68&#x02013;0.96)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82(0.67&#x02013;0.995)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85(0.64&#x02013;1.14)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94(0.48&#x02013;1.84)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84(0.69&#x02013;1.03)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71(0.54&#x02013;0.94)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td></tr><tr><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No adjustment for education</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91(0.75&#x02013;1.12)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98(0.87&#x02013;1.11)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89(0.89&#x02013;1.00)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88(0.68&#x02013;1.14)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10(0.83&#x02013;1.47)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89(0.73&#x02013;1.10)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28</td></tr><tr><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adjustment for FHPC</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84(0.73&#x02013;0.95)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75 (0.59&#x02013;0.94)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89(0.67&#x02013;1.16)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75(0.39&#x02013;1.44)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87(0.70&#x02013;1.07)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.66 (0.48&#x02013;0.93)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td></tr><tr><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No adjustment for FHPC</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97(0.77&#x02013;1.22)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99(0.90&#x02013;1.09)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84(0.74&#x02013;0.97)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.014</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94(0.72&#x02013;1.23)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04(0.81&#x02013;1.34)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91(0.78&#x02013;1.08)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27</td></tr><tr><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adjustment for smoking</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94(0.81&#x02013;1.09)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99(0.81&#x02013;1.20)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95(0.82&#x02013;1.10)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78(0.53&#x02013;1.15)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91(0.68&#x02013;1.20)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73(0.56&#x02013;0.96)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No adjustment for smoking</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80(0.65&#x02013;0.98)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88(0.77&#x02013;1.00)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85(0.69&#x02013;1.05)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05(0.84&#x02013;1.32)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00(0.79&#x02013;1.26)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94(0.82&#x02013;1.08)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td></tr><tr><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adjustment for alcohol</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61(0.39&#x02013;0.97)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00(0.86&#x02013;1.17)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88(0.57&#x02013;1.36)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55(0.21&#x02013;1.47)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43(0.13&#x02013;1.46)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63(0.36&#x02013;1.12)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td></tr><tr><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No adjustment for alcohol</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90(0.79&#x02013;1.02)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89(0.78&#x02013;1.01)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88(0.75&#x02013;1.03)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98(0.77&#x02013;1.25)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98(0.83&#x02013;1.16)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85(0.72&#x02013;1.02)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td></tr><tr><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adjustment for PA</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90(0.77&#x02013;1.04)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90(0.68&#x02013;1.18)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92(0.81&#x02013;1.05)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74(0.55&#x02013;0.98)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.48(0.67&#x02013;3.28)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70(0.53&#x02013;0.93)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No adjustment for PA</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83(0.69&#x02013;1.01)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91(0.80&#x02013;1.02)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86(0.69&#x02013;1.07)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98(0.75&#x02013;1.29)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94(0.79&#x02013;1.12)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85(0.70&#x02013;1.03)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t002fn001"><p>Abbreviations: NCCS, nested case-control study; CCS, case-control study; BMI, body mass index; FHPC, family history of prostate cancer; PA, physical activity; NAM, No adjustment; CI, confidence interval.</p></fn><fn id="t002fn002"><p>*Subgroup analysis was performed in a random-effects model.</p></fn><fn id="t002fn003"><p><sup>#</sup>Exclusion of the study conducted by Jian, et al. yielded a pooled risk ratio: 0.97(95%CI:0.83&#x02013;1.00, p = 0.04) with no heterogeneity among the remaining studies(I<sup>2</sup> = 0.0%,p = 0.65).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>For dietary intake of &#x003b1;-carotene exposure, subgroup analyses indicated that the protective effect of &#x003b1;-carotene was more evident in Asian countries than in the North America or European countries. In addition, inverse association was more evident in studies that adjusted for education, FHPC, and alcohol compared with studies without such adjustments. &#x003b2;-carotene intake also exerted a protective effect on Asian populations. Overall, our stratified analyses showed that &#x003b2;-carotene intake has no association with PCa risk. For dietary intake of lycopene exposure, the inverse association between lycopene intake and PCa risk was evident in 4 cohort studies(RR:0.87; 95%CI:0.77&#x02013;0.99).</p></sec><sec id="sec014"><title>Blood levels of &#x003b1;-carotene, &#x003b2;-carotene, lycopene and PCa risk</title><p>Carotenoids concentrations, compared with dietary assessment, may provide a more accurate estimation of intake. However, pooled results showed that only blood levels of lycopene were significantly associated with reduced PCa risk(0.81, 0.69&#x02013;0.96)(<xref rid="pone.0137427.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>,right). Subgroup analyses demonstrated that neither &#x003b1;-carotene nor &#x003b2;-carotene concentrations was associated with reducing the PCa risk(<xref rid="pone.0137427.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). The inverse association between lycopene concentrations and PCa risk was more evident in studies that adjusted for BMI, education, FHPC, smoking and physical activity compared with studies without such adjustments.</p><p>Two studies [<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0137427.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>] and 4 studies [<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0137427.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0137427.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0137427.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>] reported the RRs of advanced PCa risk concerning blood levels of &#x003b1;-carotene and lycopene, respectively. However, both of them could not lower the risk of advanced PCa. RRs for blood levels of &#x003b1;-carotene and lycopene were 1.07(95%CI: 0.75&#x02013;1.52; I<sup>2</sup> = 0%) and 0.75(0.44&#x02013;1.28; I<sup>2</sup> = 63.2%), respectively(<xref rid="pone.0137427.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>).</p><fig id="pone.0137427.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0137427.g003</object-id><label>Fig 3</label><caption><title>Association between blood &#x003b1;-carotene and lycopene levels and risk of advanced PCa.</title><p>Advanced PCa was defined as stage III or IV or Gleason score &#x02265;7.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0137427.g003"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec015"><title>Dose-response analysis</title><p>With respect to the lycopene exposure, 7 studies [<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0137427.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0137427.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0137427.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0137427.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0137427.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0137427.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>] and 8 studies [<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0137427.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0137427.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0137427.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0137427.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0137427.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0137427.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>] were eligible for dose-response analysis of dietary intake and concentrations, respectively. In the cubic spline model, we showed a nonlinear association between dietary lycopene intake and risk of PCa (<xref rid="pone.0137427.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4A</xref>; <italic>P</italic>-nonlinearity = 0.014, <italic>P</italic><sub>heterogeneity</sub> = 0.048) and PCa risk was reduced by 3% per 1mg/day (95%CI: 0.94&#x02013;0.99) increment of dietary lycopene intake. However, we showed no significant association between lycopene concentrations and risk of PCa(<xref rid="pone.0137427.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4B</xref>;<italic>P</italic>-nonlinearity = 0.24, <italic>P</italic><sub>heterogeneity</sub> = 0.21). With respect to the &#x003b1;-carotene exposure, 3 studies [<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0137427.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0137427.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>] were eligible for dose-response analysis, a nonlinear association between dietary &#x003b1;-carotene intake and risk of PCa was observed(<xref rid="pone.0137427.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4C</xref>; <italic>P</italic>-nonlinearity = 0.15, <italic>P</italic><sub>heterogeneity</sub> = 0.02) and PCa risk was reduced by 2% per 0.2mg/day (95% CI: 0.96&#x02013;0.99) increment of dietary &#x003b1;-carotene intake. The dose-response relationship in terms of PCa risk was not found in either &#x003b1;-carotene concentrations or &#x003b2;-carotene(both dietary intake and concentrations)(data not shown).</p><fig id="pone.0137427.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0137427.g004</object-id><label>Fig 4</label><caption><title>Dose-response relation plots between carotenoids consumption and risk of PCa.</title><p>(A) Dietary lycopene intake(mg/day) and risk of PCa; (B) Blood lycopene levels (ug/dl) and risk of PCa; (C) Dietary &#x003b1;-carotene intake(mg/day) and risk of PCa. These relationships were estimated by using random-effects metaregression. Dotted lines represent the 95% CIs for the fitted trend.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0137427.g004"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec016"><title>Discussion</title><p>Our meta-analysis indicated that &#x003b1;-carotene and lycopene, but not &#x003b2;-carotene, were inversely associated with the risk of PCa and both &#x003b1;-carotene and lycopene could not lower the risk of advanced PCa. Inverse association between &#x003b1;-carotene and PCa risk was augmented by adjustment for education, FHPC, and alcohol and attenuated by adjustment for age and smoking, suggesting that the association was largely mediated through education, FHPC, and alcohol, smoking and age(<xref rid="pone.0137427.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Similarly, significant inverse association between lycopene and PCa risk was largely mediated through FHPC. With respect to carotenoids concentrations, inverse association between lycopene and PCa risk was largely mediated through education, FHPC, smoking and physical activity.</p><p>Lycopene is found to be a more efficient antioxidant than &#x003b2;-carotene, &#x003b1;-carotene, and &#x003b1;-tocopherol [<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. Among all major carotenoids, lycopene and tomato products have been most extensively studied [<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. A meta-analysis [<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>] including 11 case-control studies and 10 cohort studies showed a modest, significant inverse relation between dietary intake of lycopene and PCa risk in cohort studies. However, the CUP report concludes that the link between PCa risk and foods containing lycopene has been downgraded from strong evidence of a decreased risk, to no conclusion possible [<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. This updating is based on a considerable amount of global research focusing on specific types of PCa, for example, fatal, advanced and early (non-advanced) prostate cancers rather than grouping all prostate cancers together. However, this does not mean that no link exists, variations in diagnosis and classifications of the PCa has made the link more difficult to see. In addition, the CUP report has not adjusted the confounding variables when interpreting the evidence. Even more important, frequent lycopene intake may reduce PCa risk via multiple mechanisms. Rafi, et al. informed that lycopene attenuates PCa by modulating the expression of growth and survival associated genes, e.g. CDK7, BCL2, EGFR, and IGF-1R [<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]; in addition, lycopene can inhibit PCa cell proliferation via PPAR&#x003b3;-LXR&#x003b1;-ABCA1 pathway [<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]; Further, Zu, et al. [<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>] found that dietary intake of lycopene is associated with reduced risk of lethal PCa and with a lesser degree of angiogenesis in the tumor.</p><p>In 1995, van Poppel and Goldbohm [<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>] summarized all previous studies exploring the risk between &#x003b2;-carotene intake and all types of tumors. They concluded that the association appears most consistent for lung and stomach cancer, whereas the association seems inconsistent for breast and PCa. More recently, a meta-analysis [<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>] of randomized controlled trials demonstrated that no effect of &#x003b2;-carotene supplementation was observed in the incidence of PCa(RR, 0.99; 95% CI, 0.91&#x02013;1.07). Although there was <italic>in vitro</italic> study indicating that &#x003b2;-carotene may act as a growth-inhibitory agent in PCa cells by modulating the caveolin-1 pathway [<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>], subsequent big data from the Alpha-Tocopherol, Beta-Carotene Cancer Prevention(ATBC) Study, a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial, suggested that serum &#x003b2;-carotene, serum retinol, and supplemental &#x003b2;-carotene had no apparent effects on PCa patients&#x02019; survival [<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. Our pooled and stratified analyses suggested that neither dietary &#x003b2;-carotene intake nor its concentrations was related to the PCa risk, moreover, the null dose-response relationship(data not shown) supported this conclusion. Also, the CUP report concludes that there is strong evidence that consuming &#x003b2;-carotene (either through food or supplements) is unlikely to have a substantial effect on the risk of PCa [<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. The studies on which the CUP report based are all cohort studies which should be given high priority.</p><p>Although &#x003b1;-carotene is chemically similar to &#x003b2;-carotene, &#x003b1;-carotene has higher biological activity in inhibiting the proliferation of human neuroblastoma cells [<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>] and liver carcinogenesis [<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. Besides, serum &#x003b1;-carotene concentrations are inversely associated with risk of death from all causes, cardiovascular disease, cancer, and all other causes [<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. Our pooled analysis indicated a significant inverse relation between &#x003b1;-carotene intake and PCa risk, which was further verified by dose-response analysis(<xref rid="pone.0137427.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4C</xref>).</p><p>It was reported that in Caucasians, the frequencies of fusion of <italic>TMPRSS2</italic>:<italic>ERG</italic>, the most common known genetic alteration in PCa, are 50%&#x02013;70% [<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>], while in Asian patients the frequencies are lower than 20% [<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. Mao et al. revealed that low-level expression of <italic>PTEN</italic> is detected in 69.8% (111/159) of UK PCa samples, but only in 34% (31/91) of Chinese samples [<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. Whereas, <italic>RAS</italic>-<italic>RAF</italic>-<italic>MAPK</italic> pathway mutants are much more frequently found in Asian PCa patients than patients from Western countries [<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. All these abnormal genes are likely to contribute to susceptibility to PCa in different ethnic groups. Broccoli, green beans, green peas, spinach, turnip greens, leaf lettuce, the main source of vegetables for China adults, are rich in &#x003b1;-carotene [<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. Specially, our study showed that &#x003b1;-carotene exerted a greater protective effect on Asians. All of these suggested &#x003b1;-carotene may attenuate the PCa susceptibility by interacting with the genetic or environmental factors. However, the fundamental researches that aim at elucidating the links between &#x003b1;-carotene intake and PCa risk are lacking. Altogether, this may shed fresh new light on &#x003b1;-carotene&#x02019;s mode of action.</p><p>Compared with a meta-analysis [<xref rid="pone.0137427.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>] conducted in 2004, we put emphasis on the single-ingredient of carotenoids rather than raw tomato or its processed products, which may provide more detailed and accurate assessment on the links between carotenoids consumption and PCa risk. Furthermore, dose-response analysis was utilized for the first time to reveal the links between carotenoids consumption and PCa risk. However, our study was subject to one inconsistency: significant association was only found in dietary intake, but not its concentrations. There are 3 case-control studies involving in exploring the links between &#x003b1;-carotene concentrations and PCa risk(<xref rid="pone.0137427.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). These retrospective studies may have biased the pooled results.</p><p>Not all included studies have adjusted for some important covariates, which are major concerns in our study, may have confounded these associations. For example, the inverse association between dietary &#x003b1;-carotene intake and PCa risk was more evident in studies without adjustment for smoking compared with studies with such adjustment(<xref rid="pone.0137427.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>), suggesting more high-quality observational studies are warranted to verify the effect of dietary &#x003b1;-carotene intake on PCa risk. In addition, although subgroup analyses were performed, heterogeneity could not wholly explained by the remaining variables, suggesting that other unknown factors are introduced. Furthermore, in terms of &#x003b1;-carotene and lycopene consumption, not all studies were eligible for dose-response analysis, indicating that risks corresponding to dose increments are partially right.</p><p>In summary, findings from our study indicate that &#x003b1;-carotene and lycopene, but not &#x003b2;-carotene, are inversely associated with the risk of PCa. However, both &#x003b1;-carotene and lycopene can not lower the risk of advanced PCa. Our results, if replicated in other cohort studies and populations, suggest a need for clinical research into the health benefits of &#x003b1;-carotene and lycopene supplementation.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec017"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0137427.s001"><label>S1 PRISMA Checklist</label><caption><title>PRISMA checklist.</title><p>(DOC)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0137427.s001.doc"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0137427.s002"><label>S1 Table</label><caption><title>Methodological quality assessment based on the NOS.</title><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0137427.s002.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0137427.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jemal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bray</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Center</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ferlay</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Forman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Global cancer statistics</article-title>. <source>CA Cancer J Clin</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>61</volume>:<fpage>69</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>90</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3322/caac.20107">10.3322/caac.20107</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21296855</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Potosky</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Albertsen</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name>. <article-title>The role of increasing detection in the rising incidence of PCa</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>273</volume>:<fpage>548</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>52</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7530782</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nomura</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kolonel</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name>. <article-title>Prostate cancer: a current perspective</article-title>. <source>Epidemiol Rev</source>. <year>1991</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>200</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>27</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1765112</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">World Cancer Report 2014. World Health Organization. 2014. pp. Chapter 5.11. ISBN 9283204298.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">PCa Statistics-Australia. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.prostates.com.au/statistics/">http://www.prostates.com.au/statistics/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gomez</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wey</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hsing</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name>. <article-title>Soy and isoflavone consumption in relation to PCa risk in China</article-title>. <source>Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>665</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12869409</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>World Health Organization</collab>. <source>Noncommunicable Diseases Country Profiles 2011</source>.<publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name>; <year>2011</year> p. <fpage>50</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bolhassani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Cancer chemoprevention by natural carotenoids as an efficient strategy</article-title>. <source>Anticancer Agents Med Chem</source>. <year>2015</year>. [Epub ahead of print].</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stahl</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sies</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>beta-Carotene and other carotenoids in protection from sunlight</article-title>. <source>Am J Clin Nutr</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>96</volume>:<fpage>1179S</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>84S</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3945/ajcn.112.034819">10.3945/ajcn.112.034819</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23053552</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Viuda-Martos</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sanchez-Zapata</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sayas-Barbera</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sendra</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Perez-Alvarez</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fernandez-Lopez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Tomato and tomato byproducts. Human health benefits of lycopene and its application to meat products: a review</article-title>. <source>Crit Rev Food Sci Nutr</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>54</volume>:<fpage>1032</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>49</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/10408398.2011.623799">10.1080/10408398.2011.623799</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24499120</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>O'Neill</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Corridan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Olmedilla</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Granado</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Blanco</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>A European carotenoid database to assess carotenoid intakes and its use in a five-country comparative study</article-title>. <source>Br J Nutr</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>85</volume>:<fpage>499</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>507</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11348565</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Krinsky</surname><given-names>NI</given-names></name>. <article-title>The antioxidant and biological properties of the carotenoids</article-title>. <source>Ann N Y Acad Sci</source>.<year>1998</year>;<volume>854</volume>:<fpage>443</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9928451</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Peto</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Doll</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Buckley</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sporn</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>. <article-title>Can dietary beta-carotene materially reduce human cancer rates?</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>. <year>1981</year>;<volume>290</volume>:<fpage>201</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7010181</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shibata</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Paganini-Hill</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name>. <article-title>Intake of vegetables, fruits, beta-carotene, vitamin C and vitamin supplements and cancer incidence among the elderly: a prospective study</article-title>. <source>Br J Cancer</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>66</volume>:<fpage>673</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1419605</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>SO</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wolk</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bergstrom</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Giovannucci</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lindgren</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baron</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Energy, nutrient intake and prostate cancer risk: a population-based case-control study in Sweden</article-title>. <source>Int J Cancer</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>68</volume>:<fpage>716</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>22</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8980172</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schuurman</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goldbohm</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brants</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>van den Brandt</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>. <article-title>A prospective cohort study on intake of retinol, vitamins C and E, and carotenoids and prostate cancer risk (Netherlands)</article-title>. <source>Cancer Causes Control</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>573</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>82</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12195647</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dhakal</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ning</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Greene</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Plasma carotenoids and prostate cancer: a population-based case-control study in Arkansas</article-title>. <source>Nutr Cancer</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>59</volume>:<fpage>46</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>53</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17927501</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sies</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stahl</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sundquist</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Antioxidant functions of vitamins. Vitamins E and C, beta-carotene, and other carotenoids</article-title>. <source>Ann N Y Acad Sci</source>.<year>1992</year>;<volume>669</volume>:<fpage>7</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1444060</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Clinton</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Emenhiser</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bostwick</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>cis-trans lycopene isomers, carotenoids, and retinol in the human prostate</article-title>. <source>Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>823</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>33</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8896894</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">World Cancer Research Fund International/American Institute for Cancer Research Continuous Update Project Report:Diet, Nutrition, Physical Activity, and Prostate Cancer. 2014. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wcrf.org/sites/default/files/Prostate-Cancer-2014-Report.pdf">www.wcrf.org/sites/default/files/Prostate-Cancer-2014-Report.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stang</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Critical evaluation of the Newcastle-Ottawa scale for the assessment of the quality of nonrandomized studies in meta-analyses</article-title>. <source>Eur J Epidemiol</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>603</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10654-010-9491-z">10.1007/s10654-010-9491-z</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20652370</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>DerSimonian</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Laird</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>. <article-title>Meta-analysis in clinical trials</article-title>. <source>Control Clin Trials</source>.<year>1986</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>177</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>88</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3802833</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>. <article-title>Quantifying heterogeneity in a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Stat Med</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>1539</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>58</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12111919</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Greenland</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Longnecker</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Methods for trend estimation from summarized dose-response data,with applications to meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Am J Epidemiol</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>135</volume>:<fpage>1301</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1626547</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Orsini</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bellocco</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Greenland</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Generalized least squares for trend estimation of summarized doseresponse data</article-title>. <source>Stata Journal</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>40</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>57</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alberg</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Norkus</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Comstock</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Helzlsouer</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Prospective study of antioxidant micronutrients in the blood and the risk of developing prostate cancer</article-title>. <source>Am J Epidemiol</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>157</volume>:<fpage>335</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>44</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12578804</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Leitzmann</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chatterjee</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Albanes</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gelmann</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Serum lycopene,other carotenoids, and prostate cancer risk: a nested case-control study in the prostate, lung,colorectal, and ovarian cancer screening trial</article-title>. <source>Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>962</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17507623</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>McCann</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ambrosone</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moysich</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brasure</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Freudenheim</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Intakes of selected nutrients, foods, and phytochemicals and prostate cancer risk in western New York</article-title>. <source>Nutr Cancer</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>53</volume>:<fpage>33</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>41</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16351504</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Erdman</surname><given-names>JW</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name>, <name><surname>Clinton</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vadiveloo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Strom</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yamamura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Relationship between plasma carotenoids and prostate cancer</article-title>. <source>Nutr Cancer</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>53</volume>:<fpage>127</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>34</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16573373</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Roswall</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Friis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Outzen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Olsen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Micronutrient intake and risk of prostate cancer in a cohort of middle-aged, Danish men</article-title>. <source>Cancer Causes Control</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>1129</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>35</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10552-013-0190-4">10.1007/s10552-013-0190-4</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23519640</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Umesawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Iso</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mikami</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kubo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Relationship between vegetable and carotene intake and risk of prostate cancer: the JACC study</article-title>. <source>Br J Cancer</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>110</volume>:<fpage>792</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/bjc.2013.685">10.1038/bjc.2013.685</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24169341</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jian</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Binns</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name>. <article-title>Do dietary lycopene and other carotenoids protect against prostate cancer?</article-title>
<source>Int J Cancer</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>113</volume>:<fpage>1010</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15514967</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kirsh</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mayne</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chatterjee</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Subar</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Supplemental and dietary vitamin E, beta-carotene, and vitamin C intakes and prostate cancer risk</article-title>. <source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>98</volume>:<fpage>245</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>54</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16478743</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Key</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Appleby</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Travis</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Roddam</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jenab</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Plasma carotenoids, retinol, and tocopherols and the risk of prostate cancer in the European Prospective Investigation into Cancer and Nutrition study</article-title>. <source>Am J Clin Nutr</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>86</volume>:<fpage>672</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>81</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17823432</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Erdman</surname><given-names>JW</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name>, <name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Platz</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Leitzmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Clinton</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Plasma and dietary carotenoids, and the risk of prostate cancer: a nested case-control study</article-title>. <source>Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>260</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14973107</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Beilby</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ambrosini</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>de Klerk</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Musk</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name>. <article-title>Serum levels of folate, lycopene, beta-carotene, retinol and vitamin E and prostate cancer risk</article-title>. <source>Eur J Clin Nutr</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>64</volume>:<fpage>1235</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ejcn.2010.124">10.1038/ejcn.2010.124</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20683458</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schaffer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Omenn</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>King</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>. <article-title>The association between lung and prostate cancer risk, and serum micronutrients: results and lessons learned from beta-carotene and retinol efficacy trial</article-title>. <source>Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>518</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>26</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12814997</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ambrosini</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>de Klerk</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fritschi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mackerras</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Musk</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>. <article-title>Fruit, vegetable, vitamin A intakes, and prostate cancer risk</article-title>. <source>Prostate Cancer Prostatic Dis</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>61</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17519926</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Franke</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Steven Morris</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cooney</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wilkens</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Le Marchand</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Association of selenium, tocopherols, carotenoids, retinol, and 15-isoprostane F(2t) in serum or urine with prostate cancer risk: the multiethnic cohort</article-title>. <source>Cancer Causes Control</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>1161</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>71</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10552-009-9304-4">10.1007/s10552-009-9304-4</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19212706</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gann</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Giovannucci</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Willett</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sacks</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hennekens</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Lower prostate cancer risk in men with elevated plasma lycopene levels: results of a prospective analysis</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>59</volume>:<fpage>1225</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>30</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10096552</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Giovannucci</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ascherio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rimm</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stampfer</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Colditz</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Willett</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Intake of carotenoids and retinol in relation to risk of prostate cancer</article-title>. <source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source>.<year>1995</year>;<volume>87</volume>:<fpage>1767</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>76</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7473833</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mettlin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Selenskas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Natarajan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huben</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Beta-carotene and animal fats and their relationship to prostate cancer risk. A case-control study</article-title>. <source>Cancer</source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>64</volume>:<fpage>605</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2743255</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bosetti</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Talamini</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Montella</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Negri</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Conti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Franceschi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Retinol, carotenoids and the risk of prostate cancer: a case-control study from Italy</article-title>. <source>Int J Cancer</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>112</volume>:<fpage>689</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>92</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15382052</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Norrish</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sharpe</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Skeaff</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Prostate cancer and dietary carotenoids</article-title>. <source>Am J Epidemiol</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>151</volume>:<fpage>119</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>23</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10645813</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nomura</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stemmermann</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Craft</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name>. <article-title>Serum micronutrients and prostate cancer in Japanese Americans in Hawaii</article-title>. <source>Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>487</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>91</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9232334</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref046"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Agalliu</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kirsh</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kreiger</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Soskolne</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rohan</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name>. <article-title>Oxidative balance score and risk of PCa: results from a case-cohort study</article-title>. <source>Cancer Epidemiol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>35</volume>:<fpage>353</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>61</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.canep.2010.11.002">10.1016/j.canep.2010.11.002</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21145797</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref047"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kristal</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stanford</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Fruit and vegetable intakes and PCa risk</article-title>. <source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>92</volume>:<fpage>61</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10620635</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref048"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Deneo-Pellegrini</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>De Stefani</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ronco</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mendilaharsu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Foods, nutrients and PCa: a case-control study in Uruguay</article-title>. <source>Br J Cancer</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>80</volume>:<fpage>591</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10408871</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref049"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hsing</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Comstock</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Abbey</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Polk</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name>. <article-title>Serologic precursors of cancer. Retinol, carotenoids, and tocopherol and risk of PCa</article-title>. <source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source>. <year>1990</year>;<volume>82</volume>:<fpage>941</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2342127</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref050"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hislop</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Howe</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ghadirian</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>Plant foods, antioxidants, and PCa risk: findings from case-control studies in Canada</article-title>. <source>Nutr Cancer</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>173</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>84</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10578485</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref051"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Karppi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kurl</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nurmi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rissanen</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pukkala</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nyyssonen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>Serum lycopene and the risk of cancer: the Kuopio Ischaemic Heart Disease Risk Factor (KIHD) study</article-title>. <source>Ann Epidemiol</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>512</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.annepidem.2009.03.017">10.1016/j.annepidem.2009.03.017</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19443241</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref052"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>QY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hung</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Heber</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Go</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reuter</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cordon-Cardo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Inverse associations between plasma lycopene and other carotenoids and PCa</article-title>. <source>Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>749</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>56</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11440960</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref053"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bairati</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fradet</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>Dietary energy and nutrients in relation to preclinical PCa</article-title>. <source>Nutr Cancer</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>120</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9427974</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref054"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Daviglus</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dyer</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Persky</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chavez</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Drum</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Dietary beta-carotene, vitamin C, and risk of PCa: results from the Western Electric Study</article-title>. <source>Epidemiology</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>472</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8862976</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref055"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Druesne-Pecollo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Latino-Martel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Norat</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Barrandon</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bertrais</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Galan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Beta-carotene supplementation and cancer risk: a systematic review and metaanalysis of randomized controlled trials</article-title>. <source>Int J Cancer</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>127</volume>:<fpage>172</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>84</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/ijc.25008">10.1002/ijc.25008</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19876916</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref056"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Di Mascio</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kaiser</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sies</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Lycopene as the most efficient biological carotenoid singlet oxygen quencher</article-title>. <source>Arch Biochem Biophys</source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>274</volume>:<fpage>532</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2802626</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref057"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Etminan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Takkouche</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Caamano-Isorna</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>. <article-title>The role of tomato products and lycopene in the prevention of PCa: a meta-analysis of observational studies</article-title>. <source>Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>340</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15006906</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref058"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rafi</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kanakasabai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reyes</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bright</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Lycopene modulates growth and survival associated genes in PCa</article-title>. <source>J Nutr Biochem</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>1724</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>34</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jnutbio.2013.03.001">10.1016/j.jnutbio.2013.03.001</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23746934</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref059"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>. <article-title>Lycopene and the LXRalpha agonist T0901317 synergistically inhibit the proliferation of androgen-independent PCa cells via the PPARgamma-LXRalpha-ABCA1 pathway</article-title>. <source>J Nutr Biochem</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>1155</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>62</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jnutbio.2011.06.009">10.1016/j.jnutbio.2011.06.009</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22137263</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref060"><label>60</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mucci</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rosner</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Clinton</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Loda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stampfer</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Dietary lycopene, angiogenesis, and PCa: a prospective study in the prostate-specific antigen era</article-title>. <source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>106</volume>:<fpage>djt430</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/jnci/djt430">10.1093/jnci/djt430</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24463248</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref061"><label>61</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>van Poppel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goldbohm</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Epidemiologic evidence for beta-carotene and cancer prevention</article-title>. <source>Am J Clin Nutr</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>62</volume>:<fpage>1393S</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>402S</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7495237</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref062"><label>62</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Palozza</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sestito</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Picci</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lanza</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Monego</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ranelletti</surname><given-names>FO</given-names></name>. <article-title>The sensitivity to beta-carotene growth-inhibitory and proapoptotic effects is regulated by caveolin-1 expression in human colon and PCa cells</article-title>. <source>Carcinogenesis</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>2153</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>61</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/carcin/bgn018">10.1093/carcin/bgn018</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18635524</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref063"><label>63</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Watters</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gail</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Weinstein</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Virtamo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Albanes</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Associations between alpha-tocopherol, beta-carotene, and retinol and PCa survival</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>69</volume>:<fpage>3833</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>41</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-08-4640">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-08-4640</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19383902</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref064"><label>64</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Murakoshi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Takayasu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kohmura</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nishino</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Iwashima</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Inhibitory effects of alpha-carotene on proliferation of the human neuroblastoma cell line GOTO</article-title>. <source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>81</volume>:<fpage>1649</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>52</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2795693</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref065"><label>65</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Murakoshi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nishino</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Satomi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Takayasu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hasegawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tokuda</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Potent preventive action of alpha-carotene against carcinogenesis: spontaneous liver carcinogenesis and promoting stage of lung and skin carcinogenesis in mice are suppressed more effectively by alpha-carotene than by beta-carotene</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>52</volume>:<fpage>6583</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1423303</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref066"><label>66</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Balluz</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Giles</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Serum alpha-carotene concentrations and risk of death among US Adults: the Third National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey Follow-up Study</article-title>. <source>Arch Intern Med</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>171</volume>:<fpage>507</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>15</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1001/archinternmed.2010.440">10.1001/archinternmed.2010.440</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21098341</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref067"><label>67</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Maher</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chinnaiyan</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Common gene rearrangements in PCa</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>3659</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>68</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1200/JCO.2011.35.1916">10.1200/JCO.2011.35.1916</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21859993</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref068"><label>68</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stankiewicz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kudahetti</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Chinese and Western PCas show alternate pathogenetic pathways in association with ERG status</article-title>. <source>Am J Cancer Res</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>736</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>44</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23226619</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref069"><label>69</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chaplin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Distinct genomic alterations in PCas in Chinese and Western populations suggest alternative pathways of prostate carcinogenesis</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>70</volume>:<fpage>5207</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-09-4074">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-09-4074</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20516122</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0137427.ref070"><label>70</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>KRAS and BRAF mutations in prostate carcinomas of Chinese patients</article-title>. <source>Cancer Genet Cytogenet</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>198</volume>:<fpage>35</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.cancergencyto.2009.12.003">10.1016/j.cancergencyto.2009.12.003</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20303012</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>