<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26730743</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4701378</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0145774</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-15-17045</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A Genome Wide Study of Copy Number Variation Associated with Nasopharyngeal Carcinoma in Malaysian Chinese Identifies CNVs at 11q14.3 and 6p21.3 as Candidate Loci</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">CNVs Associated with Susceptibility to NPC</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Low</surname><given-names>Joyce Siew Yong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chin</surname><given-names>Yoon Ming</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mushiroda</surname><given-names>Taisei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kubo</surname><given-names>Michiaki</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff004"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Govindasamy</surname><given-names>Gopala Krishnan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff005"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pua</surname><given-names>Kin Choo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff006"><sup>6</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yap</surname><given-names>Yoke Yeow</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff007"><sup>7</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yap</surname><given-names>Lee Fah</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff008"><sup>8</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Subramaniam</surname><given-names>Selva Kumar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff009"><sup>9</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ong</surname><given-names>Cheng Ai</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff010"><sup>10</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>Tee Yong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff011"><sup>11</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Khoo</surname><given-names>Alan Soo Beng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff012"><sup>12</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><collab>The Malaysian NPC Study Group</collab><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff013"><sup>13</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn001"><sup>&#x000b6;</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>Ching Ching</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff001"><label>1</label><addr-line>Institute of Biological Sciences, Faculty of Science, University of Malaya, Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff002"><label>2</label><addr-line>Translational Genomics Lab, High Impact Research Building (Level 2), University of Malaya, Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff003"><label>3</label><addr-line>Laboratory for Pharmacogenetics, RIKEN Center for Integrative Medical Sciences, Yokohama, Japan</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff004"><label>4</label><addr-line>Laboratory for Genotyping Development, RIKEN Center for Integrative Medical Sciences, Yokohama, Japan</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff005"><label>5</label><addr-line>Department of Otorhinolaryngology, Faculty of Medicine, University of Malaya, Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff006"><label>6</label><addr-line>Department of Otorhinolaryngology, Hospital Pulau Pinang, Penang, Malaysia</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff007"><label>7</label><addr-line>Department of Surgery, Faculty of Medicine and Health Sciences, Universiti Putra Malaysia, Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff008"><label>8</label><addr-line>Department of Oral Biology &#x00026; Biomedical Sciences and Oral Cancer Research &#x00026; Coordinating Centre, Faculty of Dentistry, University of Malaya, Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff009"><label>9</label><addr-line>Department of Otorhinolaryngology, Head and Neck Surgery, Sarawak General Hospital, Sarawak, Malaysia</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff010"><label>10</label><addr-line>ENT Department, Hospital Queen Elizabeth, Karung Berkunci No. 2029, Kota Kinabalu, Sabah, Malaysia</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff011"><label>11</label><addr-line>Department of Otorhinolaryngology, Sarawak General Hospital, Kuching, Sarawak, Malaysia</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff012"><label>12</label><addr-line>Molecular Pathology Unit, Cancer Research Centre, Institute for Medical Research, Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff013"><label>13</label><addr-line>The Malaysian Nasopharyngeal Carcinoma Study Group: Hospital Pulau Pinang, Hospital Kuala Lumpur/Universiti Putra Malaysia, University of Malaya, Institute for Medical Research, Cancer Research Initiatives Foundation, Sarawak General Hospital/Universiti Malaysia Sarawak, Queen Elizabeth Hospital and Hospital Universiti Sains, Malaysia</addr-line></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>Qian</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1"><addr-line>The Chinese University of Hong Kong, HONG KONG</addr-line></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: JSYL YMC CCN. Performed the experiments: JSYL. Analyzed the data: JSYL YMC. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: TM MK GKG KCP YYY LFY SKS CAO TYT ASBK The Malaysian NPC Study Group CCN. Wrote the paper: JSYL YMC ASBK CCN.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>&#x000b6; The complete membership of the Malaysian NPC Study Group can be found in the Acknowledgments.</p></fn><corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>ccng@um.edu.my</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>5</day><month>1</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>e0145774</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>4</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>8</day><month>12</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2016 Low et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Low et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="pone.0145774.pdf"/><abstract><sec id="sec001"><title>Background</title><p>Nasopharyngeal carcinoma (NPC) is a neoplasm of the epithelial lining of the nasopharynx. Despite various reports linking genomic variants to NPC predisposition, very few reports were done on copy number variations (CNV). CNV is an inherent structural variation that has been found to be involved in cancer predisposition.</p></sec><sec id="sec002"><title>Methods</title><p>A discovery cohort of Malaysian Chinese descent (NPC patients, n = 140; Healthy controls, n = 256) were genotyped using Illumina<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> HumanOmniExpress BeadChip. PennCNV and cnvPartition calling algorithms were applied for CNV calling. Taqman CNV assays and digital PCR were used to validate CNV calls and replicate candidate copy number variant region (CNVR) associations in a follow-up Malaysian Chinese (NPC cases, n = 465; and Healthy controls, n = 677) and Malay cohort (NPC cases, n = 114; Healthy controls, n = 124).</p></sec><sec id="sec003"><title>Results</title><p>Six putative CNVRs overlapping <italic>GRM5</italic>, <italic>MICA/HCP5/HCG26</italic>, <italic>LILRB3/LILRA6</italic>, <italic>DPY19L2</italic>, <italic>RNase3/RNase2</italic> and <italic>GOLPH3</italic> genes were jointly identified by PennCNV and cnvPartition. CNVs overlapping <italic>GRM5</italic> and <italic>MICA/HCP5/HCG26</italic> were subjected to further validation by Taqman CNV assays and digital PCR. Combined analysis in Malaysian Chinese cohort revealed a strong association at CNVR on chromosome 11q14.3 (<italic>P</italic><sub>combined</sub> = 1.54x10<sup>-5</sup>; odds ratio (OR) = 7.27; 95% CI = 2.96&#x02013;17.88) overlapping <italic>GRM5</italic> and a suggestive association at CNVR on chromosome 6p21.3 (<italic>P</italic><sub>combined</sub> = 1.29x10<sup>-3</sup>; OR = 4.21; 95% CI = 1.75&#x02013;10.11) overlapping <italic>MICA/HCP5/HCG26</italic> genes.</p></sec><sec id="sec004"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Our results demonstrated the association of CNVs towards NPC susceptibility, implicating a possible role of CNVs in NPC development.</p></sec></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by High Impact Research Grant UM.C/625/1/1HIR/MOHE/CHAN-02 (H-50001-A000023).</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="5"/><table-count count="7"/><page-count count="17"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>All relevant data are available in the paper and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><title>Data Availability</title><p>All relevant data are available in the paper and its Supporting Information files.</p></notes></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec005"><title>Introduction</title><p>Nasopharyngeal carcinoma (NPC) (OMIM 161550 and 607107) is a malignant tumour arising in the nasopharyngeal mucosa. NPC displays a geographic bias. It is a rare malignancy in most parts of the world (ASR = 1 case per 100,000 per year), but a highly endemic disease in selected demographics such as Southern Chinese population of Guangdong (as high as 15 to 25 cases per 100,000 per year) [<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>], native Greenlanders [<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] and migrants of the Southern Chinese in America, Australia, and Malaysia [<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0145774.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. The skewed demographic distribution of the disease coupled with familial aggregation [<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], Epstein-Barr virus (EBV) infection and environmental factors such as air pollutants [<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], dietary intake of salted fish and preserved food [<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], suggest possible interplay between genetic and environmental factors in NPC pathogenesis. Many genetic studies on single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) have reported associations to NPC. Genes linked to NPC include <italic>HLA-A</italic> (Human leukocyte antigen A) [<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0145774.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], <italic>HLA-B</italic> (Human leukocyte antigen B) [<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], <italic>GABBR1</italic> (Gamma-aminobutyric acid (GABA) B receptor 1) [<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], <italic>CYP2E1</italic> (cytochrome P450 2E1) and <italic>hOGG1</italic> (human 8-oxoguanine DNA N-glycosylase 1) [<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Despite many reports linking SNP variants to NPC predisposition, structural variants such as CNVs and its possible influence on NPC predisposition remain grossly neglected. Thus far, only deletions linked to NPC have been reported at chromosome 3p [<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] and 6p21.3 [<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>].</p><p>Copy number variants are structural variants present in multiple copies involving DNA segments of &#x02265; 1 kb [<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. CNVs can have simple structures such as tandem duplication or complex structures like sequence complexity at junctions that arise from complex amplification and deletion rearrangements. Some CNVs remain neutral in function, others convey differences in phenotypes by disrupting genes, creating fusion genes, changing copy number of dosage sensitive genes and altering the regulatory transcription levels [<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. These changes in phenotypes can be benign or can have detrimental implications in diseases such as osteoporosis [<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], schizophrenia [<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], Li-Fraumeni-syndrome-associated cancers [<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] and neuroblastoma [<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>].</p><p>The Malaysian Chinese population is largely made up of descendants from Southern China. This population comprises various dialect groups of the Hokkien, Hakka, Cantonese, Teochew and Hainanese. NPC incidence is high among the Malaysian Chinese, especially in Chinese males (ASR = 14 per 100,000) [<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. As for the Malaysian Malay population, they are a heterogeneous ethnic group with different ancestral origins based on migration patterns of centuries ago. They were the descendants of the Proto-Malays, admixed with Siamese, Javanese, Sumatran, Indian, Thai, Arab and Chinese traders [<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. The Malays make up the majority of the Malaysian population. NPC incidence is low among the Malays, including the Malay males (ASR = 4.0 per 100,000) [<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>].</p><p>This study aims to evaluate the role of CNVs in NPC predisposition in the Malaysian Chinese and Malay populations. We report a case control genome-wide SNP microarray approach to identify CNVs associated to NPC in the Malaysian Chinese and Malay populations.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec006"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="sec007"><title>Study samples</title><p>Samples were recruited from the University Malaya Medical Centre (UMMC), Penang General Hospital (HPP), Kuala Lumpur General Hospital (HKL), Sarawak General Hospital (HUS) and Queen Elizabeth Hospital Sabah (QES) from year 2006 to 2013. All cases were histo-pathologically diagnosed according to the World Health Organization (WHO) classification. GWAS discovery cohort consisted of 193 cases and 290 controls (140 cases and 256 healthy controls after QC filtering) of Malaysian Chinese descent and the replication cohort consisted of 465 NPC patients and 677 healthy controls of Malaysian Chinese descent, giving a combined cohort of 605 cases and 933 controls after QC filtering. The Malaysian Malay replication cohort consisted of 114 cases and 124 controls of Malaysian Malay descent. Demographic characteristics of Malaysian Chinese study participants are described in <xref rid="pone.0145774.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Table</xref> and demographic characteristics of Malaysian Malay study participants are described in <xref rid="pone.0145774.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="sec008"><title>Ethical approval and consent</title><p>All cases and controls gave written informed consent and the study was approved by Medical Research Ethic Committee (MREC) Ministry of Health Malaysia (Registration ID: NMRR-13-969-17878), ethical committees of the Yokohama Institute, The Institutes of Physical and Chemical Research (RIKEN), Yokohama, Japan and Medical Ethics Committee of University Malaya Medical Centre.</p></sec><sec id="sec009"><title>Genotyping, quality control and correction for population structure</title><p>Genome-wide genotyping of NPC cases and healthy controls of Malaysian Chinese was conducted using Illumina<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> HumanOmniExpress_12 v1.1 Genotyping BeadChip (San Diego, CA, USA) according to manufacturer's protocol. The genomic DNA was extracted from peripheral blood leukocytes using conventional phenol-chloroform method. Samples with sample call rates &#x0003c;0.99, mismatch between recorded and estimated gender, cryptic relatedness and population outliers were excluded from the subsequent studies. Population outliers were identified using Principal component analysis (PCA) performed in EIGENSTRAT version 2.0 [<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec010"><title>Generation of CNV calls</title><p>Samples passing quality control measures were used for generating CNV calls. Log R ratio (LRR) and B allele frequency (BAF) were generated from intensity data of the genome-wide genotyping using GenomeStudio (v.3.1.6) (San Diego, CA, USA) and CNVs were called using PennCNV (v.2011 Jun16) [<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] and cnvPartition (v.3.1.6) (San Diego, CA, USA). For uniformity, samples with standard deviation (SD) of LRR&#x02265; 0.20, SD of BAF &#x02265; 0.2, BAF drifting value of &#x02265; 0.01, waviness factor &#x02265; 0.05 and samples with more than 50 CNV calls were removed from analysis using PennCNV prior to CNV calling. Centromeric regions, telomeric regions, XY chromosomes and regions coding for immunoglobulin genes were also excluded from CNV calling. Minimum number of markers of 5 were set as threshold for all CNV calling. For cnvPartition analysis, confidence score threshold was set to 35 and minimum number of probes was set to 5.</p></sec><sec id="sec011"><title>CNV validation and replication</title><p>Validation of GWAS CNV calls and replication of CNV association at candidate loci on chromosome 11q14.3 and chromosome 6p21.3 were performed using Taqman CNV genotyping assays (ABI, Foster City, CA) on the GWAS discovery cohort (Malaysian Chinese only) and replication cohort (Malaysian Chinese and Malaysian Malay). Quantification cycle (C<sub>q</sub>) of each region of interest was determined by QuantStudio<sup>&#x02122;</sup> 12K Flex Software (v.1.0, Applied Biosystem, Foster City, CA) and copy numbers were determined using Copy Caller (v.2.0, Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA) according to a comparative delta Cq method. Random samples with a mixture of copy number (CN) state of 1, 2 and 3 were subjected to validation with Droplet digital PCR (ddPCR) (Bio-Rad Laboratories, Hemel Hempstead, UK) following manufacturer&#x02019;s protocol.</p></sec><sec id="sec012"><title>Gene-set enrichment analysis</title><p>Five pathways previously found to be associated to NPC were subjected to enrichment analysis [<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Enrichment analysis was carried out using cnv-enrichment-test [<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] implemented in PLINK v.1.07 [<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Gene sets were compiled from the Molecular Signatures Database (MSigDB) v.3.1 namely KEGG WNT signalling pathway, ST ERK1 ERK2 MAPK pathway, KEGG NOTCH signalling pathway, REACTOME regulation of apoptosis and REACTOME signalling by EGFR in cancer. One sided empirical <italic>P</italic>-values with 10,000 permutation of enrichment of a subset of genes of a pathway relative to all genes were acquired.</p></sec><sec id="sec013"><title>Global CNV burden analysis</title><p>PLINK v.1.07 [<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] was used to perform global CNV burden analysis. CNVs were classified as rare when found in &#x0003c;1% of total GWAS samples or common when found in &#x02265; 5% of total GWAS samples. Tests for CNV burden (one-sided) were done for number of CNV segments per individual, number of genes overlapped by CNVs per individual and number of genes intersected per total CNV kb using UCSC RefSeq (hg18) gene annotation. CNVs were considered co-localized if they overlapped by at least 50% of their length.</p></sec><sec id="sec014"><title>HLA allele imputation</title><p>SNPs that pass quality control filtering on chromosome 6 were input into the SNP2HLA software [<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] in forms of PLINK formats of (.bed/.bim/.fam). SNP allele annotations were mapped to forward strand and physical coordinates corresponding to hg18. Default parameter settings for SNP2HLA were used in the phasing and imputation. The Pan-Asian reference panel was used for this study [<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0145774.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec015"><title>Statistical association analysis</title><p>Copy number variant regions (CNVRs) are identified using reciprocal overlap (minimum threshold 50%). Logistic regression using PLINK v.1.07 was carried out to assess the frequency difference between NPC cases and healthy controls using gender and age as covariates. Gene-based association was carried out using ParseCNV v.17 [<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. GWAMA v.1.4 [<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>] was used for <italic>I</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup> heterogeneity analysis. G*Power v.3.1.9.2 was employed for power analysis for z tests logistic regression, using post-hoc computation of achieved power, one tail at &#x003b1; = 0.05 setting [<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec016"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec017"><title>Genome-wide CNV Distribution in the Malaysian Chinese GWA Sample</title><p>Our CNV analysis workflow is detailed in <xref rid="pone.0145774.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>. From the 733,202 genotyped SNPs, 13,365 SNPs were removed due to low call frequency (&#x0003c;0.99). In total, 9 cases and 24 controls were removed due to population outliers, mismatch between recorded and estimated gender and cryptic relatedness. CNV calling quality control measures removed a further 44 cases and 13 controls due to high standard deviation of Log R ratio (SD BAF &#x02265; 0.2), excessive CNV calls (&#x02265;50 CNVs) and drifting B allele frequency values (BAF drifting value of &#x02265; 0.01). Post quality control measures, 140 cases and 256 controls remained and were used for downstream CNV analysis.</p><fig id="pone.0145774.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0145774.g001</object-id><label>Fig 1</label><caption><title>Flowchart illustrating workflow for whole genome CNV analysis and NPC susceptibility associated candidate gene selection from our GWAS discovery cohort.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0145774.g001"/></fig><p>For global CNV analysis, we used only stringent consensus CNVs from both PennCNV and cnvPartition calling algorithms. Total of 1679 CNVs were called (mean size = 147,798bp; median size = 66739bp; range size = 720bp- 4,979,575bp). CNV burden analysis revealed no significant difference in global distribution of rare CNVs between cases and controls (<xref rid="pone.0145774.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). There was also no significant difference in common CNV rates (CNV<sub>freq</sub>&#x02265;5%) (<italic>P</italic> = 0.5326) (<xref rid="pone.0145774.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>), although common CNVs were 5.62 times more enriched with genes in cases than in controls (<italic>P</italic> = 7.00x10<sup>-4</sup>) (<xref rid="pone.0145774.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). NPC cases also had an over-representation of common genic deletions compared to controls (Case/control ratio = 2.26, <italic>P</italic> = 0.03). There were however no significant difference between cases and controls in terms of rare CNV (CNV<sub>freq</sub>&#x0003c;1%) rate and gene enrichment.</p><table-wrap id="pone.0145774.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0145774.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Global CNV burden in NPC patients and healthy controls.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0145774.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0145774.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Rate<xref rid="t001fn001" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Gene count (GRate)<xref rid="t001fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Gene count (GRich)<xref rid="t001fn003" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref></th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case/control ratio</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>-value<xref rid="t001fn004" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case/control ratio</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>-value<xref rid="t001fn004" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case/control ratio</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>-value<xref rid="t001fn004" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Types</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Deletion</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8421</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9432</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9967</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5112</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2589</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0310<xref rid="t001fn005" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Amplification</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2225</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0029<xref rid="t001fn006" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9426</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.677</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3646</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2043</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" align="left" rowspan="1">Size</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" align="left" rowspan="1">&#x0003c;100kb</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;Deletion</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8849</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9945</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2726</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8394</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.8430</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0085<xref rid="t001fn006" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;Amplification</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3108</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0022<xref rid="t001fn006" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2394</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0816</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2736</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1975</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" align="left" rowspan="1">&#x02265;100kb</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;Deletion</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7314</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9874</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8658</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7288</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0636</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3843</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;Amplification</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1217</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1739</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8587</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8292</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1051</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2074</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Rare</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9120</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8867</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9924</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5443</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5081</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1318</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Common</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9967</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5326</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.9612</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4x10<sup>-05</sup><xref rid="t001fn007" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.6200</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0007<xref rid="t001fn007" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t001fn001"><p><sup>a</sup>Rate: Number of CNVs per individual</p></fn><fn id="t001fn002"><p><sup>b</sup>Gene count (GRate): Number of genes spanned by CNVs per individual</p></fn><fn id="t001fn003"><p><sup>c</sup>Gene count (GRich): Number of genes per total CNV kb</p></fn><fn id="t001fn004"><p><sup>d</sup><italic>P</italic>-value: Based on comparison between cases and controls, one-sided, permuted 100,000 times</p></fn><fn id="t001fn005"><p>*0.01&#x0003c;<italic>P</italic>-value&#x0003c;0.05</p></fn><fn id="t001fn006"><p>**10<sup>&#x02212;04</sup>&#x0003c;<italic>P</italic>-value&#x0003c;0.01</p></fn><fn id="t001fn007"><p>***<italic>P</italic>-value&#x0003c;10<sup>&#x02212;04</sup></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec018"><title>CNVRs associated to NPC susceptibility and pathway enrichment</title><p>We focused on consensus CNVs called from both PennCNV and cnvPartition calling algorithms. From the consensus CNVRs, we selected regions overlapping genes and genomic regions previously linked to NPC and other cancers. We also checked for genes differentially expressed in NPC tissue specimens compared to normal nasopharyngeal tissue [<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0145774.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Six candidate CNVRs fulfilling the selection criteria were presented in <xref rid="pone.0145774.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. Further qPCR validation was done on CNVR 11q14.3 and 6p21.3 and <xref rid="pone.0145774.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref> provided showed example LRR and BAF in these CNVs. LRR and BAF from SNP data within CNVs in chromosome 6 (<xref rid="pone.0145774.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Text</xref>) and chromosome 11 (<xref rid="pone.0145774.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Text</xref>) can be found in the supporting information. Concordance rate between CNV calls generated from calling algorithms and qPCR was shown in <xref rid="pone.0145774.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>. As shown in <xref rid="pone.0145774.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>, PennCNV calls had higher concordance for both CNVRs on chromosome 6p21.3 (99.75%) and 11q14.3 (91.67%). Taqman genotyping of CNVRs 11q14.3 and 6p21.3 confirmed suggestive association in the Malaysian Chinese discovery cohort (<italic>P</italic><sub>11q14.3_Discovery</sub> = 4.60x10<sup>-3</sup>; <italic>P</italic><sub>6p21.3 Discovery</sub> = 0.051) (<xref rid="pone.0145774.t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). CNVRs 11q14.3 and 6p21.3 were selected for further replication in a separate Malaysian Chinese (465 cases and 677 controls) and Malaysian Malay (114 cases and 124 controls) replication cohort.</p><fig id="pone.0145774.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0145774.g002</object-id><label>Fig 2</label><caption><title>An illustration of B allele frequency, Log R ratio, and CNV value for CNVs at chromosome 6p21.3 (left) and 11q14.3 (right) generated from GenomeStudio (v.3.1.6).</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0145774.g002"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone.0145774.t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0145774.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>List of most significantly associated candidate CNVRs identified from GWAS cohort.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0145774.t002g" xlink:href="pone.0145774.t002"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cytoband</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Risk allele</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intersecting genes</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Potential function in cancer</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CNV from Database of Genomic Variants</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Previous studies (Association to cancer/ NPC)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Previous studies (Differential expression in NPC tissue)<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chromosome 11q14.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amp</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>GRM5</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glutamatergic signalling has been shown to stimulate proliferation and migration of tumour cell lines.[<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">- Implicated in melanoma,[<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>] oral squamous cell carcinoma[<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Upregulated</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chromosome 6p21.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Del</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>MICA</italic>, <italic>HCP5</italic>, <italic>HCG26</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cytolytic responses of T cells and NK cells against MICA-expressing tumour cells were activated when NKG2D binds with MICA.[<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">- CNV association with several NPC study cohort[<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0145774.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No differential expression for all genes.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chromosome 19q13.42</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Del</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>LILRB3</italic>, <italic>LILRA6</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B cell receptor signalling.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">- CNV associated to NPC in NPC Taiwan genome-wide study cohort[<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No differential expression</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chromosome 12q14.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amp</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>DPY19L2</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">- Loss of heterozygosity associated with lung adenocarcinoma[<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No differential expression</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chromosome 5p13.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amp</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>GOLPH3</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vesicular trafficking.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">- Associated with various cancers e.g. lung cancer,[<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>] prostate cancer,[<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>] gastric cancer [<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No differential expression</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chromosome 14q11.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Del</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>RNase3</italic>, <italic>RNase2</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ribonuclease family</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">- Associated with pancreatic cancer[<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Downregulated</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t002fn001"><p>Amp (Amplification); Del (Deletion); <italic>GRM5</italic> (Metabotropic glutamate receptor 5); <italic>MICA</italic> (MHC class I polypeptide-related sequence A); <italic>HCP5</italic> (HLA complex 5); <italic>HCG26</italic> (HLA complex group 26); <italic>LILRB3</italic> (Leukocyte immunoglobulin-like receptor subfamily B member 3); <italic>LILRA6</italic> (Leukocyte immunoglobulin-like receptor subfamily A member 6; <italic>DPY19L2</italic> (Dpy-19-like protein 2); <italic>GOLPH3</italic> (Golgi phosphoprotein 3); <italic>RNase3</italic> (Ribonuclease, RNase A family, 3); <italic>RNase2</italic> (Ribonuclease, RNase A family, 2).</p></fn><fn id="t002fn002"><p><sup>a</sup> Differential expression data was extracted from Dodd <italic>et al</italic>.[<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] MSigDB v4.0[<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>] curated gene sets.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone.0145774.t003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0145774.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Results from multiple CNV calling algorithms and qPCR validation of CNVRs on chromosome 6p21.3 and chromosome 11q14.3.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0145774.t003g" xlink:href="pone.0145774.t003"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cytoband</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Risk allele</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CNV calling algorithm</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CNVR boundaries</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Concordance rate with qPCR</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genes overlapped</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr 6p21.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CN = 1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PennCNV</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr6:31468233&#x02013;31562343</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.75%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>MICA</italic>, <italic>HCP5</italic>, <italic>HCG26</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cnvPartition</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr6:31468233&#x02013;31571696</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.50%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr 11q14.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CN = 3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PennCNV</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr11:88309000&#x02013;88433828</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.67%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>GRM5</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cnvPartition</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr11:88336310&#x02013;88433828</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.15%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t003fn001"><p><italic>MICA</italic> (MHC class I polypeptide-related sequence A); <italic>HCP5</italic> (HLA complex 5); <italic>HCG26</italic> (HLA complex group 26); <italic>GRM5</italic> (Metabotropic glutamate receptor 5)</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone.0145774.t004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0145774.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Association of CNVRs on chromosome11q14.3 and chromosome 6p21.3 with susceptibility in discovery and validation cohorts of Malaysian Chinese.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0145774.t004g" xlink:href="pone.0145774.t004"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" align="center" colspan="1">CNVR genomic position</th><th colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1">Discovery cohort<xref rid="t004fn001" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></th><th colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1">Malaysian Chinese replication cohort</th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Combined</th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case (%) n = 140</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control (%) n = 256</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>-value</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95% CI)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case (%) n = 465</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control (%) n = 677</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>-value</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95% CI)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>-value</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95% CI)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr6p21.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (5.00)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (1.17)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.051</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.84 (0.99&#x02013;34.49)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (3.00)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (1.18)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.74 (1.36&#x02013;10.31)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.29x10<sup>-3</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.21 (1.75&#x02013;10.11)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr11q14.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (10.71)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.39)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6x10<sup>-3</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.59 (2.78&#x02013;274.50)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (4.2)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (1.18)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6x10<sup>-3</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.79 (1.73&#x02013;13.30)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.54x10<sup>-5</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.27 (2.96&#x02013;17.88)</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t004fn001"><p><sup>a</sup> Results are based on CNV calls from genome-wide genotyping data after validation with qPCR.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>From our combined analysis, CNVR on chromosome 11q14.3 showed the strongest association to NPC susceptibility in our Malaysian Chinese cohort (<italic>P</italic><sub>combined</sub> = 1.54x10<sup>-5</sup>; OR = 7.27; 95% CI = 2.96&#x02013;17.88) (<xref rid="pone.0145774.t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). In our study, the most common recurrent CNVs at chromosome 11q14.3 were hg18 chr11:88,336,310&#x02013;88,384,073 (8 cases) and hg18 chr11: 88,336,310&#x02013;88,387,195 (6 cases) (<xref rid="pone.0145774.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>). CNVR 11q14.3 was however not associated to NPC susceptibility in the Malaysian Malay cohort (<italic>P</italic> = 0.99; OR = 10.14; 95% CI = 0.54&#x02013;190.47) (<xref rid="pone.0145774.t005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>). Heterogeneity test done between discovery and Malaysian Chinese validation cohorts using GWAMA v.1.4 provided <italic>I</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup> value of 0.7. <italic>I</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup> value was 0.7 between discovery and validation cohort of Malaysian Chinese, however the association of CNV 11q14.3 for both discovery (p-value = 4.6x10<sup>-3</sup>) and validation cohorts (p-value = 2.60x10<sup>-3</sup>) were significant and consistent in direction.</p><fig id="pone.0145774.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0145774.g003</object-id><label>Fig 3</label><caption><title>Schematic representation of the genomic organization according to the human genome hg18 at chromosome 11q14.3 with the positions of CNVs called in the region and reported CNVs in the vicinity found in the Database of Genomic Variants, accessed by July 2015.</title><p>Blue bars represent gains identified by other studies that were deposited in the database while red bars represent losses. Brown bars depict CNVs with both losses and gains documented.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0145774.g003"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone.0145774.t005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0145774.t005</object-id><label>Table 5</label><caption><title>Association of CNVRs on chromosome11q14.3 and chromosome 6q21.33 with susceptibility in Malaysian Malay replication cohort.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0145774.t005g" xlink:href="pone.0145774.t005"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" align="center" colspan="1">CNVR genomic position</th><th colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1">Malaysian Malay replication cohort</th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case (%) n = 114</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control (%) n = 124</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>-value</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95% CI)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr6p21.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (5.26)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (3.23)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.10 (0.48&#x02013;9.28)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr11q14.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (3.51)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.14 (0.54&#x02013;190.47)</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>The combined association of CNVR on chromosome 6p21.3 was more modest in the Malaysian Chinese cohort (<italic>P</italic><sub>combined</sub> = 1.29x10<sup>-3</sup>; OR = 4.21; 95% CI = 1.75&#x02013;10.11) (<xref rid="pone.0145774.t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>) (<xref rid="pone.0145774.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4</xref>). From our results, we observed that carriers of the 6p21.3 deletion also carried the <italic>HLA-B*4801</italic> (8/10) or <italic>HLA-C*0801</italic> (8/10) allele (<xref rid="pone.0145774.t006" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>). CNVR 6p21.3 was not associated with NPC susceptibility in the Malay cohort (<italic>P</italic> = 0.32) (<xref rid="pone.0145774.t005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>).</p><fig id="pone.0145774.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0145774.g004</object-id><label>Fig 4</label><caption><title>Schematic representation of the genomic organization according to the human genome hg18 at chromosome 6p21.3 with the positions of CNVs called in the region and reported CNVs in the vicinity found in the Database of Genomic Variants, accessed by July 2015.</title><p>Blue bars represent gains identified by other studies that were deposited in the database while red bars represent losses. Brown bars depict CNVs with both losses and gains documented.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0145774.g004"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone.0145774.t006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0145774.t006</object-id><label>Table 6</label><caption><title><italic>HLA-A</italic>, <italic>HLA-B</italic>, and HLA-C alleles of samples with heterozygous deleted <italic>MICA</italic> from HLA imputation software SNP2HLA.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0145774.t006g" xlink:href="pone.0145774.t006"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sample ID</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>MICA</italic> copy number</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HLA-A allele</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HLA-B allele</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HLA-C allele</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E19_case1_C01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0201/1101</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4001/4801</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0304/0702</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E19_case1_C09</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1101/1101</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1301/1502</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0801/0801</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E19_case1_D04</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0207/2402</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4601/4801</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0102/0801</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E19_case1_D08</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0206/2402</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1501/4801</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0401/0801</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E19_case1_E11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0203/2402</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4801/5101</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0801/1402</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E19_case2_D07</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1101/2402</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4002/4801</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0702/0801</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E19_case2_G03</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0201/0207</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4601/4801</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0102/0801</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E19_cont2_G01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1101/2601</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3901/4801</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0702/0801</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E19_cont2_G03</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0201/0203</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4001/4601</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0102/0702</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E19_cont3_D10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0206/1101</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4801/5401</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0102/0801</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>The CNVR 11q14.3 and 6p21.3 copy numbers identified through Taqman qPCR were highly concordant with digital PCR copy numbers though comparison of CNV copy numbers was limited to only 10 random samples.</p><p>The CNVs were subjected to pathway enrichment using a gene set-enrichment method [<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] implemented in PLINK v1.07. The ERK1/ERK2-MAPK pathway and NOTCH Signaling pathway were identified and deemed to be significantly enriched (<italic>P</italic><sub>ERK-MAPK</sub> = 7.00x10<sup>-4</sup>; P<sub>Notch</sub> = 8.30x10<sup>-3</sup>) (<xref rid="pone.0145774.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5</xref>) (<xref rid="pone.0145774.t007" ref-type="table">Table 7</xref>).</p><fig id="pone.0145774.g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0145774.g005</object-id><label>Fig 5</label><caption><title>-Log<sub>10</sub> of one-tailed empirical p-values from pathway enrichment analysis implemented using PLINK v.1.07 <italic>cnv-enrichment-test</italic>.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0145774.g005"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone.0145774.t007" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0145774.t007</object-id><label>Table 7</label><caption><title>p-values of gene-set enrichment analysis for five pathways previously associated to nasopharyngeal carcinoma.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0145774.t007g" xlink:href="pone.0145774.t007"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pathway</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genes</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KEGG WNT signalling pathway</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>JUN</italic>, <italic>LRP5</italic>, <italic>LRP6</italic>, <italic>PPP3R2</italic>, <italic>SFRP2</italic>, <italic>SFRP1</italic>, <italic>PPP3CC</italic>, <italic>VANGL1</italic>, <italic>PPP3R1</italic>, <italic>FZD1</italic>, <italic>FZD4</italic>, <italic>APC2</italic>, <italic>FZD6</italic>, <italic>FZD7</italic>, <italic>SENP2</italic>, <italic>FZD8</italic>, <italic>LEF1</italic>, <italic>CREBBP</italic>, <italic>FZD9</italic>, <italic>PRICKLE1</italic>, <italic>CTBP2</italic>, <italic>ROCK1</italic>, <italic>CTBP1</italic>, <italic>WNT9B</italic>, <italic>WNT9A</italic>, <italic>CTNNBIP1</italic>, <italic>DAAM2</italic>, <italic>TBL1XR1</italic>, <italic>MMP7</italic>, <italic>CER1</italic>, <italic>MAP3K7</italic>, <italic>VANGL2</italic>, <italic>WNT2B</italic>, <italic>WNT11</italic>, <italic>WNT10B</italic>, <italic>DKK2</italic>, <italic>LOC728622</italic>, <italic>CHP2</italic>, <italic>AXIN1</italic>, <italic>AXIN2</italic>, <italic>DKK4</italic>, <italic>NFAT5</italic>, <italic>MYC</italic>, <italic>SOX17</italic>, <italic>CSNK2A1</italic>, <italic>CSNK2A2</italic>, <italic>NFATC4</italic>, <italic>CSNK1A1</italic>, <italic>NFATC3</italic>, <italic>CSNK1E</italic>, <italic>BTRC</italic>, <italic>PRKX</italic>, <italic>SKP1</italic>, <italic>FBXW11</italic>, <italic>RBX1</italic>, <italic>CSNK2B</italic>, <italic>SIAH1</italic>, <italic>TBL1Y</italic>, <italic>WNT5B</italic>, <italic>CCND1</italic>, <italic>CAMK2A</italic>, <italic>NLK</italic>, <italic>CAMK2B</italic>, <italic>CAMK2D</italic>, <italic>CAMK2G</italic>, <italic>PRKACA</italic>, <italic>APC</italic>, <italic>PRKACB</italic>, <italic>PRKACG</italic>, <italic>WNT16</italic>, <italic>DAAM1</italic>, <italic>CHD8</italic>, <italic>FRAT1</italic>, <italic>CACYBP</italic>, <italic>CCND2</italic>, <italic>NFATC2</italic>, <italic>NFATC1</italic>, <italic>CCND3</italic>, <italic>PLCB2</italic>, <italic>PLCB1</italic>, <italic>CSNK1A1L</italic>, <italic>PRKCB</italic>, <italic>PLCB3</italic>, <italic>PRKCA</italic>, <italic>PLCB4</italic>, <italic>WIF1</italic>, <italic>PRICKLE2</italic>, <italic>PORCN</italic>, <italic>RHOA</italic>, <italic>FRAT2</italic>, <italic>PRKCG</italic>, <italic>MAPK9</italic>, <italic>MAPK10</italic>, <italic>WNT3A</italic>, <italic>DVL3</italic>, <italic>RAC2</italic>, <italic>DVL2</italic>, <italic>RAC3</italic>, <italic>FZD3</italic>, <italic>DKK1</italic>, <italic>CXXC4</italic>, <italic>DVL1</italic>, <italic>FOSL1</italic>, <italic>CUL1</italic>, <italic>WNT10A</italic>, <italic>WNT4</italic>, <italic>SMAD3</italic>, <italic>TCF7</italic>, <italic>SMAD4</italic>, <italic>RAC1</italic>, <italic>TCF7L2</italic>, <italic>SMAD2</italic>, <italic>WNT1</italic>, <italic>MAPK8</italic>, <italic>EP300</italic>, <italic>WNT7A</italic>, <italic>GSK3B</italic>, <italic>WNT7B</italic>, <italic>PSEN1</italic>, <italic>WNT8A</italic>, <italic>WNT8B</italic>, <italic>WNT2</italic>, <italic>WNT3</italic>, <italic>WNT5A</italic>, <italic>WNT6</italic>, <italic>CTNNB1</italic>, <italic>PPP2CB</italic>, <italic>PPP2CA</italic>, <italic>PPP2R1A</italic>, <italic>TBL1X</italic>, <italic>PPP2R1B</italic>, <italic>ROCK2</italic>, <italic>NKD1</italic>, <italic>FZD10</italic>, <italic>FZD5</italic>, <italic>NKD2</italic>, <italic>TCF7L1</italic>, <italic>RUVBL1</italic>, <italic>PPARD</italic>, <italic>PPP3CB</italic>, <italic>TP53</italic>, <italic>PPP3CA</italic>, <italic>PPP2R5A</italic>, <italic>PPP2R5E</italic>, <italic>PPP2R5D</italic>, <italic>PPP2R5C</italic>, <italic>PPP2R5B</italic>, <italic>FZD2</italic>, <italic>SFRP5</italic>, <italic>SFRP4</italic>, <italic>CHP</italic></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1283</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ST ERK1 ERK2 MAPK pathway</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>SOS1</italic>, <italic>RPS6KA3</italic>, <italic>TRAF3</italic>, <italic>CREB3</italic>, <italic>MAPK3</italic>, <italic>EIF4E</italic>, <italic>SOS2</italic>, <italic>MAP3K8</italic>, <italic>RPS6KA2</italic>, <italic>EEF2K</italic>, <italic>CREB5</italic>, <italic>MAP2K1</italic>, <italic>SHC1</italic>, <italic>KLF6</italic>, <italic>RAP1A</italic>, <italic>ARAF</italic>, <italic>DUSP4</italic>, <italic>MKNK1</italic>, <italic>GRB2</italic>, <italic>DUSP9</italic>, <italic>BRAF</italic>, <italic>KAT5</italic>, <italic>MKNK2</italic>, <italic>BAD</italic>, <italic>MAP2K2</italic>, <italic>ATF1</italic>, <italic>NFKB1</italic>, <italic>CREB1</italic>, <italic>RPS6KA1</italic>, <italic>MAPK1</italic>, <italic>MOS</italic>, <italic>DUSP6</italic></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0007</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KEGG NOTCH signalling pathway</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>HES5</italic>, <italic>DTX3</italic>, <italic>NOTCH4</italic>, <italic>DTX3L</italic>, <italic>NOTCH3</italic>, <italic>NOTCH2</italic>, <italic>EP300</italic>, <italic>HES1</italic>, <italic>NOTCH1</italic>, <italic>NUMB</italic>, <italic>PSEN2</italic>, <italic>PSEN1</italic>, <italic>PTCRA</italic>,<italic>SNW1</italic>, <italic>APH1A</italic>, <italic>KAT2A</italic>, <italic>ADAM17</italic>, <italic>RFNG</italic>, <italic>RBPJ</italic>, <italic>DTX1</italic>, <italic>CREBBP</italic>, <italic>DTX2</italic>, <italic>MAML1</italic>, <italic>CTBP2</italic>, <italic>NCOR2</italic>, <italic>CTBP1</italic>, <italic>DVL3</italic>, <italic>JAG2</italic>, <italic>DVL2</italic>, <italic>NUMBL</italic>, <italic>MAML2</italic>, <italic>KAT2B</italic>, <italic>DLL4</italic>, <italic>PSENEN</italic>, <italic>DLL3</italic>, <italic>DVL1</italic>, <italic>CIR1</italic>, <italic>DLL1</italic>, <italic>LFNG</italic>, <italic>JAG1</italic>, <italic>MAML3</italic>, <italic>HDAC1</italic>, <italic>HDAC2</italic>, <italic>NCSTN</italic>, <italic>DTX4</italic>, <italic>MFNG</italic>, <italic>RBPJL</italic></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0083</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">REACTOME regulation of apoptosis</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>PSMD14</italic>, <italic>PSMA8</italic>, <italic>DAPK1</italic>, <italic>DAPK3</italic>, <italic>DCC</italic>, <italic>UNC5B</italic>, <italic>PSME4</italic>, <italic>DAPK2</italic>, <italic>APPL1</italic>, <italic>PAK2</italic>, <italic>PSMA1</italic>, <italic>PSMA2</italic>, <italic>PSMA3</italic>, <italic>PSMA4</italic>, <italic>PSMA5</italic>, <italic>PSMA6</italic>, <italic>PSMA7</italic>, <italic>PSMB1</italic>, <italic>PSMB2</italic>, <italic>PSMB3</italic>, <italic>PSMB4</italic>, <italic>PSMB5</italic>, <italic>PSMB6</italic>, <italic>PSMB7</italic>, <italic>PSMB8</italic>, <italic>PSMB9</italic>, <italic>PSMB10</italic>, <italic>PSMC1</italic>, <italic>PSMC2</italic>, <italic>PSMC3</italic>, <italic>PSMC4</italic>, <italic>PSMC5</italic>, <italic>PSMC6</italic>, <italic>PSMD1</italic>, <italic>PSMD2</italic>, <italic>PSMD3</italic>, <italic>PSMD4</italic>, <italic>PSMD5</italic>, <italic>PSMD7</italic>, <italic>PSMD8</italic>, <italic>PSMD9</italic>, <italic>PSMD10</italic>, <italic>PSMD11</italic>, <italic>PSMD12</italic>, <italic>PSMD13</italic>, <italic>PSME1</italic>, <italic>PSME2</italic>, <italic>RPS27A</italic>, <italic>LOC652826</italic>, <italic>RPS27AP11</italic>, <italic>UBA52</italic>, <italic>ARHGAP10</italic>, <italic>CASP3</italic>, <italic>CASP9</italic>, <italic>UNC5A</italic>, <italic>PSMF1</italic>, <italic>MAGED1</italic>, <italic>PSMD6</italic></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0670</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">REACTOME regulation of EGFR in cancer</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>AKT3</italic>, <italic>ADAM10</italic>, <italic>SPRY1</italic>, <italic>SPRY2</italic>, <italic>STAM2</italic>, <italic>CDKN1A</italic>, <italic>CDKN1B</italic>, <italic>ADCY1</italic>, <italic>ADCY2</italic>, <italic>ADCY3</italic>, <italic>ADCY5</italic>, <italic>CDC37</italic>, <italic>ADCY6</italic>, <italic>ADCY7</italic>, <italic>ADCY8</italic>, <italic>CHUK</italic>, <italic>ADCY9</italic>, <italic>THEM4</italic>, <italic>AP2M1</italic>, <italic>AP2S1</italic>, <italic>CLTA</italic>, <italic>CLTC</italic>, <italic>CREB1</italic>, <italic>CSK</italic>, <italic>ADRBK1</italic>, <italic>AP2A1</italic>, <italic>AP2A2</italic>, <italic>AP2B1</italic>, <italic>EGF</italic>, <italic>EGFR</italic>, <italic>ADCY4</italic>, <italic>EPS15</italic>, <italic>AKT1</italic>, <italic>AKT2</italic>, <italic>FOXO1</italic>, <italic>FOXO3</italic>, <italic>PHLPP1</italic>, <italic>MTOR</italic>, <italic>RICTOR</italic>, <italic>GAB1</italic>, <italic>LRIG1</italic>, <italic>GRB2</italic>, <italic>GSK3A</italic>, <italic>EPN1</italic>, <italic>SH3KBP1</italic>, <italic>NR4A1</italic>, <italic>HRAS</italic>, <italic>HSP90AA1</italic>, <italic>ITPR2</italic>, <italic>ITPR3</italic>, <italic>KRAS</italic>, <italic>MDM2</italic>. <italic>FOXO4</italic>, <italic>NRAS</italic>, <italic>PDE1A</italic>, <italic>PDE1B</italic>, <italic>PDPK1</italic>, <italic>PIK3CA</italic>, <italic>PIK3R1</italic>, <italic>PLCG1</italic>, <italic>PRKACA</italic>, <italic>PRKACB</italic>, <italic>PRKACG</italic>, <italic>PRKAR1A</italic>, <italic>PRKAR1B</italic>, <italic>PRKAR2A</italic>, <italic>PRKAR2B</italic>, <italic>PRKCA</italic>, <italic>PRKCD</italic>, <italic>PRKCE</italic>, <italic>PRKCG</italic>, <italic>PAG1</italic>, <italic>MAPK1</italic>, <italic>MAPK3</italic>, <italic>MAP2K1</italic>, <italic>MAP2K2</italic>, <italic>BAD</italic>, <italic>PTEN</italic>, <italic>TRIB3</italic>, <italic>EPS15L1</italic>, <italic>RAF1</italic>, <italic>RPS6KB2</italic>, <italic>RPS27A</italic>, <italic>MLST8 SH3GL2</italic>, <italic>SHC1</italic>, <italic>SOS1</italic>, <italic>SRC</italic>, <italic>ADAM17</italic>, <italic>TSC2</italic>, <italic>RPS27AP11</italic>, <italic>LOC729120</italic>, <italic>LOC730418</italic>, <italic>UBA52</italic>, <italic>LOC731292</italic>, <italic>YWHAB</italic>, <italic>MAPKAP1</italic>, <italic>CALM1</italic>, <italic>STAM</italic>, <italic>ADAM12</italic>, <italic>CALM2</italic>, <italic>CALM3</italic>, <italic>CAMK4</italic>, <italic>CASP9</italic>, <italic>AKT1S1</italic>, <italic>CBL</italic>, <italic>HGS</italic>, <italic>CDK1</italic>, <italic>CDC42</italic></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9891</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec019"><title>Discussion</title><p>Common CNVs have been associated with predisposition to cancers such as neuroblastoma [<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] and breast cancer [<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. The over-representation of common deletion genic CNVs in cases as compared to controls (Case/control ratio = 2.26, p-value = 0.03) could potentially bring about deleterious and pathogenic consequences that would lead to susceptibility to NPC. No previous studies on global CNV burden analysis were reported in NPC.</p><p>The most significantly associated CNVR from our study was within the metabotropic glutamate receptor 5 (<italic>GRM5</italic>) gene, suggesting its potential role in NPC pathogenesis. <italic>GRM5</italic> gene (approximately 563kbp) located on the minus strand of chromosome 11q14.3 encodes a group I Gq-coupled receptor. Alternative 5' splicing and usage of multiple promoters were involved in the regulatory mechanisms of GRM5 expression [<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Evidence from studies suggests a role for glutamatergic signalling in the biology of cancer in peripheral tissues [<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0145774.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], especially those of mucosal nature. Different groups have also shown evidence for a role of glutamate and its receptors in regulation of tumour growth [<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Examples of metabotropic glutamate receptors being implicated in development of cancers are the involvement of GRM1 [<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] and GRM5 [<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>] in the induction of melanoma in transgenic mice. In addition, GRM5 was found to play a role in tumour cell migration and invasion in oral squamous cell carcinoma [<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>] and found to be overexpressed in lung cancer cells [<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>].</p><p>Deletion on chromosome 6p21.3 which overlaps MHC Class I Polypeptide-Related Sequence A (<italic>MICA)</italic>, HLA complex 5 (<italic>HCP5</italic>) and HLA complex group 26 <italic>(HCG26</italic>) genes was previously associated to NPC predisposition. <italic>MICA</italic> encodes a ligand for the natural killer-cell receptor NKG2-D type II. MICA is highly expressed on cancer cells and can activate antitumor effects from natural killer cells and CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells [<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Meanwhile the function of HLA complex P5, <italic>HCP5</italic> is not fully understood.</p><p>The <italic>MICA/HCP5</italic> region has been linked to NPC susceptibility and HCV-associated hepatocellular carcinoma [<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0145774.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. <italic>MICA-STR</italic> has been implicated in NPC predisposition among male Southern Chinese Han population [<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. The frequency of the deletion in our results from combined Chinese cases and controls was 0.02, similar to the frequency reported by Tse <italic>et al</italic>., 2011. In addition, we also found similar results in which deleted <italic>MICA</italic> gene was frequently found in the <italic>HLA-B48</italic> (<italic>B*4801</italic>) associated haplotype in a Japanese study cohort [<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. They found 62.5% (5/8) of their samples with homozygous <italic>HLA-B*4801</italic> allele lack intact <italic>MICA</italic> gene while we found 53.55% (8/15) of our samples with single copy of <italic>HLA-B*4801</italic> allele (HLA allele imputation results) had one copy number for <italic>MICA</italic> gene. The concordance rate between the results from <italic>HLA</italic> allele imputation software and previous genotyping results of <italic>HLA-A</italic> allele in our laboratory [<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>] was 98.52%.</p><p>CNVs identified from our study were enriched for ERK1/2 and Notch signalling pathways. Mutations in GRM5 influenced Ca<sup>2+</sup> oscillations in transgenic mice that showed tumour/melanoma phenotype in addition to dramatic increase in phosphorylation of ERK in these tumour samples. They had implicated ERK as a downstream effector of GRM5 signalling in tumours. The possible role of ERK pathway in NPC pathogenesis had also been corroborated by Lan <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref rid="pone.0145774.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Further studies are needed to better understand the dynamics and interaction of GRM5 within the ERK pathway and its role in NPC.</p><p>We report the association of CNV 11q14.3 and 6p21.3 as well as the ERK1/2 and Notch signalling pathways with NPC susceptibility in the Malaysian Chinese cohort using a case control genome-wide SNP microarray approach. The caveat attached to SNP microarray CNV detection remains the diverse algorithmic calling methods, resulting in considerable variation in the CNV calls. We have employed extensive validation and replication using Taqman real-time PCR and a further more sensitive digital PCR method to negate false CNV calls for CNVs 11q14.3 and 6p21.3. Our study was able to detect association of CNV 11q14.3 and 6p21.3 in the Malaysian Chinese cohort but not in the Malaysian Malay cohort. However power analysis showed that power for CNV study for Malay replication cohort at 11q14.3 and 6p21.3 is 0.26 and 0.11 respectively, hence a larger sample size would be needed to improve the achieved power for better confidence. To increase reproducibility and confidence in our association, replication efforts with new NPC cohorts will aid to confirm the link between CNV 11q14.3 and 6p21.3 and NPC.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec020"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0145774.s001"><label>S1 Table</label><caption><title>Basic characteristics of Malaysian Chinese NPC patients and healthy controls in the study.</title><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0145774.s001.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0145774.s002"><label>S2 Table</label><caption><title>Basic characteristics of Malaysian Malay NPC patients and healthy controls in the study.</title><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0145774.s002.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0145774.s003"><label>S1 Text</label><caption><title>Log R ratio and B allele frequency of SNPs involved in CNVR on chromosome 6.</title><p>(TXT)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0145774.s003.txt"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0145774.s004"><label>S2 Text</label><caption><title>Log R ratio and B allele frequency of SNPs involved in CNVR on chromosome 11.</title><p>(TXT)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0145774.s004.txt"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors would like to thank the Director General of Health, Ministry of Health of Malaysia for his permission to publish this article, and the Director of the IMR for his support. We would like to thank the Malaysian NPC Study Group: <bold>Hospital Pulau Pinang-</bold> K.C. Pua (Project Leader), S. Subathra, N. Punithavati, B.S. Tan, Y.S. Ee, L.M. Ong, R.A. Hamid, M. Goh, J.C.T. Quah, J. Lim;, <bold>Hospital Kuala Lumpur/Universiti Putra Malaysia-</bold> Y.Y. Yap, B.D. Dipak, R. Deepak, F.N. Lau, P.V. Kam, S. Shri Devi;, <bold>Queen Elizabeth Hospital-</bold> C.A. Ong, C.L. Lum, Ahmad N.A., Halimuddin S., M. Somasundran, A. Kam, M. Wodjin; <bold>Sarawak General Hospital/ Universiti Malaysia Sarawak-</bold> S.K. Subramaniam, T.S. Tiong, T.Y. Tan, U.H. Sim, T.W. Tharumalingam, D. Norlida, M. Zulkarnaen, W.H. Lai; <bold>University of Malaya-</bold> G. Gopala Krishnan, C.C. Ng, A.Z. Bustam, S. Marniza, P. Shahfinaz, O. Hashim, S. Shamshinder, N. Prepageran, L.M. Looi, O. Rahmat, J. Amin, J. Maznan; <bold>Hospital Universiti Sains Malaysia-</bold> S. Hassan, B. Biswal; <bold>Cancer Research Initiatives Foundation-</bold> S.H. Teo, L.F. Yap; <bold>Institute for Medical Research-</bold> A.S.B. Khoo (Program Leader), A. Munirah, A. Subasri, L.P. Tan, N.M. Kumaran, M.S. Nurul Ashikin, M.S. Nursyazwani, B. Norhasimah, R. Sasela Devi, S. Shri Devi, C.Y. Koh. We also extend our gratitude to all the participants of this study, staff of the Department of Otorhinolaryngology, UMMC and staff of the Blood Bank, UMMC.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0145774.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hepeng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Zeng Yi profile. A controversial bid to thwart the 'Cantonese cancer'</article-title>. <source>Science (New York, NY)</source>
<volume>321</volume>: <fpage>1154</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1155</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>You</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>He</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Nasopharyngeal carcinoma&#x02014;review of the molecular mechanisms of tumorigenesis</article-title>. <source>Head &#x00026; neck</source>
<volume>30</volume>: <fpage>946</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>963</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18446839</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kutty</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dharmalingam</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name> (<year>1974</year>) <article-title>Incidence of nasopharyngeal carcinoma in Malaysia, with special reference to the state of Selangor</article-title>. <source>British journal of cancer</source>
<volume>30</volume>: <fpage>86</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>94</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4413823</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>McCredie</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Coates</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Cancer mortality in East and Southeast Asian migrants to New South Wales, Australia, 1975&#x02013;1995</article-title>. <source>British journal of cancer</source>
<volume>79</volume>: <fpage>1277</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1282</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10098772</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>YX</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>XJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>LX</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Complex segregation analysis of nasopharyngeal carcinoma in Guangdong, China: evidence for a multifactorial mode of inheritance (complex segregation analysis of NPC in China)</article-title>. <source>European journal of human genetics: EJHG</source>
<volume>13</volume>: <fpage>248</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>252</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15483644</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Imrey</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lye</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Nasopharyngeal carcinoma in Malaysian Chinese: occupational exposures to particles, formaldehyde and heat</article-title>. <source>International journal of epidemiology</source>
<volume>29</volume>: <fpage>991</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>998</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11101539</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gallicchio</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Matanoski</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>XG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Adulthood consumption of preserved and nonpreserved vegetables and the risk of nasopharyngeal carcinoma: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>International journal of cancer Journal international du cancer</source>
<volume>119</volume>: <fpage>1125</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1135</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16570274</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Simons</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wee</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Day</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shanmugaratnam</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>De-The</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name> (<year>1974</year>) <article-title>Immunogenetic aspects of nasopharyngeal carcinoma: I. Differences in HL-A antigen profiles between patients and control groups</article-title>. <source>International journal of cancer Journal international du cancer</source>
<volume>13</volume>: <fpage>122</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>134</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4131857</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bei</surname><given-names>JX</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>LZ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>A genome-wide association study of nasopharyngeal carcinoma identifies three new susceptibility loci</article-title>. <source>Nature genetics</source>
<volume>42</volume>: <fpage>599</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>603</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ng.601">10.1038/ng.601</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20512145</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Day</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kunaratnam</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chia</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Simons</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>1983</year>) <article-title>HLA and nasopharyngeal carcinoma in Chinese&#x02014;a further study</article-title>. <source>International journal of cancer Journal international du cancer</source>
<volume>32</volume>: <fpage>171</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>176</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6874140</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tse</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tsang</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Genome-wide association study reveals multiple nasopharyngeal carcinoma-associated loci within the HLA region at chromosome 6p21.3</article-title>. <source>American journal of human genetics</source>
<volume>85</volume>: <fpage>194</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>203</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ajhg.2009.07.007">10.1016/j.ajhg.2009.07.007</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19664746</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hildesheim</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mittl</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Nasopharyngeal carcinoma and genetic polymorphisms of DNA repair enzymes XRCC1 and hOGG1</article-title>. <source>Cancer epidemiology, biomarkers &#x00026; prevention: a publication of the American Association for Cancer Research, cosponsored by the American Society of Preventive Oncology</source>
<volume>12</volume>: <fpage>1100</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1104</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>A susceptibility locus at chromosome 3p21 linked to familial nasopharyngeal carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Cancer research</source>
<volume>64</volume>: <fpage>1972</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1974</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15026332</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tse</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tsang</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>A gender-specific association of CNV at 6p21.3 with NPC susceptibility</article-title>. <source>Human molecular genetics</source>
<volume>20</volume>: <fpage>2889</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2896</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/hmg/ddr191">10.1093/hmg/ddr191</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21536588</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Feuk</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carson</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Scherer</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Structural variation in the human genome</article-title>. <source>Nature reviews Genetics</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>85</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>97</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16418744</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lupski</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Mechanisms for human genomic rearrangements</article-title>. <source>PathoGenetics</source>
<volume>1</volume>: <fpage>4</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19014668</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>XD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Genome-wide copy-number-variation study identified a susceptibility gene, UGT2B17, for osteoporosis</article-title>. <source>American journal of human genetics</source>
<volume>83</volume>: <fpage>663</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>674</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ajhg.2008.10.006">10.1016/j.ajhg.2008.10.006</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18992858</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Need</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Weale</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Maia</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Heinzen</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>A genome-wide investigation of SNPs and CNVs in schizophrenia</article-title>. <source>PLoS genetics</source>
<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>e1000373</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgen.1000373">10.1371/journal.pgen.1000373</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19197363</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shlien</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tabori</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pienkowska</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Feuk</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Novokmet</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Excessive genomic DNA copy number variation in the Li-Fraumeni cancer predisposition syndrome</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source>
<volume>105</volume>: <fpage>11264</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11269</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0802970105">10.1073/pnas.0802970105</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18685109</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Diskin</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Glessner</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Attiyeh</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Laudenslager</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bosse</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Copy number variation at 1q21.1 associated with neuroblastoma</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>459</volume>: <fpage>987</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>991</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nature08035">10.1038/nature08035</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19536264</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Omar ZA, Ali ZM, Tamin NSI (2006) Malaysian Cancer Statistics-Data and Figure, Peninsular Malaysia 2006. National cancer registry, ministry of health Malaysia.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hatin</surname><given-names>WI</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nur-Shafawati</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zahri</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Population genetic structure of peninsular Malaysia Malay sub-ethnic groups</article-title>. <source>PloS one</source>
<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e18312</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0018312">10.1371/journal.pone.0018312</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21483678</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Plenge</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Weinblatt</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shadick</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reich</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Principal components analysis corrects for stratification in genome-wide association studies</article-title>. <source>Nature genetics</source>
<volume>38</volume>: <fpage>904</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>909</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16862161</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hadley</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Glessner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>PennCNV: an integrated hidden Markov model designed for high-resolution copy number variation detection in whole-genome SNP genotyping data</article-title>. <source>Genome research</source>
<volume>17</volume>: <fpage>1665</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1674</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17921354</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tulalamba</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Janvilisri</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Nasopharyngeal Carcinoma Signaling Pathway: An Update on Molecular Biomarkers</article-title>. <source>International journal of cell biology</source>
<volume>2012</volume>: <fpage>594681</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1155/2012/594681">10.1155/2012/594681</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22500174</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Raychaudhuri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Korn</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McCarroll</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Altshuler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sklar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Purcell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Accurately assessing the risk of schizophrenia conferred by rare copy-number variation affecting genes with brain function</article-title>. <source>PLoS genetics</source>
<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e1001097</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgen.1001097">10.1371/journal.pgen.1001097</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20838587</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Purcell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Neale</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Todd-Brown</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bender</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>PLINK: a tool set for whole-genome association and population-based linkage analyses</article-title>. <source>American journal of human genetics</source>
<volume>81</volume>: <fpage>559</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>575</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17701901</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Onengut-Gumuscu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W-M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Concannon</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rich</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Imputing Amino Acid Polymorphisms in Human Leukocyte Antigens</article-title>. <source>PloS one</source>
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e64683</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0064683">10.1371/journal.pone.0064683</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23762245</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Okada</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pillai</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ong</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Saw</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Risk for ACPA-positive rheumatoid arthritis is driven by shared HLA amino acid polymorphisms in Asian and European populations</article-title>. <source>Human molecular genetics</source>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pillai</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Okada</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Saw</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ong</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tantoso</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Predicting HLA alleles from high-resolution SNP data in three Southeast Asian populations</article-title>. <source>Human molecular genetics</source>
<volume>23</volume>: <fpage>4443</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4451</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/hmg/ddu149">10.1093/hmg/ddu149</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24698974</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Glessner</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hakonarson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>ParseCNV integrative copy number variation association software with quality tracking</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
<volume>41</volume>: <fpage>e64</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/nar/gks1346">10.1093/nar/gks1346</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23293001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Magi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>GWAMA: software for genome-wide association meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>11</volume>: <fpage>288</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2105-11-288">10.1186/1471-2105-11-288</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20509871</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Faul</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Erdfelder</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Buchner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>A-G</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Statistical power analyses using G*Power 3.1: Tests for correlation and regression analyses</article-title>. <source>Behavior Research Methods</source>
<volume>41</volume>: <fpage>1149</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1160</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3758/BRM.41.4.1149">10.3758/BRM.41.4.1149</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19897823</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dodd</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sengupta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>den Boon</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Westra</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Genes involved in DNA repair and nitrosamine metabolism and those located on chromosome 14q32 are dysregulated in nasopharyngeal carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Cancer epidemiology, biomarkers &#x00026; prevention: a publication of the American Association for Cancer Research, cosponsored by the American Society of Preventive Oncology</source>
<volume>15</volume>: <fpage>2216</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2225</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sengupta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>den Boon</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Newton</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dahl</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Genome-wide expression profiling reveals EBV-associated inhibition of MHC class I expression in nasopharyngeal carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Cancer research</source>
<volume>66</volume>: <fpage>7999</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8006</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16912175</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Delahanty</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>A common deletion in the APOBEC3 genes and breast cancer risk</article-title>. <source>Journal of the National Cancer Institute</source>
<volume>105</volume>: <fpage>573</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>579</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/jnci/djt018">10.1093/jnci/djt018</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23411593</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Corti</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Clarkson</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Crepaldi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sala</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xuereb</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ferraguti</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Gene structure of the human metabotropic glutamate receptor 5 and functional analysis of its multiple promoters in neuroblastoma and astroglioma cells</article-title>. <source>The Journal of biological chemistry</source>
<volume>278</volume>: <fpage>33105</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>33119</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12783878</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cavalheiro</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Olney</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Glutamate antagonists: deadly liaisons with cancer</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source>
<volume>98</volume>: <fpage>5947</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5948</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11371628</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hinoi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Takarada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ueshima</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tsuchihashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yoneda</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Glutamate signaling in peripheral tissues</article-title>. <source>European journal of biochemistry / FEBS</source>
<volume>271</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>13</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14686914</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ishiuchi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tsuzuki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hagimura</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Okado</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Blockage of Ca(2+)-permeable AMPA receptors suppresses migration and induces apoptosis in human glioblastoma cells</article-title>. <source>Nature medicine</source>
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>971</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>978</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12172541</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pollock</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cohen-Solal</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sood</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Namkoong</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Martino</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Koganti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Melanoma mouse model implicates metabotropic glutamate signaling in melanocytic neoplasia</article-title>. <source>Nature genetics</source>
<volume>34</volume>: <fpage>108</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>112</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12704387</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>KY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pickel</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Badger</surname><given-names>JD</given-names><suffix>2nd</suffix></name>, <name><surname>Roche</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Expression of the metabotropic glutamate receptor 5 (mGluR5) induces melanoma in transgenic mice</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source>
<volume>108</volume>: <fpage>15219</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>15224</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1107304108">10.1073/pnas.1107304108</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21896768</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Clinical significance of metabotropic glutamate receptor 5 expression in oral squamous cell carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Oncology reports</source>
<volume>17</volume>: <fpage>81</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>87</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17143482</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Overexpression of G protein-coupled receptors in cancer cells: involvement in tumor progression</article-title>. <source>International journal of oncology</source>
<volume>27</volume>: <fpage>1329</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1339</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16211229</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yi Lo</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sawai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Soluble MICA and a MICA Variation as Possible Prognostic Biomarkers for HBV-Induced Hepatocellular Carcinoma</article-title>. <source>PloS one</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e44743</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23024757</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref046"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lange</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bibert</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dufour</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cellerai</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cerny</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Heim</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Comparative genetic analyses point to HCP5 as susceptibility locus for HCV-associated hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Journal of hepatology</source>
<volume>59</volume>: <fpage>504</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>509</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jhep.2013.04.032">10.1016/j.jhep.2013.04.032</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23665287</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref047"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>XM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>LX</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>QZ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Gender-specific associations between MICA-STR and nasopharyngeal carcinoma in a southern Chinese Han population</article-title>. <source>Immunogenetics</source>
<volume>58</volume>: <fpage>113</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>121</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16547745</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref048"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ota</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bahram</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Katsuyama</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nose</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>On the MICA deleted-MICB null, HLA-B*4801 haplotype</article-title>. <source>Tissue antigens</source>
<volume>56</volume>: <fpage>268</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>271</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11034563</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref049"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chin</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mushiroda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kubo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Krishnan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yap</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>HLA-A SNPs and amino acid variants are associated with nasopharyngeal carcinoma in Malaysian Chinese</article-title>. <source>International journal of cancer Journal international du cancer</source>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref050"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lan</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hsiao</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Epstein-Barr virus latent membrane protein 2A promotes invasion of nasopharyngeal carcinoma cells through ERK/Fra-1-mediated induction of matrix metalloproteinase 9</article-title>. <source>Journal of virology</source>
<volume>86</volume>: <fpage>6656</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6667</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1128/JVI.00174-12">10.1128/JVI.00174-12</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22514348</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref051"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Groh</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Steinle</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lanier</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Activation of NK cells and T cells by NKG2D, a receptor for stress-inducible MICA</article-title>. <source>Science (New York, NY)</source>
<volume>285</volume>: <fpage>727</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>729</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref052"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Job</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bernheim</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Beau-Faller</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Camilleri-Bro&#x000eb;t</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Girard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hofman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Genomic Aberrations in Lung Adenocarcinoma in Never Smokers</article-title>. <source>PloS one</source>
<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>e15145</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0015145">10.1371/journal.pone.0015145</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21151896</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref053"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>GOLPH3 high expression predicts poor prognosis in patients with resected non-small cell lung cancer: an immunohistochemical analysis</article-title>. <source>Tumour Biol</source>
<volume>35</volume>: <fpage>10833</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10839</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s13277-014-2357-3">10.1007/s13277-014-2357-3</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25081375</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref054"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hua</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xian</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Increased expression of Golgi phosphoprotein-3 is associated with tumor aggressiveness and poor prognosis of prostate cancer</article-title>. <source>Diagn Pathol</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>127</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1746-1596-7-127">10.1186/1746-1596-7-127</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23006319</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref055"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Mechanisms of GOLPH3 associated with the progression of gastric cancer: a preliminary study</article-title>. <source>PloS one</source>
<volume>9</volume>: <fpage>e107362</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0107362">10.1371/journal.pone.0107362</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25286393</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref056"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Maeda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mahara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kitazoe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Futami</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Takidani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kosaka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>RNase 3 (ECP) is an extraordinarily stable protein among human pancreatic-type RNases</article-title>. <source>J Biochem</source>
<volume>132</volume>: <fpage>737</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>742</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12417023</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145774.ref057"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Subramanian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tamayo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mootha</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ebert</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gillette</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Gene set enrichment analysis: A knowledge-based approach for interpreting genome-wide expression profiles</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source>
<volume>102</volume>: <fpage>15545</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>15550</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>