<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Theor Biol Med Model</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Theoretical Biology &#x00026; Medical Modelling</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1742-4682</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21711537</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3141687</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1742-4682-8-24</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1742-4682-8-24</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A biochemical hypothesis on the formation of fingerprints using a turing patterns approach</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A1"><name><surname>Garz&#x000f3;n-Alvarado</surname><given-names>Diego A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>dagarzona@bt.unal.edu.co</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A2"><name><surname>Ram&#x000ed;rez Martinez</surname><given-names>Angelica M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>amramirezm3@ucentral.edu.co</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Associate Professor, Mechanical and Mechatronics Engineering Department, Universidad Nacional de Colombia, Engineering Modeling and Numerical Methods Group (GNUM), Bogot&#x000e1;, Colombia</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Professor, Mechanical Engineering Department, Fundaci&#x000f3;n Universidad Central, Bogot&#x000e1;, Colombia</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>6</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><fpage>24</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>26</day><month>5</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>6</month><year>2011</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9;2011 Garz&#x000f3;n-Alvarado and Ram&#x000ed;rez Martinez; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Garz&#x000f3;n-Alvarado and Ram&#x000ed;rez Martinez; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.tbiomed.com/content/8/1/24"/><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Fingerprints represent a particular characteristic for each individual. Characteristic patterns are also formed on the palms of the hands and soles of the feet. Their origin and development is still unknown but it is believed to have a strong genetic component, although it is not the only thing determining its formation. Each fingerprint is a papillary drawing composed by papillae and rete ridges (crests). This paper proposes a phenomenological model describing fingerprint pattern formation using reaction diffusion equations with Turing space parameters.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Several numerical examples were solved regarding simplified finger geometries to study pattern formation. The finite element method was used for numerical solution, in conjunction with the Newton-Raphson method to approximate nonlinear partial differential equations.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>The numerical examples showed that the model could represent the formation of different types of fingerprint characteristics in each individual.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Fingerprint</kwd><kwd>Turing pattern</kwd><kwd>numerical solution</kwd><kwd>finite element</kwd><kwd>continuum mechanics</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Fingerprints represent a particular characteristic for each individual [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. These enable individuals to be identified through the embossed patterns formed on fingertips. Characteristic patterns are also formed on the palms of the hands and soles of the feet [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Their origin and development is still unknown but it is believed to have a strong genetic component, although it is not the only thing determining its formation. Each fingerprint is a papillary drawing composed by papillae and rete ridges (crests) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. These crests are epidermal ridges having unique characteristics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>].</p><p>Characteristic fingerprint patterns begin their formation by the sixth month of gestation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. Such formation is unchangeable until an individual's death. No two fingerprints are identical; they thus become an excellent identification tool [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. Various theories have been proposed concerning fingerprint formation; among the most accepted are those that consider differential forces on the skin (mechanical theory) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>] and those having a genetic component [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. From a mechanical point of view, it has been considered that fingerprints are produced by the interaction of nonlinear elastic forces between the dermis and epidermis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. This theory considers that the growth of the fingers in the embryo (dermis) is different than growth in the epidermis, resulting in folds in the skin surface [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref> shows a mechanical explanation for the formation of the folds that give rise to fingerprints.</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Fingerprint formation Taken from </bold>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. An explanation for the formation of grooves forming a fingerprint. The first figure on the left (top) shows the epidermis and dermis. Right: rapid growth of the basal layer. Below (right) compressive loads are generated. Left: generation of wrinkles due to mechanical loads.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1742-4682-8-24-1"/></fig><p>Fingers are separated from each other in the fetus during embryonic formation during the sixth week, generating certain asymmetries in each finger's geometry [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. The fingertips begin to be defined from the seventh week onwards [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. The first waves forming the fingerprint begin to take shape from the tenth week; these are patterns which keep growing and deform until the whole fingertip has been completed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. Fingerprint formation finishes at about week 19 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. From this time on, the fingerprints stop changing for the rest of an individual's lifetime. Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> shows the stages of fingerprint formation.</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Stages of Fingerprint formation Taken from </bold>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. Fingerprint formation. a) primary formation, b) the first loop is generated, c) development. d) complete formation, e) side view, f) wear.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1742-4682-8-24-2"/></fig><p>Alternately to the proposal made by Kucken [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>], this paper presents a hypothesis about fingerprint formation from a biochemical effect. The proposed model uses a reaction-diffusion-convection (RDC) system. Following a similar approach to that used in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>], a glycolysis reaction model has been used to simulate the appearance of patterns on fingertips. A solution method on three dimensional surfaces using total Lagrangian formulation is provided for resolving the reaction diffusion (RD) equations. Equations whose parameters are in the Turing space have been used for pattern formation; therefore, the patterns found are Turing patterns which are stable in time and unstable in space. Such stability is similar to that found in fingerprint formation. The model explained in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>] was used for fold growth where the formation of the folds depends on the concentration of a biochemical substance present on the surface of the skin.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Reaction-diffusion (RD) system</title><p>Following a biochemical approach, it was assumed that a RD system could control fingerprint pattern formation. For this purpose, an RD system was defined for two species, given by (1):<disp-formula id="bmcM1"><label>(1)</label><graphic xlink:href="1742-4682-8-24-i1.gif"/></disp-formula></p><p>where <italic>u<sub>1 </sub></italic>and <italic>u<sub>2 </sub></italic>were the concentrations of chemical species present in reaction terms <italic>f </italic>and <italic>g, d </italic>was the dimensionless diffusion coefficient and &#x003b3; was a constant in a dimensionless system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>].</p><p>RD systems have been extensively studied to determine their behavior in different scenarios regarding parameters [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>], geometrics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>] and for different biological applications [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. One area that has led to developing extensive work on RD equations has been the formation of patterns which are stable in time and unstable in space [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. In particular, Turing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>], in his book, "The chemical basis of morphogenesis," developed the necessary conditions for spatial pattern formation. The conditions for pattern formation determined Turing space given by the following restrictions (2):<disp-formula id="bmcM2"><label>(2)</label><graphic xlink:href="1742-4682-8-24-i2.gif"/></disp-formula></p><p>where <italic>f</italic><sub>1 </sub>and <italic>g</italic><sub>1 </sub>indicated the derivatives of the reaction regarding concentration variables, for example <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-4682-8-24-i3.gif"/></inline-formula>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. These restrictions were evaluated at the point of equilibrium by <italic>f</italic>(<italic>u</italic><sub>1</sub><italic>, u</italic><sub>2</sub>) = <italic>g</italic>(<italic>u</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic>u</italic><sub>2</sub>) = 0.</p><p>Equations (1) and constraints (2) led to developing the dynamic system branch of research [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]: Turing instability. Turing pattern theory has helped explain the formation of complex biological patterns such as the spots found on the skin of some animals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>] and morphogenesis problems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. It has also been experimentally proven that the behavior of some RD systems produce traveling wave and stable spatial patterns [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>].</p><p>The equations used for predicting pattern formation in this paper were those for glycolysis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>], given by:<disp-formula id="bmcM3"><label>(3)</label><graphic xlink:href="1742-4682-8-24-i4.gif"/></disp-formula></p><p>where <italic>&#x003b4; </italic>and <italic>&#x003ba; </italic>were the model's dimensionless parameters. The steady state points were given by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-4682-8-24-i5.gif"/></inline-formula>. Applying constraints (2) to model (3) in steady state point (<italic>u</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic>u</italic><sub>2</sub>)<sub>0 </sub>a set of constraints was obtained. This constraint establishes the geometric site known as Turing space [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Epidermis strain</title><p>The ideas suggested in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>] were used to strain the fingertip surface regarding the substances (morphogens) present in the domain; i.e. surface <italic>S</italic>, was strained according to its normal <italic>N </italic>and the amount of molecular concentration (u<sub>2</sub>) at each material point, therefore:<disp-formula id="bmcM4"><label>(4)</label><graphic xlink:href="1742-4682-8-24-i6.gif"/></disp-formula></p><p>where K was a constant determining growth rate.</p><p>Including the term for surface growth (equation (4)) modifies equation (1), which presented a new term taking into account the convection and dilation of the domain given by:<disp-formula id="bmcM5"><label>(5)</label><graphic xlink:href="1742-4682-8-24-i7.gif"/></disp-formula></p><p>where new term <italic>div</italic>(<italic>u</italic><sub>i</sub><bold>v</bold>) included convection and dilatation due to the growth of the domain, given by velocity<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-4682-8-24-i8.gif"/></inline-formula>.</p><p>The finite element method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>] was used to solve the RDC system described above in (5) and the Newton-Raphson method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>] to solve the non-linear system of partial differential equations arising from the formulation. The seed coat surface pattern growth field was imposed by solving equation (4), giving the new configuration (current) and velocity field to be included in the RD problem.</p><p>The solution of the RD equations by using the finite element method is shown below.</p></sec><sec><title>Solution for RDC system</title><p>Formulating the RD system, including convective transport, could be written as (6) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]:<disp-formula id="bmcM6"><label>(6)</label><graphic xlink:href="1742-4682-8-24-i9.gif"/></disp-formula></p><p>where <italic>u<sub>1 </sub></italic>and <italic>u<sub>2 </sub></italic>were the RD system's chemical variables. This equation could also be written in terms of total derivative (7) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]:<disp-formula id="bmcM7"><label>(7)</label><graphic xlink:href="1742-4682-8-24-i10.gif"/></disp-formula></p><p>where it should be noted that</p><p><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-4682-8-24-i11.gif"/></inline-formula>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>].</p><p>According to the description in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>], then the RDC system in the initial configuration, or reference &#x003a9;<sub>0 </sub>(with coordinates in <bold>X(x)</bold>), was given by the following equation, written in terms of material coordinates:<disp-formula id="bmcM8a"><label>(8a)</label><graphic xlink:href="1742-4682-8-24-i12.gif"/></disp-formula><disp-formula id="bmcM8b"><label>(8b)</label><graphic xlink:href="1742-4682-8-24-i13.gif"/></disp-formula></p><p>where U1 and U2 were the concentrations of each species in initial configuration &#x003a9;0, i.e. U(<bold>X</bold>,t) = <italic>u(<bold><sc>X</sc></bold>(<bold>X</bold>,t),t)</italic>. Besides <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-4682-8-24-i14.gif"/></inline-formula> was the inverse of the strained gradient given by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-4682-8-24-i15.gif"/></inline-formula>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>], <italic>x<sup>i</sup></italic> were the current coordinates (at each instant of time) and <italic>X<sup>I </sup></italic>were the initial coordinates (of reference, where the calculations were to be made) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>].</p><p>Therefore, equation (8) gave the general weak form for (9) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>].<disp-formula id="bmcM9"><label>(9)</label><graphic xlink:href="1742-4682-8-24-i16.gif"/></disp-formula></p><p>where U was either of the two studied species (U<sub>1 </sub>or U<sub>2</sub>), W was the weighting, J was the Jacobian (and equaled the determinant for strained gradient <bold>F</bold>) and <bold>C<sup>-1 </sup></bold>was the inverse of the Cauchy-Green tensor on the right [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>].</p><p>In the case of total Lagrangian formulation, the calculation was always done in the initial reference configuration. Therefore, the solution for system (8) and (9) began with the discretization of the variables U<sub>1 </sub>and U<sub>2 </sub>by (10) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]:<disp-formula id="bmcM10a"><label>(10a)</label><graphic xlink:href="1742-4682-8-24-i17.gif"/></disp-formula><disp-formula id="bmcM10b"><label>(10b)</label><graphic xlink:href="1742-4682-8-24-i18.gif"/></disp-formula></p><p>where <italic>nnod </italic>was the number of nodes, <bold>U</bold><sub>1 </sub>and <bold>U</bold><sub>2 </sub>were the vectors containing <italic>U<sub>1 </sub></italic>and <italic>U<sub>2 </sub></italic>values at nodal points and superscript <italic>h </italic>indicated the variable discretization in finite elements. The Newton-Raphson method residue vectors were obtained by choosing weighting functions equal to shape functions (Galerkin standard) given by [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>] (11):<disp-formula id="bmcM11a"><label>(11a)</label><graphic xlink:href="1742-4682-8-24-i19.gif"/></disp-formula><disp-formula id="bmcM11b"><label>(11b)</label><graphic xlink:href="1742-4682-8-24-i20.gif"/></disp-formula></p><p>with p = 1, ..., <italic>nnod</italic>, where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-4682-8-24-i21.gif"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-4682-8-24-i22.gif"/></inline-formula> were residue vectors calculated in the new time. In turn, each position (input) of the Jacobian matrix was given by (12):<disp-formula id="bmcM12a"><label>(12a)</label><graphic xlink:href="1742-4682-8-24-i23.gif"/></disp-formula><disp-formula id="bmcM12b"><label>(12b)</label><graphic xlink:href="1742-4682-8-24-i24.gif"/></disp-formula><disp-formula id="bmcM12c"><label>(12c)</label><graphic xlink:href="1742-4682-8-24-i25.gif"/></disp-formula><disp-formula id="bmcM12d"><label>(12d)</label><graphic xlink:href="1742-4682-8-24-i26.gif"/></disp-formula></p><p>where <italic>J </italic>was strained gradient determinant, <bold>C<sup>-1 </sup></bold>was the inverse of the Cauchy-Green tensor on the right <italic>p, s </italic>= 1, ..., <italic>nnod </italic>and <italic>I, J = 1, .., dim</italic>, where <italic>dim </italic>was the dimension in which the problem was resolved. Therefore, using equations (11) and (12), the Newton-Raphson method could be implemented to solve the RD system using its material description. It should be noted that (11) and (12) were integrated in the initial configuration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Applying the velocity fields</title><p>Equation (4) was used to calculate the movement of the mesh and the velocity at which the domain was strained, integrated by Euler's method, given by [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]:<disp-formula id="bmcM13"><label>(13)</label><graphic xlink:href="1742-4682-8-24-i27.gif"/></disp-formula></p><p>where <italic>S<sub>t+dt </sub></italic>and <italic>S<sub>t </sub></italic>were the surface configuration in state t and t+dt. Therefore, velocity was given by (14):<disp-formula id="bmcM14"><label>(14)</label><graphic xlink:href="1742-4682-8-24-i28.gif"/></disp-formula></p><p>where the velocity term had direction and magnitude depending on the material point of surface S.</p></sec><sec><title>Aspects of computational implementation</title><p>The formulation described above was used for implementing the RD model using the finite element method. It should be noted that although the surface was orientated in a 3D space, the numerical calculations were done in 2D. The normal for each element (Z') was thus found and the prime axes (X'Y') forming a parallel plane to the element plane were located. The geometry was enmeshed by using first order triangular elements with three nodes. Therefore, the calculation was simplified from a 3D system to a system which solved two-dimensional RD models at every instant of time. The relationship between the X'Y'Z 'and XYZ axes could be obtained by a transformation matrix T [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>].</p><p>A program in FORTRAN was used for solving the system of equations resulting from the finite element method with the Newton-Raphson method and the following examples were solved on a Laptop having 4096 MB of RAM and 800 MHz processor speed. In all cases, the dimensionless problem was solved with random conditions around the steady state [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>] for the RD system.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>The mesh used is shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>. This mesh was made on a 1 cm long, 0.5 cm radius ellipsoid. The number of triangular elements was 5,735 and the number of nodes 2,951. The time step used in the simulation was dt = 2 (dimensionless). The total simulation time was t = 100.</p><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>Mesh used in the simulation</bold>. Mesh used in developing the problem. In this figure the mesh has 5735 triangular elements and 2951 nodes.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1742-4682-8-24-3"/></fig><p>The dimensionless parameters of the RD system of glycolysis were given by <italic>d </italic>= 0.08, <italic>&#x003b4; </italic>= 1.2 and <italic>&#x003ba; </italic>= 0.06 for Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4a</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4b</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4c</xref>) <italic>d </italic>= 0.06, <italic>&#x003b4; </italic><italic>= </italic>1.2 and <italic>&#x003ba; </italic>= 0.06. Therefore the steady state was given at the point of equilibrium (<italic>u</italic><sub>1</sub>,u<sub>2</sub>)<sub>0 </sub>= (0.8,1.2), so that the initial conditions were random around steady state [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. K = 0.05 in equations (4) and (13) was used for all glycolysis simulations.</p><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><bold>Results of the simulation of Fingerprint a) photo of the fingerprints, b) results for parameters <italic>d </italic><bold>= </bold>0</bold>.08, <italic>&#x003b4; </italic>= 1.2 and <italic>&#x003ba; </italic>= 0.06. c) results for parameters <italic>d </italic>= 0.06, <italic>&#x003b4; </italic>= 1.2 and <italic>&#x003ba; </italic>= 0.06.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1742-4682-8-24-4"/></fig><p>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4b</xref>)-<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4c</xref>) shows surface pattern evolution. The formation of labyrinths and blind spots in the grooves approximating the shape of the fingerprint patterns can be observed (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4a</xref>). The pattern obtained was given by bands of high concentration of a chemical species, for which the domain had grown in the normal direction to the surface and hence generated its own fingerprint grooves.</p><p>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref> shows temporal evolution during the formation of folds and furrows on the fingertip. In 5a) shows that there was no formation whatsoever of folds. In b), small bumps began to form, in the entire domain, which continued to grow and form the grooves, as shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5f</xref>).</p><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><bold>Stages of Fingerprint formation simulation</bold>. Different instants of time in the evolution of the folds and grooves forming the fingerprint. a) t = 0, b) t = 20, c) t = 40, d) t = 60, e) t = 80 f) t = 100. Time is dimensionless.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1742-4682-8-24-5"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Discussion and conclusions</title><p>This paper has presented a phenomenological model based on RD equations to predict the formation of rough patterns on the tips of the fingers, known as fingerprints. The application of the RD models with Turing space parameters is an area of constant work and controversy in biology [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>] and has attracted recent interest due to the work of Sick <italic>et al</italic>., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>] confirming the validity of RD equations in a model of the appearance of the hair follicle. From this point of view, the work developed in this article has illustrated RD equation validity for representing complex biological patterns, such as patterns formed in fingerprints.</p><p>This paper proposes the existence of a reactive system (activator-inhibitor) on the skin surface giving an explanation for the patterns found. The high stability of the emergence of the patterns can also be explained, i.e. the repetition of the patterns was due to a specialized biochemical system allowing the formation of wrinkles in the fingerprints and skin pigmentation.</p><p>The formulation of a system of RD equations acting under domain strain was programmed to test this hypothesis. Continuum mechanics thus led to the general form of the RD equations in two- and three-dimensions on domains presenting strain. The resulting equations were similar to those shown in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>], where major simplifications were carried out on field dilatation. The RD system was solved by the finite element method, using a Newton-Raphson approach to solve the nonlinear problem. This allowed longer time steps and obtaining solutions closer to reality. The results showed that RD equations have continuously changing patterns.</p><p>Additionally, it should be noted that the results obtained with the RD mathematical model was based on assumptions and simplifications that should be discussed for future models.</p><p>The model was based on the assumption of a tightly coupled biochemical system (non-linear) between an activator and an inhibitor generating Turing patterns. As far as the authors know, this assumption has not been tested experimentally, so the model is a hypothesis to be tested in future research. It is also feasible, as in other biological models (see [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]), that there were a large number of chemical factors (morphogens) involved, interacting to form superficial patterns found in the fingers. In the case of patterns with superficial roughness, the biochemical system could also interact with its own mechanical growth factors. Therefore, determining the exact influence of each biochemical and mechanical factor on the formation of surface patterns becomes an experimental challenge that will reveal the morphogenesis of fingerprints.</p></sec><sec><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>The work was made by equal parts, in manuscript, modelling and numerical simulation. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec></body><back><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This work was financially supported by Division de Investigaci&#x000f3;n de Bogot&#x000e1;, of Universidad Nacional de Colombia, under title Modelling in Mechanical and Biomedical Engineering, Phase II.</p></sec><ref-list><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kucken</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Newell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Fingerprint formation</article-title><source>Journal of theoretical biology</source><year>2005</year><volume>235</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jtbi.2004.12.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15833314</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kucken</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Newell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>A model for fingerprint formation</article-title><source>EPL (Europhysics Letters)</source><year>2004</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>146</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1209/epl/i2004-10161-2</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bonnevie</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><article-title>Studies on papillary patterns of human fingers</article-title><source>Journal of Genetics</source><year>1924</year><volume>15</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>111</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02983100</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hale</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Breadth of epidermal ridges in the human fetus and its relation to the growth of the hand and foot</article-title><source>The Anatomical Record</source><year>1949</year><volume>105</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>763</fpage><lpage>776</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ar.1091050409</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15403872</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hale</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Morphogenesis of volar skin in the human fetus</article-title><source>American Journal of Anatomy</source><year>1952</year><volume>91</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>147</fpage><lpage>181</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/aja.1000910105</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12976353</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hirsch</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><article-title>Morphological evidence concerning the problem of skin ridge formation</article-title><source>Journal of Intellectual Disability Research</source><year>1973</year><volume>17</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>58</fpage><lpage>72</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kucken</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Models for fingerprint pattern formation</article-title><source>Forensic science international</source><year>2007</year><volume>171</volume><issue>2-3</issue><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.forsciint.2007.02.025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17459625</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Prabhakar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pankanti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>On the similarity of identical twin fingerprints</article-title><source>Pattern Recognition</source><year>2002</year><volume>35</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>2653</fpage><lpage>2663</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0031-3203(01)00218-7</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bonnevie</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><article-title>Die ersten Entwicklungsstadien der Papillarmuster der menschlichen Fingerballen</article-title><source>Nyt Mag Naturvidenskaberne</source><year>1927</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>56</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Cummins</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Midlo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><source>Fingerprints, palms and soles: An introduction to dermatoglyphics</source><year>1961</year><volume>778</volume><publisher-name>Dover Publications Inc. New York</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cartwright</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>Labyrinthine Turing pattern formation in the cerebral cortex</article-title><source>Journal of theoretical biology</source><year>2002</year><volume>217</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>103</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/jtbi.2002.3012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12183134</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Madzvamuse</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><source>A numerical approach to the study of spatial pattern formation. D Phil Thesis</source><year>2000</year><publisher-name>United Kingdom: Oxford University</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Meinhardt</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><source>Models of biological pattern formation</source><year>1982</year><volume>6</volume><publisher-name>Academic Press, New York</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Madzvamuse</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Time-stepping schemes for moving grid finite elements applied to reaction-diffusion systems on fixed and growing domains</article-title><source>Journal of computational physics</source><year>2006</year><volume>214</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>239</fpage><lpage>263</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jcp.2005.09.012</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Madzvamuse</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sekimura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wathen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Maini</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><person-group person-group-type="editor">T. Sekimura, S. Noji, N. Nueno and P.K. Maini</person-group><article-title>A moving grid finite element method for the study of spatial pattern formation in Biological problems</article-title><source>Morphogenesis and Pattern Formation in Biological Systems-Experiments and Models, Springer-Verlag, Tokyo</source><year>2003</year><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>65</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Madzvamuse</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wathen</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Maini</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><article-title>A moving grid finite element method applied to a model biological pattern generator* 1</article-title><source>Journal of computational physics</source><year>2003</year><volume>190</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>478</fpage><lpage>500</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0021-9991(03)00294-8</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Madzvamuse</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>RDK</given-names></name><name><surname>Maini</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Wathen</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><article-title>A numerical approach to the study of spatial pattern formation in the Ligaments of Arcoid Bivalves</article-title><source>Bulletin of mathematical biology</source><year>2002</year><volume>64</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>501</fpage><lpage>530</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/bulm.2002.0283</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12094407</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gierer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Meinhardt</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><article-title>A theory of biological pattern formation</article-title><source>Biological Kybernetik</source><year>1972</year><volume>12</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>30</fpage><lpage>39</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00289234</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chaplain</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Ganesh</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><article-title>Spatio-temporal pattern formation on spherical surfaces: Numerical simulation and application to solid tumor growth</article-title><source>J Math Biol</source><year>2001</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>387</fpage><lpage>423</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s002850000067</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11419617</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Turing</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>The chemical basis of morphogenesis</article-title><source>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London Series B, Biological Sciences</source><year>1952</year><volume>237</volume><issue>641</issue><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rstb.1952.0012</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>De Wit</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Spatial patterns and spatiotemporal dynamics in chemical systems</article-title><source>Adv Chem Phys</source><year>1999</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>435</fpage><lpage>513</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Maini</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Painter</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chau</surname><given-names>HNP</given-names></name><article-title>Spatial pattern formation in chemical and biological systems</article-title><source>Journal of the Chemical Society, Faraday Transactions</source><year>1997</year><volume>93</volume><issue>20</issue><fpage>3601</fpage><lpage>3610</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/a702602a</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Kapral</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Showalter</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><source>Chemical waves and patterns</source><year>1995</year><volume>10</volume><publisher-name>Kluwer Academic Pub</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Garz&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><source>Simulaci&#x000f3;n de procesos de reacci&#x000f3;n-difusi&#x000f3;n: aplicaci&#x000f3;n a la morfog&#x000e9;nesis del tejido &#x000d3;seo</source><year>2007</year><publisher-name>Universidad de Zaragoza</publisher-name><comment>Ph.D. Thesis</comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name><surname>Wehner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Holloway</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><article-title>Complex morphogenesis of surfaces: theory and experiment on coupling of reaction-diffusion patterning to growth</article-title><source>Faraday Discussions</source><year>2002</year><volume>120</volume><fpage>277</fpage><lpage>293</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Holloway</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><article-title>Pattern selection in plants: coupling chemical dynamics to surface growth in three dimensions</article-title><source>Annals of botany</source><year>2008</year><volume>101</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>361</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18045793</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>T.J.R</surname></name><name><surname>Hughes</surname></name><source>The finite element method: linear static and dynamic finite element analysis</source><year>2003</year><publisher-name>New York: Courier Dover Publications</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><source>Numerical methods for engineers and scientists</source><year>1992</year><publisher-name>McGraw-Hil</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Holzapfel</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><source>Nonlinear solid mechanics: a continuum approach for engineering</source><year>2000</year><publisher-name>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Belytschko</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Moran</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><source>Nonlinear finite elements for continua and structures</source><year>2000</year><volume>36</volume><publisher-name>John Wiley and Sons</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Crampin</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Maini</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><article-title>Reaction-diffusion models for biological pattern formation</article-title><source>Methods and Applications of Analysis</source><year>2001</year><volume>8</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>415</fpage><lpage>428</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sick</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Reinker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Timmer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlake</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><article-title>WNT and DKK determine hair follicle spacing through a reaction-diffusion mechanism</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2006</year><volume>314</volume><issue>5804</issue><fpage>1447</fpage><lpage>1450</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1130088</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17082421</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Madzvamuse</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Maini</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><article-title>Velocity-induced numerical solutions of reaction-diffusion systems on continuously growing domains</article-title><source>Journal of computational physics</source><year>2007</year><volume>225</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>100</fpage><lpage>119</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jcp.2006.11.022</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>